[MUSIC]
Stanford University. >> Welcome to Lecture Number
10 of Stanford CS193P. It's the Spring of 2016.
Today we have one topic only, which is Core Data, okay,
which is an object oriented database. Sometimes when
you're building an app you need to store a huge amount of
data like you're doing some kind of twitter thing where
you're collecting all the tweets and
you've got all these tweets and
you want to search through them and
do some kind of queries or something like that. And
of course there's lots of technologies out there for
doing that kind of thing. SQL databases and
things like that. But really when we're programming,
we want obviously all of our stuff to be object oriented.
So iOS has this awesome object oriented database system
called Core Data. It's very powerful.
It's actually based on SQL underneath so
it's got all the full kind of power of that.
And yet it interacts with your code just like all your other
object oriented stuff that you do,
especially if you're doing things like table and
stuff like that that has a lot of good integration,
with that. So it's essentially a way of
creating an object graph that's backed by a database,
a SQL database in this case.
It can actually be backed by other kinds of databases
like XML or just in memory stuff but
primarily we're using Core Data with SQL as our,
backing store. And the way it works,
is you're going to create this visual mapping, okay? And
then you're gonna create objects in your code. Visual
mapping's gonna basically describe your database,
then you're gonna create objects in your code,
that are in that database. And you're gonna access
the columns in the database, and the rows, and
the columns and
the tables if you want to think of it that way, but
you can access the attributes just using vars.
So you're gonna have objects and vars on them and
those are gonna be stored in the database, okay.
So I'm gonna walk you through all that. Let's start with
creating that visual mapping of the database, okay.
Now just like anything, that you do when you're
adding a new file to x code, whether it's a swift file or
something like that, you're going to start with new file.
But in this case, we're not going
to be adding a code file, we're actually going to be
adding a database mapping file. So, you say new file,
and you're going to go down to iOS Core Data, okay? You see
where it says Core Data down there instead of, iOS source,
and inside of there, you're gonna pick data model.
Don't pick mapping model, you want data model, okay? And
it's gonna ask you what you wanna call this mapping.
Okay, this mapping, by the way,
what we're mapping between is these objects that we're gonna
describe in this database and what's gonna be in our code.
And usually if you only have one database in your app
you'll call it model, because it's usually the model for
a lot of your view controllers, but you could
also call it the name or your app or if you had multiple of
them you could kind of name them appropriately, right, so
any name will, is fine here. When you create it,
looks like this, okay? It's called Model.xcdatamodeld
right here. And this is the contents of it, right?
We're looking at the contents of it. And,
it's kind of like a storyboard for the database, okay?
You're gonna graphically,
visually edit your database schema right here. So
the database lets you store things obviously.
The main things that you're storing are called entities,
okay? And they're kinda analogous to objects,
all right? So here I'm gonna create an entity so
I'm gonna click on this add entity button at the bottom.
And just say add entity. When I do, it creates one up here.
And I'm gonna change the name of it to Tweet.
So for my examples today, let's say we're building
a database that's storing some Twitter stuff.
We're all in kinda Twitter mode
right now with your assignment stuff. So we'll store some
tweets and some Twitter users into this database, okay? Now
this entity Tweet that we're gonna store in the database,
they're gonna appear in our code as NSManagedObject
instances. So there's a class in iOS NSManagedObject, okay.
And so all these entities will appear in our code as
NSManagedObject, okay. All right so in addition
to entities these entities have attributes. So those
are kind of like properties on a class right there.
They have relationships. Relationships are kind of like
vars that point to other objects in the database, okay.
And then there also have this thing down here called fetch
properties. Which I'm not gonna really talk about but
kind of the name implies what they are.
They're essentially properties that are, that basically
represent fetching in the database. So pulling objects
out that meet some query or something like that. You can
make it look like that's just a property on you're entity.
Unfortunately, don't have time to talk about that.
We're gonna focus here on these attributes and
relationships, okay?
So to add an attribute, we're going to hit this little plus
sign right here under the attributes and
it's going to add one. Here, I'm doing a Tweet, right,
that's my entity as a Tweet, so I'm going to put the text
of the Tweet. Notice as soon as I type, as I added this and
typed it in, I get start getting an error right here.
See, red error up in the, upper corner there, okay.
And that's because this Tweet or
this text attribute on the Tweet has no type, okay.
Everything that goes in there obviously has to have a type,
so you just click on this type to set it and
I'm gonna set the text to be a string. Okay, so these are all
the types that the attributes, the vars in your Tweet entity
can be basically. All the ones like integers, decimal,
double, float, even Boolean, those are actually stored as
an NS number. Those appear in your code as an NS number.
Okay, this binary data is in NS data.
The date is an NSDate, and the string here is an NSString.
Now remember that you get the automatic bridging, right?
From NSString to string, things like that,
even from double and int to NSNumbers, right?
So, even though these are NSNumbers and NSString,
you're still gonna get your Swift-like things when you're
using them, in your code. Now, you can set any of these
things, like this text attribute using these two
methods right here on NSManagedObject, okay?
Value for key which gets the value, and set value for
key. Okay, so valueForKey returns any object,
could be an NSNumber or an NSDate or an NSData, right.
And setValue(forKey:) the key is a string like text and
the value is, again, NSNumber, NSData, NSDate, whatever,
okay? So that's how you can set the data on your object
once you get a hold of one of these NSManagedObject.
Now I haven't shown you how to get those NSManagedObject yet,
but I will soon.
See the error's gone because I set this to be a string. So,
here's I'm going to add some more attributes, an ID,
which is some unique identifier for this Tweet.
Also created, which is the date the Tweet was created,
you can see that's an NSDate right there. By the way,
this ID you're probably going to want that in your homework.
Just a little hint.
I like to give you hints sometimes in the lecture.
So you'll need your unique ID there at some point.
We're looking at these attributes on this entity in
kind of a table format here. But we can also do it in
a graphical way by clicking on this little button down here,
this editor style. It changes the style of this editor and
it looks like this. So the graphical one basically has
all of my entities and my attributes, but in kind of
on a graph paper graphical format. And this is going to
make sense when I start having a lot of relationships between
entities, right.
Then I'm gonna be able to see them here on the graph paper
all pointing to each other so
I can see what their relationships are. Okay, so
let's add another entity in this. We can add entities and
attributes in this view just as much as in the table view.
So I'm gonna go down here and add another entity.
This is gonna be a Twitter user, okay? And you can see it
added the Twitter user here. It has no attributes or
relationships yet. What's really cool,
if you move these around and they do have wires pointing
to each other, it'll rearrange the wires all over the place
to look nice, okay? So that's kinda fun. I can also add
attributes from here. So I'm just going down here and
say add attribute to add an attribute to my Twitter user.
I'm gonna call this attribute screen name, okay,
that's like the at sign, whatever, screen name
of the user. Notice that if I have this selected,
then the Inspector over here can be used to inspect things
about this attribute. So let's do that. Here's a screen name,
its attributes. For example, here's its type.
I'm going to say this type to be a string. It has some other
attributes here which I'm not really going to have time to
talk about. But you'll definitely, you can look up.
You won't need it for any of your homework obviously, but
for your final project you might. So
you can look those up in the documentation for core data.
Mkay I'm gonna add another attribute here which is name.
So that's the user's real name.
Okay not their at time whatever but their actual real
name. So I'll add that. And now I'm gonna add
a relationship between these two entities and of course we
know that a Twitter user Is the one who tweets the tweet.
Right? So, there's a relationship between this two.
And to create a relationship between these two,
I just Ctrl-drag from one to the other.
And I can Ctrl-drag from either to the other.
It really doesn't matter which direction.
And when I do that, it's going to create
a new thing over here called a relationship on both sides,
it called it new relationship by default,
we're going to change the name of that, okay, on both sides,
and you can see it's got an arrow that points both ways.
So now we know there's a relationship on both sides.
Now, we want to rename these relationships
just like the attributes have names that are meaningful,
we want these to be meaningful names too. So the tweet okay,
if you look at this relationship to this guy.
This is the tweeter. Okay this is the tweeter for
this tweet so I'm gonna call the relationship tweeter
on this side. Okay I could probably call it user or
something as well but tweeter is kind of fun.
On the other side this is tweet. Okay.
So this is the tweet that this user has tweeted. Okay.
Now notice when you do this if you inspect either one,
like if you inspect tweets right there,
it's showing me that the inverse is tweeter.
So it knows the inder-, inverse right there,
okay. Now there's something different though about
this tweets relationship to the tweeter relationship. Cuz,
there are multiple tweets per Twitter user, right?
So user could have tweeted hundreds of times. So
this basically is multiple things,
this is a to-many relationship to use database jargon there
are many tweets per user even though there's only one user
per tweet. And you define that up here in the inspector,
if you have tweet selected.
You go here to the type of relationship it is. And
you can say it's a too many relationship. And when I do
that notice I get this little double arrow right here. Okay?
That's telling me that there's many tweets per Twitter user.
Now, this is gonna show up differently in my code.
This one right here is gonna show up in my code, okay,
this tweet thing that I have, this
tweet entity is gonna have a var, right here,
called tweeter. It's gonna be of type NSManagedObject,
because I told you all of these entities, this, and
this, are gonna show up in your code as NSManagedObject,
so that's gonna be the type of this var.
The type of this var over here is gonna be ns set. Okay?
And NSSet I can't remember if we talked about that earlier
in the quarter but it's very similar to NSArray, okay?
But it's unordered and unique. Ok, so an NS
array can have the same object in it multiple times and
an NS array is also in order. And in a set,
it's just a bunch of objects in there, and
if you add in the same object again, it would do nothing.
Okay, so it's basically a unique set and
there's no order to it's just a big jumble of them. Okay,
and since these Tweets are basically a big jumble of
tweets done by this user in no particular order, that's why
it's an NS set. Now, there is in Swift a struck called set,
and is automatically bridged just like NS array,
automatically bridged to an array. Okay?
So you can think of this as just being a set, but in fact,
it's an NSSet. Okay? And what's in that set? Of course,
ManageObject, NSManageObject, cuz these are in there. Okay?
So it's exactly what you would think. All right? Now.
There's lots of things you can do, okay, in core data.
We're gonna focus on a small part of it, but
the core of it, which is entities, attributes, and
relationships, these things that I just told you about.
Okay. How do you access all this stuff in the code?
You need an instance of one of these.
NSManagedObjectContext. You can think of that as kind of
the window into the world of your database of objects,
okay? So you need one of these to be able to do anything
from the database. All right? So how do I get one of these?
[LAUGH] Okay? I need one of these, how do I get it? Well,
there's really two ways to get it, and you use them kind
of about equally. One's not really necessarily preferred
over the other. One of them is when you create your project,
do you remember when we create a project there was a little
button at the bottom, there's three switches at the bottom.
One was You, are you gonna do testing or UI testing? And
the other one on the top of the three buttons was
I'm using Core Data. Do you remember that button? Anyway,
it's there, I promise you. And
if you click that button when you create your application,
then you're going to get a bunch of code
Provided to you.. One of which is a method that gives you one
of these shared in your whole application. Okay, and
I'm going to talk about how that works in a second.
The second way you can get one of these little guys
is to create a U-I managed document, okay?
The U-I managed document has a var on it called managed
object context, which will give you one of these. Okay?
So, I'm going to talk about both of these mechanisms for,
for getting this. All right. So, the first one,
where you click the switch: When you flip that switch,
you're going to, essentially get some code
put in that AppDelegate.Swift file. Remember
the AppDelegate.Swift? It's one of the files we always
move in to supporting files.
One of the first things I ever do, is okay,
let's take image assets and AppDelegate and info.plist.
Let's move them into a little folder called supporting
files. Well, we haven't looked at that AppDelegate cuz
there's really not much in there at this point but
in there will be a bunch of code for core data, okay,
if you flip that switch. Okay, and one of the things in that
bunch of code is a method called managedObject,
it's a var actually called managedObjectContext.
And all you need to do is call that var and boom, you'll have
a managedObjectContext to the database for
this app. And App Delegate is kinda a global resource but
your database is often a global resource, right?
All your view controllers want to be able to see the data in
the database, so it's reasonable. Now, the way you
get at it, you get this AppDelegate. It's a little,
it seems a little complicated, but it's not too bad.
We're going to call this, this, class method on new
application called Shared Application. And this returns
you the one and only instance of UI application,
which is just a class that represents your app.
Ok now that object, UI application dot shared
application, has a delegate. You all know what delegation
is. It has a delegate. That delegate is that app delegate,
the place where that manage object code got thrown.
So you're going to cast it though as app delegate.
You could do question mark here and then If it comes
backs nil, I'm guess you're SOL you have any database, but
here I'm gonna force cast it because if I can't get this
managed object contacts. Then I can't do anything with my
app, so I'm going to let it crash here for
some reason my app delegate is not my delegate of
my UI application. So anyway, you do this line of code and
this is going to give you back your managed object context.
So, now you have the portal that you need.
To do all the database stuff. Okay? So that's one way to get
this portal. The other way is UIManagedDocument. Okay,
UIManagedDocument is a class it inherits from UIDocument
and it's only job really is to encapsulate a core data
database, that's what it does. It encapsulates a core data
database, I mean, a file on disk Alright?
And, the way you create a UIManagedDocument,
UIManagedDocument is actually really easy. And you might
ask, why would I ever do that other clicking the switch and
the- creating my project in AppDelegate? All that.
Why would I do that when I have this UIManagedDocument?
I just create one and get the managed object context.
Well, the reason it's a little more complicated here is
because it does it's work asynchronously.
You guys are only just getting used to asynchrony, so
it might seem a little complicated to you. Once
you're used to it it won't seem complicated at all, but
when asynchrony is new to you,
UIManagedDocument might seem a little
Kind of how does that work? Here is how it works. Okay,
here's a UIManagedDocument, I'm going to create it.
First I'm going to get an NS File Manager here.
This is a thing we haven't talked about yet, which lets
you access the file system. And of course, I'm going to
store my UIManagedDocument in the file system. So,
I obviously need this little file manager guy right here.
Then, I also need to know where to put my managed
document. And I'm gonna put it in the documents
directory for my app. So we're gonna learn later that
your app has a documents directory,
it has a caches directory, it has a temporary directory.
It has all these kind of named magic directories
where you put stuff, and the document directory right here
is the one where you probably wanna put your users data.
Okay, that's what that directory's really for.
So you're gonna do this thing URLs for
directory which returns the document directory and
then you can get the first one.
This returns an array of URLs like there might be multiple
document directories out there.
In iOS, there's always only one.
If you're on the Mac, some of these directories can return
multiple things because there might be one on the network,
there might be one on your local machine, etc. But
in iOS, there's always only the users, so it's always only
one. So we just get the first one out of there. Okay now, I
have the document's directory. Now I'm just going to append
to the end of that, it's a URL. So, I'm gonna append
to the end of that URL the name of the document.
Okay, so the URL is pointing to the document's directory.
If I append the name of the document now I've got a URL to
the document. Now that I have that I can just create a new
UIManagedDocument. Right? Just tell at the URL where it is.
Boom, so now I have UIManagedDocument. Okay, and
I could go get the managed object context from it,
except that managed object context is no good unless it's
open. Okay? So here's where the asynchrony comes in. Okay,
we have to open this ui managed document okay?
Usually we check first to see if it's already open.
Okay, you can ask the document is your document state normal?
That means it's already open and ready to go. So
if that if it's in that state then you're good to go.
You can just start using that managed object context thing,
but it might be in this state closed right here,
which means it has not yet been opened. In that case,
you cannot use the managed object context yet. Now,
what if it's closed? How do you open it?
Well, you have to use this asynchronous method here.
Okay? It's called open with completion handler, all right?
First you can find out if the file exists right here by
using this file manager thing, file exists at path. Okay,
see if you Document's already there.
If it does exist then you're gonna open it,
by calling openWithCompletionHandler,
if it doesn't exist you're gonna create it by using
saveToURL. These are both methods in UIMangedDocument
right? Notice that they take, both of them, a closure.
See that? Okay? Why do they take that closure?
That's because the open, or save, happens on another
thread. Why is that? Well, because UIManageDocument is
really awesome. It works great with iCloud for
example, okay? And
so, it might actually make a quick check on the network
to see what the status of this document is. Okay,
you do not want that block in your main queue, okay.
So these things, these closures, get called
after the document has been opened, asynchronously.
Now usually these documents open almost instantaneously,
but you're still going to get them open with this callback
and it tells you whether it was successful in doing it.
Okay? So the fact that this is asynchronous is
gonna make your code a little trickier, okay?
Cuz you wanna open the document and start
using ManagedObjectContext right away, but you can't.
You have to wait until this closure gets called,
then you can start using your ManagedObjectContext, okay?
That's the only trickiness about it. All right, and
it's a little tricky that you have to see if it exists or,
to know whether to open it or to save it. Okay,
when you save it for the first time you're gonna do
forSaveOperation .ForCreating, okay? You can actually save
your document if you want on top of the existing one by
doing forSaveOperation for overriding. Okay.
So it's all asynchronous so be careful about that.
There's other states besides closed and
normal that you might run into. These are pretty rare
states I'm not gonna talk about any of them.
Some of them have Have to do with iCloud,
like in conflict. Remember iCloud let's you see this
document on two different devices, your iPad and
your iPhone, let's say. And you might change it on one and
then try to change it on the other and now they conflict,
the two changes might conflict in the database, right? So
they can be in that state.
I'm not gonna ask you to handle any iCloud or
anything like that for this class,
but you need to know if you're gonna do iCloud.
Then you might have some of these other states cropping
up. I thought it might be a fun thing to do in your final
project. One of the things in your final project you have to
do some feature I didn't go over in lecture.
Well, iCloud might be one of those. So maybe that would be
something you want to do. All right, let's talk about saving
the document, because I got this managed object context.
And I'm going to be getting these in as managed objects,
like tweets and
twitter users aren't going to be changing them.
When does is actually get saved? Okay, and for
UIManagedDocument, it autosaves, which is really
cool. Basically autosaves when it thinks it's a good time, so
you really don't ever have to save a UIManagedDocument.
You can, by doing that ForOverwriting that I was
talking about. But you really don't ever have to do that,
okay? It's just gonna automatically autosave for
you. Closing the document, it also automatically closes,
so as soon nobody has a strong pointer to it and
it wants to leave the heap, it'll close automatically and
then leave the heap. So that's cool too. But if you wanted to
forcible close it and still keep a strong pointer to it,
you could do close with completion handler,
again here's a closure, it takes time for
it to close. Probably micro seconds but anyway this will
tell you when it is actually closed. And then it's state,
document state will go back to dot closed okay.
All right so now we have an NSManagedObjectContext.
We either call that method in our app delegate to get it or
we create new unmanaged document, opened it. And
in the closure once the closure's executed, bam, now
we have this managed object context that we can access our
databases, okay? So, what do we do with it? How do we make
it work, okay? Well, let's talk about putting objects
in the database cuz until we've put something in there,
we can't really do anything else with it.
How do we do that? Well, we create objects
in the database by using this method right here called
InsertNewObjectForEntityForN- ame, okay?
This is a static method, a class method.
In the class NSEntityDescription.
NSEntityDescription is kind of a simple little class,
That just describes the entities okay,
knows what all the properties are and all that.
We only really use it for this one thing which is to create
one of these things in the database okay. But
notice that it takes in managedObjectContext, so
you have to have a managedObjectContext or
you cannot create a new object. Okay now when you
create this document or this object in there,
all of its properties or either nil or you can actually
go in the inspector. In the little visual mapper.
You can set defaults for some of the properties. Okay, so
it's either gonna be the default you set there or
if you didn't set a default, it'll just be nil. Okay, and
remember they're all objects, they're NSNumbers, NSDates,
all these properties. So that'll just be nil, okay. So
this creates one. So now you've got a Tweet, it's of
class, look what its class is, NSManagedObject, right.
Tweet is an NSManagedObject. I just created one, so
I've got an empty Tweet. All it's Properties, it's text and
everything is nil, okay? All right, so
now I've got one of these. How do I set the values?
Okay, well I already told you how to do that,
it's with this set value for key. Right,
so I can do setValue, some string, for key text, and I
can set the text of the Tweet for example, okay? Same thing,
I kept the value for the key. One thing that's kind of cool,
there's also this method called valueForKeyPath, okay?
There's valueForKey and valueForKeyPath and
valueForKeyPath, the string you pass to it can have dots
in it to follow relationships. So, if you said on a Tweet,
valueForKeyPath Tweeter dot name,
it would give you the name of the Twitter user. It would
follow that relationship over to the user and get the name.
Even though I'd be saying valueForKeyPath on a Tweet,
tweeter dot name on a Tweet is followed through
the relationship so that's what the keyPath will do,
got that? Now that sounds exciting I'm sure, but
we actually almost never use these methods and
you'll find out, in a moment why that is, okay.
So that's the key that's the value I already talked about
what all the values are right NSData NSDate,
NSSet if it's a to-many relationship.
An NSManagedObject if it's not, okay?
All right, now changes, when you're changing something
in the database, that only happens in memory, okay?
Doesn't actually get stored in the database on disk until
it saves. Now, we know that UIManagedDocument autosaves,
so we're good to go there. But what if you use that other
ManagedObjectContext? It's not in the UIManagedDocument, so
there's no autosave there. You have to save it, okay. And
you do that with this method called save, you send it to
the ManagedObjectContext, right, so here's that
ManagedObjectContext I got from my app delegate.
And I wanna save it so I'm gonna say contact.save.
Now, that looks simple, right,
simple little four-letter function name there saved. But
actually it's gonna cause me to have to give you two or
three slides worth of information about swift, okay?
Because, this is the method that I'm showing you in this
class that can throw an error, okay?
And why might save throw an error? Eh, disk could be full,
there could be some problem the database that it can't be
saved, there's lots of reasons,
okay that it could so, throw an error, but
what you need to know is how do I deal with that?
Okay, if it throws an error, what do I do,
how do I look at the error, etc. And to do that, you need
to learn about how throw works in Swift. So let's take
a little time out from Core Data, you probably, you're
supposed to read about this in your reading assignment, but
I'm sure it probably went right over your.
How many people in this room feel like yeah,
I pretty much understand throw? See, zero.
Okay, so that's why I'm gonna take a couple slides here and
explain it to you. So all right, this is throwing errors
in Swift, a little side, you know, okay. So any function in
Swift, like the save method in MSManagedObjectContext if
it can throw an error, it will have the word throws,
at the end of its declaration, okay? So, the functions,
you read that when you're reading the closing,
the function save throws, all right?
So, if you have a function that throws,
you must deal with that. You cannot just ignore the fact
that it throws, you must catch the error usually, okay?
There's other ways to deal with it, but
generally you must catch it. So, how do you catch it? Well,
you just put the word try in front of it. The try just
means please try this. Because I know it might throw but
try it. Okay, so that's why it's called try. And if it's
successful fine, if it doesn't then it throws an error.
Now when it throws the error you have to catch it and
the way you catch it is you put this try inside of a do.
See it says do open curly brace closed curly brace?
Anything inside this do that you try that throws,
will allow you to catch the error right after the do,
okay? And so I can take catch let error here,
I can actually catch different kinds of errors by having
multiple catches here. Catch this, catch that, catch this,
as many catches as I want, okay. And
when I catch it you see I have this let error,
that basically lets this local variable here that's gonna be
in this context error, it lets it be equal to the error
that was thrown, okay. So now you have this error and
you, inside here inside this second curly brace here,
you can look at that error and find out what it is and
why clean up or try again or whatever you want to do,
you can do it in here. Now these errors that get thrown
they are all implementors of this protocol ErrorType.
And this ErrorType protocol doesn't have much in it.
It's mostly just a way to identify that this is an error
that got thrown, okay. Now iOS has a very important class
called NSError which implements this protocol.
When iOS throws an error it's always gonna
be an NSError. Okay, and that class you should go look at.
Okay, it has methods in there like localized description of
the error. Things like that that
you can use to put errors up to the user even or certainly
put things on the console to say what's going on or
just to look at it yourself, like what did that error etc.,
okay. So NSError is kind of iOS's thing.
But if you had something that you thought
would be good to throw an error,
you can invent your own thing that gets thrown as long as
it implements this ErrorType protocol,
okay. Now usually the things that implement the ErrorType
protocol are enums. Because when you have something that
can throw an error it usually can throw two or
three different kinds of things. And so
that each of those is an enum case with associated data that
goes along with the error. All right, that's the great thing
about enums, if you've got this associated data so
if there's an error you can, you know, hand along some
interesting information about the error. Okay,
now if inside the catch you can't deal with this error,
you could re-throw it by just saying throw error.
In fact in general anytime you wanna throw an error,
that's how you do it, you say throw error and
again this has to be a type error type protocol there.
You can throw it and re-throw it now,
the only thing about this is if you're gonna re-throw here
maybe then your whole method also has to say throws at
the end, because you might be re-throwing, okay? Okay,
so that's basically how fundamentally works.
Now, there's an extra little interesting thing here which
try with an exclamation point.
Okay, if you try with an exclamation point, that means
forget all this junk. I'm not gonna put in a do.
I'm not gonna catch anything. And if this throws,
crash my app. Okay, we know that exclamation point
usually means force this thing and crash if it doesn't work.
That's what for implicit for Optional unwrapping right,
we do exclamation point boom that means crash if this thing
is nil. So same thing here you can say try and it'll crash.
Now you would never wanna do that with context save because
context save can get errors unpredictably right.
So you never wanna do that here but
other methods sometimes it's like this method has to
succeed or I'm just doomed. So I'm going to
try exclamation point. There's one other way which I'm going
to talk about in a few slides which is try question mark.
Okay? Try question mark means try this, I'm not going to
catch the error, but return nil if there was a thrown
error. Okay? That's right, question mark and I'm gonna
show you an example of that in a couple slides. Okay, so
that's throwing errors. You got that. There's not
a lot of things that throw errors, but
you are gonna run across them. Both in some of the homeworks
and also certainly in your final project. Okay, so let's
get back to core data here. Now, calling valueForKey and
setValue(forKey:) is pretty ugly. Okay,
there's no type-checking there, because it's any object
is the type of the argument. Okay, and
you've got all these literal strings [LAUGH] like text and
created and id inside your code, which
you probably are gonna put in a struct static let like you
do all your constants. But it's just a mess, okay.
What you really want is vars. You want these Tweets,
you wanna be able to have a var on there called text.
And you just wanna say that tweet.text equals,
that's what you want, okay? An object-oriented.
So, of course, we can do that. And the way we do that is
we're gonna create a sub class of ns managed object. Okay? So
for each thing a tweet, Twitter user whatever, we're
gonna create a sub class of ns object managed object for
it and it's gonna have vars which are all the properties.
Okay? Couldn't be easier. Really simply.
And x code will even generate this sub class for
us. Okay, so let's look at how you do that. So I'm
gonna select the entities that I wanna generate these little
sub classes for. Okay, so I'm selecting both in this case
right here. Then I go up to the editor menu and
I pick Create NSManagedObject Subclass. When I do
that it's gonna say okay for which of your models do you
want to do that because you might have multiple models,
so I'll pick the only model I have here.
Then it says okay which entities?
Well, I selected both so it's got these both pre-selected.
I wanna create a menus managed object subclass for tweet and
one for twitter users. It can be two different classes.
Okay now, it's saying where do you wanna put it, it's also
asking what language? Be careful right here sometimes
this comes up Objective-C even if you're in a Swift project.
So make sure that says Swift otherwise you're gonna get an
Objective- C class. Which is a subclass of that's a swift.
The other thing is there's this uscaler properties for
primitive data types. Be careful of this one,
if you turn this on, then for
example NSDate, the property it creates, or the var,
is going to be an NSTime interval.
Which is going to be the number of seconds since 1970,
okay. So you probably don't want that most of the time,
right, you want it to be an NSDate object. Also you're
gonna put it, this is gonna say where you're gonna put it.
By default it usually says to put it at the very top
level, but you usually actually want it down where
all the rest of your files are down here like in core data
example, right?
So make sure you get that right too. So, be,
pay attention to this thing and
answer all these questions the way you want. Okay?
It's not one that you can just click Create and just move on
through or you won't get what you want, I don't think.
All right, so it created these things. Here they are,
you can see them on the side here. There's one,
Tweet.swift, okay? There's TwitterUser.swift.
And it's just a class tweet as promised.
Look at that, it inherits from NSManagedObject, and
you could put any code you want in here to do
tweet specific stuff. Because the fact
that the tweet is stored in the database is great but
it might also have some other behavior that you want to add.
It's just a class, right, you're using it in your app so
you might want to put some code in there, okay, so
it's perfectly good for that. Here's TwitterUser,
right Okay, put all your Twitter user stuff here. But
what about those vars? Okay,
I thought there was going to be vars for text and
created and the screen name for, where are those? Well,
it turns out those are put in extensions, you see them right
here, there's two of them, that one and that one, so
let's look at those, okay. This file right here,
this extension. This is creating a property of R for
each of the things, the attributes and
relationships to in my Tweet object.
Now, why does it put them off in an extension here? Why
didn't it just put it in the other class? Can anyone think
of a reason why this would be an extension? It's a good
reason actually which is that, you might wanna change these
attributes in relationship over time that you're working
on your app. You decide you need a new property, okay?
Well you gonna regenerate this file. When you do that, you
don't wanna blow away in the other code that you wrote for
tweet. Right, so it keeps all the stuff that's being
generated by x code when you do that create subclass,
it's keeping it all in one file so it can be constantly
overwritten. Make sense? See, that's why we put an extension
there. Now lets look at this wacky extension here,
what's going on here? Well these are obvious,
text, ID and created, why are they optional? Because they're
nil when you first create a tweet it's empty those things
are all nil so it has to be an optional, and then look at
this one. Tweeter has promised again twitter users.
Now I told you that tweeter since it's a relationship
would be an NS managed object But the system is smart enough
to say, well not only is it an NSManaged object,
but I know it's a TwitterUser. Okay,
which is this other class over here that it created.
By the way, sometimes when you generate a whole
bunch of things at once, it will miss that. Okay,
it will notice, it will just have this NSManaged object,
just regenerate them again if that happens. Okay?
It's just like, cause it's like a one,
instead of being a two phase generation, it's like a one
phase generation; if it does one class before the other.
It didn't know that twitter user existed by the time it
did tweet. So, I don't know, hopefully they'll fix that
someday. Might already be fixed in the latest version,
but just regenerate if you get that problem. So
anyway, Tweeter is a Twitter user,
that makes sense, right? That's what a Tweeter is,
it's a Twitter user. Let's go look at Tweet,
it's the same thing here. Here's the screen name and
the name, those are string. Now look at tweets,
it's an NS set and inside this NS set is going to be,
what? Tweet objects, right because that's what this is,
the Tweets that this Twitter user has Tweeted. So
this NS set is gonna have Tweet, Tweet objects.
See this class right up here. Okay,
now what about this @NSManaged thing? What the heck,
we never seen that before. What is that?
Okay, well, that's basically just some magic that says
the system is gonna take of that, of this bar, okay?
Because otherwise, where is this bar stored?
It can't just be a normal stored property because
when it changes, it needs to change in the database, so
it's got to be code going on there.
It kind of could be a computer property but you certainly
don't want the computer property code in here. So,
this NSManage basically says that it's a dynamic, bar and
when it gets accessed it causes other code in core data
to be executed.
And that's basically going to do value and value for key and
set value for key for you. Yeah.
>> A name like "TwitterUser",
would it change every time >> [INAUDIBLE] Yeah, so
the question is what if I change the key like like
if I rename screen name to be an ampersand name or
something like that. No, you have to go back and
regenerate them okay they will always have to regenerate.
This is not captain sync with the visual map you have to
regenerate all the time. Again that's why you want this to be
a separate file from the other thing.
Okay, so ns manage is just magic that core data uses.
You don't even have to worry about it, you're never gonna
have to actually type this in or anything.
It's always just in this generated thing. Okay, so,
how do I access these entities using these sub classes and
get the properties. Okay, so, it's pretty simple.
Let's say I get my manage of the context.
Here, I'm getting it from my UI managed document,
but I could have got it from my app delegate, whatever,
I got my context.
I'm gonna create one by saying insert new object for
a different name, same as before. Except for
look at the yellow text, I'm gonna cast it, downcast it
to be a tweet. Because I know that these tweet entities have
this associated subclass with them. Got it? So that's
the magic right there. That's the thing that turns this
Tweet that you're creating into a tweet so that now
that it's a tweet you can say things like tweet.tweeter = or
tweet.created = or tweet.text =, tweet.tweeter.name =,
you can even do. Okay, see what's happened here?
Tweet.tweeter.name.
I'm actually just using properties. To go through,
we know the type of Tweeter is a Twitter user, and
we know the twitter user has a bar which is the name.
So, this is a lot nicer than saying set value, this,
comma, for key, text.
Swift code, and also Swift can type check all of this to make
sure you're providing the right types, all right? Okay,
so now let's talk about deletion briefly.
You can delete objects from the database. It's very easy,
it's almost too easy. You just call deleteObject, okay?
And it will delete from the database.
There's a little bit of a question, if I delete a tweet,
does it delete the Twitter user who tweeted it?
Probably not. If I delete a Twitter user, does it delete
all the tweets that the Twitter user tweeted? Maybe
so, okay? So you can determine that rule for what happens
when something is deleted back in the Visual Mapper. You just
inspect the relationship and you can put the delete rule in
there. You can read all about what the settings are,
in the documentation. But you can basically have cascading
deletes that delete, like that's probably what
you would have if you deleted a Twitter user.
It would cascade and
delete all the tweets. And you can have just a nilling one,
where if you deleted a certain tweet, it's just going to
remove it from the set, and the Twitter user's set will be
automatically updated, okay? One thing, once you delete
this tweet, make sure you don't keep a strong pointer to
it because it now points to something that's invalid.
Cuz you deleted it from the database so you can't set any
of its attributes or do anything cuz it's gone.
So it kinda gets into a weird state here [COUGH].
Just make sure you don't do anything with that. All right,
one thing that's kind of fun about deletion here is that
your NsMangedObject subclass like tweet or
TwitterUser will be sent this method, prepareForDeletion,
when someone tries to delete it, and in there you can
do a lot of things. You could decrement some count for
example if you're keeping a track of a count or
something like that. One thing you don't have to do in here
though is modify in a relationships.
That happens for you automatically.
So if I delete a tweet k? From the database, it automatically
gets removed from any ns sets that Twitter users point to,
even if I go into an NS set, okay, of tweets and
I delete a tweet out of there, it will [INAUDIBLE] you know,
any, both sides of every relationship get updated. So
you never have to update either side of a relationship.
You touch one, the other side stays in synch.
That's one of the really cool things about core data. So
you don't have to do that in a prepare for
deletion. Prepare for deletion lets you do other things,
other things you might be counting or
doing other things.
So now we know how to create our database, set all the data
in there, it's awesome. Now we get to the real value of
having the data in there which is querying, okay. So
now we wanna go and look in the database and
get the objects we want based on certain criteria, okay. And
how do we do that? The main
Piece of this is this class called NSFETCH request,
okay? And in NSFETCH request we're going to specify
which objects we want out of the database, and
they're going to come back in an array, it's as simple as
that, okay? So, how do we create an NSFETCH request?
We need four things. One, the entity to fetch.
This is very important to understand. Okay. You can only
fetch one kind of thing with a fetch request. There's no
fetch request in the world that's gonna give you an array
of some tweets and some Twitter users.
It's always gonna give you an array of all the same thing,
all tweets, or all Twitter users. Okay?
So, you specify the entity, the one entity that's going to
be in this fetch request. All right? Second thing is
how many objects you want to limit your fetch to,
like maybe you only want to fetch 100 or
you want to fetch them in groups of 20 or 40 or
something like that. You can specify that in the request.
You can specify how to sort the result because I told you
the result comes back as an array, arrays are ordered. So
you can specify what order the things you're fetching come
back in. All right? And then lastly and most importantly,
you're gonna specify the predicate.
This is the description of which objects you want. Okay?
So, let's look at all of this things. Here's what the code
looks like. Basically to create a request right here.
So, let's look at all parts of this.
So, we're creating a request for
the certain entity. Here I'm saying the BatchSize and
fetchLimits and then the sortDescriptors and
predicate, we'll talk about it in the next slide.
So the batch size of 20 here, just means that when I fetch
it's gonna look like it returns all the objects, but
it's actually only fetch them at 20 at a time.
This is really great for things like table views,
where you know the person's scrolling through it, so
you don't wanna fetch all million item.
You know that you can fetch them in batches as they go
along. Okay. We're gonna talk a little bit about another
important thing called faulting, which it so you can
have a million items on the table and it's still pretty
lightweight even if you don't set a batch limit but you can.
Also you might have something where there's thousands of
objects but maybe your UI can only show a hundred,
it's just the maximum you can show.
Well then you can say only give me the first hundred.
Okay that's also Allowed. Alright so
let's talk about the two most important ones,
you don't really use these very much, but
the sortdescriptor and
the predicate you are going to use a lot.
Let's talk about those in detail. The sortdescriptor is,
is an array of descriptions of things to sort by.
Okay? And it's gonna use those sort by things
to sort the things that come out of the array, or
come out of the database when it puts them
in the array. Okay? So here's what it's like to create
a sort descriptor. It has a few different initializers,
but here's kind of one of it's most, verbose ones.
First is the key that you're going to be sorting by. So
if I'm looking for Twitter users, I might want the array
to come back sorted by the screen name, okay, at sign,
whatever. Okay, I wanna sort it so
I would create a descriptor where the key is screenName,
cuz that's what I want it to sort by.
Ascending is whether it's you know the @ sign
A people come first or the @ sign Z people come first
right? So [INAUDIBLE] is it an ascending list or a descending
list? And then this selector which is usually optional,
you don't usually need it, is interesting.
It's basically something that just says, how do I sort?
These strings, okay? Do I just sort them alphabetically?
Well, what does it mean to sort alphabetically? Okay,
this localized standard compare means
alphabetically in the way that people are used to seeing it
in the finder on the Mac, basically, so it's kind of
like user-sensible alphabetical order.
Okay, there's other alphabetical orders that
are more like strict alphabet order.
But maybe they don't deal with diacritics, you know?
They don't look, they don't sort diacritics properly,
things like, or capitalization they might not do right. So
this is a good one. And this is the default, so
you probably don't need to put this in here. But
this can basically be, if this is a string, okay,
if screenName is a string, which it is, then this can be,
any string method. Now there are some string methods that
are magic and are actually done on the database side.
So they're super efficient, okay. And
you can read the documentation to find out which ones.
This is definitely one of them. Okay, so
this method is not actually being called on every single
screen name in the database. You know, in other words, it,
it's not fetching them calling that method,
fetching the next one, calling it, comparing them,
trying to sort it. No, this is happening in the database.
Okay, the database knows how to do the sort. All right, so
that's the sort descriptor. Now, notice that, we,
when we create our fetch request,
we actually provide an array of sort descriptors.
We don't just give one sort descriptor, we do an array.
Why would we need an array?
Well, sometimes you, maybe you're searching for names,
people by name, and you wanna search by last name first and
then by first name, right, the common thing to do. So
you can give an array of sort descriptors.
The first sort descriptor is the last name sort descriptor,
and the second one is the first name sort descriptor,
okay? That's why it's an array. All right, now,
NSPredicate, the real gut of how we do all this.
The predicate is a really flexible object, okay, you,
this is one where you really have to go read NSPredicate
documentation. Okay, it would take me, I could have a whole
lecture on all of the things NSPredicate can do.
The format of NSPredicate is NSPredicate is basically you
have a constructor here, an initializer,
which takes a format string, like this, with little percent
at signs in it that you put then at the end.
See, here's two %@ signs, you put them at the end, joe and
aDate, right? And these values get put into this spot.
It's like printdef, okay, you all know printdef.
It's, who, who doesn't, does everyone know, who,
if you don't know what printdef is,
raise your hand. Okay, so
everyone knows what printdef is, just like printdef,
in that way. But of course, this is, has meaning, okay,
meaning in terms of what you can search in the database.
So, here's just some examples. Here, for example,
I'm searching the database to find all the tweet,
these are all searches for tweets by the way,
all these things you're seeing right here,
searches for tweets. So here I'm trying to find a tweet
whose text contains case insensitively,
that's what that square bracket [c] means, this text,
and the text is the search string, okay? So I have some
search string, I'm trying to find all the tweets, that,
contain that text, okay? Or here's another one down here,
I wanna find all the tweets that were tweeted by Joe and
were created before or after some date, aDate right there.
See that? And then here is, an interesting one,
I'm saying give me all the tweets, not Twitter users,
tweets whose Twitter screen name is CS193p. So
this is all of CS19 p's tweets,
okay? So even though this says tweeter.screenName,
this is a tweet query. You see that?
Okay, now here's interesting, th, this is only the tip of
the iceberg, you can do some pretty powerful things. Here,
for example, I'm doing a tweet u,
TwitterUser request down here at the bottom, and
I'm trying to find all the Twitter users that have tweets
that contain the search string, okay? So
that's pretty powerful, since tweets is a too many
relationship, but it can do that. All right, so you gotta
read up on NSPredicate to know what you can do.
In your homework, I'm gonna ask you to do something
pretty straightforward. So don't worry too much,
but you're gonna need to not skip the step of going and
reading this. You can also make compound predicates.
Basically, you have this NSCompoundPredicate.
You can make an AND predicate or an OR predicate. And
you just give it an alid, an array of other predicates,
and you'll AND them together.
Now you don't need to do that because you could put OR and
AND in the predicate string. But sometimes,
you wanna like calculate which ones you want, okay,
you will by some if thens or something, you wanna decide
which ones are there, and so this is a good way to AND
them together. All right, or and or or. Okay, I'm
not really gonna talk about this whole slide actually,
advanced querying, but there are some kind of weird little,
things you can put in your predicate, like @average,
which will assume that this is returning an array, and it'll
average all of these keys in that array. Okay, so here for
example, I have tweets.tweet, I'm basically looking at all
of the tweets that this Twitter user has tweeted.
And I'm averaging the latitude,
assuming they had a latitude and longitude on the tweet.
I'm averaging the latitude to find the average latitude at
which someone tweets. Okay, that's kinda weird,
but you can do that. So same thing with counts, okay?
Now you're seeing counts here, but in, in your homework,
you're gonna be asked to do a count, but not with this.
Okay, this won't work for
the kind of counting I'm asking you to do.
You're just gonna have to have code that counts for that.
Okay, so don't get confused by this.
Do not use @count in your homework, all right. And
down here, it's talking about this class NSExpression,
which lets you create these arbitrary expressions to
search for. Again, I'm not gonna talk about it,
you don't need to do it for your homework.
You can certainly take a look at the class NSExpression.
It's pretty amazing what's in there. Okay, all right, so
let's put this all together, all this querying business,
so I'm gonna create this fetch request for
a Twitter user. Okay, I wanna have all the tweets
that this Twitter user has created in the last 24 hours.
So how do I do that? Okay, I'm gonna fetch into, actually
I know I'm gonna create all the, sorry, be clear here.
I'm fetching all the Twitter users who have tweeted in
the last 24 hours. Okay, so I'm fetching Twitter users.
So that's my entity, I'm gonna create the time yesterday,
which is just the time interval since now of minus 24
hours. This is in seconds, okay?
Then I'm gonna create the predicate,
which is any tweets that were created after yesterday,
24 hours ago, okay? See that predicate? Pretty fun. And
then I'm gonna sort the result by the name of the Twitter
user, not a screen name, but the actual name.
And ascending is true, so
I want the As at the beginning and the Zs at the end, okay?
So this, I create this request. Now I have request,
how do I get the array, which is all of these things, okay?
We do that with a method in your managedObjectContext.
I told you you need a managedObjectContext for
everything, and you do, creating, and
also for fetching. You're gonna use this method in your
context called executeFetchRequest, and
you just give it the NSFetchRequest.
It returns an NSArray, okay, or an array,
a bridge to an array, okay, of all the things.
Now if that array is empty, not nil,
but empty, that means nothing matches your request.
There's nothing in the database that matched that.
In other words, in the, using the previous slide, there
are no Twitter users who have tweeted in the last 24 hours.
That's empty array. Otherwise it's gonna return a sorted
array of all the Twitter users, sorted by their name,
who have tweeted in the last 24 hours. Okay?
And the objects in there, in that array,
will be Twitter user, instances of Twitter user.
Okay, cuz that's what I searched for.
Now notice that I have to try, okay, context try, okay,
that's because this method throws. Now, if this throws,
it probably means there£s some problem with your database.
Okay? Like maybe your database is not opened, maybe tried to
send this to a UI managed object manage documents
context and you never opened it, so it£s not open or
something like that. You could ignore the throw, by doing
tri question mark. The thing that tri question mark does
that you have to realize is, it turns whatever this is,
this method call. Whatever it returns, it turns it into
an optional. So execute fetch request returns an NS array,
or an array. So, by putting tri question mark, it makes
this now return an optional array. And why is that?
That's because if it throws it's gonna return nill. Okay?
So it's a little funky to realize this but
this just gonna turn this into an optional array, and so
let users, users right there, is going to be of type,
optional array. Okay optional array of And
his managed object actually, to be exact. All right so
a lot of times we do do try question mark here because we
don't really know what to do to handle an error so if we do
a fetch and it comes back nil, and there was some problem,
it's kind of like [SOUND] we're reporting error
to the user or something but it's not like much we can do.
Okay, so sometimes, this is a case where we might do try
question mark there. Okay, so that's it, very simple and
now you have the array of objects back,
you can do whatever you want with them.
I want to talk a little about performance. What if you had
a million objects and you said show me all the Twitter user,
a million tweets or something or a million Twitter users and
you said, show me all the Twitter users that tweeted in
the last 24 hours. And there were 750, or 7,000 of them.
Are you really gonna get an array with 7,000 objects
all of, each of which has a screen name and the name and
whatever else it. I mean, that would be massive, right.
And the answer is no, you don't get that.
You get this kind of magical thing which is an array of
husks of those objects if you want to think of it that way.
So they're not really there and
in fact if you tried to print them, if you used print to
print them, it would just say this is an NS managed object,
it wouldn't show you the screen name or the name or
anything else about it because it doesn't actually pull that
data Until you ask for it. Until you ask specifically for
a Twitter user's name or his screen name.
It doesn't get that out of the database.
This is called faulting. The objects live in this kind of
husk state where they don't actually have their data. And
when you ask for them the data gets faulted in. Now when that
faulting happens, it might be happening in big bunches,
because it might be more efficient for
the database to fault in a hundred at a time. Okay? But
it's all happening behind the scenes.
The only reason I even mention it is because you might be
trying to print these things out, and you're like, what?
Where's my name and screen name? Okay? And you'll know
why it's because it's not been faulted yet. Okay? So
if you really want the name or screen name, you want,
you have to .name so it faults it in, and can see it. Okay?
All right let's talk about thread safety with core data.
Okay, NSManagedObjectContext is not thread safe. So
you cannot have a context fork off some
closure on another thread with dispatch and
access it. Okay? So that sounds really bad. Because
a database you can imagine I'd want to have another thread
doing some heavy intensive database thing.
Like loading the database up or
doing some complicated queries or something like that.
And you're telling me I can't do it?
Because it's not thread same? Well no of course you can do
it. And the way you have to do it is ns managed object each
NSManagedObejct instance has to have its own thread. Okay.
Now, the cool thing is you can have multiple
NSManagedObjectContext on the same database. Okay? So, how
does that work? So, you have this NSManagedObjectContext.
It's writing into the database.
When you hit save that save goes out to the database and
other ManagedObjectContext will start seeing it. Okay?
When they do fetches they'll see it.
So it basically works through the saves.
When you save through one context boom the other ones
start seeing it. Automatically as soon as they, next time
they fetch they're gonna automatically see it. Okay, so
it's really kind of cool that it just uses threads,
okay, queues, to do this.
Now that does mean that the cues to use them on, they have
to be serial queues, can't have concurrent queues because
then you'd have one manage object in different threads,
because a concurrent queue can fire off multiple threads to
go execute its little blocks. All right?
So it has to be serial queue. Now the kind of,
NSMangedObjectContext that you get by doing that app delegate
thing and the one you get from doing UI manage documents,
those are both main cue in this managed object context.
It could only be used in the main cue so don't ever like,
fork those off and start using those on another queue.
Now you can create your own NSManagedObjectContext on
other queues if you want. There's an initializer for it.
I'm not really gonna talk about that.
You're not gonna need to do that for this class.
But that's how you would do concurrency, okay?
Now when you have, because of this, because
you can have this multiple context, you gotta know about
this method right here, performBlock.
Very important method in manage ManageObjectContext.
And it basically takes a closure here. Closure that
take no arguments, returns nothing, and inside this block
you always know with 100% certainty whatever code you're
executing in here is going to be performed on this context,
safe queue. Okay, the queue that it was created on,
the queue that it's running on,
the queue that won't cause any problems, always.
Okay, so really anytime you do anything with core data
any time you access an NSManagedObjectContext,
or any of the NSManagedObjects you get out of it, you want to
do it inside a performBlock. Did you hear what I just said?
I'm going to say it again. performBlock wants to be
wrapped around every access to any NSManagedObjectContext or
NSManagedObject of any kind. Okay. Now
in your homework you're only ever gonna have one context or
you might say what a waste. Why do you put these
stupid perform blocks around everything?
I know everything's in the main context.
Well the answer you'll want to get used to doing this.
Okay? Because maybe down the road you do add another thread
that loads up the database with more tweets or
something like that and also, it starts breaking if
you're not performing things on the right context, okay.
So just get in the habit of doing this.
So you can also perform block and wait, which will cause
this code to be executed on the safe queue and
wait till it's done and then continue on this queue, okay.
So you can do that as well. So, always wrap perform block
around anything you do in core data.
All right? Quick thing on the parent context. Most context,
most management contexts have a parentContext, all right?
That parentContext is either the context that actually
writing it to the database, or in some cases, it's another,
and it's may context. So that when you save, it's actually
saving to another context, and then that context saves again.
UI manage document works this way.
Okay, and what's kinda cool is that that parent context is
almost always on a different queue.
So if you're using UI managed documents you can actually
do a little trick which is if you wanna run something for
that database on another queue just performBlock
on the parentContext.
ParentContext is just a method in ManagedObject context,
right or for a property. Just do performBlock on that.
Now you'll be performing it on a different queue off the main
queue, okay. And it'll be in that database.
Everything will be fine so it's kind of a trick.
Okay, again, you won't need that for your assignment,
but just understand that you can do that.
All right, so there's so much more to Core Data, no wait,
I mean we've already been here an hour so and barely covered
the basics. So there's optimistic locking in there,
it has full Undo/Redo which is incredible. Specify thing like
staleness, you know, when I have to refetch this thing,
how much time goes by before I have to refetch.
All that stuff. You have to go look at the documentation for
NS Managed Object Context. Okay, that's really the core
of where this stuff is all happening.
Eh, to find out more about it. Again,
I'm not gonna ask you to do any of this for
your homework but you gotta know that it's out there or
when you get in the real world and
start doing this you'll be missing opportunities to do
cool features. All right, the last thing I wanna talk about
is the interrelationship between Core Data and
UITableView. As you can imagine,
if you got this huge database of stuff,
a great place to show it is in a TableView. Okay, in fact,
99% of the time, either a TableView or a CollectionView
is how you're gonna show the stuff in a big database, okay.
And that's so common that iOS provides this awesome class
NSFetchedResultsController okay, which is a call which
will hook up an NSFetchRequest to a UITableView.
And not just hook it up once but hook it up so that if
the database changes in any way that the FetchRequest
would return different results it updates the table. Okay, so
the database can be changing behind the scenes.
The table is just always staying in sync with it.
So that fetch request and
that table are always in sync, okay, which is really,
really cool. Okay, it makes it really easy for
you to implement your table views with stuff
out of the database. Okay, so
how do you use this NSFetch, FetchedResultsController?
Well, first of all, let's talk about how,
how FetchResultsController actually works.
It's very simple. It provides methods to implement all those
UITableView delegate methods like number of sections and
tables, number of rows and sections. The only one it
doesn't implement is self row and index path.
You still have to implement that. Because of course,
self row and index path knows about, you know, the custom UI
cells or whatever, so, you have to be the one who's
putting that data on screen in the right way. But in terms of
all the other, things in the UITableView data source
even things like section hea- headers and all that stuff,
NSFetchedResultsController will do all that for you.
It has methods to implement all those things.
So here's a couple examples for what it looks like here.
Okay? The other thing you can do, which is kinda cool,
well, I'll talk about that in a second. Let's talk about
cellForRowAtIndexPath, since you're responsible for
im- implementing that. The key method you need to know from
FetchedResultsController is object and
index path, okay. This is a method that you can send
to it. You give it an index path into the table and
it will return you the NSManagedObject at that row.
Okay, now this might be a subclass of NSManagedObject
like Tweet or Twitter User, but
it's gonna return it to you so in your cellForRowAtIndexPath,
you're gonna call this, okay, of this index path
to get the object that's at that row and then you're gonna
use that object to fill out the information in that row.
Okay, that's what cellForRowAtIndexPath does.
Everyone understand this? Super important you understand
this cuz otherwise, you'll be like, how do I, okay,
cellForRowAtIndexPath? This is how you do it. Okay. So
this FetchedResultsController is probably gonna be a var in
your UITableViewController. Okay, that you're going to
have created with a fetched results, with the NS fetched
request. And then with your cellForRowAtIndexPath you're
gonna find out each of the things that are in
the database that match your fetch. One per row, and
this is gonna return it. Okay? All right, so how do we create
an NSFetchedResultsController by the way? All you do,
really all you have to do is create that NS fetch request
that's it, okay? So for example
here I'm going to create a FetchResultsController.
You can see that its initializer takes the fetch
request. Obviously the context, and
then this is kind of a cool thing, the sectionNameKeyPath,
if all of the objects in your database, okay,
know the section they should be in, they have some key in
there that is the section they're supposed to be in.
Then you can specify that sec that key right here and it'll
automatically do the sections for you. Okay. The only
thing is you gotta make sure you sort the result of your
fetched sort in the same order as those sections sort. But
it'll do that for you. And then there's cache right here.
It'll actually cache the results on disk, okay.
So if you have a really complicated fetch that might
take a lot of resources, it will cache the result.
The only thing about this is you cannot change the request.
The data can be changing all the time but
the request itself, the predicate and
the source scrubbers has to be the same.
If you ever change it,
then this cache obviously becomes kinda useless. All
right, so how would we create a FetchResultsController doing
this? I'm gonna create the request. So like I'm gonna
fetch Tweets here. I'm gonna put Tweets in my TableView.
So each row of my TableView is gonna be a different Tweet.
I'm gonna sort by the created so
the newer tweets maybe are gonna be at the beginning.
Ad then my predicate is going to be all Tweeters who
whose Tweeter's name equals a certain name.
So I'm looking for all the tweets by a certain tweeter
who has a certain name, okay.
And when it gets this result, each row in my TableView
is going to be that tweet that matches. Okay? And
FetchResultsController's gonna make sure that's always true,
even if I added in another tweet to the database
that matched it, the TableView would
add in another row at the bottom automatically.
Okay, yeah I talked about the cacheName. And yeah, this key
that says which attribute is the section name has to sort
in the same order as the sort descripter. Sort descripters.
Okay, all right. The FetchResultsController also
while it's watching the database, okay, the, well,
I told you it watches the database and
keeps them in sync.
The way it does that is it has a delegate,
the FetchResultsController has a delegate, okay?
So here's one of its delegate methods.
Controller did change object and
index paths forChangeType: newIndexPath. Okay, here,
see how it's basically noticing the database change,
telling you what changed, tell you what index paths changed
in the TableView. It's basically telling you exactly
what to do cuz the database changed. Now in here you're
supposed to call all the UI TableView methods that will be
appropriate to cause this to update the table, okay.
Insert a row, put something there, whatever, delete a row,
all that. Well,
now you're probably starting to think hey I thought
this NSFetchResultsController was supposed to be easy. But
I gotta implement all this? In here? For
all these delegate methods, eh that's just too hard. Okay,
well lucky for you, we're gonna provide a class for
you called CoreDataTableViewController,
something we wrote that does all that for you. Okay, this,
all that stuff it does for you, you can actually see all
that in the documentation for NSFetchResultsController right
at the top. It actually shows you the code
that you want to use.
Unfortunately it's in Objective-C, so
we've written it all in Swift for
you, and provided this class CoreDataTableViewController so
you're just going to make this TableViewController be your
subclass or your super class of your TableViewController so
that you'll inherit all this NSFetchResultsController
functionality. And
all you need to do to make it work is, it has a var, this
CoreDataTableViewController only has one public thing
which is a var which is a FetchResultsController,
you just need to create this FetchResultsController
which means creating the NSFetchResult fetch request,
and then set this var.
And once you set this var, it's automatically going to
start updating your table. Okay now of course you're
gonna have to implement cellForRowAtIndexPath,
because you gotta load up your thing however you're gonna
load it up. But that's all you have to do.
cellForRowAtIndexPath, set this var, you're winning.
Okay. Now that's it for Core Data. Remember that
Assignment Four has nothing to do with Core Data. Okay.
So do not do anything with Core Data in Assignment Four.
Assignment Five is gonna be a lot of core data.
Okay. So I mean I have to teach you this
stuff before I give it to you, like I did for Assignment
Four, but then I have to teach you the stuff for
the next thing and sometimes people get confused and they
think the thing I'm teaching now goes into the assignment
that went out a couple days ago, but no. Okay so, A4,
Assignment Four, no Core Data. A5, all Core Data basically.
Okay, so next day, week I'll do a demo on this, okay?
On Monday I'm gonna do a big old demo where
we're gonna do all of the stuff I talked about today, so
you can see how it all works in action as always. And
then you'll have A5 go out that's on Monday, and
that's gonna be due the next Monday. On Wednesday, I'm
gonna do Auto Layout because I've kind of been hinting at
Auto Layout, showing you a little bit here and
there but now I'm gonna talk about really how
Auto Layout works to lay out you're, user interface.
You can use stack view for a lot of things but sometimes
you need a little bit of extra layout capabilities and
next week I'm also gonna talk about the requirements for
your final project, okay? What you are required to do
to have a successful final project.
And, so it's time, now, for you to start thinking a little
bit about what you might want to do for a final project. And
certainly, as soon as I give this lecture next week
on final project requirements, right away you're gonna wanna
nail down what you want to do because you only get three
weeks to do it so that only gives you a week or so to
think of what you want to do. Okay? So be ready to kinda go
outta the gate with that next week. Okay, that's it!
I will see you next week. >> For
more, please visit us at Stanford.edu.