[MUSIC]
Stanford University. >> All right.
Welcome to Lecture Number 11 of CS193P, the Spring of 2016.
Today it's all demo, okay. All demo all the time. We're gonna
do a core data demo. And just to let you know what's coming
up since I, cuz I won't come back to the slides obviously.
On Wednesday, we'll be talking about Auto Layout, and also,
we'll be talking about the final project requirements on
Wednesday, okay? No Friday section this week.
And then, next week, we'll start talking about animation.
You have an assignment that's out now which is Number Five.
Which is a core data assignment. And
then there will be Assignment Six which will be an animation
assignment which will probably go out next Monday and
due the Monday after maybe next Wednesday,
due the Wednesday after. I'm not sure, but
probably next Monday and then that'll be your last
assignment before the final project. Okay. All right,
so let's talk about this core data demo that we're gonna do.
We're gonna continue with Smashtag,
leave off where we were before. Okay so here's
the user interface that we had at the end of Lecture Nine.
And you're probably very familiar with it because your
homework builds on this. And
we're gonna build on this as well with this core data demo.
What I'm gonna do is add another, table view
controller, here. In fact let's just drag it out.
So here it is. And I'm going to segue to this table
view controller from a bar button item in this existing
table view controller. Which is a little different,
like in your homework you're segueing from the row.
Here I'm actually gonna segue from a little bar button item.
Now most of you have figured
out that if you wanna add a button to the navigation bar
up here you can't use this regular button that's up here.
You have to use these bar buttons that are down towards
the bottom. Here's one right here, a bar button item so
you're just gonna drag it out and see if you drag it up at,
up at top of a navigation bar, then it'll jump in there. And,
what we're gonna have this UI do is, I'm gonna call
this button Tweeters, and we're gonna have this MVC,
this new one we're gonna write today, it's
gonna show a list of all the tweeters who tweeted a tweet
that we've ever downloaded with the search term that's in
this MBC. Right? Our main MBC. So we type #Stanford here and
search for some tweets and then we hit Tweeters.
Over here, we would see a list of all the Twitter users who
tweeted those tweets with #Stanford in there.
Okay, not just in the most, latest search of #Stanford,
but ever. And we're gonna do this by having us
coordinate a database where every time we get a tweet,
we're gonna put it in the database, okay?
And so, we then, we can query those tweets and
get all the information we want,
including getting a list of the users who have tweeted. So
of course we will need a custom subclass of UITableView
for this guy, so let's go ahead and create that. File,
New File as usual, iOS source,
it's a Cocoa Touch class. It's a UITableView controller also.
We'll call this our Tweeter's TableView controller,
cuz that's what's gonna be in here,
tweeters. We'll put it in the same group we put all the rest
of our stuff there. Okay, here's our tweeters.
We're not actually going to keep any of this except,
actually I'll keep myself a row and index path here. But
we'll get rid of the rest of this boiler plate that we get.
Okay, there's our tweeters table view
controller. And we always want to make sure we go back into
our storyboard and set with the identity inspector this to
be our tweeter's table view controller.
This guy right here. And
let's go ahead and wire up this segue right here too.
I'm just gonna select this guy and control drag over to here.
We're in a navigation controller so
we won't show if we were in a split view,
we'd be show detail maybe but
here we're in navigation se we're gonna show.
Here's our segue, let's give it an identifier, we'll call
this the tweeter's, we'll make this very verbose,
Tweeters Mentioning Search Term segue. Okay, so
that's what this segue does. When you click tweeters,
it shows you all the tweeters that mention this particular
search term whatever that'll be that be, #Stanford or
whatever. Okay. So that's pretty much setup our UI right
there. One thing that we need here is core data, we wanna be
able to access a core data database, so
we need that manage object context,
remember that's the hook that let's us in there.
And I've told you there is two ways to do that,
one is UI manage document, I'm not gonna demo that,
that's extra credit by the way in Assignment Number Five,
if you wanna try and tackle that.
Only thing difficult about that is the asynchronous stuff
but if you're got it comfortable now with
asynchrony, it shouldn't be very difficult at all.
The other way was to use code that would get generated for
you when you create a new project and
turn on the core data button and that's what I'm gonna use.
We started this project and if we look in our app delegate
Okay? This is Smashtags, AppDelegate here.
You can see that it's got some empty methods in here,
basically with some comments about them.
We'll be covering this stuff, by the way.
This is part of what we call the Application Life Cycle,
these methods. But there's nothing in here about core
data because, when we created Smashtag, we didn't
think we were building a core data app at that time,
so we didn't switch that button. So no problem though,
I'm just gonna create a new project. Go to File, New,
Project. Okay, and again, iOS application, single view like
we usually do, and you can call it anything you want.
I'm gonna call mine Foo, okay. And just make sure that this
button right here is switched, Use Core Data, okay, and
probably also wanna make sure it's Swift unless you're
building something Objective C.
And then when you click Next put it anywhere you want.
I'll put mine in my same place as always developer here.
And it makes this Foo, now this Foo is just a blank
app right? It's got a blank view controller here.
But we don't care about any of that.
All we care about is in its app delegate, we look
down it's got all those same methods but starting here,
Core Data stack it's got a whole bunch of other code,
okay. And we just basically want to pick this code up.
So I'm just going to select it all, okay.
Starting from this Mark Core Data stack going down to
the end. And I'm just gonna cut it out of here.
Copy or cut it. And I'm gonna go to my AppDelegate back in
Smashtag here. And I'm just going to paste it in.
Okay. Now it's not quite that easy there's two more things
we gotta think about. You can see there are errors here.
Okay there's an error there, error here.
That's because Core Data is in a separate framework just like
the Twitter stuff you had is in a separate framework, so
is Core Data. So you have to,
at the top, anywhere you're going to be using Core Data,
say import CoreData. Okay? So that'll get rid
of all of our errors okay,
because of the types like in this manage object model, and
in this persistent core coordinator, things like that.
But there's one more thing we have to be careful of here.
And, you're really going to want to be careful of this
in your homework assignment, which is that,
this code that gets generated, it actually uses the name of
the app as the name of the data model. You know, you know
that visual map we're gonna make with all the entities and
attributes? Things I showed you in the slides.
It calls that thing the name of the app so, in this case,
Foo, because that's what I called that other app.
So you're gonna wanna change this to whatever you're
gonna call your mapping model and
you get to choose, so you can pick anything you want.
The default happens to be Model, okay, but you could
also put the name of your app or whatever you want in here.
Just make sure that whatever you put in here Is the same
thing as the name you pick when you create the mapping
okay, which we're gonna do next. Okay, so that's it.
So once you do that you're gonna get a few vars in here
but the main one that's Import here is this one.
Manage object context, so that's the thing,
that's the hook that you're gonna get into your database,
right. Okay, so let's go ahead and create the schema for
that database. And we do that with File > New > File. But
here instead of doing iOS source,
we're gonna go down to iOS Core Data. Okay? And
in here there's three things. And this is the one you want,
Data Model, cuz that's what we're gonna be doing,
that's our description of raw enti, entities and attributes,
our Data Model. Don't accidentally pick
Mapping Model. It sounds similar, but it's different,
okay? So Data Model's what you want.
So we'll double-click on that. Okay, you're gonna get this,
so you can see the default is Model. Just make sure this is
the same as whatever you put in your app delegate,
that code that you copied in and, make sure you put it
where you want. Like, I really don't want this in supporting
files or I don't want it down here in supporting files,
I want it up at a higher level here at the smash tag level,
okay? So let me put that there, hit Create and
it creates this empty map, okay. It has no entities yet,
no attributes. Now our app is going to have some Twitter
users. It's gonna show Twitter users for,
that have tweeted a certain mention in a bunch of tweets.
So clearly we're gonna need an entity which is a Twitter user
and we're probably gonna need an entity which is a tweet.
So let's create our entities and see where it takes us.
So I clicked this button down here,
Add Entity, and I added this entity called, Entity. And
I'm gonna double-click on it to rename it.
I'm gonna call it TwitterUser. Okay, so this is gonna be
the entity that represents a Twitter user in my database.
Okay, gonna add another entity, clicking down here,
okay? This one I'm gonna call Tweet, so it's gonna represent
a tweet. Now, once we have these entities,
we obviously need attributes on them. So Tweet, we're going
to add text, which is, every tweet has a text, 140
characters worth. You can see I have an error right up here.
It says, Tweet text must have a defined type.
And it's right now undefined. So I'm gonna pick it to be
a string and I could add other things here.
Maybe one thing that'd be really important with tweet,
with a tweet, when I'm fetching these tweets,
if I typed #Stanford and fetched 100 tweets, and
then I typed #Stanford and fetched another 100 tweets,
it would probably be mostly the same tweets, maybe one or
two new ones. So I need some kind of unique identifier in
the database to identify a tweet so
I don't get all kinds of duplicates. I don't want,
you know, the same Tweet in there tons of times.
So I'm gonna call it Unique. Luckily, we're gonna find that
the Twitter, framework provides a nice unique ID that
we can use to be, to uni, to unique our tweets so
that's good. And I can put other things in here, like,
maybe, you know, the created date of the tweet,
maybe I would call that posted and you see I'm making
the type here be date. These names don't have to match
the names in the Twitter framework at all.
In fact, the Twitter framework is completely separate.
It has nothing to do with core data.
It just gets the data from Twitter. Okay,
it's our responsibility to take that data from Twitter
and put it into this database with whatever attributes and
entities we want. Okay, now we happen to call this tweet and
we also have a class in our Twitter framework called tweet
also and we're gonna have to be careful about that. But
they're totally different. Okay,
they represent the same thing conceptually, a tweet,
but they're different classes. All right, our Twitter user,
what does a Twitter user have? Well, a screen name,
obviously, that's the most important thing,
that's your Twitter handle, you know, @whatever,
that's a string. You know, the, we don't really need much
else for our app here, but maybe there's the actual name,
we could have other attributes of a user, put whatever we
want in here. Okay? Now, as time goes by, as you enhance
your app, you're gonna be adding more attribute,
more entities, and that's perfectly fine.
The only thing to notice is every time you change your
model here, okay? The database that's on your simulator or
on your device is now invalid, okay? Now, there is a way to
make compatible changes, I'm not really gonna talk about
that. But there is a way to do that. Once you, if you started
shipping an app on the app store, then that would start
to matter to you because you wanna ship a new version.
Maybe it has some new attributes, you
want all the data the user's created to still be good. But
when you're in development and you're changing things,
what you can do is just go on to your device, or
your, simulator, and
delete your app. Okay, every time you change your schema,
you're gonna have to delete your app and then run again.
Of course, you'll lose all your data in the database too,
but, that's just, you're doing development cycles anyway, so
it shouldn't, probably shouldn't matter. Okay.
All right, so we have this great thing.
Let's take a look at it in the graphical view,
clicking this little button down here, and
you can see here's our two things. Notice if I move one,
the other one kind of moves around to keep it all,
in a nice space here.
And you can see here's my attributes, the name,
the screen name, you can see that the inspector over here
is showing us things like the type of it. All right?
Click on this one, type. You can even set some things like
minimum and maximums for dates and things like that.
I'm not really gonna talk about this inspector. You can
play around with it, certainly read the documentation and
find out all the things you can do over here. But
what I'm interested now is the relationship between Twitter
users and Tweets, okay. And
we know that a Twitter user Tweets and creates a bunch of
these things, okay, creates a bunch of Tweets.
So there's a relationship between these two, and anytime
there's a relationship between entities in your data model,
you just go to this graphical view, hold down Ctrl, and
drag between them, okay? When you let go, you're gonna get
these new things. These are also gonna be vars ju-, in
your code, just like these are vars, which is a relationship
between the two. And each side has a relationship, okay? And
you'll, first thing you'll want to do
is rename these to be more meaningful names than
newRelationship. So a Twitter user,
Twitter user's relationship to their tweets is probably gonna
be called tweets. It's the tweets that they've tweeted,
right? And similarly a tweet, the relationship it has
to the Twitter user who tweeted it is probably,
you could call it user, or poster, or
I'm gonna call it tweeter, but it doesn't really matter,
it's just the name of a var, that we're gonna have in our
code, that represents the relationship between the two.
Now, as we talked about in the slides about core data,
there's something special about this relationship,
this tweet's relationship to tweet, which is that a Twitter
user can have multiple tweets, could have hundreds of tweets
possibly, okay? A given tweet only has one tweeter. But
a good, a twitter user could have hundreds of tweets. So
this relationship's a little different. So
when we click on it here and look at it in the inspector,
and see the inspector is pretty smart.
It knows there's an inverse relationship tweeter
over here. That's the inverse of tweets. And
it also knows the type of connection here is To one and
we want to tell it no. This is a To many, To many connection,
okay, meaning there are many tweets per Twitter user. And
when we do that to To many, you can see that the arrow
here gets double arrowed in this direction. Only this
direction, it's still single To one in that direction, but
it's To many in this direction. Okay, and
that's perfectly fine for one to be a To one and
one to be a To many, as you can see here. You can also
have both of them be To many. That's legal as well.
All right, and we also know from the slides that what this
means is that tweets var, okay, on our Twitter user,
is gonna be an ns set. And
in that ns set are gonna be ns managed objects.
This is an ns managed object. This is an ns managed object.
This var, that points this way in Tweet, is gonna be an ns
managed object, okay, because it's only a single one.
Every single entity in the database is represented by
an ns managed object. Now, that's a little bit kind
of hard to use, to have every single thing,
Twitter users and tweets be NS managed object.
Because the only way we can set the attributes
is using that set value for key. And get the attributes
with value for key. It's a little unwieldy. So of course,
we want to have subclasses of NS managed object for
each of our entities. So a class called tweet, which
is a subclass of NS managed object that represents these
things, and has vars for all this. And the same thing for
Twitter user. Okay. And again, remember from the slides we
can go up here and have, in the editor menu,
Xcode generate those sub classes for us. One thing I'll
remind you if you're gonna do this, see where it says model
dot x c model. Do you see how that's selected? This menu,
the editor menu is contact sensitive,
it depends on what thing you have selected.
So for example if I go over here and
pick Story Board, look this menu£s completely different,
it£s doing Story Board things over here,
okay like embedding and stuff like that. So
you wanna make sure you have this data model selected so
that you get the data model editor menu.
So we're gonna pick Create NS managed sub class here.
So NS Managed sub class,
it's saying which of these do you wanna create it for?
We only have one okay, so it's obviously selected.
But you can actually have multiple of these mappings and
have multiple databases. Here it's saying which of
the entities do you wanna generate sub classes for and
I'm gonna click them both. Okay? I want both of these.
Click next. And be very careful of this one, okay?
This is asking you where you want to put these things.
Well, look where it wanted to put it.
Right at the very top of my work space.
I definitely don't want it there.
I definitely want it somewhere in my Smash Tag project.
Probably right at this level. Not in supporting files, but
right here. Make sure you set this you'll be unhappy if you
put it up in your top work space level,
files won't be in the right place it'll be bad.
Also make sure you're language is right of course.
This scaler remember that's, all the things that,
integers and doubles are represented as NS numbers,
okay? And if you do the use scalers the Vars
that it will create will be
not be NS numbers will be instant doubles. And
fortunately, in this time intervals. I don't want that.
I have it in this date right here posted. So
I'm not going to switch this, but if you change your mind
on this you can always go back and regenerate these. Okay,
it's not like you generate these once and you're done,
you can always go back. All right. So I'm going to
hit create to create this thing. We'll see the files
are created, okay. You can see right here this first one is
tweet okay? Tweet.swift.
It's a sub class of NS managed object as we would expect. And
this is just a place we can put any code we want,
okay? Any code that in an object oriented design sense
would make sense to be in the tweet, class.
Okay this is a bizarre place to do thing. If we go back and
regenerate these this file will not get changed. Okay? So
it won't stomp our, whatever code we put in here. Okay,
similar we have TwitterUser, okay, right here. Same thing,
okay? Just a place to put a TwitterUser.
It's a sub-class of NSManagedObject. And
then there are these, these two really cool extensions
that were created for us, okay, one for TwitterUser and
one for Tweet that have vars that represent each of our
attributes, so we don't have to use set value for
a key, okay? You can see its screenName is a string,
name is a string, tweet, as promised, is an NSSet.
And in that NSSet, we NSManage objects, in fact,
they'll be tweets, okay? A subclass of NSManagedObject.
Notice that they are all optional,
that's because when we create a twitter user in this
case in the database all the. Okay,
we can set them to whatever we want and similar for tweet.
Okay, it's got an extension as well as you can see, and
notice it's tweeter relationship
is a pointer to a TwitterUser If you do this, and
you find this to be managed object, okay? It could be
because your Tweet and Twitter user files got generated
in the wrong order, so that twitter user hadn't been
generated at the time tweet was, and so it gets object.
The fix is just go back and regenerate them again, okay?
Cuz it takes into account what is generated in the past.
Okay? Otherwise this is all pretty straightforward.
Now these files you never edit.
These files get regenerated every time you go into that
create ns manage object thing. So as you change your schema
these might change. All right now I like to take all of
these core data things, okay, including my model file and
I like to put them in their own groups.
I'll select them all and say new group from selection and
call it core data. So this is my core data group.
Inside this group,
I've got all my stuff that has to do with core data, and
we're going to add a little bit more to that in a minute.
Alright, so back to our app and
what we're trying to accomplish here.
All right, so here's what our app looks like,
right? Just got this thing that's gonna segue,
there's really two parts to making this new NVC work.
One is we have to put data in the database,
that's actually something this NVC does, cuz it's the thing
that does the fetching. When we type #Stanford,
it's the thing that goes out and gets them.
So this is going to load up the database with Tweet and
tweeter users. And
then this one is going to look in the database, okay,
to find things out. So let's do this part first,
let's go to our existing tweet table view controller and
have it update the database every time we do a fetch.
All right, so here's our code for
our tweet table view hopefully your you i remember this where
you intimately famil, familiar with it as our search text.
Here's where we're doing our search for tweets, right.
Here's where we find new tweets and
insert them in the table. So I'm just gonna,
in addition here to putting them in the table,
I'm gonna call some method, let's say updateDatabase and
pass along these new tweets to go put them in the database,
all right. Now, we're gonna be doing CoreData here, so
I wanna make sure I import CoreData up at the top here,
okay? And then I have to write this method here, private func
updateDatabase, okay? It takes the new tweets that it got,
which is an array of tweet, but
now I have to be careful here, okay?
Cuz which tweet is this? Is that the tweet in the Twitter
framework, or is that this tweet right here that's an ns
managed object? Hm, okay we have to be careful here. And
the way we distinguish the two is by putting the framework
name in front. So this update database takes Twitter tweets
and we're gonna put them, turn them into, in [INAUDIBLE]
tweets and put ' in the database so be careful if you
do that. Now when you do your homework, you're welcome to
not call this thing in your database tweet.
If you don't wanna have to deal with twitter.tweet.
Okay you can call it something else. But it, if you do call
it tweet, then you wanna make sure to distinguish which ones
you're talking about at any given time. All right? Now,
to update our database, here's where we need that
object context, right? That little hook that lets us put
things in the database, search through the database, etc ect.
I'm actually gonna make that part of the model of this NVC,
because if you think about what this NVC does, yeah,
it lets you search, but it also updates that database.
Which database it updates is really part of
describing its model. Okay, so
I'm gonna have a var here called managedObjectContext.
It's gonna be an NSManagedObjectContext, and
it'll be optional. And if this is nil,
this is not set to anything, then I just won't update any
database. Okay, so I'm gonna write my code, so if this is
nil I'm not gonna update it. I'll still do my searching,
but I'm not gonna update any database. So
if anyone wants me to update a database they better set this,
okay, to the database they want me to update.
Now especially for demo purposes, I'm actually gonna
have this have a default which is that App delegate thing.
Remember that code that we just copied over into app
delegate over here? This manage object context?
I wanna call this property, access this property on my
app delegate, to get the managed object context. Again,
if you're using a UI managed document, you'd be doing this
differently. Okay? So I got a call then.
If you remember how that code goes, we're gonna get
UI applications, shared applications.
So this is just an instance of UI application that's shared.
So outta your whole app, it's the only one you're ever
gonna use. Now I'm gonna get its delegate.
Okay, now its delegate is of type UI application delegate.
Right, it's a protocol. You know how delegates work,
it's always a protocol. And we don't want that, okay?
We want it to be this particular app delegate class
right here. Okay. This app class app delegate, kind of
a generic name app delegate. It happens to implement the UI
application delegate protocol so that's good. Okay. So
that means I can go over here and say as AppDelegate, okay?
So now I have a hold of that AppDelegate
instance, all right? And all I need to do now is send it
ManagedObjectContext. So let's go ahead and do that.
I had to put a parentheses around here.
Now this might be nil, okay? What if the delegate is for
some reason not set, or what if it isn't this class
AppDelegate for some reason? You change it mid-flight,
okay? Then I'm gonna optional chain here and get the managed
object content. Okay. So this all might come out nil,
that's okay because this is an optional. We just won't do,
put in anything in the database in that case.
All right, now it's a little weird to have this default.
More likely you would just have this be nil and
someone would have to explicitly set it, but
that would require probably to create a little subclass of
tweet table view called root tweet table view, and
it would do this line of code, and
then call super.manage.object context equals this.
Okay, and then we would go in our storyboard and
we would set the identity inspector for this table view
to be root table, Tweet table view controller.
So that's a little more than I wanna go through in the demo
here, so we're just going to kinda go cheap mode here and
just make it default to be this managedObjectContext. All
right, so this is where we're gonna store our database when
we, or our information when we do this update database.
Okay. Now remember, any time we access the database,
we have to do it with that perform block because these
database, these managedObjectContext, are only
thread safe within the thread they were created on.
And I'm gonna write all my code in this demo as
if I don't know what thread these managedObjectContexts
are created on. Even though we know that that AppDelegate one
is always a main queue one. But I'm not gonna write my
code assuming that, just so you can see what it looks like
to write multi-threaded managedObject, code, okay? So,
that means we always have to have our managedObjectContext
and do performBlock, okay? Now if this is nil,
what happens here? Nothing, good, that's what I want.
Okay, I, I've, if I don't have a managedObjectContext,
I don't wanna update the database.
So this is perfect so far, all right?
So we're gonna perform a block here. Inside this block,
all we gotta do is put these newTweets, okay,
into the database. So, that's pretty straightforward.
I'm just gonna have a little for
loop that goes through those tweets. Let's say for
twitterInfo in the newTweets. And then here,
I have to, you know, create a new but unique Tweet,
in the N-S managed objects sense. With that, you know,
Twitter info. Okay, so that's what I need to do in here. So
I need a method to do that. Now that method doesn't really
want to go in this Tweet table view controller,
okay. That's really something that wants to go in the Tweet
class. Okay. A tweet class is one stop shop for
everything tweet when it comes to the database. So
if you had a method that takes Twitter info from the network
and turns it into a tweet in the database,
that needs to believe, live in the one stop shop. Okay.
So we're gonna actually put that code some method that
does this in tweet.
Okay, remember Tweet is this subclass of NSObject, so
we're gonna do exactly what that comment just said and
insert the code we want in here. Now this code,
what is this method gonna do? Well, this method is going to
look in the database and if there's already a tweet there
with that unique ID, then it's just gonna just return that.
If not, it's gonna create one and load it up with
the Twitter information, okay that it got from from,
from over the network and then, it's gonna return that.
So, it either looks it up and returns it or
create it if necessary. Okay. I'm gonna call this thing,
first of all, it's gonna be a class function,
meaning I'm gonna send this to the tweet class
because I'm creating an instance here,
I can't really send it to an instance yet,
I haven't created one. I'm gonna call this thing
tweetWithTwitterInfo and it's gonna take some Twitter info
which is gonna be a Twitter.Tweet, okay? So I have
to import Twitter here. So then making a Twitter.Tweet.
And the other thing I gotta have if I'm gonna create
something in the database is inManagedObjectContext.
Okay, I have to have the NS ManagedObjectContext that you
want to create this thing in, or, or
it just can't create it, okay.
And this thing is gonna return a tweet. Okay, it's either
gonna return the tweet that it found in the database by
looking at the unique ID of this Twitter.Tweet, or
it's gonna create one in the database and return that.
Okay, so let's have it return nil. Actually, let's just make
it so it returns an optional tweet in case for
some reason we can't create one.
We'll have it return nil by default. Okay, we'll get back
to how we're going to implement this in a second. I,
I want to go back to the code that calls this,
which is here. Okay, this update database. And use it
here. And so you just call, you know how you call class
functions, you just have the name of the class, tweet, and
then this is tweet, what's it called? TweetWithTwitterInfo,
and we're gonna pass the Twitter info along.
Okay, this is the Twitter info that we're pulling out of this
array of Twitter.Tweets, right? In a for loop here.
And ininManagedObjectContext, we're gonna pass our own
managed object context. And we can go ahead and unwrap it,
because we know we wouldn't, have made it into this block
if this were not nil. All right? And notice that it's
complaining here about you gotta put self in, sorry,
you've gotta put self in front of this because this right
here is a block, okay? So we gotta make sure we avoid any
loops, you know, any any memory cycles and
what else is it complaining about here? Cannot,
I must have typed that wrong. Let's go back here. All right,
go back here to tweet. I must have, yes,
I forgot to put context okay in this iManagedObjectContext
there. All right, back. All right, so we got this,
so this, now one thing that's interesting about this
tweetWithTwitterInfo, it returns a value, right,
it returns a tweet. Now I don't care.
I don't want the tweet here, I'm just creating it, I'm just
the guy loading the database, so I don't want that tweet. So
notice that swift doesn't complain, even though I'm
ignoring it. But some would say it's pretty good code to
say_ = here, okay. That tells someone reading this code,
yeah, I understand that this returns to a value but
I'm not interested in it.
Remember the underbar in Swift is the universal,
I don't care about this thing, okay. So, looks a little odd
to do this but, some would say this is a little bit better
coding style, it's just looks, it makes it a little clearer
to people reading your code that this is what you intend.
Okay? Now this will, once we implement this,
this'll load up the database with these tweets, but it's
not gonna save that database. Okay, now if we're using a UI
managed document, okay, then it would all be autosaving,
fine. But here we use an app delegate one and
even if we're not sure which one we're using, it can't hurt
to save, okay, the context in the UI managed document case.
So how do we save? Well, it's simple.
We just say inManagedObjectContext, save.
Okay? But of course, we're gonna have an error here,
because it's gonna say hold on a second, well,
first it's saying we're inside a block so we have to do self,
so we'll do that. And we still have another error, which it
says this call can throw, but it's not marked with try. So
it's to say hey, pay attention, this can throw.
So we need to put try in front And of course if we're going
to try something we need to put it inside of a do loop.
And catch any errors that come out. Okay, and
we'll put it in a local variable we'll call error.
This is going to be an N-S error instance,
okay. We could look at the error code etcetera.
I'm just going to go ahead and print it out.
I'm going to say core data error. Error,
something like that. This is bad,
you wouldn't want to do this in your real code, okay.
This is just demo ware here, you would want to decide what
you wanted to do if you tried to save and it failed for
some reason. Okay? So, anyway, so this is gonna save it.
So this will work again, even if you were in an autosave and
you iManage document, it's gonna work just fine. Okay?
All right, let's jump back to where we were over here.
Tweet. And implement this thing, TweetWithTwitterInfo.
So I said that what TweetWithTwitterInfo's gonna
do is first it's gonna look in the database and
see if it can find this Twitter.Tweet. Okay.
In the database already and if so it's gonna return it. So,
how do we look in the database and find something? Well,
we use this NSFetchRequest thing. Okay?
So, we're gonna make a Fetch Request, okay? It always wants
to know the entity name. So, here we're looking for Tweet
in the database. Okay. So we've got this fetch request.
I am going to sign that to a local variable here.
Let request equal. And this request needs a predicate
that says which tweet do you want. So I am gonna say okay,
my predicate is NSPredicate with a format.
And I am gonna say that the unique ID of this tweet
equals something And what is that something?
Well, it's the whatever the unique ID is in twitter.tweet.
K? Which happens to be called ID. So
I'm going to get my twitter info.id. K? So that, this
is just a property and you might have used it with your
homework number four but it's just a property that uniquely
identifies this tweet. Okay, so i'm gonna go look in
the database and see if i can find that, and the way we look
in the database is we say, let query results.
Just a local variable,
equal the context that we are supposed to look in here,
that's this context up here dot execute fetch request.
And then, you give it that request, okay?
So that's how we look in the database,
but there's some problems with this. As you can see,
little errors over here. One is that this thing throws,
okay? Execute fetch request throws. So I need to say, try,
okay? So that's problem number one of this. And
if I'm going to try, then of course, I need to.
Do a little do loop here and catch any errors.
Now, if I'm actually getting this fetch request to look for
this tweet and it's not there, what am I gonna Gonna do?
There really nothing I can do.
I just continue and try to create it.
I'm gonna assume it's not there. Right if I search for
it and I don't find it, I'm gonna assume it's not there.
So basically when I catch an error I'm just gonna ignore
the error and move on down here to keep trying to
create it. But if I am able to find it right here, okay,
if I do get a result there from,
from doing this fetch. Then I'm going to say if I can let
the tweet that's in there equal the query results,
now remember the query results are an array of tweets.
All the tweets that match my predicate My predicate is
unique, so there should only be one in there. Either one or
zero, okay? There's one in there if it found it.
There's zero of them in there if it didn't find it, right?
So, I'm gonna go use this method in array called first.
Okay, that returned to the first item in the array,
or nil, if the array is empty.
So it never does array index out of bounds, so it's kind of
a cool, there's also last, but first is kind of a cool one.
And when I pull it out of there, of course,
it needs to be a tweet. Okay, so
if I can pull the first thing out of this result array and
it's a tweet, I'm good to go. I can just return that tweet.
Okay? Otherwise, I couldn't find the thing in there.
I got to go create it in the data base.
Everybody cool with this code? Now this is unfortunate
a lot of code, okay? Seven lines of code here.
This can all be done in one line. LIne of code, okay?
So let's look at that. How can we do that? And in this is,
requires you to start getting more and more familiar
with optional chaining, okay. >> Cuz we got a lot of things
that can go wrong here, okay? Things can be nil,
all kinds of things happening right here. So believe it or
not we can do this just by doing this.
If let tweet = we're gonna try,
and if we fail, return nill. Try? means try it, and if it
fails return nill. To ask our context to execute this fetch
request. Okay, this same fetch request we just did, okay.
If that is successful, then go on to get the first thing in
the array. And see if you can cast it to a tweet, okay.
That is identical to this, okay. And
it reads a little more simply a little more like English,
okay. Try to use the context to execute this Fetch request.
Get the first thing, a-and if you can get this
first thing as a tweet, Then return it. Okay? So
it's actually better code, I believe more readable than
the other. Yeah? >> So
where would we link the catch? >> Yeah, so
we can't do this if we're gonna catch.
If we're gonna catch and do something we ignore so,
we didn't do that, but if we're gonna catch and
do something then we would have to use this more verbose
Good question there.
Alright, so we got that, okay. So, what if we can't? Okay?
What if we could not find the tweet in the database?
Now we need to create the tweet, okay?
So here I'm gonna say, okay I couldnt it so
I couldn't look it up. So if I can create it which is,
if you'll remember from the slide, NS entity
description.insert, insert new object for
entity for name, okay? We're creating a tweet.
The manage object context is context, okay, and
we obviously want it to be a tweet. Okay?
So here we've created the tweet.
If we£re able to, okay if let, so we£re gonna see if we can
create it by inserting something in the database.
Everybody cool with that line of code.
All right, now we've created a tweet, but it£s empty, okay.
It£s all everything£s nill in there,
so we need to start setting some of the values like really
importantly we better set that unique equal to the Twitter
info£s ID. Okay, make sure it's unique, we also wanna set
the tweets text equal to the Twitter info's text. I think
we also had the tweet posted which would be the Twitter
info's created, okay? So we just wanna go through here and
grab the information that we got from it network, and
put it in the database that's basically what we're doing
here. Okay? Now, what about this one,
tweet.tweeter =? Ooh, what do we, how do we do that?
Gotta set up that relationship between [LAUGH] tweeter and
tweets, okay? Well, to do that,
we have to create the Twitter user. That goes for this,
okay, and by that I mean this Twitter user right here.
This managed object Twitter user. Okay. And to create
a twitter user, I'm going to use the exact same kind of
code that I just was in the middle of typing and tweet.
I'm going to type it in really fast because
it's exactly the same, okay. So I'll go through it here but
it's exactly the same.
So I need to import twitter, just like I did in that one.
So here we're in twitter user. Okay? And this one's called
Twitter user with Twitter info. This time the Twitter
info is not a Twitter, tweet, it's a Twitter.user. Okay,
and we still have to pass the the manage object context.
And it returns a Twitter user if it can find one or create.
Okay, now for Twitter user the unique is the screen name.
Every Twitter user has their own unique screen name, so
we don't have a unique
we just use the screen name as the unique thing. Here,
we're doing that try to see if we can find it, if we can, we
return it. If we can't, we're inserting a new one, okay, and
setting the screen name and the name, and returning it.
Okay? Now, notice that I'm not setting the tweet's NS set.
I'm not adding anything to the tweet NS set here. Okay,
at this point I don't know any tweets that are in a set.
that's because I,
So I'm just creating a twitter user that so
far, has no tweets in the database, okay, when I create.
Alright? Now let's go back here to where we're creating
the tweet, and now to set this tweet.tweeter all we need to
do is say twitter user Twitter user with Twitter info.
And now we pass the user, which is the Twitterinfo.user
in inManagedObjectContext.
The context, okay? This creates that Twitter user.
Okay, and sets it to this bar which is that relationship.
The NS Set in the Twitter user, will have this tweet
auto, tweet automatically added to it, okay.
You don't have to do both sides, if you do one side,
it does the other, if I'd put a tweet in the Twitter user
NS Set, the Twitter would have been set to it. Okay? If you
do, if you touch one side, the other side gets kept in sync,
that's the awesome thing about Core Data. So
you never have to worry about database integrity,
it manages the integrity all the time for you, okay?
Very important to understand. All right, so we got it.
So as long as we were able to do,
either look it up or create it, we can return it okay?
Whoops. Return the tweet, otherwise if we couldn£t do
either of those things then we£ll just return nill.
Okay very unlikely cuz this almost never fails. Inserting
a new object, it£s gonna work for G1 100% of the time. Okay?
Got that? All right. So back to where we were calling this.
Right here. Everybody cool with this?
You can see how this is going to put this array of tweets,
okay, into the database. All right.
Now, let's go ahead and before we do our new mvc
let's just make sure this is working okay?
I'm gonna write a little function here that prints out
what's in the database.
How many Twitter users, how many tweets.
Let's just see if this working okay? So let's write,
let's write that function, see what that would look like.
So I'm gonna have a private funk. I'm gonna call
it PrintDatabaseStatistics cuz it's basically going just
print how many, Twitter users are and how many, of the,
how many tweets and how many Twitter users, so of course we
have to perform this in a block Okay, cuz we always
have to do that when we're doing manage object context
stuff and I'm going to watch this,
if let results equal try to execute on our context and
actually we can exclamation point that.
Execute fetch request. Now watch.
I'm going to create a fetch request on the fly here.
Fetch request with an entity name and what am I looking for
here? Okay, let's count the Twitter users first. So
Twitter user. Now, notice I have a fetch request here with
now predicate. I just created an quest
with no predicate set on it. That gets all twitter users.
If you have a without a predicate, that means give me
all of them, all of whatever the entity is
that you're looking for. Okay, so if I'm able to do that and
get the results, then I'm just going to print that we have
Result.count how ever many we go here.
Twitter users. Okay so, that£s this little code right
here, we£ll print out how many Twitter users are in
the database. Alright, now there£s actually a better
way to do this because this is a bit of a problem, when I
execute that vet request it gives me every single
Twitter user out of the database and
into my memory. Now, there just husks because remember I
talked about the faulting thing. So, the attributes like
the Twitter user screen name and name those aren't pulled
from the database. But, like a little husk is there and
if I had thousands thousands of Twitter users,
that would be unnecessarily thousands of bytes
being pulled into my memory. Okay. So there's a better way
to do this. There's actually an execute equivalent, which
only counts how many things there are, and it counts it on
the database side without pulling everything over and
counting it in an array. So for the tweets I'll use that
way of doing it and that looks like this. I'm gonna let tweet
count equal our context-managed object,
countForFetchRequest, it's called. Okay? Instead of
execute fetch request it calls count for fetch request.
I'm still gonna create a fetch request on the fly here, and
this time, I am, In this fetch request entity name.
This time I'm searching for tweets, not Twitter users.
Notice there's this little error pointer right here.
You see this error pointer? This is an interesting method.
I'm not sure why it does
it this way. But instead of throwing the error,
it actually returns it through a pointer.
And if you're not interested, you can just say, nil. Say,
I don't want any error information. Okay?
So it's kind of an odd little method in that way.
That's going to return the tweet count.
And now, I can just print. The tweetCount,
Tweets. So this is better code right here than this, okay?
It's gonna be much more efficient.
I'll leave them both in here so that when I post the demo,
you can see the difference.
Here, I'll even put a comment in here. A more efficient way
to count objects. Okay, but they're both just counting.
This is counting the number of Twitter users,
this is counting the number of tweets. Okay, so
let's call this print every time we update the database,
let's go ahead and
call this print database statistics thing, and I'm
actually gonna put a little print in here saying, done
printing database statistics. Okay, I'm gonna put
this in here because something interesting is going to happen
with that print. Okay? All right,
let's go ahead and run. Now we should be
loading up the database with Twitter users and tweets every
time we search for something, hashtag Stanford.
We're not showing any of it but hopefully we'll be loading
up the database. Okay, we have to,
we'll set our prototypes here when we get to that.
So, here's our segue. You can see our table here is empty.
We haven't done anything to implement that MVC, so
it's just a blank MVC. But if we do #stanford,
okay, it searches and we'll see down here in our console
that it had a hundred tweets, which is right,
because remember here in our code,
we fetch a hundred tweets, okay?
So, that's doing that properly and it's only 75 users,
why is that? Well, probably there are people in here who
are tweeting more than ones, okay?
Numerous fill like here, this guy, I am not the clone. Okay?
He tweeted twice right there, so you only count it once.
So that sounds right that there's something,
75 and 100. Now, here's a very important test
to make sure things are working.
I'm gonna look for hashtag Stanford again and
I better not get 200 tweets. There it is, only 100.
So nobody even tweeted to Stanford,
one of you maybe tweeted, make it work for us here. Okay,
let me try something else.
How about #SFGiants, believe they're playing right now.
Okay, now we have 200 tweets because we searched for
something different, okay. So we've got the 100 tweets from
Stanford, and hundreds of tweets from Giants, so
I'm gonna do Giants again. Still nobody tweeting.
Nobody's interested in the Giants or
in Stanford currently, I guess. There we go.
Somebody finally tweeted something new for the Giants.
Okay. So now, we have 201 tweets,
okay. Doesn't sound like things are going well for
the Giants. Hope I didn't spoil it for anybody. Okay.
So, we got our thing working right here.
Look at this though, dome printing database statistics,
that's printing out before it prints, isn't that weird?
This print is definitely after print database statistics, so
why is this printing out before? Anyone have an idea?
It begins with an A. Asynchronous,
yeah. Okay, this stuff, these performed blocks both this
performed block right here, and also this performed block
up here happen asynchronously. These blocks just get put onto
their queue, and in this case it's the main queue, but
that doesn't matter, whatever the queue is and
they get put on that.
So, when I do printdatabase for statistics,
it does this line of code which returns immediately.
It instantly returns, it puts that block on some queue and
returns immediately. It doesn't wait to execute
this code because this is not perform block and wait, it's
just perform block. So this goes, returns immediately, and
then this prints out immediately. Then later, this
block gets pulled off onto the queue, the main queue, and
run does its thing which causes this output. Okay,
see why I put this in here so
you understand that? This is happening asynchronously
unless you say perform block and wait. It's asynchronous.
All right, now we got the data in our database. Excellent,
now we can go on back to our storyboard right here.
And we can implement this NBC, this new NBC of ours.
We need to do some things to do that.
We need to make sure that we have for example,
reuse identifier for this cell. So what is that cell?
It's basically a Twitter user, so I'll call it Twitter user
cell. We want these probably to be subtitle,
okay, instead of custom cell.
We don't need custom cells for any reason.
Whoops. We can make sure we have our identities for
the whole table. We do. That's all looking good.
We can make sure we have this set, okay? Which we do. Okay?
So it's all good, all right? So we're all ready to.
Basically implement this guy's class his custom sub class.
So let's go take a look at that, that's right here.
Whenever we implement a new mvc, a great thing to do
I think, it's the fourth time I've said it in this class.
Come up with this model first, try to understand what this
thing is actually doing by understanding its model. Now,
this is a very simple NVC, it takes some mention,
like hashtag stamper and it searches for all the users,
okay, who have tweeted that, okay, in, in our database.
So a clear, very important part is that mention. Okay,
whatever that mention is, hashtag Stanford,
that clearly needs to be part of our model. Okay,
without that we can't do anything. But
another really important part of the model is that database.
Okay? Without that database I can't look
this mention up. Okay? So another one is
a managed object model just like our other one, actually,
had part of its model as well. Okay,
that's an NSManaged not models and NSManagedObjectContext,
NSManagedObjectContext, okay? I'll have that be optional,
but to be frank, if that's nil I'm not gonna, I'm gonna have
an empty table, okay? Because this time really demands that.
If either of these change I'm gonna do a did set here and
update my ui, which basically means I'm gonna have to reload
my table, okay? So, I'll do for either of these, and
then of course I need a private,
private funk update ui. Okay,
and in here we're gonna have to use this information. Okay,
it's complaining here because we have to import core data.
Okay. Notice that this particular NBC does not import
Twitter. Okay. Because it's purely using the database,
the other MVC uses Twitter and the database, this one
only uses the database, so it doesn't import Twitter,
just core data. All right, so we'll get to
update U-I. A second one thing I wanted to do before that is
do our prepare for Segway and set these two things,
okay, so we have to be prepared for Segway
back in this MVC over here. So let's go back to that NBC,
we'll put it, right here, prepare for segue this prepare
for segue, by now prepare for segue should be old
hat for you guys. You've done so many segues, but we're just
going to check to see if the segue's identifier is right.
That's going to be, what did I call that thing?
I can't even remember now,
let's look in our story board. This was called, copy and
paste. Tweeters mentioning search term, okay?
So, if it's the tweeters mentioning search term segue,
then I need to get the destination view controller as
a tweeter table u controller. So I'm gonna say if I can let,
the tweeters TVC we'll call it,
equal the segue.destinationViewContro-
ller as a TweetersTableViewController.
Okay, so I've got a hold of it.
Now I can just set the public API the model of this, so
it's got the mention which is just our search text, and
actually don't even need to do that.
This is our search text and tweeters.tvc.managedobjectsco-
ntext is our managed objects context, okay, so
we just prepare.
That's all we're doing here is preparing. Now that's okay,
now back to here. Update U-I. So, how are we going to update
this U-I? We need to have this table,
and we need to have it full of Twitter users who have Tweeted
a Tweet that has this mention hashtag Stanford in there or
whatever, okay. How are we going to do that? Well,
we're gonna use an NS fetched results controller,
that really cool object I told you about the end of the last
lecture. And that is an object that basically just glues
an NS fetch request to a table view,
and that's exactly what we want here.
We're gonna create an NS fetch request,
which fetches the twitterings, we want, then we're
gonna glue it on this table, okay? And in that way, anytime
the database changes in a way that those users would change,
it's gonna automatically update the table, and
we don't have to do anything else, okay?
Now, let's remind ourselves how NS Fetch Request,
NS Fetch Request, NS Fetch Request Controller How
it works, okay? It's got two pieces to it, and
I'm gonna have both of those pieces implemented for
you using this class that you're gonna be able to use
for your homework, it's right over here,
called core data table view controller.
So let's drag this core data view controller.
I'm gonna put it in my core data group right here and
copy it in, okay. All right so let's take a look at this
thing and see how ns fetched results controller works.
So, here's core data table view controller,
it's a sub class of ui table view controller,
you're gonna make it be a sub class, you're gonna make it
be the super class of your ui table view controller.
So back here in our TweetersTableView,
instead of inheriting from UITableViewController,
I'm going to inherit from CoreDateTableViewController.
That way, I'll get everything you get from
UITableViewController.
But I'm also going to get this NS Fetch results controller
stuff, okay? So let's look at that some more. There's two
parts to the NS Fetch results controller. One is that
I can use the [INAUDIBLE] to implement my entire UI table
view data source except for its self erodement index
path, okay? You still have to implement that. But all
the other ones look numbers of sections in table view,
numbers of rows in section,
even the section header titers, titles,
right the header titles, and footer titles section indexes.
All this stuff, it implements all that stuff.
See how the implementation of these is all using the fetch
results controller? So that's part A of how the NS
fetch results controller works. Part B is that
the fetch results controller has a delegate, okay? And
that delegate can implement these methods.
That will be called anytime the database changes. So
anytime anything happens in the database that might affect
this NS fetch request, okay? The delegate,
the NS Fetch delegate is going to be called and
sent these messages. And look what these things do. They
just update the table view, see? Table view, insert rows,
delete rows. You know, reload rows, that's because you know,
this is because something got deleted from the database,
this is something got inserted in the database,
this something changed in the database. Okay? So that's part
two is this, delegate of the NSFetchedResultsController.
So I've given you the codes to do both those things. Okay,
to implement this delegate, and
also to implement all of this UI table view data source.
All you have to do is set this var
in the CoreDataTableViewController,
which is an NSFetchedResultsController.
And all that happens when you set this var in didSet is,
it sets itself as the delegate, so
that all these methods down here at the bottom will work.
Okay, then it tries to perform the fetch. Okay, if it
catches it, it will report an error if there is any.
And then it reloads the table and that's it, okay.
The fetch results are always going to automatically
be linked now. So all you have to do to use Core Data table
controller is set this fetch results controller.
You have to create and set one of these and then it will just
work by magic. Okay. So let's go back here. Do exactly that.
In our update UI, we need to say self dot fetched results
controller equals. We do not actually need to say self
dot, but I just wanted to ehm emphasize that it is something
we are inheriting from core table core data tableview.
Okay, we can just set our fetch results control or
something. So we are going to create a new fetch result
controller. Okay.
And here are all of what the things in the initializer
look like. Okay. First, there's the request.
This is the NSFetchRequest that is going to
glue on to the table view. Okay.
We'll have to create that in a second. Second is the context.
So we have to go what context? What database are we looking
in? Next is this section named key path. Okay. N.S.
Spec Controller results will do the section titles,
if you have an attribute in the entities that here in
the table that you're looking up here which is the section.
Okay? The string the represents the section.
Can I call that actually with anything you want. And
you put the name of it here, whatever name the section
attributes here. The only thing about this, and
you can put Neil if you don't section, if we don't.
The only thing about this is that your table must sort
in the same order as these sections would sort.
When you think about it,
if you're going to have them grouped by section
the things need to be in the same order.
Otherwise you'd have some sec-, things in section here,
some in a different section, another different section.
You can't have that, they have to sort in the same order.
Okay, so sometimes you'll have you're sort descriptors of
your effect request. Maybe sort by the section first and
then sort by whatever you want to do.
That's an easy way to make it work. And
then there's the cash which we're also not using. Okay?
Not just a name. It's a string that it represents it.
So, I'm even gonna put this so
you can really see this four arguments right here. Okay.
So, we need to do a request right here and
we need to do the context.
Well, the context is easy, that's part of our motto.
So I'm just going to say if I can let the context equal
my own managed object context, K? Then this
will get to go here. Otherwise I'm gonna set my fetch results
controller to nil. If you set your fetch results controller
to nil, core data table view control will clear your
table okay. Which is what I want if I don't have a manage
object context because I don't know what database to look in.
Okay. So now what we need to do is request, okay?
We just need to have a request which is an NSFetchRequest.
Okay. It's going to be what?
What entity is going to be in this table? What is this NBC
show What kind of things? Twitter users, right? Showing
all the Twitter users that are mentioned in this tweet.
So this is twitter user, okay. Now, how about the predicates,
okay. We need a predicate of this for this thing. And so
that's in this predicate. Predicate with format here.
Okay so what is gonna be our predicate for this?
Well this is a little kind of complicated actually if
you think about it. We really wanna get all the Twitter
users who have a tweet that contains that string.
And it turns out you can do that very straightforwardly
within this predicate, you're just gonna say any
Tweets whose text contains, case insensitively, please,
that mention, okay. Now I have to do %@ whenever
anything that I'm doing here is not a reserved keyword. So
I have to do %@ and then put it here in this VarArgs.
So this is our mention right there Now that's an optional.
So I need to exclamation point here.
But I need to be careful here. What if this mention is nil?
This is gonna crash. And mention is part of my public
API. You should not have objects where people can set
your public API to something that will crash internally.
Okay, that's a bad API design, so
I wanna check right here, by saying where, this mention and
actually I also don't want to look up if the mention is
empty string. That doesn't make any sense either.
So I'm gonna say mention?.characters.count > 0.
So I'm using where here with this if, and this is kind of
interesting look mention characters count. If mention
is nil this whole thing is gonna be nil and the greater
sign operator knows that nil is never greater than zero.
It also knows nil is never less than zero nor
if nil equal to zero okay so it knows all those things.
So it's kind of fun you can put nils.
On the sides of these greater than's or
less than's really kinda makes your code pretty nicely here.
Okay? Now the thing we need to do is sort. Okay so we
need our sort descriptors, and remember that's an array of
sort descriptors because we can sort by last name first,
and then first name or by section name and
then by something else. But
here we only have one sort descriptor okay.
The sort descriptor has numerous things that you can
specify in its initialize. What if you used the simplest
one here which is I'm going to search by the key screen
sort by the key screen name. So we're gonna list our users
by their screen name, you know their at sign, whatever.
That's gonna be the order of this table and
I'm going to have it be ascending true.
So A capital A will be first always to capital Z
then all the way to a all the way down from there. Okay?
So that's the only thing I'm gonna search by, so this one,
or sort by this one sort to script Okay?
So now, that's it. The only thing I have to do now is
implement my self row at index path and I'm good to go. Okay?
Because this is going to always be keeping the Twitter
users associated with the rows. All right so self for
row index path of course we need to set
our reuse identifier which I think was Twitter user cell.
All right. And it says configure the cell.
Now, obviously, to configure the cell in any row,
I need to know what Twitter user is in that row, okay. So,
how do I do that, let twitterUser equal and
I'm gonna ask my fetched results controller, okay.
I'm gonna say, what is the object that act this
index path? Okay, remember this is cellForRowAtIndexPath,
so indexPath is what, the row we're talking about here. And
I'm just gonna ask the Twitter, the,
I'm gonna ask my fetchedResultsController
what it is.
And of course, it better be a TwitterUser. So
I'm gonna put as TwitterUser there and say if let, okay?
So if I'm able to get to twitterUser here,
then I can just do for example cell.TextLabel.text
= the twitterUser's screenName let's say. Okay?
Now there's a problem with this line of code right here.
Can anyone guess what this problem is right here? Looks
perfectly fine, right? This is accessing the database,
okay? And we know that anytime we access the database,
we gotta put it inside performBlock, okay? So
we actually have to put some context here, performBlock.
Okay, around this code. Now, what context are we gonna
use here? We could use our manage object context.
That's true. And that would be fine.
I'm actually gonna use a different context.
I'm gonna use the Twitter user's manage object context.
Every NS managed object, this is a Twitter user. Okay?
But we also have Tweet. Every NS managed object
knows the managed object context it's in. And
you can ask it. That will often keep you from having to
have var ManagedObjectContext as public var.
Because you'll have some other var which is a Twitter user or
a tweet or something like that and when that gets passed to
you now you know the managed object context.
Got it? So that makes it so that you don't have to
pass both of managed object context and a Twitter user or
something. Cuz if you pass in a Twitter user you're passing
the context along. Okay. So I'm just gonna use that down
in here. I'm doing this intentionally so
that you know that this method exists.
It's a really cool var on an ms managed object.
Now this is still no good, okay? What's wrong here?
What's going on right there? That's accessing the ui.
That can only happen on the main queue. Okay? This,
I happen to know, is the main queue, okay? I know, but
what if I was writing my code to truly be multi-threaded and
ms managed conduct? I couldn't count on that. Okay? So,
I can't do that, so instead, I'm gonna create a little var
here screen name, okay. Which is going to be a string. And
inside here I'm going to get rid of this and say
screen name equals that and then out here I'm going to set
this equal to screen name. Okay. But
there is still a problem with this. Anyone can guess what
this problem is? You're a quiet crowd today. This
is a synchronic. Okay, that screen name is going to happen
some other time. Certainly not in time for this. Okay, so
we need to perform block and wait here. Okay.
We have to wait for this to happen before we can do this.
Got it? Okay, so that's it, let's go ahead and run and
see what this looks like. All right,
let's look for Stanford again. Okay, we got 206 tweets,
we got this many Twitter users.
'm going to click this Tweeters right here, and
sure enough, look! Her's all the people who tweeted hashtag
Stanford that w've ever seen. Now, this is not
quite exactly what we want. I's close, okay? Notice
our alphabetization. You see, all the capital letters first.
Then [LAUGH] all the lowercase letters. Really,
I want interspersed, right? I want case insensitive.
Lowercase. Or, sorry, case insensitive so,
sorting as well. [SOUND] what else is going on here? Also,
maybe some of these I don't like. Like, look at this guy.
Darksidedub16. Okay, that sounds kind of evil, so
I don't even want Darkside to appear in my results. Okay?
So, let's fix both of those things,
let's fix the sorting and
let's make sure dark side does not appear in our results,
okay? So, how do we do those things? First, the sorting,
case intensively is quite easy, okay? Here is where our
sort descriptor is right here, here is the key and
here is the ascending, right there. We can just add
another argument here, which is the selector. To use, okay?
We'll use the hashtag selector here. Selector.
And the selector I'm going to use is NF strings,
I've got one called localizedcaseinsentivecompare
right here, okay? And so you guys remember this format for
specifying a selector, right? So
I'm just gonna use this instead of the standard one,
which is compare, which is not case insensitive.
So that's gonna effect our, case insensitive sorting.
Okay, it's just how we specify our sort descriptor.
How about getting the dark side out of there? Well,
what appears in that table is determined by this predicate.
Okay? Any tweets containing this currently, but I can say,
and the screen name does not begin with,
case insensitivity, the darkside.
Okay, and again I can't put anything but keywords in here,
so I have to put it out here Okay? Like that.
I just wanted to do this to show you that you can update
this predicate to change what shows up in your table,
this what controls within the table. So, now when we run.
Let me do #stanford. Okay, and
now Tweeters, we can see that the sorting is right,
you see? Capitals and lower case and look, no dark sides.
Okay, this is only a light side query here. All right.
Now I have five minutes left, I'll show you one
last other fun thing. See this subtitle right here? What if
instead of saying subtitle I wanted to say how many tweets
this guys has tweeted, right? So we're show,
these are all the people who have tweeted #stanford,
you know, had mentioned #stanford in their tweets.
I wanna know how many, so tell me how many each of these,
how many tweets this guy does, have done. All right?
So, to do that, I need another little function, okay?
It's going to be a private func. I'm going to call it
tweetCountWithMentionByTwitte- rUser.
And it's going to take a Twitter user.
And it's going to return an int.
Optional with how many times how many tweets, a tweet
count, where that Twitter user has mentioned that. So it's
gonna return the number that I want to show there. Okay.
So what is this little guy gonna look like right here?
Well I'm gonna have a local variable which is
the count which I am going to return at the end, K? It's
optional because maybe I won't be able to find the results,
we'll see. And I'm going to get the users managed
object context again and perform black. And
I'd better perform block and wait, k? Because this
a method that's being called, it needs to return, it can't,
it's got to do the work and have the result come back. So,
I'm just gonna create a fetch request here,
NSFetchRequest. And this time I'm searching for
tweets. Okay. Even though I'm inside the infiltration of
the twitter user table, I'm now counting tweets.
So, when I'm doing a different fetch inside there for tweets.
This is not the same fetch that's filling the table.
This is kind of a little side
fetch, that I'm doing and the predicate for that is. And
then there's predicate, format,
and text. I want the text of the Tweet to contain, case
insensitively, the mention that we're talking about. And
I want the Tweeter to equal this user. Okay,
just passed in here. So I need to have the mentions.
So that's our mention. Self.mention we'll need so
.mention. And I'm just gonna go ahead and
unwrap that. I'm pretty sure this is not new
because I don't think this method would be called if I
match it with milk because we never would've got
into all the self.
And xpath and all this stuff we never would've gotten here.
Some would say protect against this. But,
I actually think it's good to crash here because you'll find
this bug if you ever call this when mentioned is nil,
which it never should be at this point. And
then the Tweeter is just this argument user. So you Tweeter
equals user and pass a Twitter user, okay? And restrict your
results to that, so that's our results. So now I'm
going to use that count thing that we talked about before.
That's the user's managed object context. Count for
fetch request. The request. Don't care about errors,it
will come back zero. That's fine.
And I'm going to return the count. Okay? Everyone see what
I did there? Just found the, the request that I wanted.
So now that I have this nice little guy right here,
I can go here and say that my cell. I can actually say if
let the count equal the tweet count mentioned by
this twitter user. Okay? So if I got an account,
then I'm gonna have the cells detail TextLabel, text= and
let's even be kinda be cute and say if the count is one.
I'm gonna say 1 tweet otherwise I'm gonna say count
tweets, plural. If I wasn't able to get it then I'm just
gonna say that the cell detail text label text to empty,
okay. Let's run that. All right. Hashtag stanford again.
Seems to be our favorite. Here it is right here.
Okay tweeters and there it is. Okay, a lot of people with one
tweet, but here's someone with three tweets.
Okay there's someone with four tweets right there.
Now there were four tweets.
Now, the next obvious thing is to say,
awesome. I want to sort this table by the people's numbers
of tweets, so the people who tweet a lot are at the top.
Wouldn't that be a lot better than alphabetical?
It sure would. But
to do that, we would need a different schema. Okay.
This is important because in your homework you're going to
be sorting by a numb numerical value right here. And
you gotta make sure you have a schema that supports it.
Why would we need a different schema to sort
to sort this by the number of tweets? It's because of this.
Okay, if we go back up here and
look at our sort descriptor. Okay. For this table.
It's sorting by the screen name. This always has to be
an attribute in this entity. Okay,
the sort descriptor cannot be anything but
an attribute in this entity. Well, Twitter user
does not have an attribute which is that number. So
I cannot sort by it. You see? And not only that.
It would be very difficult for me to keep a number
on my Twitter user that would be that. Because
it depends on the mention. I'd have to have a different
Twitter user for every mention.
So this schema that we've designed right here,
which I will show you this schema, is insufficient.
To have that table sorted by a number, you need
a different schema. A slightly more powerful schema and
really the hardest thing about semi five for you is probably
design that schema. Once you design that schema,
look how incredibly it is easy to load these tables over
that coordinated table it's just like, it's trivial. Okay?
So, make sure you spend your brainpower on assignment five,
getting a good schema,
understanding what you're being asked to do,
and then getting a good schema that supports that, okay?
You'll, you'll find the rest of assignment five is very,
is straightforward, okay? All right, that's it.
I will see you on Wednesday we'll talk about the final
project requirements among other things.
>> For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.