[MUSIC]
Stanford University. >> Welcome to
Lecture 12 of Stanford CS193P, spring of 2016. Today
we have Autolayout, which we've actually been doing
quite a bit of Autolayout, so far, but we're gonna talk
a lot more in detail about the concepts of Autolayout and
things like that. And we're gonna introduce an important
Autolayout feature called Size Classes, okay?
All right, so let's dive in to Autolayout.
So you already know a lot about Autolayout, right? For
example, you know you can use those dashed blue lines when
you drag things in and move things around to kinda tell
Xcode what you intend about how things are laid out, okay?
But you know that those blue lines are really only just
kind of a hint, right? But you can say reset to
suggest a constraints. And it'll use the dashed blue line
information to try and guess, what constraints you want.
And sometimes that's what you want, sometimes not. Really
that's just minimal help from the system to do Autolayout.
It's kinda maybe to get you started,
or to get some initial constraints or
something like that, okay? And
you know that you can look in the Size Inspector, okay?
You can click, click on any view and
look in the Size Inspector, and now,
now, down there you'll see all of the constraints.
We've looked at those before that are on a particular view.
Okay, you also know that you can click on a constraint
itself and look at it in the Attributes Inspector.
So just like we click on a view and inspect that,
you can click on any constraint,
like a little i-beam or, you know, some bar,
something that's connecting something to an edge or
something. You can click on those things.
You can even double-click on them and
edit them kind of in a little window.
But you can single-click on them and
then edit them in the Attributes Inspector as well.
Now we know that the other way, another way we can set,
constraints is to control drag like we control drag to
the edge and say, you know, make it be a certain distance
from this edge. Okay, we saw that quite a bit.
That Ctrl-dragging can also be done between views.
So you can Ctrl-drag between two views and then say,
make these two be the same with, okay? Things like that.
And we'll see a little bit of that today in the demo. So
that Ctrl-dragging is probably the number one way you do
Autolayout, okay? But there's also a couple of menus down in
the bottom right corner where that menu that you bring up
that says reset to suggested constraints or update frames.
You know that thing,
there's two other little menus right by it. Okay the pin and
arrange menus, and they also let you say things like
make these. You can select five views, and then bring up
the arrange menu and say, make all of these equal widths.
And now we have a constraint on all five of the views to
make them equal widths. So, those menus, frankly
you don't use them that much because the Ctrl-drag is so
incredibly convenient for doing that, but
sometimes we will. You can look at your constraints by
inspecting things, but really the way to see a big picture
of all of the constraints is in the document outline, okay?
Remember the document outline? That's the thing on the left
in the storyboard that you can kinda
bring out with the little button on the bottom and
it shows you all your views and the hierarchy of it and
all that stuff.
Well it'll also show all your constraints in there. Okay,
a big long list of your constraints.
And, that's a good place where you can go to see them.
It also has a constraint resolution
UI which I might have brief, briefly shown but
I'll certainly show today. Where it'll actually tell you
all the constraints that are conflicting or
not fully specifying things, that kind of stuff.
So it's kind of, Document Outline is your constraint
headquarters to go try and fix things with constraints and
understand what's going on with your constraints. Now
mastering Autolayout requires experience. I can tell you all
these things what the, what the things you can do are, but
until you get in there and start trying to lay things out
and make things line up, and do things like that,
you really won't be able to master it, okay?
So it requires experience. So hopefully in your final
project you'll have some UIs that require quite a bit of
Autolayout. You know the UIs we've had so far have not
required that much Autolayout because I haven't gotten to
this lecture yet. So you know we've been using StatView
a lot, okay? We're heavily relying on StatView to make it
so we don't have to do so much Autolayout, cuz StatView kind
of is a thing for doing Autolayout in a very simple
way when you want to line things up in grids, okay? So
there's no, no substitute for experience in Autolayout. It
is possible to do Autolayout constraints from code, okay?
There is a class called ns layout constraint. And
it does all the things you can do in the storyboard and
possibly even a little bit more.
Actually definitely a little bit more.
I'm not gonna teach that in this course.
If you wanna learn about it, you might think about trying
to do something in your final project, maybe. It requires
a certain understanding of mathematics and
really understanding relationships between things,
to really set things up and make things work. It's a heck
of a lot easier just to do it all in the story board. So
unless you wanna kinda make that one of your investigative
things for your final project, which you're gonna see
is required that you go investigate something that I
don't teach in lecture. You're probably gonna wanna try and
do Autolayout from the story board, okay. And
you can certainly do everything you need to do
almost all the time in your story board. Okay,
so, let's see what's next here. Let's talk about,
rotation, okay? So sometimes, when you rotate your UI,
the geometry of it changes so drastically that
Autolayout is not enough to reposition everything, okay?
A great example of this is our calculator, okay? Our
calculator had five across, five buttons across and
four buttons down, I think, okay? And that looked fine.
Or it was four across and five down, I guess.
And that looks fine in portrait.
All the buttons were almost square. They were rectangular,
but they were close to being square. But
when we went into landscape,
all of our buttons got really squished down, okay.
They're really wide and really short. Okay, and really, it
would have been a lot better if we had gone five across and
four down. Because we'd have more space
across than we do have down in landscape. Okay, well there's
no way to do Autolayout. No way so that that would happen.
Okay, there's no way to put any relationships between them
so that they would just somehow flip over.
Some of the buttons would flip over from being along the top,
for example, to being along the left, okay? So you can't
do it that way. So what would you do if you wanted to build
a calculator that repositioned the buttons when you flipped
it over? Because it's not just the calculate,
the calculator that might want to do this. For
you example you know when you're in the master of
a split view okay it's not you're not in portrait.
You're probably on an iPad or
at least you might be on an iPhone 6+. In that master,
you also want it to be the right arrangement of buttons.
Okay, more like iPhone portrait, okay, than iPad.
Okay, so the solution to doing this is called size classes.
Okay, so your view controllers,
any view controller that you're doing,
like the calculator view controller,
always lives in a size class environment, okay, for
its width and its height. Okay, and that size class is
either compact or regular. Regular means
it's not compact, okay? So your view controller for each,
for horizontally and vertically, will get something
told to it, okay you are in a compact vertical environment,
or you are in a compact horizontal environment. And
you can react to that, okay? So in the calculator's case,
if we're in a compact vertical environment,
let's put five across and four down, because we're squi,
you know, squished down vertically so
we'll spread them out a little bit. And if we're not,
then we'll go ahead and use the vertical space and make it
be four across and five down, okay? So getting all this,
kind of all the different kinds of aspect ratios, and
things for all the devices to fit into this compact in
regular. You know it's not a perfect fit, but
here's a kind of general idea of how these fit, all right?
So the iPhone 6 Plus in Portrait, right when it's,
it's stand, standing upright basically.
That is compact width, regular height. Makes perfect sense,
right? Okay, compact width, regular height.
When you go to Landscape, now it's compact height,
regular width. Okay. So iPhone 6 Plus makes the most sense of
all of the devices. Okay? Now iPhone non-plus,
okay, is compact, in width.
Sorry, in Portrait, it's compact in width and
regular in height. But in Landscaped, okay,
non 6 Plus now I'm talking about here, it's
compact in both directions. So on a normal iPhone, non plus
iPhone, in width, you would think it would be regular
cuz it was regular when it was in Portrait in height, but no,
it's compact. So you can actually tell the difference
between whether you're on a 6 Plus or a regular iPhone 4 or
S or 5 or 6 or whatever, non Plus because you'll
be compact in both directions in Landscape. Okay?
So it's just kinda weird gotta be used to that.
iPad is always regular in both directions. Cuz it£s so big,
it£s not compact in any way, in any direction. However,
if you£re an MVC that is in the master of a split view,
you£ll be compact in width. Okay, understandably right cuz
you're kinda, jammed in there. This whole system,
by the way, is extensible. It's not just rock solid,
you know, hooked up to whether you're on a 6 Plus or
an iPhone or in a split view master or
a whatever. It has a whole mechanism for
an MVC to find out what size class it's in. It can even say
based on its environment I wanna be in this size class.
And then if it has MVCs inside of it like it's a navigation
controller or something like that.
Then they would inherit that size class information, okay.
Now I'm not gonna talk about that all the code side of it.
The only code you're probably gonna be interested
in is this method here in view controller,
Self traitCollection. Horizontal size class and
vertical size class and
it's gonna give you back compact irregular.
Okay? So that's how you'll know if you're compact
irregular. Now, that's only if you wanted to react
to your compactness in code. A lot of times we're gonna
be doing this in our story board. Okay? And I'm gonna
show you how in the story board we'll react to that. So
in summary it looks like this, okay? You got compact width
and regular width. Compact height and regular height.
So, iPhones (non-Plus) in Landscape are here. Compact,
compact. Regular width compact is iPhone 6 Plus in Landscape.
Regular height and
compact width is iPhones in Portrait or
you're the Master of the Split View. And
then iPads are regular in both. Okay. So,
if you want to look at the calculator, for example,
it would look something like this, all right. Now here is,
I'm drawing my UI here as if I've adapted to this. In
in this case right here, I've decided to go four across and
five down because I gotta lot of down, a lot of vertical
space. Whereas here I've gone five across and
four down cuz I'm kinda compact in height,
you see. Even here I've done the same thing.
I've decided here, compact and
regular width to go five across and four down. And
down here, in regular both directions I decided it
looks a little better to have the four across and five down.
Okay? Now you would imagine if I wanted my calculator to work
this way I might have to build fi, four different UIs, one,
two, three, four. For all four of these. Okay, and
that would normally be the way it is.
Except for that, we actually do size classes with a little
more subtlety than that. Because if you look here,
compact height always is five across and
four down. Whether it's compact width or
regular width, doesn't matter. And
here, in regular height, it's always four across,
five down, no matter what the width. So
really I should only have to do two things here,
okay, based on the height. I shouldn't have to do anything
different based on the width. And that's why the whole size
class thing is actually treated as a grid like this.
With nine things in it and in the middle you
have this special width and height called any. Okay. So
now if I want what I had on the previous screen,
all I have to do is two UIs. One for regular height,
any width, and one for compact height, any width. And
even better than that, I can actually put some of my UI
here in the middle, any height, any width. And
only put the differences out here in these other two. So
this the part of the UI that's the same on both right,
I got the display and I've got this part of the keypad.
It's the same on both. And it's only that piece that's
either gonna be here or here okay that is different.
And that's all I'm gonna have to do in these two things. All
right? So, we just add this idea of this any width and
any height to make a nine way thing. And I, in your story
board, you can actually go to any of these nine squares and
edit the UI. Okay? And that's what we're gonna show in our
demo here. Okay? So, I'm gonna do this calculator thing,
exactly what I just showed there. And
we'll see what it looks like to the size class business
in Xcode. Okay so here we are in calculator.
This is how we left off in calculator.
Actually it's a little different cuz I this is
the version before we did that save restore. So
I don't have save restore. So otherwise it's just a normal
calculator thing here. I'm gonna start right off
by noticing that I have this warning up here. You see this,
this yellow triangle that's all over the place here.
Telling me about warnings. What are this warnings?
If I click them, it's the old frame will be different at
run time. You guys, I'm sure, are well acquainted with that.
That you get it all the time, when you're doing auto layout
stuff. And you know the fix to this? Anyone wanna tell me
what the fix for this is? What do I do? Go down here,
right. Select this view controller. Go down here and
say update frames, right. Okay let's try it.
No. It didn't work. What's going on here? Okay, so
have you seen this? Where you do this update frames and
it doesn't work. I'm sure some of you have seen that as well.
Okay, well I'm gonna show you another way to fix this, okay,
which is also not going to work. In the document outline,
so here's our document outline right here.
You see this? I told you the document outline is
kinda the headquarters for constraints. In fact,
here's all my constraints, okay?
Look at this little guy right here, this little button.
This is telling me there's a problem with your constraints.
And you can actually click on this little button,
which I'm going to do. And it'll show you all the places,
all the misplaced views in this case.
It's going around showing them,
I can even highlight them as I mouse over them.
And you can even fix them, if you click on this little
triangle, right here. It'll come up and
you can do update frames to fix this. You can try and
update the constraints to match what's here.
I recommend against that, generally Because it's gonna
put hardwired constraints in there to try and
hold that thing in position. That's usually not what you
want. You can also reset to suggested constraints here.
That might be something you want sometimes if you know
that you put it on the blue lines,
but usually you want to try and update frames.
And you can even apply it too all the views in
the container, cuz we know we got five problems right here.
So, I can click those and hit fix displacement here, and
that should fix it. Nope, it didn't, okay. Now, I'm not
exactly sure why those either of those things didn't fix it.
It should've. But I'm gonna show you a tricky way,
to fix this misplacement problem.
Would you just pick up something, okay,
that's misplaced like this, and just put it back down
where you think it's supposed to be. Okay? Voila, okay?
some reason that causes the entire constraint system to
Because for
reevaluate everything's in the right spot, no issues, see?
No auto layout issues here, no yellow buttons up here. Okay?
So that's a real nice little trick to know, okay?
Just pick the thing up and put it back down in the right
place, might fix everything All right, okay.
So let's talk about our calculator here.
Our calculator wants to use size classes so that instead
of being four across and five down like this, okay, in
compact situations, it's gonna be five across and four down.
So I told you there's those nine little spots?
Here they are, right here, right down at the bottom.
See this W Any H Any? That tells you you're editing with
any height, any. And if you click on this,
it'll show you all nine of those areas, okay?
Just mouse over them. So the middle one is any, any, okay.
Up here, this is compact height, any width.
This down here is regular height, any width, okay?
Here is compact width, compact height.
So if I were to click on this and
go edit that UI, what device would this, that ui be on?
>> iPhone 6.
>> iPhone 6,
in landscape, right? Or iPhone 5 in landscape also, okay?
Cuz that's the only one that's compact. So
this is actually specifically choosing a non-plus iPhone,
okay? So you can pick any of these positions that you want.
Now we know in our calculator that the compact height, one,
okay, is the one that we wanna move these buttons down to
the side over here. Okay, here's a compact height.
Now, I'm gonna show you a feature here that you might
be inclined to use with size classes,
but it's not gonna work for us.
Okay, but I wanna show you how it works, which is,
I might just start by saying let's at first, at least get
rid of these four buttons when we're in this compact version,
okay? See here we're in width any, height compact. We're
editing this UI. Changes that we make in here are only going
to apply to this size class, okay, which is compact height.
Any time we're in a compact height.
Now, we can only make certain changes in here, like,
we couldn't inspect objects and change their color.
That's not gonna work. But we can remove and add views,
and most importantly, we can change constraints, okay?
Those are the things we can do.
So I said we can remove and add views, how would we remove
this stack view? Let's say we don't want this x divide plus
minus stack here, we just don't want it in there.
Well, we can go over to the Inspector, okay, and
inspect this thing. And look down at the very bottom, okay?
This is just the Inspector for the stack view.
And the bottom, it says right here, Installed with a check.
That means it's installed in all size classes.
And if we didn't want it installed in this one,
we can actually click this little plus, and
pick this size class, which is with any height compact,
or we could actually pick any other one we wanted, okay?
So we can pick any combination we want.
Since this is the one we're editing, it's,
the kind of the first choice right here, any width,
compact, height. So I'm gonna pick that. And when I pick
that, it breaks that one out. It's still installed, but
it breaks that one out with any height compact.
But if I click this off, it will no longer install this
view in this size class. So now anytime I'm running in
a modern environment where it's compact, that view,
that stack view's not even gonna be there. Okay,
if I go back to any any here, it's still there,
okay. It's only in this compact height that it's gone.
So let's go run and see if this is working for us.
All right, here we go. It's five high and
four wide in portrait. Looks good, okay. Hopefully,
if we go to landscape, which we know is compact height,
it should get rid of those four buttons, right? It did!
Excellent, see, this size class stuff works.
And now we'll just go back over to portrait. Oops, okay,
look what happened there. When I went back to portrait,
it tried to put that stack view back, but the size class
system can't put things back into other view hierarchies,
you can only put it back at the top level.
So it couldn't do that, so it decided to put it back, and
just put it back as 0,0 up there, okay?
So that's clearly not what we want,
that's clearly not gonna work. So
we need a different strategy, but I just wanted to show you
there is this feature where you can use this mechanism to
decide that certain views exist in certain places, okay?
And you're gonna see this is gonna automatically happen
when we start putting views in different kinds of views,
vertical stack views and things like that.
You'll see that this will automatically be happening for
us. So I'm gonna undo here, get that thing back, okay?
So let's get this back in our width any horizontal compact.
So that's not gonna work.
So what could we do instead? All right, well, since I
know I can't have this thing inside this stack view, right,
working, I'm gonna have to pull it out. I'm gonna have to
pull all of these things out of the stack view. So let's
just do that, okay? I'm just going to move this thing. And
actually, you know what? I'm gonna do all this in any any.
Because when I think about it, I can't have this here in any
any, otherwise, it's always gonna appear there.
Okay, in other ones, and I don't want it there,
on the top in compact, so
I'm gonna take this whole stack view right here, okay?
This one, the one that I don't want here, and
I'm going to just delete it, hit cut to delete it. Okay, so
now in the any any, that means on all size classes,
that thing is gone. It's not there. And what's more,
I'm going to take this stack view right here, and
I'm gonna pull the things out of it.
So for example, I'm gonna pull the display out of it, okay,
I'm gonna take this inner stack view right here and
pull it out, leaving this empty stack view, okay? Which
we don't even need anymore, so I'm gonna delete it, okay?
So now, this is all part of all size classes,
right? This is in all size classes. In the compact case,
it's this with buttons down here. And in the regular case,
it's this with some buttons along here. We all agree with
that? So in any any, we always wanna build as much of the UI
as we can that we know applies to all size classes, okay?
So this one, we know that this is gonna go
in the corner down here, right? And
we also know that this goes up at the top,
right? And we can even do the constraints here, or at
least some of the constraints. I'm gonna go down here and
reset all of our constraints by picking Clear Constraints
in the same place you Update Frames and all that.
I'm gonna Clear Constraints to get all these constraints out
of here, and now I'm gonna put new constraints in.
Now this part is exactly what you're used to,
I'm just going to Ctrl + Drag to the edge here and
hook up that trailing space. I'm gonna Ctrl + Drag to
the bottom down here, okay, at the bottom.
I'm gonna, for the display up here, Ctrl + Drag to the top,
Ctrl + Drag to the leading edge, okay?
Ctrl + Drag to the right edge, okay? So look, no errors,
no auto-layout issues over here in my document outline.
No little yellow thing, so everything is perfectly fine.
I can even run right now. Let's run and
see what happens. Okay, so here it is in portrait. Okay,
it's doing what we want, which is this down in the corner,
this up here. Of course,
I haven't added the buttons that I want right here.
And how about in landscape? It's working here too.
Of course, I haven't added the buttons here, all right?
So it's putting the display in the right space.
It's keeping these buttons over in the corner.
So this is great, okay? It's all working fine so far.
Now let's go and fix the two size classes. So let's start
with compact height, okay. In compact type, actually let's
start with regular height cuz it's the similar,
the most similar to the other one we have.
So here's regular height. Unfortunately, it's so
big I have to scroll up and down, but in this one,
we basically just want to put, take these things.
I just pasted them back, I had cut them before, and
we just to put it right here. Okay, right along the top.
Now the problem here though,
is that we need to put some constraints to make it be
the same as the rest of those buttons in the stack view.
Right? So, how are we gonna do that? Well there's a couple
of different ways that we can do it.
1. Is with these menus down here I told you about so
I'm gonna select this one so these two views are selected,
this whole big stack view here, and
this stack view here. And we're gonna go down here, and
we're gonna look at these alignment and pin menus. So
here's an alignment one. We can do thing here to, for
example, align the edges of these things. So it might make
a lot of sense to take this guy and have his leading and
trailing edges aligned with this one, right? So
let's try that I'm just going to turn on leading and
trailing edges here to align those.
I could also align things like the horizontal center,
vertical centers, I could horizontally in the containers
centered in the container etcetera. But I'm going to do
it, but also notice it's going to align the leading edges
with no delta. It's just like right along the leading edge.
So I'm going to add those two constraints. Okay.
It's added the constraints.
Now what's interesting here is now these
constraint complaints are red not yellow red.
And why is that? Okay, let's go over here and look at this.
And it says vertical position is ambiguous for
stack view, okay? It says it over here as well in my docu-,
no-, outline.
It's saying this guy has no vertical position to find. And
in fact, that's true. There, it's just floating there.
There's nothing that says where it is vertically.
We've defined where it is horizontally,
but we haven't defined where it is vertically. So
to do that, I'm gonna re-, go back to our Ctrl-drag, okay?
So I'm just gonna Ctrl-drag from this one to this one,
and this time, I'm gonna put Vertical spacing, okay?
Now he's got vertical spacing, so now his problem's right
here, are just the frames are not, are wrong, okay. And
again, I could pick up this thing right here and try and
put it there. I can take this, put it down here, you know,
try and move things back or
I could do update frames, but we're not done yet
either with this. Because there we fix the width
to be the same width as this cuz we align the edges but
what about the height, okay. We need the height of this row
to be exactly the same height as all these rows. And
it's perfectly legal for us to do that by going control drag,
okay, from this guy down to this guy. And
then saying that we want them to be equal heights.
Okay? See that Equal Heights? Okay, so
now they're gonna be equal heights. So you see how we've
put this thing basically and really stack view does a very
similar thing to what we're doing right here, okay,.
When you said all things like fill and fill equally,
it's making equal heights and all that stuff.
But unfortunately,
we had to move this stack view out because it doesn't exist,
in some of the size classes. All right, so
we're not quite done,
because we still want this thing to fill the whole space,
right? We want this nice block that we've built to fill this
whole space. So I'm gonna do exact same thing we did
before which is control drag okay from the edge of this.
And make it leading space, right be fixed here.
I'm gonna double click on it, try to make it standard.
That's not available so I'll go zero. Okay, makes it wide.
And same thing here.
I wanna make the distance between here and
here be a standard distance so let's do that. Control drag.
And down to here and this is the vertical spacing right
here. Okay, which makes this beam. Double click on that
and of course when we click on it it's also showing over here
not just in this little window, but
it's over here as well. And here standard is available.
Okay, so we can do standard height. Okay, so
this looks pretty good. In the regular height situation,
we've got four wide and five high.
So let's go into run, see if it worked. All right,
here it is, four wide and five high. Okay,
let's go to landscape. Perfect we don't want four wide and
five high there so we're just getting the any any
situation right back to here and is back. Okay so
it's working fine. And now, what we need to do is the same
thing we just did for regular for compact. Okay so
let's go to that we do that by going to this little nine grid
here we're going up to compact height any width. And
here we want that same thing right here,
but this time this has to be vertical. Okay.
So I'm just gonna go to the stack views inspector.
Here's the stack view inspecting it.
And I'm gonna make it vertical this time. Okay?
And I want to put it along here. Okay?
So I'm gonna use control drag to do it this time and
I can actually set up most of this using shift in here.
I think I told you before when this comes up You can actually
click multiple things, okay, with shift. So I can make it,
for example, the horizontal spacing, the top, the bottom.
I can line those all up. Okay? Now,
I don't actually want this to be equal widths, because I
don't want this to be the same width as this whole thing.
So, I'm going to have to do equal widths,
by making this the same width as one of these buttons. Okay.
So we do that to set those. So I'm gonna Control drag
from here to one of these buttons and
do Equal Widths, okay, so that this will be the same width.
Of course, we've got this whole frames are wrong,
so this time, just to be different,
I'll go up here and click one of these and
apply to all views in container. Fix it. Okay. So
now, we've got it there where we want it. Again,
same thing here. We want to put a vertical spacing
constraint here. Okay, we'll do standard if available,
yep. Okay, and same thing over here. We will put this to
the leading edge and again, no standard. Sorry,
so we'll do zero. Okay, there we go. We've got five wide,
four high in this compact situation, all right?
So let's run that. Okay,
here it is, portrait, looking good, landscape,
looking good. Okay,
any questions about that? Make sense? All right, now I wanna
show you a couple of things about what we've wrought here.
One thing is let's look at this stack view right here.
Look at it's installed state down there. See that?
It's not installed in any any. It's only installed in any
with compact height. That's exactly what we want. So
see how it automatically did this when we pasted this one
in? Any time we add a view to the size class, it's going to
automatically do this install magic for you here. Okay?
Now another think I told you was that the document outline
is kind of your constraint central. Okay?
So let's understand what the document outline is telling us
about constraints here okay? Here's all our constraints and
notice that some of them are grayed out and
some of them are dark blue. See that?
Well, as you might imagine the grayed out ones
are constraints that only apply in other size classes.
That don't apply here. So since this is any width
compact height, we're not seeing any of the constraints
that have to do with any width regular heigth.
if I switch over okay watch these carefully right here.
Okay? But,
You're gonna see some of these are gonna go like right and
some of these are gonna go dark blue. Okay.
So I'm gonna switch down here to any width, regular height.
Which has different constraints.
You see how this changed? So you can always tell
which ones apply to you, okay, by which ones are dark.
Now another thing you wanna do when you are using constraints
is to go magic number hunting. Okay. You want to look at
these constraints and hunt for magic numbers and
get rid of them. Unless you really mean to have one. Okay,
very important. So in here let's find some magic numbers.
Okay. Here's one, 8, here's 282, 82,
88 and 20. So those are all of our magic numbers right there.
First thing you wanna do is, only you can only hunt for
magic numbers in the ones that are dark blue. Okay,
you can£t, these 282 is in some other constraint in some
other size class, so just ignore it here. It£s like
you£re not even seeing it. But this eight right here, okay?
This is the one we do need to look at, okay? Cuz we just
don't want this magic number here. So what is this one?
This is the display's top to the top layout guide's bottom.
It's this one right here. Okay, so that's eight.
Okay, let's go ahead and inspect this. We're inspecting
this constraint. And you can see that it's 8 and
really what you wanna change that to is standard value.
And when you change that to standard value, look.
The eight's gone, okay? Now you might ask,
where did that eight come in in the first place?
Well probably we dragged that thing to, and used a blue line
to do, to put it there. And it was eight points from the top.
And so when we added constraint,
it added it as eight. But what we really wanted was standard
distance. Okay, how about this one right here?
This is the stack view's top to the stack view bottom.
That's this one right here. Okay, uh-oh, [LAUGH] that one
is a magic number, but that's the wrong magic number.
Because what is the distance in all these other things.
In this stack view, what's the spacing?
It's ten, remember that? Okay? So, we want the space in
between these two stack views to also be ten. Okay? So
this constant wants to be a magic number and
it wants to be ten, and it truly is a magic number. Okay?
So we want that magic number,
because we intended it to be a magic number.
All right? How about this one? 20.
Okay, stack view bottom right here. That one also,
we probably don't want that to be a non-standard value, so
I'm just gonna pick Standard Value, okay?
And we'll do the same thing in our other size classes,
so we'll go here. This one right here has
this Stack View.leading to Stack View.trailing,
that's right here, see it highlighted right there?
That wants to be ten. What else have we got here?
Anything else? No? All the rest of these are good?
And don't forget any any when you do these things.
So go to any any. Now it looks good.
They're all good. Okay, so I have no magic numbers now. So
my UI is all nice and arranged.
Now why do we wanna get rid of these magic numbers?
Because the built-in numbers, the standard numbers,
are gonna be the same in every single app,
not just your app. So when people are running other apps,
things are gonna look similar, similar spacing, etc. And
that's what you want, cuz you want a consistent experience,
not just inside your own app, but within you know,
two other apps, as well. What else did I want to show here?
We talked about insufficient constraints,
we talked about, okay. Conflicting constraints.
Sometimes you'll have conflicting constraints, like
two different constraints that are trying to constrain the
same two things and they'll be across size classes.
Those can be sometimes hard to find. Okay,
let's say I have my calculator app here. Okay,
I'm looking at any any here and I go away for
a few months and I come back and I look at this, and
I forget the fact that I had these other side classes over
here. And I look at this and I'm like, my gosh, I forgot to
control drag this up to the top. No, I better do that.
Okay vertical spacing and I better put this thing over
here my lead spacing. Yeah, well have to fix that let's
make this be zero and we'll fix this and we'll
make this one be a standard. Okay whew, I fixed it. Okay,
everything's good. Look I have no conflicting constraints.
I must have fixed my app, it's in good shape.
So let's go ahead and run it. I'm sure it looks really good.
What the, okay, that one's okay but what a mess.
What the heck happened here? And look,
I'm getting all kinds of warnings on my console,
conflicting constraints. You know what, so I've totally
broken the world, even though when I go back into my app,
it looks like everything fine. That's because when you change
constraints, especially when you change any any,
you wanna go take a look at your other size classes. Now,
when we look at that. [SOUND] Two views are horizontally
ambiguous. Three conflicting constraints. If we go down
to this one down here, we got four conflicting constraints.
When you have conflicting constraints, this little
yellow thing up here will actually turn red, okay? And
then you can click on that and see all the conflicts.
So these things are all conflicting, and
of course these conflict, okay?
We know why these conflict.
Because in any any, we've fixed the edges of this stack
view to some things. And in the other size classes, we've
also fixed the edges of these, this thing to other things.
Okay, like to this thing over here, for example. So
be careful about that when you have, when you're putting your
constraints in there, it might look like everything's fine,
but you could have conflicts across.
So I'm gonna undo all this. To go back here. All right,
another thing I want to show you is
just to kind of prove to you what we were talking
about with the compact width being on some platforms
not others, I'm actually gonna go up here to a different one
which is this guy right here. This is compact width
any height. That's what this square is. I'm gonna click on
that. So here's compact width any height.
Notice that it looks like any any because we haven't done
anything special in here. And I'm actually gonna drag
a button out. Okay, here's a button. I'm gonna drag it.
I'm gonna call this button, actually, we'll just do it
with a label. We don't need a button, this label here,
and we'll call this thing Compact Width.
Cuz we're putting this in the compact width any,
right? Then I'll even put it right here in the middle.
I'll do another control drag so you can see constraints.
So, I'm gonna control drag to my super view, okay, and
say center this vertically in the container. So
now it's gonna center this. So now when I run,
okay, any time I'm appearing on a compact width situation,
it's gonna say compact width. So
sure enough, this one, that's compact width, right?
We know iPhone 6 and portrait is compact width.
And here, this is also compact width cuz this is iPhone 6 not
6 Plus, iPhone 6 in landscape is also compact width, okay?
Now we know this is compact height, because look,
our times divide plus minus are not along the sides so
it's compact height. And
we know this is regular height because those things are on
the top. Okay, now let's go look at this on 6 Plus.
All right, so 6 Plus portrait is compact width,
okay. In landscape, not compact width.
It's regular width. All right? But this height is the same.
This is compact height because these are not along the top.
And this is regular height because these are the top.
Okay, let's take a look at iPad.
All right, so iPad, not compact width in portrait,
also not compact width in landscape. And it's
regular in height because, see these buttons on the top?
In landscape and it's regular in height in portrait as well.
So regular in both directions. Both landscape and portrait.
Okay now I'm gonna do something here,
I'm gonna go back to the calculator here and
I'm gonna put it in a split view. Okay?
So this is my calculator here, I'm gonna pop this thing into
split view,so let's grab a split view. I'm gonna make
this calculator be the master of the split view.
There is the split view. I'm to, delete this and this.
And I'm just gonna make this be the entry point, right?
This split view is gonna be the entry point. And then I'll
make this be the master. Okay? So now let's run on iPad and
see what we got. Okay.
Here we go. This is portrait. Here's landscape.
Okay notice or my calculator is compact width
when it's even if it's on iPad. But it's still compact
width because it's in the master here. Here's a really
interesting one. What happens if I'm in portrait and
I pull the master out? Not compact width. Okay
not compact width, even though it's the exact same width
okay as in landscape. It's not compact width, and that's
because there's actually API in the split view what when
you put that thing out it can pull out different distances.
And rather than have them try to be changing the size class
on the fly, sometimes it's compact, sometimes regular.
They just said, okay,
because it lets you tell these two different states, okay?
Whether you're in the landscape as the master or
you're pulled out as the master, okay?
Everyone got that? Okay, so that's it, for size classes,
that's it for auto layout. Again, only experience will
really teach you auto layout in the long run,
but you know where all the pieces of it are now,
and you know how to do control drag.
That's probably the main thing you're gonna be doing.
And maybe you'll be doing these menus down here,
possibly. Okay, Friday, no section again on this Friday.
Monday your current assignment is coordinate a smash tag
is due. There will be another assignment, Assignment 6 going
out next week. Not sure, probably gonna go out on
Wednesday. It might go out on Wednesday, not 100% sure.
I'll think about it over the week can't okay but
the topic of that assignment and in the topic of next
week's lectures is gonna be animation. Okay, a very
important part obviously building an app on iOS and
that's it. So I'll be here I'm here if you have questions as
usual, that kind of business. >> For
more please visit us at Stanford.edu.