[MUSIC]
Stanford University. >> Okay, well, welcome
to Lecture 13 of Stanford CS193P spring of 2016. Today,
we're gonna be talking about animation,
primarily. I'm actually gonna show you a little class called
NSTimer first, which we really don't use for animations. But
when we're doing animations surprisingly, we end up using
NSTimer sometimes. Not for the animation itself,
but just because animation is timing-based thing, and
NSTimer obviously is a timing-based class.
And then we're gonna dive right into animation, and
there's lots and lots of mechanisms for animation
in iOS, and I'm only gonna show you, you know, two or
three different ones. I'll talk a little bit about what,
what things there are, but I'm only gonna dive into a few of
them. And one of them, the simulated physics version,
I will get started on the slides today at the end, but
I won't make it all the way through, and
I'll just continue in the next lecture, okay. All right,
so let's take this little detour and talk about NSTimer.
NSTimer is a very simple little class that allows
you to call a method periodically, okay.
And you could either have it
repeating where it's calling it over and
over every certain amount of time, or you can actually just
have it call it once sometime in the future. Okay, so
it's a way to set up a time or to call a method. It couldn't
really be simpler than that. Again, we're not gonna
use it for animation, you know, things moving around and
stuff. There's other mechanisms for
doing that. But you're gonna see from the demo I do today,
wha, where NSTimer kind of can come in and be used.
It's actually quite useful in a lot of situations.
It's not a real time timer, you know? This is not a real
time operating system. You got that main queue. Other blocks
might be executing off that main queue, and so
the timer's trying to execute, but it can't cuz it's busy.
So it could be off a little bit but it's generally
going to try to set this, call this method when you say.
The timer's built on a mechanism in iOS which I'm not
gonna talk about at all in this class, called run loops.
For the main queue, there's a run loop set up for you, so
NSTimer always works on the main queue. For other queues,
you know, you may or may not have a run loop. You might
have to set up your own run loop, etc, so for the purposes
of this class, just assume NSTimer is a main queue thing.
Of course, when a timer goes off and calls a method,
you could dispatc_async to another queue in that method,
that's fine. It is just that the actual firing of
the timer, that has to be happening in the main queue,
for the purposes of this class.
Okay, so what's the main method
look like in NSTimer that does this? This is it.
Say I just scheduled timer with time interval.
Notice that it's a class method, right,
a static method on the class. So you invoke this by saying
NSTimer.scheduledTimeWithTime- Interval. And you just specify
how many seconds from now you want this timer to go off for
the first time, and then you specify a target and selector.
That's the method in the object that you want to be
called. You got this user info, that's basically
a cookie, right? You can put anything you want in there,
some context, whatever,
you can leave it nil if you want.
And then repeat is whether it's going to go off again in
this many seconds, at the beginning there, and
then just keep going off, over and over and over.
So it couldn't really be simpler than that. So
here's an example of calling it. All right,
I'm calling it for it to go off in two seconds there.
You see? Two seconds and I'm gonna call a method in myself
called fire. It has one argument.
We'll talk about that what that argument is in a second.
And then here I'm not passing any context or
cookie or whatever right there,
just nil. And this one's gonna be re, repeating. So every two
seconds this method, fire, is going to be invoked in self.
And so let's go ahead and look at fire with this argument
NSTimer in there. Here it is.
You remember from the selector syntax up here, this hashtag,
or pound sign, whatever, hashtag we call it now,
[LAUGH] pound sign selector. Fire, see this little
under bar colon right there means it has an argument. And
that argument, for NStimer is always the timer itself, okay?
So that's the timer that is sending you this fire
method down here. And
inside of the implementation of this fire method, you can
get this cookie that you gave it up here where it's,
now it's nil but if I put a cookie up there,
I can get it back by accessing the userInfo bar on NSTimer,
see? So that's how you get the cookie back. Cuz remember this
timer is going on some number of seconds or
even minutes later, and you might want that timer to
get that cookie back at that time. Okay,
now what if you have a repeating timer and
you wanna stop it? How do you do that? You call this method
on the timer called invalidate. Now a little bit
of a warning, if you call invalidate on a timer,
that timer is no longer valid, and
you should not do anything with it. You can't restart it,
really. There's nothing you can do with it. And
so it's usually a pretty bad idea to have a strong pointer
to an NSTimer, okay? Because you've got the strong pointer,
you invalidate it. Now you've got a strong pointer to
something that's invalid.
So it's much better to make your pointers to NSTimers
be weak. And when you do that, if you hit invalidate,
no one will have a strong pointer to it anymore. And
it'll leave the heap, and your weak variable will get set
to nil. So I recommend using weak pointers to NSTimers. Or
not having any at all because remember every time it fires,
you get this timer passed back to you as the argument if you
want it. Okay, tolerance.
So you can specify in the timer a tolerance, and that's
basically how much you're willing to accept some slop in
its calculation of when it goes off,
okay? So here I'm talking about an example where you
have a timer goes off once a minute.
You set the tolerance to ten, which is in seconds,
and that means if it goes off after a minute, that's fine,
a minute and three seconds from now.
Yeah, okay, a minute and 7 seconds, fine, but
a minute and 20 seconds, that's too long, all right.
And so why would you want this tolerance?
Well, because other things are going on in the system, and
if you really don't care about getting it right on time,
then maybe the system can be more efficient about how it's
using its processor and other resources during that time.
Okay, and notice that this tolerance does not cause
drift. So if the first time it goes off, it goes off a minute
and seven seconds after, the next time it's gonna go off,
try to go off two minutes from the beginning. And
the next time, three minutes from the beginning,
you see what I mean, it's not drifting. If it's late on one,
it's doesn't start being late on the next one.
All right, so let's do a demo of this, so
you can see it in action. What I'm gonna do here is I'm gonna
take our old friend FaceIt, okay, remember FaceIt there,
and we're gonna make it so his eyes blink, okay, and
we're gonna do that using a timer. So
it's pretty straightforward actually to do this.
I'm gonna use this opportunity to teach you something else.
Okay, I always try to do that. Which is,
what if I had this MVC right here. If you look at this MVC,
if you look at the identity inspector for
it, you can see that its class, of course,
is FaceViewController.
Right, you remember our FaceViewController?
It's got all this stuff our face views.
We got all that those gesture recognizer,
all this stuff remember that? So
that makes sense that that's what the controller is for
this. What if I wanted to put all my blinking stuff in
another class? In other words, I didn't want to put blinking
in with all this other FaceViewController,
okay? In other words, what if I wanted a blinking
FaceViewController? Okay, well, you can use inheritance,
this is object-oriented programming. It's not uncommon
to create a subclass of another MVC's controller to
create a controller you want for your MVC.
And that's exactly what I'm gonna do. Okay,
I'm gonna create a new controller here, new File.
Okay, to iOS source, it's a Cocoa Touch Class. But
instead of the subclass being of some UI kit class here,
it's gonna be a subclass of my class, FaceViewController.
Okay, and I'm gonna call it BlinkingFaceViewController,
all right? So, here it is, it's creating it,
putting in all the regular places where it puts it.
Here it is, I don't need any of this stuff, so
I'll get out that out of there. So
I've got this BlinkingFaceViewController,
it's a subclass of FaceViewController. And
in my storyboard, if I went to this and
changed in the identity inspector for
this, changed it from being a FaceViewController to being
a BlinkingFaceViewController. And hit Run,
do you think this would work? Yeah it would work, because
BlinkingFaceViewController inherits everything from
FaceViewController, so it's gonna work just as well.
Cuz, full inheritance of it. So, let's go back here and
remember what face this emotions app here does. So we
can pick our various emotions. You can see it's working
just fine to have this be a BlinkingFaceViewController.
Of course, it doesn't blink,
cuz I haven't put any blinking code in there, but
I am gonna put the blinking code in now. Okay, I'm gonna
put all that blinking code up here in this subclass. So,
the, this blinking thing is pretty simple. It basically
needs a Bool here, which is whether it's blinking or not,
we'll start it out as false, it's not blinking, and
of course every time this changes, we're need,
going to, basically need to start blinking, okay?
If someone says that, you know, if someone the,
if someone says didSet, changes this blinking thing.
So, I need a little private, oops, private var here,
startBlink, and
it's going to just have to start things blinking. And
actually, it's gonna want to look at blinking, though, and
only do the blinking if blinking is true. Okay,
if blinking is not true, it's not gonna want to do that.
Private, oops, this is not func. Private func.
[LAUGH] Okay, so inside the blinking there it's gonna want
to start blinking, we'll talk about how to do startBlink in
a second. Now sort of for the purposes of demo,
but also to talk a little bit about timers here,
I'm actually in my viewDidAppear, okay,
super.viewDidAppear(animated). I'm gonna
start myself blinking. So I'm gonna say blinking = true.
It's a little bit demoware, because you probably wouldn't
want a blinking face controller to always start
blinking as soon as it comes up. You wanna let people, this
is a public var and you wanna let them control it with that.
But it's good for the demo here and
also in viewWillDisappear, I'm gonna do the opposite and
turn it back off. And we'll talk about why I'm gonna do
that in a second. Blinking = false, okay? All right, so
we got this kind of infrastructure for
our blinking right here.
How are we actually gonna do the blinking?
Blinking is really easy. We're gonna start blink,
how do we start a blink in real life? We close our eyes,
right? So, we're gonna have our faceView.eyesOpen = false.
Okay, we just closed our eyes. And now, after a moment,
open them again. That's what we do when we blink, right?
We close them, and then pretty soon after that,
we open them back up again.
That's what a blink is, okay? So that's what we need to do.
Now before we talk about how I'm gonna do this,
let's look at faceView right here. This is interesting,
faceView, where does that come from? Anyone know where that
comes from? Yeah, inherited from this guy,
from faceViewController. If I go back to faceViewController,
here it is right here, faceView.
Notice it's not private, okay? Usually, we make our outlets
private. We didn't happen to make this one private,
might've been an oversight on my part. But
we didn't make it private. One of the interesting things
about Swift is that there's no idea of protected. How many
people know what protected means? Okay, not too many.
So, we know about private and public, right?
Private means you can only use it in this class, public means
you can use it outside the framework you're in.
Everything else in Swift is internal,
which means you can use anything, anywhere,
inside the framework you're in, including your app is kind
of like a framework. So this faceView is really available
to any class that's inside our app, okay? And, so,
that's nice, but, it would be maybe better if
there were another protection class called protected. And,
what that would mean is, only subclasses can use this thing.
Cuz, that's really what I'd like here.
FaceView, I really don't want other classes even in my app,
thinking they can start mucking with my faceView,
okay? But I want to be able to allow people to subclass.
So unfortunately can't do that, so
if you want something to be subclassable, and
it's used in a subclass, you have to leave it internal,
okay? So we're gonna leave that internal, and
that means we can use it here to open the eyes.
Or to close the eyes. Okay, so now how are we going to
do this thing where we wait a moment and open them? Well,
I'm just gonna use Timer, of course, that's why we're here!
So let's, some space here. NSTimer, it's called
ScheduledTimerWithTimeInter- val, notice there's two of
them here. See this one and this one.
We don't want to use this one, this one has a NSInvocation
which is really just a wrapper for a calling a method.
But I'm not gonna show you that, you don't really need to
know it because this one's just as good right here.
This one's target and selector so
this is what we saw on the slides. So here it is.
To make this is a little more easy to see here I'm gonna add
some carat returns here. Okay, so here's our
scheduledTimerWithTimeInter- val.
So, we need a time interval. I'm gonna be a good programmer
here and I'm gonna create a little constant struct here.
I'm gonna call it my BlinkRate and, so
I'll have a static let here which is the ClosedDuration.
Which will have the, I don't know,
you close your eyes for less than half a second.
Something like that. And then we'll have our OpenDuration.
Now this really doesn't wanna be a constant. If you think
about how you blink, you don't blink and then exactly five
seconds later you blink again. Okay might seem like a robot,
unfortunately this is kind of a robot. So this really would
probably would be some sort of function you know,
the kinda I don't know does some statistical distribution
of your blinking, but we're just gonna make it every 2.5
seconds okay. So we can this guy blinking pretty quick.
All right, so he's gonna keep his eyes open for
2.5 seconds, close them for 0.4. So here eyes are closed,
so we want the interval that we're keeping it closed before
we open it again. So this is going to be our
BlinkRate.ClosedDuration, okay. The target is going to
be our self. Now there's a restriction on this self,
the same restriction we had with the other.
A pound sign selector type of APIs,
which is that this class that's receiving this has to
be available to the Objective C run time, okay? And
so that means it essentially has to inherit from MS Object.
Now luckily, self, no problem because we inherit from
faceViewController, which inherits from UIViewController
which inherits eventually from NSObjects. So we're all good
to go here, but just don't get too confused if you try and
do this and it's like it doesn't work.
Because the object you send this message to has to be
Objective C compatible. So the selector we want here,
let's call it, this is the start of the blink, so
I'm gonna call, my selector on the other side end of blink.
So, this is, we're in our BlinkingFaceViewController
here, endBlink I'll call it, the argument on there, okay?
Okay, so, that's what we're gonna, we're gonna call. So,
we're gonna need a method down here, private func endBlink.
It's gonna take that timer as an argument, okay.
But we're gonna end our blink there. UserInfo, that's
a little cookie, I don't really have anything to say.
It's pretty obvious, I open and close my eyes. And
repeat is false. Okay, I can't really have one repeating,
timer, because you don't blink like this.
Eyes closed for one second, eyes open for one second,
eyes closed for one second, you know what I mean,
they're two different timers.
One is the closing one, and one is the opening one.
So I really need Two different timers going back and
forth rather than one just going repeatedly,
okay? Missed that there. Okay, make sense?
Now let's take a look here at this error.
You see the error right here? I put this in here, it's like,
what's the problem here? And it says right here, you have
to add a objc to expose this method to Objective-C.
So I said this had to be an Objective-C compatible method.
Well, what the heck?
Why is it making me put Objective-C there?
And the answer is because I made it private. Okay?
Private methods don't get exposed to Objective-C. So
they inject a C runtime.
As soon as I made that not private, now it worked.
Okay so note that as well. It has to be public method,
okay, or otherwise exposed to objective C. Which you can
do with that at sign over J C as well. Okay, so that's good.
Now another interesting thing about this endBlink here is
that I actually don't need this timer.
Because I don't have any user info,
it's not a repeating timer that I
would want to invalidate. Why do I even need that,
I don't even need that thing. Get that outta there.
And if I get that outta there then I don't need this, okay.
And that's allowed as well. Okay, just like we have
target action, or sometimes we pass the cinder along,
same thing with the timer. All right, so that's it.
What are we gonna do in our endBlink?
In our endBlink, what happens when our blinking is ending?
We got our eyes closed. Now, we open them back up again.
So now we're just gonna say,
faceView dot eyesOpen. Equals true.
And now, we want to queue up another blink.
'Cuz we just want to keep on blinking, right? So I'm going
to do that with another timer. So we're going to copy and
paste this right here. This time, though,
it's our open duration. This is how long the ice cream will
be open until we start blinking again. And instead of
endBlink here, now we're start blinking again, okay. Again,
error because this needs to be public, okay, cuz now we're
calling this one, these guys are calling each other, okay.
That good, everyone understand all that?
Okay, so let's see if that works for us.
All right, here's our guy right here. And sure enough,
he's blinking, okay? And you know, if we go to other ones,
they'll all blink. Got it?
Okay so that's it for timer. Hopefully that's a simple
example to show you how we use timer. So the eye blinking is
not really, we wouldn't really necessarily animation but
it's kind of involved in the animation,
right? And the next demo I show you we're going to
actually animate the opening and closing the eyes.
Because right there the eyes are just popping open and
popping shut, popping open. That's not really animating
them okay? So we'll show that in our next demo. All right
back to our slides here. Okay so
let's do a little overview of the kinds of animation that
are available in iOS. Okay this is most of the kinds.
One is there are three UIView properties that you can
animate the changing of okay which is the frame,
the transform which is like that rotation thing and
the alpha which is the transparency so
you can animate those. We'll talk about doing that.
You can also animate view controller transitions.
You noticed that UINavigationController when
you click to another one it slides into another it kinda,
it animated, like cards sliding in, right? Or
sliding off. So this whole mechanism for building your
own UI navigation controller like things, right,
that have little sub UI view controllers that move in and
out, and we're not going to talk about that at all,
because you're not going to be doing that in this class,
it's a little bit of advanced design, but when you go out in
the real world, you might figure out some way,
you know. I know the Facebook app has a little tray that
slides out from the left. OK? It's something they designed
and it's kinda like U I navigation control, but
it only slides out part way. Okay? So I'm sure they had to
use this mechanism to make that animation happen.
Core animation is a non object oriented,
API that underlies almost all the animation we're gonna talk
about here. Okay? It's the big beat engine
that's gong on underneath all this, it's making it all work.
Unfortunately I don't have time to talk about it,
we're gonna talk about the higher level things that
are build on top of core animation But
you should know it's there. And then a lot of people do
do Core Animation stuff in their final projects. Okay?
It's a good not-covered-in-lecture thing,
and there's things you can do in Core Animation that you
can't do with UIView level animation. Okay? There's
a window from your UIView into the Core Animation world,
which is the layer. If you look and there's a CA layer,
Core Animation layer, that's what CA layer stands for And
there's a property in view for
that, and that's how you can kind of get down to the core
animation layer and start doing core animation things.
Like core animation can do rounded recs on the edges
of your views and things like that. Masks,
all kinds of fun stuff. Okay? If you want to do 3-D,
there's OpenGL. OpenGL is bundled with IOS, so,
how many people here have experience with OpenGL or
doing 3-D? Okay, so a few of you. So you can do that,
full OpenGL support in IOS. There's also something called
SpriteKit, which is like 2.5D. Okay, this is how,
when you make an animated thing out of images that kind
of are overlapping each other and moving around, right?
Some guy walking though a castle and you know,
you find some monster, and he's fighting against it.
And it's not really being drawn in 3D like OpenGL.
It's being drawn with images overlapping, but
they're kind of 3D looking images. And so,
SpriteKit manages not just the overlapping images and
how they all move around each other. But,
it also can do particles, so
you can do things like explosions and fire and
all kinds of things. So, it's a really great thing for
building You know these two and a half D like animated
things, we're not gonna talk anything about that in this
class sorry about it, there's gotta be limits and there's
one of them. There's also for views dynamic animation and
this is essentially animating using physics so
you assign gravity and collision boundaries and
things like that to views, and then you just say go, and
gravity starts pulling on it, and it hits the boundary and
it bounces off and things like that, okay?
So it's physics-based animation of views.
That I am going to talk about again.
I won't have time to get all the way through that, but
I have a big demo on that in the next lecture. But
today I'm going to focus on the UI View animation.
The first one is this simple one where you can change
any of these three properties; frame, transform or
alpha. These are the primary ones you can change.
It will animate the change, the from and
the to, of the values of these three properties. So,
it's done with UIView class methods.
So you say, UIView, dot, animate duration, okay?
And, inside there, you're going to provide a block.
And inside that block,
you're gonna change one of these three things. Okay? And
it's going to animate that change over
time. Okay? And it animates in a very configurable
way, as you will see. What's interesting, though, is, even
though you're going to give a block to these methods and
it's going to animate these changes,
it's going to execute that block you give it immediately.
So these values are going to change instantly to the end
point of your animation. So even while the animation is
happening on screen, they're already changed.
Okay, that's something really important to understand
about how animation works in general, even core animation.
When you change things, they change immediately.
It's, on screen is really just taking your time to show
the user what the world looks like okay.
You're not actually, the animation doesn't change
the things over time, it only shows the change over time.
Okay, important thing to understand there. So
here's the method, or one of the methods, kind of the one
with the most arguments here, animate with duration right,
class function on UI view. You can see here that it has
a time interval for how long this animation's gonna take.
You know, is it gonna take two seconds, half a second, or
whatever? Also, you can delay the start of the animation,
like start this animation two seconds from now.
Why would you ever wanna delay that? Because maybe you're
gonna have some animation going on during that two
seconds, okay? So you might have three or four animations
that you queue up, one of them to start in two seconds,
one starts right now. It takes two seconds,
whatever. You can do that, so that's why you might
wanna delay the start of it, then options we'll talk about
later. Here's that block I'm talking about,
animations this first green one here, takes no arguments,
returns no arguments.
You can put anything in you want in there that changes
the frame, the transform, and the alpha, okay?
And then completion is another block, it has an argument to
the block which is boolean, whether it finished
this animation, you asked it to change to some end point,
if it got there with the animation, then this will be
called with this true. If it got interrupted somehow, and
I'll talk about how that can happen,
then this will get called with this finish being false.
In other words, I wasn't able to complete the animation
of those things you changed. All right, so
here's an example of calling this. Let's say I have a view,
my view, and it has an alpha of 1, in other words it's
fully opaque. And if I get to this piece of code, and
I find that my view is fully opaque, I'm going to make it
fully transparent and then remove it from the super,
from the view hierarchy, remove it from the super view.
Okay, take it right out of there. Okay,
that's what I'm gonna do. So, I'm not gonna,
it's gonna take three seconds for it to fade away. Okay,
I'm gonna be animating Alpha here, but I'm not gonna start
for another two seconds. I don't know why. Okay, and
again, maybe I'm making the view spin around for
a couple seconds before it animates out, I don't know.
Here are some options, for example, here the option I'm
using is curve linear, that means the fade out is going
to happen linearly, okay, it's going to fade
out from 1.0 down to zero,
which is where we're going linearly, evenly.
Okay? Smoothly. There are other curves that you can do,
and I'll talk about that in a second. Here's my block.
In my block, I just set my alpha to 0.
That's where I want it to be eventually, okay? So
I set it to 0. Now again, when I call this,
it immediately sets alpha to 0. Alpha's not going to be set
to 0 in five seconds, it's going to be set to 0 now.
It's just going to appear on screen in five seconds.
And in the completion here, I'm saying 'if $0', which
means if it finished, then remove it from the super view.
So if this animation of the alpha got interrupted,
by some other animation, then I'm not going to remove myself
from the super view, I'm only going to do it if
I make it all the way down to zero. This block, is going
to be executed five seconds from now, or whenever this
animation gets interrupted, if before then. Okay, so
this block is going to be executed later. Notice that
I put 'print("myView.alpha =\(myView.alpha)"' there.
This is going to print 'myView.alpha = 0' because
this 'animateWithDuration' executes this block and
returns immediately. So, myView.alpha is gonna be 0.
Okay? And it's gonna stay 0 all the way through this
five seconds that it takes for this animation to happen
because this animation really has nothing to do,
has no effect on the setting of alpha. It just,
is how we're presenting this change to the user. Okay
let's talk about some of those options. There are tons and
tons of options. I'm not gonna go over all of them for
time reasons here, but you saw a CurveLinear there.
Some other curves like CurveEaseinEaseout,
that means it start off animating it slowly, and
then picks up to a normal speed, and then slows down
again at the end. That's an, curve that we usually use for
moving things. Okay? If you have a view on screen and
you want to move it, so you're changing its frame,
you're animating its frame, you don't really want to go
[SOUND], okay? You kinda want it to pick up speed, move,
and then slow down at the end. Okay?
It's just less abrupt, turns out, to do it that way.
So you can specify that. Things like begin from current
state that's an interesting one. If you have an animation
in motion let's say our animation before, let's say
we're half way through showing the alpha going to zeros so
it's half transparent. And then some other animations
comes along and wants to animate it going to full or
peak. Okay, if the other animation said begin from
current state, then when it starts, it would start at 0.5,
alpha of 0.5. Okay, in other words it would grab onto
the alpha of whatever animations and process.
You can think of this as begin from current state means
use the values of these in the animation world,
not in the real world, because in the real world,
the alpha is zero. It was zero as soon as I set it to zero.
So, if you don't have BeginFromCurrentState,
then this new one is gonna use the real world one, and
it's gonna be going to half transparent,
back to zero, up to one, okay?
Because if you don't put that BeginFromCurrentState,
it pays no attention to what's going on in the animation
alone. AllowsUserInteraction, exactly what you think.
You need to put gesture, you've got some view flying
across the screen, can you touch on it while it's moving?
That kind of stuff, you know auto reversing,
does the animation repeat all these things you can go look
this up in the documentation of UIView. Okay.
Sometimes you wanna make other changes to views, not frame,
transform, or Alpha, okay? And you wanna animate the entire
change in there In, at once with some kind of cool looking
thing on screen. For example, dissolve you'd want
to change to dissolve in from the old what it looked like
before to what it's going to look like have it dissolve
over time. Or have it flip over, like I'm gonna use
an example of a playing card. If you have a playing card and
you change it from face down to face up,
you'd like it to flip. Okay you don't want to just [NOISE]
change to face up, that's very abrupt.
You want it to kind of flip over. Okay. And there's even
a curl up if you have a view that fills the whole screen,
it can curl up from the bottom like it's a piece of
paper that someone is looking under.
Okay you've probably seen that sometimes. You do this with
another U-I view class method called transition with a view.
Kay, you specify the view like a playing card view or
whatever, so this is the view that's changing,
and this is duration of the animation just like we
have the duration of the previous one,
how long it's gonna take the card to flip over or
whatever. More options the same options as before.
Here's the closure okay? This closure this green closure
here it can change anything at once about the view okay?
Because it doesn't have to be restricted to those three that
we know because it's not gonna actually animate any
in between states. It's just gonna take the end state and
the beginning state and flip between the two or
cross dissolve between the two. You see what I mean?
It's not going to show intermediate positions of
the frame moving around or anything like that, okay? Umm,
so this contains anything you want and it also gets executed
immediately, okay, even though the animation will take time
to show the flip, the change gets made immediately.
And then here's completion, the same completion thing that
will let you know whether it finished. This one is almost
always going to finish here, it's hard to interrupt. And
one like this. All right, so here's the playing card
example. I've got my playing card view up here.
I'm gonna take a little less than a second.
I'm using the transition flip from left option.
So, it's gonna flip my card over from the left edge being
lifted up and over. All I'm doing in my block is changing
some attribute of my playing card view. Card is face up
to card is not face up, so I'm toggling card is face up,
now when I do this that's going to change the whole look
of my playing card view from the back of the card to one
of the front, you know, cards face up. So essentially,
the system's gonna take a snapshot of what it looked
like before, take a snapshot of what it looked like after.
And then do a flip animation to show the new thing.
Or cross dissolve or whatever options teaches,
okay. So that's that.
Now if you're animating a change to the view hierarchy,
which is to say you've got a view in there and
you're going to remove it from consumer view and
replace it with another view, okay? You've got a view that
you're gonna hide and unhide some other view in its place.
Then you're going to want to use this one,
transitionFromView(toView So, the fromView is the view
that's in the view hierarchy, that's going to leave or be
hidden. And the toView is the one that is going to appear.
All right? And here's the time, and here's the options.
And here's the completion. Okay? Now if you use
the option Show Hide Transition Views,
then instead of removing it from view hierarchy and
adding the other one at the same place,
it'll actually just set dot hidden. Right?
Remember the dot hidden of our on a view, which makes it just
not appear. It's still in the view hierarchy, but
doesn't appear. This will set the .hidden of one, clear
the .hidden of one and, set the .hidden of one to true and
tip the other one to false so that it appears. Okay. So,
that's basically View Animation.
So let me show you a demo of that.
And the demo we're going to do,
two parts here in Face View.
One, we're gonna make our blinking actually, be smooth.
And to do that we're gonna use the flip. But
instead of flip from left, I'm gonna do flip from top.
As you can imagine, if you had the eye open and
you flipped from top, it would, you know,
more smoothly look like it's blinking. And
then for the head shake, so I'm gonna have
this face. It's only 2D, so to shake its head it has to turn
its head sideways like this. It's gonna shake its head,
and to do that,
I'm going to use the things where I change the transform,
which is the rotation of that view. Right,
remember transform is scale, rotation, and translation.
So I'm going to change that to make it shake its head,
basically. Okay, now that's an interesting one because
there's actually multiple moves there, and we're going
to have to chain them together to make it shakes its head.
All right, so let's go back over to A face view,
same place we were there. Now,
to make face view eyes blink, all right, right here.
These eyes need to be views. Okay, because I'm going to use
view animation. So if I want them to flip, okay, they're
going to have to be views. So I have to change my code. It
will turn these eyes into sub views of my face view. Now,
it's really not gonna change the face view that much, okay.
Let's see what it's really like to do that. So
to save a little bit of time, I create an a Eyeview which
we're gonna look at don't worry, okay. So
this is Eyeview. It's just going to be
a view that represents one of these eyes, okay. So,
let's take a look at the eye view. Here it is right here.
The eye view, this code in eye view is
identical to the code I used to have in face view, or still
have in face view which we're going to have to get rid of,
which is this path for eye. Remember path for
eye? We got either a circle, or it was a line, depending
on whether it was open or closed. If you look at this
code here path for eye, it looks just like this.
Okay, now I had to bring over line with color and
eyes open as VARs in my eye view, which I'll have to set
those from here in my face view. Okay, so
I don't need this path for eye anymore, because I'm going to
use subviews to draw my eyes. This is also good, another
way to show you using subviews of other views in code and
how we do that. All right, so I don't need path for i,
I also don't need to do path for i stroke over here.
Because I'm not drawing my i's in my drawRect anymore,
I'm letting a sub-view of mine draw them. Okay? All right, so
how we gonna do this, thing here? So I have a little,
again a little code here. That will, this little piece of
code right here okay this is how we're gonna do this. One,
I'm creating a couple of vars one for the left eye one for
the right eye. It's an EyeView right EyeView is just a UIView
okay that draws those eyes. So it's an EyeView, and
I'm creating it by calling this method create eye
on myself. Now, I'm gonna take a time out
here to talk about these lazys right here.
If I take these lazys out, this will generate an error.
Can anyone tell me why that's an error right there?
Nobody knows? What? >> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Yes. Exactly.
We're in initialization right here. We're initializing these
during initialization, self is not fully initialized.
We can't send it any methods. We can't send create eye to
self right here in the middle of initialization. Okay?
This is part of this class being initialized.
Until the class is fully initialized,
we can't call our own method. That's why putting,
by the way the error message you get in here
is kinda cryptic. So, kinda what it'd look like.
So if you see something like this, all right?
Then you might get the idea, maybe it's that thing where
I'm trying to call a method on myself while I'm initializing.
So why does putting lazy in here fix it? Because lazy
means that the initialization here doesn't happen until
someone asks for this var. Okay, until someone asks for
the leftEye or asks for the rightEye,
these =self.createEye are not gonna happen, and
no one is allowed to ask for
these vars until this thing is fully initialized. So,
all is well.
Because now we can call this createEye to initialize it. So
you see how lazy gets you out of that little conundrum of,
initializing there? And don't forget also you want to put
self dot right here when you're doing a createEye.
Okay? If you're gonna say this equals, you need to make it
clear in your initialization that you're accessing your
self. This creates each of these two eyes.
What does this create eye look like. Let's just create a new
eye view. I'm just calling the initializer here.
I'm going to set it to be not opaque, because eye view
doesn't draw background or have any background set, so
if there was something behind my eye view,
maybe some eye shadow eyeliner or something,
it would show through. Also, I got to transfer the color and
the line with on to the eye view, and
in fact, I need to do this not only here when I create it,
but I probably want to do up here if someone sets the color
right here. In addition to doing set needs display,
I probably want to set my left
eye's color equal to the color and
I want to set my right eye's Color equal to the color. And
same thing here with line width,
in addition to set needs display left eye dot line
width goes to the line width. And right eye dot line width
goes to the line width, and interestingly,
eyes open. Of course, we also want to pass that along,
but we don't actually need set needs display anymore for
eyes open, do we? Because eyes open is no longer drawn by us.
So if it changed, the eye view is the thing that
here we just need to say lefteye.eyesopen = eyesOpen.
needs to change, so
And rightEye.eyesOpen = eyesOpen,
okay? Since there and don't understand why we don't need
setNeedsDisplay? Because we're not drawing the eyes anymore.
We have a subview that does it for us now. Okay, so
here we've got the eye created.
Now after we've set the color and line width,
then we're just going to add it as a subview of ourselves,
which are great, okay. Now,
a little bit of a problem here, where is this eye? Okay,
we haven't specified where this eye.
We created it with this initializer which doesn't
specify the frame. So, it's like, we don't even know where
this eye is. It's probably at zero, zero and it's also size
zero, zero. So, we obviously need to position and
size each of these two eyes. Okay, to make this work. So
I created this little function right here to position an eye
okay, and it just takes the eye you want to position and
where you want the center of the eye to be. Okay, now it
knows the size the eye is supposed to be because it has
this skull radius to eye radius thing, so
it's setting the size to that. And it creates a rectangle
that's initially in the upper left with the proper size. And
then it sets the eye center to be whatever center you wanted,
okay? So, trivial little piece of code that just positions
the eye. So now the question is,
where do we call this position eye? Okay,
where do we set the position of these eyes. I can't do it
here, this create eye is could be happening any time.
I don't what my bounds are at this point.
Might not even be, my bounds might be zero zero also, so
I don't even know where my eye goes, so that's no good.
There's no view did layout sub views, okay. This is a UI
view, not UI view controller. Okay, so there's no view to,
there's no view controller life cycle. We're in a view,
not a view controller. So, we can't do that. I can't call it
from my controller. Here's my controller.
Because my controller has no idea that faceView is using
a subview to draw its eye. If you go look back in face view,
all this stuff about the eye, it's all private. Private.
Private. It's all private. So there's absolutely no way that
my controller can reach down into me and do that. This
is going to show you how you find out when your view needs
to lay out it's subviews. It's a method called conveniently.
layoutSubviews(). Okay? So,
layoutSubviews() is the method in view that's called whenever
the system wants the view to lay it's subviews out. Okay?
And those two eyes are subviews of ours. So we get to
lay them out. Okay? So, we'll call super.layoutSubviews().
Always nice to do that,
definitely wanna do that for
that. And then we're gonna position these eyes so
we're just going to call it positionEye with position to
leftEye. Where does the leftEye center belong.
Actually, believe it or not, from our old code,
we have this getEyeCenter method here, okay. So
we'll just use that that tells us the center of the eye.
Awesome. So we'll say GetEyeCenter,
the left eye. Okay? And we'll do the same thing for
the right eye. Okay? There we go.
So be don't confused in the difference between layout
subviews and view did layout subviews, okay?
If you did layout subviews as part of the view controller
life cycle, that's a view controller thing.
Layout subviews is a view method where a view's
being asked to actually lay it's subviews out, okay? Now,
a lot of times your subviews get laid out by auto layout.
Right, in that case you don't need to do anything in layout
subviews. But here these eyes, we can't really put an auto
layout for the eyes, maybe we could I'd have to
think about that actually, it might be possible,
believe it or not, but we're just going to do it in code,
so you can learn how to do it in code as well, and so
when layout subjects happen, we're just always going to be
moving our eyes to the right thing. Layout subjects is
always going to be called if our bounds changed. Because of
our balance change, we clearly need to lay our subviews out.
This ads of view right here is gonna call layout subviews,
because layout subviews to be called. Because anytime you
change your subviews you gotta lay them out again, okay?
All right, so see if anything else we wanna do here.
I think that's pretty much everything. Hopefully
this will work. Let's see if this works. I just want to
make sure I haven't broken anything. Obviously,
we haven't done any animation for the eye blinking here.
But hopefully, we've replaced our view. Or our eyes, rather,
with a view. And it looks like it's working, okay? Got these.
Let's see if we can rotate. Yep,
it's all still working. Okay, so we haven't broken anything.
So now, we want to make these eyes animate closing and
opening, okay, by using that transition flip from top,
okay? So, how are we going to do that?
So I'm going to do all that in the eye view,
I am going to be object oriented here.
The animation of the eye, that's an eye thing so
it should be in the eye view,
that shouldn't be in the face view. Okay,
to be in the EyeView. So we're gonna animate this thing right
here, this eyesOpening, okay. We want to animate eyesOpen.
So, how are we gonna animate eyesOpen?
Well, basically anytime an eyesOpen gets set, okay,
we need to set it in an animated way. So I'd
almost like to put something in didSet, except for
didSet would be too late, because it already got set
Okay, I have to animate the setting of it.
I have to provide a little closure there, right,
to that animate method that does the setting of it. So
it did set a little too late.
So I'm really gonna have to have eyesOpen via var
that has its own get and set. So
that in this set right here I can animate the setting, okay.
But I still need storage for the eyes open so here's what
I'm gonna do, this trick. If you ever find yourself in
a situation where you need to do something when something,
you need to animate the setting of something or
otherwise be Involved in the actual setting.
Not the react to the setting, this would didSet is for.
But you actually have to do the setting of it. And you ni,
make a public var like this that's computed. You can take
the storage and put an under bar in front of it.
That's kinda the convention we use to mean this is
the storage for another property that is computed.
Okay? We just call underbar. So I still have_eyesOpen.
It's just that I'm gonna set this, in here, animated.
Right? I'm gonna, say _eyesOpen = newValue in here.
But I'm gonna have to animate this happening. Now the get is
just return_eyesOpen I don't have to animate the getting of
this value. But this I have to animate. Okay, so I'm going to
animate this of course using UI view, transition with view.
Okay so here's transition, see there's the with view on and
here's the from view two view. So I'm going to use the with
view. And we'll do the same thing You do when there's
lots of arguments like this so you can see them all.
Okay, so we just have to animate the setting of this.
Now, let's start with the actual setting of this. That
happens here in this block. You see this animations block,
right here? So I'm just going to double click on this block.
Here it is. And I'm gonna put, what I want to happen,
inside here. See? So I'm animating this change. Okay.
This is gonna complain that this needs to be self. That's
because this is a closure. Okay? So we have to be clear.
Now, is there any problem with memory cycles here?
No, because this animation's only going to take
less than a second and this this closure will be gone,
so there's no worries about someone holding onto it and
it pointing back to us and keeping a cycle there. So
what view are we doing this in? We're doing this in self,
it's the eye view itself that's being animated,
it's being flipped over. And the time interval? Well,
we know that we close our eyes for 0.4, in 0.4 seconds, for
0.4 seconds. So, our time of causing the,
animating the change better be less than that.
So, maybe we'll say 0.2 seconds?
Something like that. We could play with these numbers.
Again, I should make a constant for this, but for
time, I won't do it. The animation options here,
we talked about. We want this transition, sure I find out
what it's called here. Transition flip from top,
I think it's called, yes. TransitionFlipFromTop, okay.
The addition, and we could put other ones in here. Maybe we,
you know, dot curve linear, or whatever. Put whatever
other options we want in here. And then completion. Once this
thing has closed we don't need to do anything. So
my completion here is nil. Everybody cool with that?
All right, let's see it work. All right, there it is.
So you see how the eyes kind of, see how they're kind of
squinching closed instead of jumping closed?
Yeah? All right. So it's getting better by the second.
All right, now let's do this head shake.
So now I want this little head to, to shake.
I don't know, to say, like he's saying no or something.
I'm not sure what. But let's do the head shake. So
the head shake, we're going to do by changing one of those
three special properties,
namely the transform. Okay, we're going to have
the transform of that thing changed.
And I'm gonna do that, mm,
I'm gonna do that in my FaceView right here.
Okay, it doesn't really have anything to do with blinking,
so there's no reason to put it there. So
I can put it in my FaceView. And so let's do it so that
it shakes its head when we tap on it. Right now, when we tap
on our FaceView, it does this, toggleEyes, right. If we
go look at our storyboard right here and
we look at this Tap Gesture Recognizer and right-click
on it, you see that toggleEye is doing toggleEyes in
our FaceViewController. So I'm gonna disconnect that and
create a new thing, which is gonna be a head shake. Okay,
so let's do a head shake. Now, I want to put head shake into
the FaceViewController superclass, okay?
I do not want head shake in BlinkingFaceViewController,
because it's not a blinking thing, it's nothing to do with
blinking, okay. But when I have this on automatic up
here, okay, it picks the BlinkingFaceViewController.
So how can I Ctrl+drag to put this in the superclass?
The answer is, just go to Manual. Okay,
if you go to Manual over here and
pick the FaceViewController and then you try to Ctrl+drag
in here, we'll put it right near toggle eyes, right here,
it's going to work. Because Xcode is smart enough to know
that even though this is a BlinkingFaceViewController
you're connecting it to one of its superclasses.
Okay, so we'll make a tap gesture action here,
we'll call it headShake. Okay, to tap gesture, right?
There's our tap gesture right there. Let's go ahead and
get the wider screen here. So,
like a real wide screen. All right, so here's headShake.
This is going to happen when we tap,
okay? So here's where we need to modify our transform,
and we want it, we know we want it to be animated,
so let's start right off the bat by doing our
UIView.animateWithDuration. Now,
you'll notice there's quite a few animateWithDurations here.
There's even one down here that has springiness in it so
that you can animate things springing,
things like that. But we're gonna pick the simplest one,
which is right here, almost [INAUDIBLE].
Let's do the same thing where we put this on separate lines.
All right, so here's our animateWithDuration.
So here I am going to make a little private struct, struct,
which I'm gonna have be my animation constants. And so
let's do static let, let's have the ShakeAngle. So that's
gonna be the angle of the head that we're going to shake, and
we'll go, let's see. It's gonna be a CGFloat. It,
let's go pi over 6. It's gonna be in radians, so we'll do pi
over 6, which is a little bit of a head shake there.
And then I'm also gonna have the shake duration,
how long it takes to move. And for that one,
let's do maybe half a second.
So it's gonna do half a second to move each direction.
So it'll take about a second a half to do the full shake,
okay. So here, let's use our duration here, which is
Animation.ShakeDuration. And here's
our animation, okay, so we're gonna put our animation. This
is where we're gonna change one of those three special
things. And then here's our completion,
which is gonna have this finished boolean and
then some code here when we're finished, okay?
And actually, in this case, I'm not going to, well, yeah.
I'm not gonna use closing trailing syntax here.
This is an interesting thing to talk about. So
this is one of the few times when I don't like the trailing
closure syntax here, because there's really nothing special
about this closure versus this closure,
they're kinda equal in power, maybe this one's even
more powerful. So I'm gonna keep them all inside here,
just kinda, to me, I think it reads a little better. But
it's totally a style thing,
whatever you wanna do. All right, so in here,
we get to change one of these three things. Well,
I'm gonna change the transform of this, of our FaceView.
So I'm gonna say face, oops,
and I'm gonna do self because I'm in a closure here.
faceView.transform, and I'm gonna use this nice,
function called CGAffineTransformRotate.
It takes an existing transform,
which I'm gonna take the FaceView's existing transform.
Okay, transform, is, remember, it's just a var in UIView,
that's all it is is a var, and it encapsulates the rotation,
scaling, and translation, okay. So
we're gonna be messing with the rotation here. And it's,
we'll rotate it by this angle which we know is our
Animation.Head, or, ShakeAngle.
Okay? So that's going to do the rotation there. All right,
let's see, what do we got here, what are we missing?
Completion. Yeah, sorry. Completion.
It's part of that trailing closure syntax, it deleted
the last keyword. All right, so everyone cool with this?
Now, what to do in here, we'll see later, okay. First we're
gonna see if this is working at all. So we're gonna see,
this is only doing the first part of the head shake, so
let's see if that animation works.
Okay, so our eyes, our eyes are still blinking,
they're still doing the flip from top. And if we click,
sure enough, it rotated it by pi over 6.
In fact, if we click again,
it'll keep on rotating. Now, notice the other animation
keeps working completely independently. Okay, all
animations, they, completely independent. They're only
gonna start interacting with each other if you're animating
the same thing, the same transform, the same alpha or
whatever. Here these are completely different views,
okay, and even though that view is being transformed,
it still continued to flip from top, okay,
which is kinda cool, it lets you make, lets you build
your UI animation very object-oriented. Just make
each piece animate however it wants to animate. Okay, but
our head shake, it needs to turn back the other way and
then back to the middle. So how are we gonna do that?
Well, it can't turn back to the other side until it's
finished turning to the right. Okay? So
we're gonna use the completion block to animate it going back
the other way. So as soon as it's finished, if it's
successfully moved over, if it finished. If it finished,
then we're gonna animate back.
Well, how the heck are we gonna animate back? Well,
let's just copy and paste this, because we know this,
right, this whole thing right here does an animation. So
we wanna do almost the exact same animation. I'm just gonna
copy and paste it right in there. The only difference is
that instead of the shake angle going to the right,
now it wants to go backwards times two. Okay, it wants to
go all the way back past the middle and to the other side.
And then sure enough, when that one's finished,
we want to do it again and get back to the middle.
So we're just doing three transforms here, and
we're just chaining them, okay, in the completion blocks
of each of them, we're just doing the next animation. That
make sense? Right? So that's how we chain animations.
So let's see if that works. All right?
So, here we go, he's blinking, and
he shakes his head. And again, we could play with this,
do we want to curve in, ease in, ease out. Do we want to
take a little longer maybe to swing back over.
And so you can play with those numbers really easy in here
just by setting options or Or durations. I didn't use
the version of animate durations that had the options
as an argument, but you could certainly add that back in,
okay? Any questions about that? You getting a good feel
for this whole UI view based animation? All right. Okay,
in the time we have remaining here, hopefully I can get
us going on this next kind of animation which is this
physic based one. So now let's talk more about animation.
We're gonna talk about dynamic animation,
which is this physics based animation and it's a little
different approach than the UIView-based. The
UIView-based, your pretty much directly changing the things
you wanna change and then animating that change, okay.
Here you're just describing how things interact and
then letting them go, okay? However they, they wanna go
based on whatever restrictions and physics you put upon them,
okay? So, here's how you do dynamic animation, here's
the steps. One, you're gonna create a UIDynamicAnimator.
This is the thing that does the animation. Very simple
object to create, it, but very powerful implementation,
it's the thing that actually is doing the animation.
Then you're gonna create UIDynamicBehaviors and
add them to the animator. Behaviors are things like,
gravity is a behavior. Collisions are a behavior.
Pushing things is a behavior, okay?
Then you're gonna add UIDynamicItems, which
are usually UIViews, but not always, but 90% of the time.
You're gonna add those to the behaviors, and that's gonna
make those behaviors start acting on those items,
okay? So it's a three way thing there. Items get
added to behaviors, behaviors get added to the animator and
as soon as those are all hooked up,
things will just start moving, okay?
Nothing else, you don't need to say go.
It just automatically goes. As soon as you add it,
it starts going. All right, so let's talk about each of those
steps. First creating the dynamic animator,
there's only two initializers of it. One takes no arguments,
that just creates a dynamic animator. But
if you're animating views, if the UIDynamic items you want
to animate are views, then you're going to want to create
it with a referenceView, okay? And that's just gonna be like
your top level view, usually, where all the animation is
happening. All right? So that's it.
That's easy,
it couldn't be easier creating a UIDynamicAnimator.
Next you're gonna create the DynamicBehaviors, okay.
The behaviors, generally you create,
their initializers take no arguments, okay? And so
you just create them, and add them to the animator here
using addBehavior, this addBehavior method.
Now, oftentimes, you'll create something like gravity or
the collider there and you're going to configure it.
Because the gravity can be strong gravity or light
gravity, like Martian gravity or Earth gravity, okay?
You can change that. Same thing with collider obviously.
You've got to decide what's gonna collide with what, okay?
But once you create them, you're going to just add them
to the animator using addBehavior. And
then you add the dynamic items to the behavior and you do
that with addItem on the behavior. So gravity.addItem,
collider.addItem, gravity.addItem 2. Now if you
did these three things right here, notice that item1 and
item2 would both be affected by gravity cuz I added them to
that. But notice that item2 would not collide with item1.
If item2 and item1 came, next to each other on screen,
they'd pass right through because they're not
both being affected by the same collider, okay?
Now if I said collider add item2,
then they would smash into each other and
bounce off, okay? So, which, behaviors you add, which
items to really determines how they're gonna interact.
All right, so UIDynamicItem, I keep mentioning this.
What is this? I said that usually this would be views,
UIViews. But UIDynamicItem is actually a protocol, okay? And
it has these three vars in it, bounds, which is the bounds of
the thing being animated, notice that that is get only,
okay? You cannot animate the bounds of something
in the animator. However, you can animate the center,
which is where it is, because that one is get and
set, okay? So the position of something in the animation
world is animatable, but not the bounds. In other words,
not the size, okay? However, the transform which
views have is settable. So you can rotate things, okay?
And scale them, things like that, as part of the animation
as well. So, this like I said, is usually a UIView but
you could actually animate off screen things or
things that you draw on screen using sprites or
something else, using this whole mechanism as well, okay.
But in this class you are only gonna do UIViews,
it's the most straightforward obvious way to do it.
Now if you think about these being UIViews, and
they've been added to all these behaviors. And
gravity is pulling on them, and they're colliding on,
off each other and bouncing and moving all around.
Maybe they're spinning around because they hit a corner or
something. Their transform is being changed.
If you want to change any of those views, if you want to
change their transform or center, okay. Then you have to
let the animator know, otherwise, it's gonna be
changing them to something else. And you do that
by sending this message to the animator which is
updateItemUsingCurrentState. When you pass the item, this
would be a UIView, right, cuz UIView implements in protocol.
And, then it will pick up whatever the current state is.
So if you move the view to a certain spot the animator
which moved the item to the spot in its world and
then keep applying all the behaviors to it, okay? But
it you don't do this,
you're gonna be fighting the animator. Okay,
so don't fight the animator, work with the animator.
Okay, so let's talk about some of these behaviors in
detail here. Gravity behavior, so gravity isn't always down.
Okay, gravity can mean any direction you want. Okay,
you specify the direction with this angle right here,
angles in radians, 0 is off to the right. So if you set your
gravity angle to 0 and put some views on there, as long
as your magnitude is greater than 0 everything starts
sliding off, accelerating off, cuz gravity is acceleration.
Right everyone know what gravity is?
It's acceleration of gravity, 9.8 meters per second squared,
right? So it's gonna start accelerating
off to the right. So if you wanted it going down,
let's say, down towards the home button,
then you would want it to be what, three pi over two or
something like that? Yeah, three pi over two I guess,
I know my radians. Cuz you want it pointing all the way
to down, okay. We're gonna talk about next week,
what if you wanted it pointing where real gravity was. And
once you know core motion, and you know how to use
the accelerometer that's in the device you could actually
be constantly setting this gravity to be actual gravity.
And so all your things could fall and
no matter way they turn their phone,
things could fall down towards the Earth. And then magnitude
is how, how fast the acceleration is happening.
What's interesting is 1.0,
the magnitude of 1.0 is 1000 points per second squared.
Okay, it's accelerating 1000 points a second,
per second, that's how fast it's accelerating.
This looks amazingly like 9.8 meters per second squared.
Okay, if you put something the top of your screen and
let it fall at this magnitude, it'll fall
very similar to how a real object would fall in space.
And it's amazing that this round number is so
close to 9.8 meters per second squared. But it's not,
it's not the same thing, but it's close. All right,
UI attachment behaviors. So what is this behavior?
This behavior allows you to take two items or an item and
a point and attach them. Basically attach
them with like an iron bar between them. But
the bar can pivot at either side, either at the point or
at the item or at the two items can pivot.
So basically if you wanna think about two items,
those two items will always stay the same distance apart
no matter what's happening to them. Okay? Now, if you had
a point, a fixed point, in an item, and this item had
gravity and an attachment behavior going onto it,
it would fall down and swing. See why? Cuz it's always
attached to this point, but gravity is pulling it down,
and eventually it would settle down. That make sense? So
attachment is basically a way to attach two things, or
attach something to a point. Now, what's
really cool about it is, while things are happening, you can
change the length of that attachment. Okay?
Right, right in the middle, so it's falling down,
you could just pull it up in close. Like a yo-yo. Right?
If you're doing yo-yo, you throw it around, and
you start pulling in, while it's still turning? Okay.
You can do the same thing.
You could build Yoyo quite easily here, by changing
the length of the attachment. Okay, the anchor point, okay,
if you have a point and an item, that can also change.
It's like maybe it's attached to the finger,
using a gesture. And you're moving your finger around and
the attachment changing, is pulling the thing around with
it. Okay, and I'm actually going to show that.
In the demo on Wednesday. So there's a lot of power in
an attachment behavior. Collision behaviors.
Another thing,obviously, that you want. Right?
Let's say you're gonna build your homework six which is
a breakout game. Okay? Obviously the breakout game
wants to collide with the bricks and knock them out, and
wants to bounce of the edge and bounce off the paddle.
So you need these collisions, right? There you can either
have things colliding off of boundaries so
like in your breakout game the bricks would probably be these
fixed boundaries. Okay your paddle's probably
a boundary that you're moving all right or
it can bounce off other things that are being animated.
Although you wouldn't want your bricks to do that because
your bricks when you hit them they disappear.
They don't go flying off the screen okay they They despair
well maybe would have a flat screen, I don't know.
So collision lets you set up collisions between boundaries
or between items, okay. You can have as many items as you
want in there, things all bouncing off each other,
the demo I'm going to do on Wednesday we're gonna have
a lot of things colliding with each other.
There's a nice little var here,
a bool translates reference bounce into boundary. And
what that'll do it'll make a boundary which is the edge
of your animator's reference view right?
So the reference view remember at the beginning of this that
kind of contains the whole space.
You can make it so that it's basically a box. So everything
that happens in the animation world as long as you add it to
this collision behavior will stay inside that box okay?
One thing that's nice to know about the collision is when
a collision happens. And the collision behavior has
a delegate, okay, which lets you find out when a collision
happens. So you get this delegate method sent to you
collision behavior. Here's the behavior that sent me to you.
And it'll tell you that contact began or ended for
an item with a boundary, or for an item with another item.
So there's the thing with item as well. Notice
the type of this with boundary identifier. NScopying okay.
NScopying is there for historical reasons but
suffice it to say NSstring and
NSnumber are what's intended to be passed there. And
we know that those are bridged to string and Int and
Double, nicely bridged. So you can pass strings and doubles,
the only tricky thing is that you're gonna have to use as
to cast this to be a string or an Int or a Double okay
because it's an NSCopying. Small quirk of the API there.
Next behavior is SnapBehavior. This is how you move something
to a new location. So, you got something sitting there and
you want it, move it over here, okay.
And, it's called SnapBehavior because it moves over there
but when it gets there it's like it's attached with
four springs to its corners so that it gets there and
goes [NOISE]. It vibrates a little bit. It doesn't just
slide up and get stuck. It slides kind of softly.
You can say how much the springs are dampened,
whether it really shakes when it gets there, or
if you get a slight shake or whatever. But snap behavior's
kinda the preferred way to move something from one place
to another, okay. Now a lot of things might be moving cuz
they have gravity and other things bouncing on them. But
sometimes you have a stationary thing that you want
to move and snap behavior is a good way to do that.
Then there's push behavior, okay. Push behavior means push
on this thing, okay, and you can either push it once and
see what happens to it or you can continue to push on it,
okay. So that's continuous versus instantaneous pushing.
And you just specify the direction or
you can do an angle and a magnitude kind of like you
do with gravity and it's going to push in that direction.
So, for example, let's say you had a view, and
gravity is working on it, so it's falling down the screen,
and you pushed up on it with a certain amount of force.
It would fly back up, but then gravity would still be working
on it, so it would come back down.
See what I mean? So pushing imparts a certain
force to it, but if it's an instantaneous push it's not
going to apply that force after the initial push and
other forces are going to continue to work on it. Right.
Okay?
Now it's an interesting about push behaviors is that if
they're instantaneous once you push on them you kind of want
to remove them as behaviors cuz they're dead.
They're never gonna push again. And
instance behavior only and
instantaneous behavior only pushes one and
then it's done so you want to really remove that behavior.
And doing that you kind of do that in an unusual way.
And I'm gonna talk about that in a few slides,
after I talk about a different method in a second. Then
there's this behavior. Okay, we're talking about behaviors,
right, for gravity and collisions.
Here's one called UIDynamicItemBehavior.
And this is kind of a meta behavior, okay.
This has a bunch of vars like allowsRotation, friction,
elasticity. These are settings that you make, okay, that, so
all the items that are added to this behavior will kind of
have these attributes. Okay. They'll be allowed to rotate,
they'll have a certain friction.
They'll have a certain elasticity when they bounce of
other things, okay? So these are really kind of effect,
affecting other behaviors. Behaviors.
So you can think of this as a configuration behavior.
You really are probably only going to have one.
Each item will in one item behavior.
It is actually legal to have multiple item
behaviors on same items. But you better be sure that you
understand how they are interacting with each other.
Generally though we think of them as just settings. For
the items, how they're gonna behave with collisions and
all these other things. The UIDynamicItemBehavior,
you almost always have one, by the way,
cuz you want to set these things. It's also really cool,
because you can ask the dynamic item behavior for
any item that's added to that behavior.
You can say, what's its current linear velocity?
I got some viewage bouncing along the screen because it
collided and gravity's pulling on it and
I want to know what's it's velocity?
Right now at this instant, how fast is it moving and in what
direction? Okay, so that's really nice to know especially
if you're gonna pause your game. Or pause what's going on
and then continue. You want to grab its linear velocity,
stop the animation and when it starts again set the linear
velocity back to what it was, cause you can set it as well,
by adding linear velocity back in.
You can also find angular velocity, if the thing is
spinning, k how fast it's spinning, spinning really fast
or just kind of slowly rotating, whatever okay.
UI dynamic behavior as opposed to UI dynamic
item behavior the last I was here UI dynamic item behavior.
This is UI dynamic behavior. This is the super class of all
behaviors okay? And you can create your own behaviors as
a composite of other behaviors by using this addChildBehavior
method and UIDynamicBehavior. So you simply
subclass UIDynamicBehavior, addChildBehavior for
all the composite behaviors you want. The gravity and
the dynamic item behaviors and collision, whatever.
You add all those child behaviors.
And then add any items to all of those behaviors, and you've
created a composite new kind of behavior, which collects
all those into one. And if we have some set of behaviors
that's operating on a whole bunch of items, we are very
often going to create our own little composite subclass.
And I'll do that in the demo cuz it's pretty common, okay?
One thing that's cool about UIDynamicBehavior is it has
a var called DynamicAnimator, which will get you
the UIDynamicAnimator that this behavior is in.
Because remember we add behaviors to dynamic animators
as like the second slide I showed you.
So you can find out what it is. And
in fact it'll even tell you if you move to an animator.
That's usually you, the animator being taken away from
you because they wanna stop animation, or
add it back to you to continue animation, okay? So
that's a good way to find out that that's happening. Okay,
UIDynamicBehavior also has a really cool var
called action which is a closure, okay?
You can set this closure to anything you want and
every time this behavior does anything,
it's gonna call this closure. So some behaviors call this
thing all the time cuz they're always acting on
the particular items, okay? So you wawnna be careful to make
sure whatever's in this closure is really efficient.
This is one of those cases where you do wanna kinda
think about optimizing prematurely here because
this could be called a lot.
So you don't wanna do anything expensive in here.
Okay, but it's really kinda cool because you can then
do things as the animation is happening, finding as things
are happening in the animation you can be getting involved.
Okay, so it's really kind of a cool method.
Now one of the uses we can do for
this is that push behavior conundrum,
you got an instantaneous push, it's already pushed. Now you
wanna remove it. Well this would be a great way to do it.
Just have an action on that push behavior then set
the push behavior to remove itself when you're done and
this is what it would look like. Oops, no, sorry.
One more thing before I talk about that. This is
the dynamic animator also has a delegate. And it'll tell
you when the animator paused or resumed. Now what causes
the animator to pause? It's when all the objects reach
stasis. In other words, none of the behaviors are causing
any of the objects to change, okay? Then it pauses.
As soon as a push comes in or something like that,
causes things to start moving again, it will resume. So you
can find out when things have reached a steady state and
when they resume, using these delegate methods
of the dynamic animator, okay? All right, back to that push
state that I was talking about. All right, so
here I've created a push behavior with a certain
magnitude and angle, right? And look what I've got.
I've set the push behavior's action to be,
remove this pushBehavaior from the dynamic animator.
You see that? And since it's instantaneous,
see how its mode is instantaneous? This is fine.
I want this thing removed. I don't want it sitting around
there collecting dust because it's not gonna fire ever
again. It fired, the action method got called,
I put this closure method in here to do this. But
of course this has a memory cycle, a really bad one, okay?
Because, this push behavior has a var
action which is a closure. So, it has a strong pointer to
this closure. Push behavior's action is a strong pointer to
this closure. And this closure references the pushBehavior,
so it has a strong pointer back to the pushBehavior. So
this will happen just fine and
now the only people pointing to this pushBehavior,
since it got removed from the dynamicAnimator, the only
thing pointing to it is this closure. And it's pointing to
closure, so they're keeping each other in the heap, okay?
So this is our classic memory cycle.
And just to remind how we break it here,
we're just gonna put unowned pushBehavior in here. Cuz we
know that this can never be out of the heap when action is
called by definition. Okay, action is only called when his
pushBehavior does anything. So it has to clearly still be in
the heap [INAUDIBLE] done anything, okay?
So we can just put out known pushBehavior, boom,
breaks our cycle. This will be just a refresher course in
breaking the recycles. Okay, I made it. Okay, so as before,
here's what we're doing coming up. If you have any
questions I will be here as usual.
>> For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu