[MUSIC]
Stanford University. >> Okay well welcome
then to Lecture 14 of CS Stanford CS193P,
Spring of 2016. Today, we have two topics. One is,
I'm gonna continue the dynamic animation we talked about in
the last lecture and slides with a big ol' demo. Okay,
that really shows a lot of dynamic, animation in action
and homework Assignment Six is all about dynamic animation,
so be preparing you for that. And then I'm gonna do a new
topic. I had said last time it was probably gonna be Alerts,
but actually I'm gonna do CoreMotion now, okay.
And we'll, I'm gonna redo some slides on CoreMation,
Core Motion, and then I'll also do a demo. Hopefully I'll
have enough time to do all of that today, all right. Okay,
so let's dive right into this demo. It's called Dropit. It's
basically as if I were gonna go write a Tetris app, okay,
with the little falling blocks that you put in place and
then you complete a row and the row would disappear and
then more blocks would come down. Kinda like that,
but this is a demo. We're starting from scratch.
So we're just gonna have little individuals
blocks come down and when they all make a row then it'll
disappear. So we're not gonna do the L-shaped and T-shaped
blocks from Tetris. We're just gonna do squares only. Okay,
so it's kind of like we're getting started on Tetris.
So I'm not calling it Tetris because it doesn't look enough
like Tetris for that.
I'll call it DropIt because we're gonna dropping,
little squares. Okay, so I'm gonna create a new project
here. It's an iOS application as always. Single view..
I'm gonna call it Dropit. Okay, we don't need core data.
Okay it can be universal app,
I don't see any reason why this app wouldn't be
universal as you'll see. Okay. So here's Dropit,
we'll put it where we always put everything. Here it is.
Now what's interesting about Dropit is I'm gonna build
the entire user interface in code. So my story board all
it's gonna have is one custom view. Okay, and then I'm
gonna do all in code because we're gonna use the animator.
We're gonna have a lot of animated views going on.
That's what's gonna be the entire UI. So,um,
I don't really want this generic ViewController here.
So I'm just gonna take this generic ViewController and
delete it, okay, move it to the trash. And
then I'm going to do the thing we always do here where we
take these little guys and move them off into supporting
files because we don't need to do anything, supporting files,
because we don't really need to do anything with them. And
so I'm gonna right off the bat create a custom ViewController
for this view controller that I have here in my storyboard.
And I'm also gonna create a custom UIView.
And that UIView is really where the logic of my game is,
you can almost think of it as like a gameView. Right, and
I could actually put this view anywhere in any UI and
it would play this game,
the Tetris-like game we gonna call DropIt. So let's go and
create those two classes. The UI view controller and
UI view. So here's to UI view, we'll call it DropItView.
Okay, it's gonna be the DropItView.
I'll put it in the same place here not in supporting files.
I'm gonna put where all the rest of the things are. Hey,
there's my DropItView.
My DropItView actually is not gonna implement DrawRect,
okay, it's gonna implement its entire existence with
subviews. Okay, so it's not even gonna have, a DrawRect in
my DropItView. And then I also need, my controller, okay.
So same thing here. But this is gonna be UIViewController,
and I'm gonna call it my DropItViewController, okay.
Same place. Okay, there's my DropItViewController,
you're gonna clear all this stuff out. All right, now that
I have these two classes, I'm gonna make my storyboard
just make it so that this ViewController that I have,
I'm gonna go to the Identity Inspector over here and
instead of having it be just
plain ViewController,
it's gonna be a DropItViewController.
Okay, and same thing inside here I'm just gonna put a view
a generic UI view, so let's scroll down and find that,
where that is. Where is that? Right here it is. Okay,
generic UI view I'm gonna put in here and
I'm gonna change its identify to be DropItView. Okay.
Now I'm gonna have, use constraints here to have this
fill my entire view controller here. You're gonna put
it right there. Use the blue lines to put it on the edges
then we'll go down to here, oops, down to here,
and we'll say reset to suggested constraints.
I always like to look in the Size Inspector, make sure it
did what I wanted, which it looks like it did. Okay. So
I've got this DropItView in here inside my
DropItViewController. I'm also gonna create an outlet from
one to the other. Okay? Okay, so I'm just gonna control drag
into my DropItViewController to create this view.
I'm gonna call it my gameView. You can see there's of type
DropItView, which is good. It's what I want. Okay, so
I've got my gameView. So this is my basic setup of
my game, all right. And really all the controller's gonna do,
maybe set up some gestures, possibly a little bit
of ViewController life cycle here and there, but most
of the logic is going to be inside this DropItView class.
Okay. So Let's make our screen bigger here. All right.
So let's dive right in to this DropItView. I'm gonna have my
DropItView start by being able to put a little square. Okay,
these things that are gonna fall down like Tetric, Tetris,
except for there's gonna be squares.
I'm gonna have a little method that puts a square there.
Okay so I'm gonna need a little bit of some private
data here. How about Private let dropsPerRow = 10.
So this is how many of these little drops that are gonna
fall down will fit across the top of my view,
they're falling down from the top, right? So
this is how many. So ten across is a good number,
I think. And then I'm gonna have a dropSize, okay,
which is gonna be a CGSize. That's gonna be the size
of each of the little things that falls down.
And I'm gonna have that be calculated. Kay?
And I'm gonna calculate it by having the size,
have it be square. And we'll have the size be the width,
whatever our width is at the time we ask this,
divided by the number of drops per row. Right, so
I'm gonna have the size be so that they'll fit across
the width of our view. Now, by the way,
our app might rotate and this width might change, so
the drops might actually change as we rotate and stuff.
But we can decide if that's what we wanted or not, but
this is perfectly fine.
So, now I'm just gonna create a CG size here whose width
is the size and whose height is the size. So it's square,
basically. So this is gonna be the size of a drop,
a square that fits ten across the top.
Now I'm gonna have a function called addDrop, that just
adds one of these things. One of these little squares that's
gonna fall down from the top to the view. So, of course,
we need the size of this drop, to be put into a frame.
So I'm gonna create a frame which is CGRect. The origin
of the frame is gonna be at CGPoint.zero to start.
I'm gonna put it up in the upper left hand corner and
then I'm gonna move it over into one of the slots along
the top. And the size of course is the dropSize. So
let's do that frame movement. So I am gonna move
the origin.x = and really what I want here is a random
float somewhere between 0 and the drops per row. Okay,
that's pretty much where I am going to put it.
So, if I like to sometimes, if I want to have a function on
CG float called random I'll actually make extensions and
so I've made some extensions, here they are right here,
UIKitExtensions.swift which I'm gonna copy in here. And
these extensions are just kinda some convenient things
that I've created that are gonna help my demo go
quicker. So you can see I have created this random function
on CGFloat. I've created a random function on UIColor
which gives me a random color. Kind of fun, right?
And then some CGRect things here, other stuff,
so you can look through this later at your leisure.
But I'm going to use one of here,
which is this CGFloat.random That takes an int,
dropsPerRow. Okay, and so that's gonna create a random
float between 0 and dropsPerRow, and
then I'm going to multiply that times our dropSize width.
So I've picked a spot across the top a random spot across
the top there. So now, I'm gonna create the drop.
I'm just gonna say it's a UIView a generic UIView
whose frame is frame. Okay, that this frame I just created
right here. So I got the drop. And let's set the drops back
color to a random color equals UIColor, that random.
Yeah, that's one of my UI kit extensions that I created
there And then we're gonna add sub-view, the drop, okay?
Just put it, on screen, okay? Make sense? Now,
I'm gonna cause this add drop to happen whenever I tap, so
I'm gonna put a gesture recognizer back here at my
control. A lot of this, by the way, is review hopefully for
you guys, but I'm going to, when my game view gets set
here I'm gonna add a gesture recognizer. So
I'm just gonna say gameView.addGestureRecognizer.
It's gonna be a tap. UITapGestureRecognizer.
The target: is gonna be my self,
and the action: will be, let's say a #selector.
We'll call it addDrop. This one has an argument. Okay?
Cuz it's a gesture recognizer. Okay, so we'll just do that.
And then, I'm gonna have a little func here. Add drop,
which takes a recognizer which is a UITapGestureRecognizer.
What did I do here that's no good? That's good.
We fix that. All right, so when we have TapGesture
we basically wanna check to see if the recognizer state
has moved to ended if it does then there was a tap. And
now, I'm just gonna tell my game view,
okay go ahead and add one of those drops. Okay everybody
see what I did there? Just create a little tap gesture,
just gonna call this method addDrop over in my drop it
view. So let's switch over to the DropItView it again.
It's gonna call it, cause this add drop to happen right here.
All right, so let's go ahead and run,
we'll run on iPhone 6 here. So now, when we tap,
it should put a random color block along the top. Okay,
so tap, there it is, a green one, purple, okay, excellent.
You see, as I click,
it puts more along the top. Now of course, we want these
things to fall down. Okay, we want them to fall down to
the bottom and we know how to do that with Dynamic Animator.
We're just gonna create a gravity behavior, okay, and
the default gravity behavior is downward gravity at 1,000
points per second squared. So that's exactly what we want.
So that's all we need to do is create a gravity behavior and
add it to an animator.
So let's do that. Up here, we're gonna create a private
let gravity equal a ui gravity behavior, okay?
And of course, I also need an animator so I'm gonna say
private let animator which is gonna be a ui dynamic
animator. And actually, let's just create one right here.
You and I dynamic animator. And we know that when
we created dynamic animator that's gonna be animating
views. We wanna say what the reference view is. Okay. Which
in this case is, self. Okay. Where Drop it view is a view.
So referring to yourself. Now, we have an error here.
Anyone know what the problem here is? Okay,
what are we doing right here? Initializing, right?
We're initializing. Can we refer to self when we're
initializing? No, because self is not fully initialized yet.
So we can get around this though with our favorite
lazy var. Okay. So now, it's not gonna initialize this
until someone ask for the animator.
And that's not gonna happen until we're finish the slide.
So we're winning, right? Okay. So we got that. Now, I'm gonna
actually make a public var called here called animating,
which is gonna be a boll, and we start it out equal
to false. And this is gonna be basically how we turn on and
off the animating. If you say, animating = true,
then we're gonna have these blocks animating. If you say,
animating = false, they'll stop animating. Okay, so
it's kind of like the on/off switch for our DropItView. So
what are we gonna do here? I'm gonna say if someone sets
this, then if they set it to true, then I'm going
to animate this. Which all I need to do to animate, is
to take the animator and add the behavior of the gravity.
Okay? As soon as you add the behavior
to the animator it's going to start animating it.
Okay? And similarly if they turn animating off,
then I'm just going to do the opposite, I'm going to remove
That gravity behaviour. Okay, and that's going to stop
it animating. Okay, got that? Let's go ahead and set this.
We're going to set this in our controllers.
I'm going to go back to our controller right here, and
let's do this in our view controller live cycle. So
how about in View Did Appear? As soon as View Did Appear
happens, let's go ahead and set this gameView's animating
To true. Okay, so that's gonna start it animating.
And similarly, on viewWillDissapear, We
will turn the animation off. Cuz we really don't want this
thing animating while we're not even on screen. So. It's
a good place to turn it on and off. Everyone understand that?
Okay. If you don't understand anything I'm saying,
feel free to stop me. Okay? All right. So
that turns it on and off. We got this thing going. The only
thing we need to do here is this behavior, currently there
are no items that have been added to this behavior.
So nothing, this gravity is not affecting anything.
So of course, every time we add a br-, a drop down here,
we're gonna want to add it to the behavior,
gravity.addItem this (drop). Okay, and
that makes that gravity start affecting that drop.
We've got all that? So that's, we've seen all the steps now,
dynamic animation of making it work, right?
We created the animator, we created our behavior, we added
the behavior to the animator, and then we added items that
we wanted affected by that behavior to the behavior.
All right, so let's go see this work.
Okay, so here we go, let's run,
let's try tap this user or
tap just just to here, and look they're falling down.
See they all fall and we can click as many as we want and
they all fall. Now the problem with this from a Tetris point
of view is they just fall off the bottom and
we really want them to hit the bottom and stop, right? And
pile up so that they will make rows and
we can clear the rows out. Right? So the next thing we're
going to do is put a boundary and we're going to put
the boundary all the way around this thing. Okay.
It's a real simple way to create a collision boundary
all the way around this reference view right here.
So let's do that. All right? Go back over here.
So do that we need to create another behavior like
the gravity behavior. And this one I'm gonna call my collider
and it's gonna be UICollisionBehavior. Okay?
Now I could just do that. The problem is I need to
configure this, cuz I wanna tell this collision behavior,
make the bounds of the reference view be a boundary.
So I'm gonna create this in kind of a cool way,
hopefully you'll remember that you can do this.
I'm gonna do it with a closure.
I'm gonna initialize this variable by executing
this closure right here, and remember that we can do that.
So I'm going to create a little local variable here.
Happens to be called the same thing but
wouldn't have to be of the same thing as a variable.
This is just a local inside this enclosure. And
I'm gonna set the collider to translateReferenceBoundsIntoB-
oundary = true. And if you do that,
the UICollisionBehavior will automatically have the bounds
of the reference view be a collision boundary.
Then, we'll return the collider here, okay?
Make sense? Now, this collider,
just like the gravity, here, sorry. If you do this when you
make a closure, don't forget that you have to explicitly
type the var here, and that's because it wants to be
able to check to make sure the return value here matches what
you want it to assign to here. Okay, so
just like we added the gravity behavior,
we're gonna have to add the collider as well, so
just like, here's the gravity, we're gonna do collider, and
same thing obviously when we stop animating,
we want to remove the collider. Okay, and also down
here, we want gravity to work on the drops, we also want
the collider to work on the drops. If I didn't do this,
then the drops would still keep falling off the end,
because the collider would not be behaving,
the collider behavior would not apply to them, okay?
Everybody got that? So let's see if that works. All right,
here we go, drop, and, sure enough, look,
they're piling up. And here when, no, we're never gonna
get a completed row there, how are we gonna do that?
All right, well, we obviously need more behaviors here than
we have. And the next behavior we want to do is a behavior
that makes it so that those things don't rotate like that,
okay, they don't tip over and start piling on top of each
other right there. We want them to stay in nice rows, so
we want to turn rotation off. And to do that,
we need a dynamic item behavior, which I talked about
in lecture. But it's starting to get to a point where I've
kinda got a lot of messy code cuz I'm adding behavior,
behavior, behavior, another one.
I'm gonna add, add, add, remove, remove, add item,
add item. So, I'm gonna do the thing I talk about in lecture
where I create a new behavior which is all these other
behaviors combined, like a composite behavior, okay. So
let's go, File > New up here.
Okay, it's a Cocoa Touch Class. This one is a subclass
of UIDynamicBehavior, okay. And I'm gonna call this
the FallingObjectBehavior, okay, cuz that's what it is,
this is a a thing falling down, a FallingObjectBehavior.
Okay, I don't wanna put it in the top level,
drop it here, I wanna put it down here,
where all the rest of my classes are.
I notice some of you sometimes make that mistake in your
homework. Really nice to keep your files together there.
Okay, so here's my FallingObjectBehavior,
it's a UIDynamicBehavior. And I'm just gonna go and copy and
paste those two behaviors I already have,
these two guys right here, out of here, and over into here,
okay. Cuz now, cuz I want this falling object behavior to
have these two behaviors right here. The other thing
we do when we create a DynamicBehavior subclass is,
we're obviously going to have an init. So I'm gonna override
the init that comes with UIDynamicBehavior,
call super.init, okay, because I, I need to that, from
the rules of init. We haven't talked a lot about inits,
by the way. Again, hopefully you haven't needed them too
much in your, your homeworks. And hopefully you understood
what the reading assignment said about inits. But anyway,
you need to call super.init before you can do stuff.
So I'm going to then add a child behavior,
which is gravity, and I'm gonna add a child behavior,
which is the collider.
Okay, so this is how you build these composites.
You add children behavior, okay. Now,
another nice thing to do is to have a func addItem, okay,
which takes an item which would be a UIDynamicItem,
okay? Remember that UIView implements this protocol.
This is a protocol, okay, UIView implements it.
And here, I just want to make sure that I add this item to
all of my sub, my children, basically, behaviors. So
let's do that. And collider. Okay, and similarly,
we probably, we don't need it for this demo, but
to be complete, we probably want a removeItem as well.
Okay, so now, we've created this new behavior that
we can add items to and that this behavior can be added
to an animator to cause this group of behaviors to happen.
So now let's go back to our DropItView,
and instead having these individual behaviors,
let's create a new behavior, we'll call it dropBehavior,
which is a FallingObjectBehavior.
Okay, so this is one behavior encapsulate all those
behaviors. So now we can put that instead of all these
details. Okay, same thing down here.
All right? So see how this code has gotten so
simple now it fits on one page to do this. And
the actual behavior, the dynamic behavior is now
encapsulated over here in this FallingObjectBehavior instead.
All right? Okay, let's run this and
make sure we haven't broken anything by doing that.
Okay, haven't really changed anything,
I've just moved the code for a different encapsulation.
Here it is, we click, hopefully these things will
still hit the bottom, they do, okay? So all is well. Now,
they're still, can be tippy. See there, they're starting to
tip over. No, they're tipping over, okay.
So they're still tipping, so we need to fix the tippiness.
But now we're gonna fix this tippiness here in
our FallingObjectBehavior. And we're gonna do that by adding
another behavior, okay? This is gonna be the itemBehavior.
This is gonna describe how each of these items behaves
when it goes in all the other behaviors. And we do that with
a UIDynamicItemBehavior, okay, and
I'm gonna initialize this in the same way that I did here,
okay, with a closure. So let's let dib,
a dynamic item behavior, equal a UIDynamicItemBehavior.
And now we can set all kinds of things that dib, this dib,
UIDynamicItemBehavior, knows how to do.
For example, allows rotation? No, so now, our block won't
rotate. We could also do stuff like friction and
also elasticity. So I'm gonna do elasticity of 0.75.
Elasticity of 1 is perfect elasticity.
In other words, no energy is lost by the collision.
They bounce off each other.
So 0.75 is a little energy lost. But, you know, so
I'm not sure what the default elasticity is. But it was low,
because those things came down to the bottom,
they didn't bounce much. They kind of just sat there.
So I'll do that. And now let's return dib.
And of course we need to do the same thing here,
add this child behavior or item behavior. And
same thing here, we want to be able to add items to this. And
we want to be able to remove items as well, okay? So
we've just added this behavior now. These things are all
going to have this kind of behavior as they bounce and
are affected by gravity and things like that. And
notice that to add this stuff, we didn't touch DropItView.
DropItView has not changed, okay? We didn't change
anything there. We're only changing this in
this custom behavior that we've built. Okay, so let's go
ahead and run. See what those changes did, what having no
rotation elasticity did. So here it comes like this, so
here we go. Look, they're much bouncier. And
notice how they'll bounce into each other, okay?
They behave like real objects in the real world.
They're bouncing, and they're not rotating, so they're not
tipping over anymore. They're still bouncing up and down,
though, see? When something lands on a row, it causes them
to bounce up a little bit. But now we're on track for Tetris,
because now we're getting completed rows that we can
have them, have the rows remove.
Now, the code for removing, for kind of removing a row,
it's a little tedious for a demo here. I'm really just
gonna go across the row and do what's called a hit test.
In UI view, it has a hit test, which basically I'm
just looking to see if there's a view there.
So I'm gonna go all the way across each row looking to see
if they're view. And if there's a view in every single
spot, then I'm gonna assume that row is complete and
I'm gonna remove all those views. Okay, so
I wrote that code outside, let's go take a look at it.
We'll put it, let's put it right here. Okay,
it's called removeCompletedRow.
It's just this one method right here, okay?
You can see it goes through, it's doing this hit testing,
it's trying to find the drops to remove. If it finds
the whole row, then it goes through each of the drops and
the drops removed, and
look what it does. It removes it from the drop behavior and
then removes it from superview, so
it just takes that drop right out of there. Okay?
So we're literally just throwing it away, okay? Now,
the question is, when do we call remove completed row?
Okay, do we just kind of call it randomly with an NS timer
or something? No, we're gonna call remove completed row
when all the bouncing stops. Okay, when our
dynamic animation engine pauses, then we're gonna try
to remove a row. Cuz if things are still bouncing, you can't
really be removing rows while things are still bouncing.
So when things have settled down,
then we'll try and remove a complete row if we can.
So, if you remember from lecture,
how do we find out the things have stopped?
We use a dynamic animators delegate, the dynamic animator
will tell it's delegate when things have paused.
When things have stasis, okay? So we're gonna have to do
the same trick here that we did with these other ones, and
use a closure Create this because we just have
the delegates of it. So let's go here and
we'll create a little let animator equal this thing.
And we are just going to set the animator's delegate
to self and return animator.
Okay, and we can use self in here because this is lazy.
Okay. Eh, right? You do that but there is as error here.
What's this error? Can't assign the DropItView to
UIDynamicDeleg eh,DynamicAnimatorDelegate so
we need to go here and say we are a UIDynamic.
Animator delegate, okay? Say we implement this
protocol. Now they're all optional so we don't have to
actually implement any, there's no errors here, but
the one we want is that it will pause.
And that we'll just start typing dynamicAnimator, and
you can se it's actually the very first one.
Here's resume and here's pause. So let's go ahead and
do the pause. So this gets called whenever everything
reach stasis and I'm just going to removeCompletedRow.
If there are no completed rows removeCompletedRow does
nothing, it only removes completed rows
if there are some. Okay, so let's try it see if it works.
Could it really be that easy? Yes. All right here we go.
Drops them down here. Okay, we'll let it
reach stasis where there's no completed row. Okay,
nothing removed, okay, let's add a whole bunch more,
bad enough so that something becomes complete here. Okay,
oops, nope, still need one more,
this column right here, so
we'll keep clicking until we get something in that column.
There it is. Okay, here we go.
Cross your fingers. Boom. Now, notice that
when I remove those views, the animator leapt into action
again. Because it noticed, woah, gravity can now work on
these ones that are not blocked by the other ones.
Okay? And same thing here. And this will happen repeatedly.
Yeah, question. >> Yeah, so the last row or so
sometimes the bottom squares are like a little bit
off the ground. >> Mm-hm.
>> What's going on there?
>> Yeah, you see a little
>> Little bit of white in
there. I'm not 100% sure what that is, but I think
it's just an artifact that all this animation stuff happened,
is happening, in CGFloat space, right?
It's not happening on integer boundaries. And so
it might be that these things landing, maybe they're 0.01,
and so the, it's up enough, round enough so
that it shows the one pixel there.
I'm not really 100% sure why it's not exactly on there.
Remember that, you know, the physics you got a lot
of things bouncing here, off of each other.
Different, amounts and stuff like that.
And these things, and when they could rotate,
you saw, they started tipping over even, and nicking into
each other. So this stuff is not all happening on integer
boundaries, I think that's the bottom line on that.
But I'm not 100% certain. All right, so anyway, this
is working great, okay? We got our tetris engine really
ready to go here, if we just made these not be squares.
And I don't have time to make them be actual you know,
L shapes and all that stuff.
But you get the idea. And you understand how this works.
So, I'm going to Let's turn the rotation back on.
I want to show you something fun here.
Let's make the rotation be true again. Run.
Okay, so put it in here. And these things are gonna bounce
off each other. Uhp! No! No!. No! But, let's
see if removeCompletedRow can work here. Because, actually,
some of these rows still might have a in every slot.
Let's see. There we go! Remove that row. So
it doesn't work quite as well, but it can kind of work.
There we go. Okay? All right.
What's next? Next I'm gonna make it so
that just to show you how the collide, collisions work cuz w
only have collisions with the edges.
I'm gonna put a little round thing in the middle, okay?
That this squares are gonna collide against. Just a little
round circles. So the bottom, there's squeezing him down and
boop bounce of a bit. With just a little round boundary,
okay? Cuz you can put, with these, with the collision
behavior you can put any arbitrary Bezier path as a,
as a boundary anywhere.
And when you're doing your breakout game.
You know, you're probably gonna use those boundaries for
the bricks, for example, okay? And maybe for your paddle
even. You'll be moving the boundary constantly,
because the bricks and the paddle, they don't go flying
around when you hit them they disappear or whatever and
the paddle, when you hit it nothing happens to it,
it stays perfectly the same. Okay, so let's go ahead and
do that. We're just going to put a little round circle
here that is a collision. So, to do that I'm going to go
in my Falling Object behavior here.
And I'm going to make this,
unfortunately my collider is private. And I actually like
to keep it private in my little dynamic behavior here.
But I am going to allow people to add a barrier.
So, I'm gonna create a public function addBarrier. And
you can specify any path you want, a UIBezierPath, that you
want to be the barrier. And let's go ahead and you can
name it as well. So, it will let you give it a name.
And that's because when you put these barriers into
the collider, you name them there as well.
That's how you know which Barrier got hit, okay, and
which barrier you're gonna add or remove or change. So those
are all named. And you just do this with a collider, method.
AddBoundaryWithIdentifier. Okay, here it is, and
so the identifier is the name, and the path is the path that
was passed along in here. If someone calls us, by the way,
I'm also going to conveniently remove any old boundary with
that name. Okay? So if you call this repeatedly,
it'll move the barrier around, just for convenience here.
Okay? So this is a nice public function for
adding a barrier. Let's use that in our drop it view to
add a little barrier in the middle. Now, Where do I
want to put the code that adds that little thing? Well, I
don't know where the middle of my bounds are until my bounds
is set, so I certainly have to wait until my bounds are set,
and actually my bounds could change, right?
They could get rotated. Now my middle is in a different
place, and I want the barrier to always be in the middle. So
you'll remember from our last
demo That when a UI views bounds change,
what gets called? Layout subviews.
All right, it doesn't have a view did layout subviews, it
has the actual layout subviews that lays the subviews out.
So that's a good place to put this thing in the middle.
Because layout subviews gonna get called every single time.
The bounds change. So, that's layoutSubviews.
I'm just gonna subclass else. Super.layoutSubviews. And
all I'm gonna do here in layoutSubviews is to
create a round path, so let path equal UIBezierPath.
And there happens to be a BezierPath ovalInRect
thing to create them. And so
let's have this rect be a CGRect whose center,
this is one of my little UI kit extensions is a,
is a CGRect has a center initializer
will be bounds.mid. That's my mid point of my bounds,
that's also a little extension that I did there. And
we'll have the size of it be the dropSize. Okay so
we're gonna put a little round circle,
the same size as a drop right in the middle. So we have that
path. Let's just call on our drop behavior. We'll add
this barrier with this path. We need to give it a name.
So let's be good programmers here and
do private struct pathNames, we'll call it.
Static let this one we'll call our MiddleBarrier and
we can use any string we want here, just has to be unique so
we'll call it MiddleBarrier. Okay, so
this is PathNames.MiddleBarrier. Okay,
so I'm just adding this named barrier here, to my
to my collision behavior in my drop behavior. All right,
so let's go try it, see what this looks like. All right,
we're dropping them here. Whoop! See that? If we drop
one in the middle, right? Aah, give me a middle one.
There one, see? They're hitting off the middle.
Now this is a little hard to see. See,
you see that it's hitting the barrier, but
you can't actually see the barrier. So
how could we draw that barrier there? Well,
we could implement DrawRect, okay? Our own DrawRect and
draw it, okay, just using just stroke, stroking the thing.
But actually, I'm gonna do something kinda fun. And
this is, really I'm doing it this way to show you, always
think object-oriented when you're building an iOS, okay?
What I'm gonna do instead to draw all that little circle,
is I'm gonna create a new UIView okay,
a new UIView subclass. And all this UIView subclass I'm gonna
create does is it knows how to draw a Bezier Path in itself.
It's just a generic Bezier path-drawing view. And
I'm gonna call it what did I call it? NamedBezierPathsView,
okay, cuz that's what it does. It's gonna have
a dictionary of Bezier paths and it just draws them.
It's really generic. It has nothing to do with DropIt.
I could well end up using this in some other app. Okay, and
this is what this Named BezierPathsView is gonna have.
It's gonna have public var called bezierPaths, okay,
which is going to be a dictionary,
which is String as the key, which is an arbitrary name,
and a UIBezierPath as the value, okay? And that's public
and anybody who wants to use this can just add something to
that, and when they do I'm gonna watch didSet and
do setNeedsDisplay, okay?
So if anyone adds a Bezier path to this,
then I'm going to NeedsDisplay and in my drawRect I'm gonna
draw all these Bezier paths that are in this dictionary.
Which is super simple to do, okay? I'm just gonna say for
_, path) because I don't really care what the names of
them are where I'm drawing them. That's
only w, if someone who's using it wants to replace one that's
already there, they can use the same name. In bezierPaths,
so I'm just enumerating my bezierPath keys and
values, and I don't care about the keys. And I'm just gonna
say path.stroke. So here I've created the world's simplest
little class but it's very powerful drawing class, okay,
cuz it, it, it draws arbitrary Bezier paths. Now if I really
were creating this, I'd probably maybe let you
set the line width and color and other kinds of things, but
here we're just gonna do the, the bar,
bare bones of it here. Okay, now how can I use this
in my DropIt? Anyone have an idea how I could really easily
use this UIView to draw that circle in my DropIt?
How's about if we make DropItView inherit from it?
Now all of a sudden, DropItView has a new instance
variable called BezierPaths which it can set to any
BezierPaths it wants and it'll be drawn in itself, okay?
Everyone got that? So let's do that, okay?
When we set this barrier, let's go ahead and
set our own Bezier paths okay? This Bezier path is,
this is the dictionary that we inherited from that class we
just created. And let's call it middle barrier again.
PathNames.MiddleBarrier, okay, we can give any name we want.
And it's equal to that path we just created. Let's go
take a look at this. And sure enough, there it is. Okay,
now it's stroked with line with one black color fine, but
there it is. And we drop things now,
it's easier to see the things banging off of it.
Okay, and this barrier, of course, if we pile up enough
stuff, the things will start piling up around this barrier,
because everything bounces off of this barrier.
It's causes collision. By the way,
if we put something inside that barrier, okay,
it would bounce around in the inside of the barrier. Okay,
you got that? No remove completed?
Ruh, okay, there we go. There we go.
All right, so that's showing you a little bit there.
Okay the next one I'm gonna do is an attachment behavior. So
I'm gonna allow myself, when a thing drops here,
to grab onto a drop, okay, with my mouse,
or with my finger, if it was on a device and I'd make
an attachment to it. And remember an attachment is like
an iron bar that hooks up from either a point to an item or
between two items. In this case it's gonna be a point,
to point my finger is. And what also cool is, as my, I'm
gonna do a pan gesture and, as my finger moves around,
I'm gonna keep moving that attachment point. And
that bar is gonna be dragged around with it and
the item too, okay?
So that's what we're gonna do. Let's do that attachment
behavior. So, to do the attachment behavior,
I certainly need an attachment behavior.
So I'm gonna create a private var, which is attachment,
UIAttachmentBehavior, okay? Actually we'll have it be
an optional, because we might not have an attachment yet. We
don't have an attachment until we put our finger down on it,
to grab onto it. And when this attachment behavior
gets set to something we need to obviously add
the behavior to our animator, otherwise this attachment
won't do anything, okay? So what do we need to do that?
I'm just going to say if this attachment is not nil, okay,
if someone has set the attachment to be something
other than nil, then animator, addBehavior this attachment.
Okay, everyone understand that? Now, one thing,
by the way, I also am gonna do something we haven't done in
a demo, which is willSet. And willSet happens before the new
value gets set. And what do I wanna do here?
Here I wanna say if my current attachment,
before I've set it, is not nil, then I want to remove it.
Okay, you see why I'm doing this?
Right, if someone sets the attachment to something new,
if there was an old attachment I wanna remove it, okay? So,
here I'm just making sure that every time I set attachment,
the old one gets removed, a new one gets added.
All right with that. Okay, so we've got this attachment,how
are we gonna set this attachment?
We gonna set it to something. I am only gonna allow you to
grab onto the last drop that was dropped.
This cause that you can drop a lot of drops,only the last one
you dropped can you drag grab onto with this pan gesture.
So I'm gonna need a var for the last drop.
So let's go ahead and put a var, I don't know,
we'll put it down here. private var lastDrop, okay,
which is a UIView, okay, and it also could be null,
it might not have dropped anything. And
every time we add a drop, I'm just gonna set the lastDrop
equal to the drop. [INAUDIBLE] understand there, that's just
grabbing the last drop. So, now, I have the last drop,
okay? And I get my finger down, I need to grab onto it,
okay? And create this attachment behavior.
So, how am I gonna do that? All right, let's go here and
create a function called grabDrop which is going to be
a hand gesture Handler, okay. Cuz we're gonna have a pan
gesture be how we grab onto this following drop. Okay,
so first I'm just gonna get the point of the gesture, or
gesturePoint, that's the recognizer locationInView, or
self. Okay, so now we know where that hand gesture is,
either at the start or as we're moving around we know
where it is. So now let's handle these pan
gesture states, okay, recognizer.state.
If it's Began, right, if this thing just began,
then we need to, you know, create the attachment. Okay,
if it's C=changed, okay, person moved the attachment
around, now we need to change the attachments Anchor point.
Okay, cuz remember I said the attachment is gonna attach
a point to that drop and so as we pan around. We're gonna
keep moving the point that it's attached to and that's
gonna drag the trop around with it by the iron bar, okay,
by the stiff bar. Otherwise, I'm just gonna set
the attachment to nil. Okay, because if it's not begin or
change, then it's either ended or some failure,
something like that, I want this attachment to go away.
Okay. If there is an attachment,
I want it to go away so that's the end of the line.
All right. This one's easy, okay. Create the attachment's
anchor point. That's super easy. That's just attachments.
If we have one. AnchorPoint = gesturePoint, okay?
That's it. Okay? Remember, the attachment is just a behavior,
it's an object. It's got a var on it,
which is the anchor point. If it's a point to,
a point connection to a item, it's got an anchor point.
And then we're just gonna change, as you drag around
with the pan, we're just gonna keep changing that. And
the animation system's automatically gonna react to
that. We don't have to do anything.
Just automatically it's going to notice that change and
deal with it. How about creating the attachment? Well,
here we better make sure we have a drop to attach to.
So I'm gonna say if the drop to drop To
attachTo equals the lastDrop. Okay, so in other words,
if we have a lastDrop, cuz we might've just started and
obviously if we start panning when
there's nothing dropping, we can't do it. And
also wanna make sure that that dropToAttachTo is in the view
hierarchy. Okay? So I want to make sure it hasn't
been removed from super view by, remove completed row or
any other way. So if I got a draft drop, I'm just gonna
create an attachment by saying it equals a UI attachment.
Attachment behavior Oops,
we forget attach. Attachment,
UIAttachmentBehavior. And you can see,
here's the different kinds of attachments you can create,
attach to an anchor, an item attached to another item.
You can even attach items to anchors or
other items offsetFromCenter. In other words,
the attachment doesn't have to be in the center of the thing,
it could be on a corner. If you do that Then as you pull
it around that thing's gonna be spinning around because,
you know if you have the corner of a rectangle and you
pull on it its gonna rotate as long as you allow rotation.
Okay? But here I want attached to anchor obviously. I'm
gonna attach it to the anchor which is the pan. The item
is the droptoattachto and the anchor is the gesturePoint.
Okay where the pan gesture went on.
By the way I'm gonna make my game so that once you drab,
grab onto this thing, you can't grab onto it again.
If you grab on and you let it go,
you can't grab it again. So last drop to nil in the case
where I create an attachment. Okay? We have to obviously
add the GestureRecognizer that call this handler, so
we were gonna do that obviously in our controller.
Okay, just like we added this TapGesture, let's go
gameView.addGestureRecognizer, UIPanGesture this time.
The target this time is the gameView.
Okay, and the action is a selector which is
the DropItView.grabDrop with an argument.
Okay, everybody got that? All right, we'll go back here so
you can see this code on the screen at the same time.
To run that. All right, so here we drop it.
I didn't grab it. Okay. We're gonna drop another one.
I grabbed it. Okay, do you see what's happening? It's kind of
hard to see. Watch this. Boing! Okay? So this thing is
bouncing around. I'm dragging it around, ok, with my finger.
Look. I can even it bounce it on the iron bar.
Wooo. Now, it's kind of hard to see this.
Wouldn't it be cool if we could draw a line there?
Okay? So that we could see this iron bar,
that this attachment behavior is creating. And, of course,
we can do that because we inherit from a class that
knows how to draw arbitrary path. So
just like we drew this little one, let's draw that bar.
But it's a little tricky cuz that bar is always changing as
I drag it around with the pen, right? That think is always
changing. So how are we going to have a hook
to know when to draw it? This is where that really cool
UI dynamic behavior mechanism I was talking about is action.
All right. Action is a closure that you can set.
It could get called every time that behavior acts. Perfect.
So I'm gonna put that behavior on that attachment, so that
every time that attachment has any affect on something,
I'm gonna re-draw my line.
Okay. Perfect opportunity to do that. All right. So
I'm gonna do that. Where is a good place to put that?
Let's put it down in where we create the attachment I guess.
Or is that here it is.
Here is where we create the attachment.
This is where we are adding the behavior.
So I'm als, in addition to adding the behavior here, I'm
going to say the attachments. Attachment, I have trouble
typing that. The attachment to action equals some closure.
So in here this is where we wanna draw that line, okay. So
how are we gonna draw this line in here?
How about let's get the attach drop. Okay?
Cuz I wanna draw a line between the point, okay,
that the gestures out and where the attached drop is.
So I need to find that attached drop. So
how can I find the attached drop from the attachment.
Well, here' how we do that. We can get the attachments. Oops,
equals. Get the attach, attachments items.
Okay, that's all the items that it's attaching.
Now it's only gonna be having this one drop attached,
okay it only attaches one drop. But, so this is an array
of items, so I'm gonna get the first one out of there cuz
I know there's only gonna be one. So I've got this first
thing, and I'm gonna make sure it's a UIView, okay?
I just wanna be 100% sure it's a UIView, and I want this var
right here to be of type UIView. Here it's complaining
because this is a closure, and so we have to have self,
explicit self, cuz we're capturing self,
which is actually gonna be a huge problem here, by the way,
to capture self, we'll talk about that in a second,
all right? So now I've got the attached drop,
I just need to create a Bézier path, okay, UIBezierPath.
And I've got a nice lineFrom. Okay,
a UIBezierPath.lineFrom the attachment's anchor point.
Oops, not replacement,
anchorPoint to the attachedDrop.center.
Okay? See what I'm doing there? Okay, we also need some
self dot going on in here. We can do that,
cuz we know we're good on the attachment. What else do
we got here okay, and so we need to give this a name,
right, cuz bezierPath is a dictionary, so
we need give it a name. So let's go back down here and
create another named path, this one we'll call
Attachment. All right, so this is gonna be our
bezierPath[PathNames.Attachme- nt]. Maybe for
readability here, I'll put this on the next line.
Okay? So there, we've created the Bezier path
to show this attachment. Everybody cool with that? Now,
the other thing is, when we remove it,
we better remove that thing. So self dot,
we don't even need self here. We're not inside a closure.
BezierPaths[PathNames.Attachm- ent] = nil.
That's a way to remove something from a dictionary,
by the way, just set it to nil. Okay,
pretty cool with that? Now, as I mentioned we have a serious
problem here with self being captured. Okay, because this
cell, okay, this closure keeps self in the heap. And
self keeps the closure in the heap,
because self.attachment.action equals this closure. So
they each have strong pointers to each other,
they can never leave the heap. Now, this one we can fix with
unowned self. Because we know that this behavior
is gonna leave the heap as soon as self leaves the heap,
so it's perfectly safe here to say, unowned self to
break that loop. Okay, self will never be around when this
attachment behavior's around, still around. Okay, so
let's see if that works. All right,
let's drop a few down. Now I'm gonna grab the next one.
There it is. Okay, so
now we can see a lot better what we're doing here. So
we balance it. Okay? Got it. Make sense?
All right, so that is all I wanted to show you for
behaviors. Any questions about that stuff? I showed you
a lot of behaviors there, attachments, colliders,
item behaviors, gravity, okay, so that's plenty of stuff to
help you get started on your homework there. All right,
let's go back and look at some slides here. So
now I'm gonna talk about Core Motion, okay? Core Motion
is an object-oriented API to get at the motion
sensing hardware on your device.
So that's accelerometer, the gyro, magnetometer,
those kinds of things, all right? Not all devices have
all of this hardware, although in recent years they all do.
But if your app wants to run back on iPhone 4 or
something like that, it doesn't have a gyro, for
example, we kind of, for good programming technique,
wanna check to make sure that we have the hardware, and
you'll see that in a second. You get at all this stuff
via an instance of CMMotionManager.
Now, you really only wanna have one CMMotionManager in
your entire app,
because there's only one gyro in your entire
device, right? So it really makes no sense to have two
motion managers trying to, you know, cross over each
other. You need to coordinate it, so if you really had two
different places in your app where you were accessing
this hardware, then you would need to have a shared motion
manager either as a static on some class
somewhere or maybe part of your app delegate or something
like that, that is, you know, dealing with the fact that two
different people wanna look at the the hardware the same
time, okay?
So how do you use this motion manager to get this
information? Well, first it was two ways really, okay. One
way is by polling, and one way is by getting constant updates
about what's going on, okay. But in either case, first
you're gonna check to see if the hardware's available, and
I'll talk about how you do that. In the polling case,
you're then going to tell the motion manager, okay, I want
accelerometer updates. Okay, and that'll turn that on. And
then you just ask it, what's the current accelerometer,
what's the current accelerometer?
Any time, you can ask it, you want,
you're polling it, basically, asking it. So that's one way,
rare that you would do that way. The second way, again,
you check to see that hardware's available,
then you're gonna set the rate at which you want
the system to tell you about accelerometer or
gyro or magnetometer updates, okay. So five times a second,
30 times a second, probably not much more than that.
I mean, you can only draw it maybe 60 frames a second,
so you're probably not gonna need information much
But you're gonna tell it how often you want it, okay?
more than that.
Then you're gonna give it a closure, okay,
a block of code. And it's going to execute that closure
that many times. Five times a second, 30 times a second. And
that closure, the arguments to it are the current state of
the accelerometer or the current state of the gyro.
Okay, so those are the two ways to do it. So, let's fix,
see how all this works. Checking the availability. You
just ask the CMMotionManager accelerometer Available.
That's a Bool, okay, and it'll tell you yes or no,
or magnetometer available, and that's how you find out. Okay,
so it's as simple as that. So you always wanna check that,
though, because if it's not available and
you start asking for things, you're gonna get errors,
all right? Now, how do you, if you're doing the polling case,
how do you start this thing up? You just say,
start Accelerometer Updates, start Gyro Updates.
And it'll start looking at that hardware. Now,
this is not free. Okay, having this thing start listening to
these pieces of hardware costs battery especially, okay, and
some CPU too, but it costs battery.
So don't turn this on unless you're really ready to start
getting the information, okay? You can ask
the CMMotionManager whether it is currently, has that
hardware fired up, basically, by saying, you know,
Accelerometer active. And that's bool, yes or no. By
the way, you're noticing all here, you see accelerometer,
gyro, magnetometer. You also see this thing, deviceMotion.
Okay, deviceMotion is kind of a special device.
It's really a combination of the other three. Okay,
an intelligent combination of the other three, and
we'll talk about that in a moment here. And
then to stop the hardware,
to turn off the accelerometer, turn off the gyro, you just
say stop whatever updates, okay, and that'll stop it. And
you wanna do this as soon as you realize, I don't need it,
even if you only don't need it for a little while and
you're gonna go back and turn it back on, fine. But
any time you don't need it, turn it off, okay,
don't waste the user's battery by having this thing
working when you're not actually using the data. Okay,
so that's how you kind of control the hardware.
Now, again, we're talking about polling here,
how do I then say, okay, well,
you got the accelerometer turned on,
what is the current value of the accelerometer? And you
just use this CMMotionManager var accelerometer data.
And it gives you this struct, CMAccelerometerData struct,
and it's got the acceleration data in x, y, and z, okay?
So what is this x, y, and z? So here I have a device, okay,
so, y Okay, y is this axis right here,
pointing down through the home button, okay?
So this is the y, okay? It's this vertical axis, okay?
X is perpendicular to that, cross the device this way.
So this is y, with the home button being down. This is x.
Z is out the back. Okay, so if I put this on a table,
z, what do, what do you think z value would be?
1.0. Okay, why 1.0? Because x, y, and
z here are in g. Everyone know what g is, right? 9.8 meters
per second squared. That's what g is. So z would be 1
g if I sit it right there, okay? Because the acceleration
due to gravity is operating on it. And it does tell you
the acceleration is due to gravity,
in addition to the acceleration due to the user
moving the thing around, okay. Acceleration going all
over the place, okay? But the acceleration due to gravity
also counts, so that would be x and y 0, z 1.0.
Similarly if I do this, this would be y 1.0, x and
z zero. Okay, so that's the acceleration there.
You get similar information for gyro, okay.
The gyro is the rotation of the device, okay. What, what,
how it's rotating, okay. And this is gonna tell you this in
radians per second, same axes, okay, radians per second,
how this thing is rotating. Now there's a bias in here.
I don't know if people know what a gyro bias is, but
one simple way to think about it is,
if I'm moving like this, what if I'm also moving like this?
Okay, you can see how that might make the gyro think this
is moving faster than it is, because it's moving this way
in addition to this. So there's a bias in there. And
also just the the gyro equipment has a bias built
into it. Now I'm gonna show you in a way, in a second,
a way to get this rotation as pure rotation without
that bias, okay? And also a way to get the accelerometer
data without gravity. The magnetometer is measuring
magnetic field, right? This is a thing that can find, you can
find true north. You can basically find out which way
each of those axes is pointing relative to true north,
by measuring the magnetic field around your device,
okay. Now, I talked about the bias and acceleration due to
gravity. Here's how you get that out of there.
Instead of using CMAccelerometer, okay, or
CMGyro, you use this device CMDeviceMotion.
And that's the one that's the combination of the other
three. And by combining them and using the data from all of
them, it can tell you the part of the acceleration that is
gravity, and the part of it is the user moving it. Okay,
because it has the gyro, you see? So it knows from the gyro
what's going on there. Similar, because it has
the accelerometer, it can unbias the gyro and
it reports the gyro to you like an airplane. Any of you
pilots or anybody flown, piloting, know about it,
okay. So imagine my iPad here is an airplane,
okay. The way an airplane describes its motion is it
has, roll. Roll is this, okay, this axis in the middle,
how you're rolling. Okay, this is roll. So
when airplanes turn, they roll and that causes them to turn,
okay. Then there's pitch, that's up and down, right,
airplane climbing and descending,
okay. And then there's yaw. Yaw is when an airplane,
let's say there's a fierce wind coming this way,
the airplane wants to go that way but
it actually has to turn this way to fight this wind. Okay,
the amount it's turned along this axis is
the yaw, okay. So you've got roll, pitch and yaw. Okay,
so that's what we reported to you with CM device motion and
that is independent of any motion,
whether the airplane is going fast or sitting still,
whatever, you're going to get that roll, pitch and yaw,
okay. So that's device motion, really powerful mechanism.
And if you're doing anything with a gyro you're probably
gonna be using Device Motion instead of CM Gyro. Okay,
magnetic field, with the CM Device Motion,
it can tell you the accuracy of the magnetic field, okay.
All right, so, that, we talked about how to poll.
You just ask for the information you want.
How about if you wanna be notified 5 times a second,
or 30 times a second of what's going on, very easy.
You just call startAccelerometer updates or
startGyro updates or startdevicemotion updates to
queue. And you give it a queue,
this is not a dispatc_queueT, this is an nsoperation queue,
the object oriented version I talked about. But
probably you're gonna be passing NSoperationmainqueue,
or maybe you'll use NSoperationcurrentqueue if
you're on a different queue. You don't really wanna do this
on the main queue if you're gonna be doing it at a very
high rate, like 30 frames a sec, 30 calls a second unless
you're doing something really simple. Just think about it,
you don't want the main queue busy doing that.
But if you're doing 4 or 5 frames a second, absolutely,
doing something simple, you can do that.
Then you give it a handler. This is just a block,
a closure, and you can see that closure as two arguments.
One is that same CMAccelerometerData we
saw from before, the x, y and z, and g, that thing,
okay, and also an error possibly.
Okay, these are optionals,
probably if one's nil the other one's not, vice-versa.
Okay, so this is just closure and inside that closure,
you can do anything you want with the AccelerometerData.
All right, similar with the gyro, startGyroUpdatesToQueue,
you're gonna get the gyro data.
StartMagnetometerUpdatesToQu- eue, you're gonna get
the magnetometer data. And of course,
startDeviceMotionUpdatesToQu- eue, okay. You get the CM,
CM button DeviceMotion, that's that thing that has vars like
gravity and attitude for the roll, pitch and yaw, that kind
of stuff. Just to talk a little bit about the errors,
you're, of course, gonna want to look in the documentation,
but some of the errors you can get are like you can't find
true north maybe, too much interference.
Maybe this activity's not authorized. Okay,
maybe user, you're not authorized to actually measure
the device's motion. Okay, that could be too.
So you do wanna be able to check for these errors to make
sure you're actually getting good data. All right, so
how often you get these closures, called, is set with
these vars in motion manager, okay. Update interval,
this is just the number of seconds between calls.
So like 0.25 would be four times a second, okay? It is
okay to, to have multiple, closures registered. You could
say startAccelerometer updates with handler and then call
it again with another handler. But understand,
they're all gonna be called at this same interval cuz there's
only this one motion manager that you're gonna create for
your whole app, okay.
All right, so let's take a look at this.
Let's take DropIt, and let's make the gravity that's in
DropIt be real gravity, okay. Right now the gravity just
goes down towards the home button, but let's make it so
that it's actual gravity. So as I move my thing around,
those blocks are gonna start swinging towards real gravity.
All right, so how are we gonna do that? I'm going to
go to my DropIt view right here, I'm gonna add a new var,
public var called realGravity, and it's gonna be a Bool,
okay? I'll start it out being false. And if this is on,
then I'm gonna use real gravity in my DropIt.
If it's off, I'm gonna use fake gravity,
the gravity I already have basically, all right? And so
let's go back to our controller and
set this to be true, so
I'm just gonna do it here in the didSet here,
gameView.realgravity. Gravity and real,
realGravity equals true. Okay, so
we've got realGravity turned on. And how am I gonna make
this real gravity work? Well anytime someone changes this,
I'm gonna call some method update real gravity or
something, and this is the method that's gonna have to
turn the accelerometer on to start using it. Okay?
So that's a private funk update real gravity.
Okay, so this is going to be the guts.
This is going to be the thing that's actually doing
the work here. All right, so
what do update real gravity going to do? Well,
it's going to do something with the accelerometer. And
we to use the accelerometer to get the gravity.
I'm not going to use device motion,
okay, just to make it simple, we'll use the accelerometer.
We want the real gravity anyway so we'll use that. So I
need a private var here which is that motion manager. As I
told you, you need a motion manager to do any of this. So,
we'll just say that equals CMMotionManager.
I'm not using any of this in
any other part of my app. So I'm putting it here.
Again, if I was using it in two different places,
I'd have to make this be some sort of shared resource.
Notice it is complaining right here, okay?
Does never heard of a CMMotionManager and
it doesn't know what the heck we're talking about.
This is because this is in a different framework,
import,CcoreMotion, okay? All this CoreMotion stuff you have
to import CoreMotion. All right, so we have our
motion manager right here. How are we going to use our
motion manager to grab that accelerometer, information?
So if we want real gravity, then we're going to do that.
By the way, if we don't want real gravity,
then I'm going to tell the motion manager to stop
accelerometer updates. Again, I always want to stop that
updating happening any time I don't want the updates, okay.
So we try to keep that off as much as possible. But if we do
want real gravity, then first I'm gonna check to see, if
the motionManager accelerometer is available.
Okay, as promised, this is first thing we need to do.
Actually I'm also going to see here if
the accelerometer is already active. Cuz maybe I already
called updateRealGravity and it's already running. So
I'm gonna actually say and the motionManager.accelerometerAc-
tive is false. Okay? So if the accelerometer is available and
it's not already running,
then I need to fire this thing up, okay? So let's fire it up.
Let's start with our update interval. So I'm going to have
the accelerometer update interval be, I,
maybe 0.25, 0.2 is probably enough. You know, gravity
doesn't really need to change that much more often than that
as I am moving my device around. This is a number
I could play with. Again, this should probably, not probably,
definitely be a constant but we're time constrained here so
I'm not gonna do that. So now I'm just gonna have the motion
manager start giving me updates to queue,
okay? So this is how I started updating. Now, what queue am I
gonna use? I'm gonna use the main cue here cuz
I'm only doing it four times a second and I'm only just
gonna set that gravity thing, that's all I'm gonna do, so
that's really lightweight so I can just use the main queue.
So, enter operation queue main queue. Okay,
here's the handler, the CM handler. I always recommend
double clicking on these things because it fills
out really nicely. Your arguments and
stuff like that. I'm also going to use the closing or
the trailing closure syntax here to do this, all right.
So I'm going to start this accelerometer,
here is my closure that I have to do,
okay? So, this accelerometer data, I'll call it data. This
error I'll call error. Okay, so, how am I gonna do this?
Well, this data might be nil, it's an optional. So, I'm
gonna see if I can get the accelerometer data first.
So, let's say if I can let, we'll call the x,
I'm only caring about x and y. Don't care about z, okay,
because I'm gonna have the my little drop it is two
dimensional so it doesn't care about z. So
if I can let dx equal the data acceleration in x, and
also we can let dy equal the data's acceleration in y so
then I'm just getting simultaneously getting and
checking to be sure the data is not nil, so
I've got the dx a new y.
Let's first try to just set the drop behaviors gravity's,
gravity direction, to just be a CG vector
which is dx and dy, okay? So we're gonna try this first.
Now, this is not gonna work because gravity is private. So
let's just go over to our behavior, falling object
behaviour here. I'm gonna make this not be private. Okay,
just for expediency. Maybe we wanna make some other public
API like we did with Glider here. I'm just gonna make this
public. Make it a little, go a little faster. All right, so
here we are, we're saving this, gravity here.
Yeah good one, that's what, okay got it.
Very good catch, bonus points, all right, so right.
So there's that, one other thing I wanna be careful of
here is memory cycle. Okay I've got this accelerometer,
cuz motion manager has accelerometer that that
thing has a hold of this closure, I have a hold of it.
Okay I have a hold the of motion manger. And
Motion manager has a hold of me, okay? So that's not good.
Again, we can do unowned to solve this one. Oops don't put
it there. Unowned goes over here. We can do unowned
self here because as soon as self leaves the heap,
this motionManager is gonna leave the heap with it,
which means this closure is gonna go out too.
So this closure will never get executed with self not in
the heap. Once self leaves the heap, this guy goes with it.
So we can do unowned here, to do that. The only other
thing I want to do here is if, I, I want to try and turn this
accelerator updates off as much as possible. So another
time I want to turn it off is if I'm not animating, right?
If I have my dropBehavior, okay, and it's not currently
animating, I do not want to be continuing to do this.
So, I'm gonna say only do this if my dropBehavior,
it's dynamic animator is not nil. That's how you can tell
whether a behaviour is currently being animated.
If it has a dynamic animator, it's being animated. If not,
it's not. So, if it's not nil, then we'll do this. Otherwise,
I'm going to stop this motion manager, okay?
Stop accelerometer updates in this motion manager. You see
how I'm trying to stop this thing as much as possible?
The only thing about this, though,
is if I do stop it because I stop animating, then I better
be sure that when I start animating up again.
Remember this is that animating bar,
you set it to true to start animating.
I better update my real gravity here to make sure that
I start the accelerometer back up again, okay? So
that allows me to start and stop animating.
It stops the accelerometers, every time I restart it,
it starts them again, okay? So let's try this and
see if it works. Now, this is the first time in this
class where I'm having to actually,
I can't do it in a simulator because the simulator has no,
accelerometer or anything like that, so
we're gonna be doing it here on this other device.
Let me run over here and show you this. All right, so
let's run this on our device here, here we go,
it's coming up here, there it is, we see our little circle,
if I tap, it's not working. What's going on here?
Why wouldn't that be working? I got the gravity going on
there, hm. Maybe if I turn my thing upside down, woah!
That worked, I turned my iPad upside down, and
all of a sudden gravity seems to be backwards here, okay?
Now why would gravity be backwards? The answer is,
because our drawing coordinate system has 0,0 in the upper
left. So this is working fine, it's falling down toward zero,
it's just that's in the upper left. So we need to add some
code here that knows what the orientation of our device is,
and adjusts, okay, for the fact that it's upside down,
basically. Also, when we turn sideways, and
we're looking at landscape mode,
we wanna make sure that's doing the right thing as well.
So let's put that in here. Okay, that goes right, so
let's put that right in here. Okay, we've got our dx and dy.
All I'm gonna do here is I'm gonna switch on my device's,
this is how you get the current device's orientation,
okay. This will return the orientation of the current
device. And so for example, in the case of portrait, okay,
we know that portrait is upside down, so
I'm gonna say dy = -dy in portrait.
In the case of portrait upside down, everything's fine.
We know that that works, okay. Portrait upside down,
we've got the right thing. How about LandscapeLeft,
or LandscapeRight, let's say. In LandscapeRight, x and
y are swapped, right, because I've turned it sideways, so
now it's the x of my device that's down. So
I need to swap them. There's actually a nice method here or
function called swap which will swap two variables, okay.
And then in LandscapeLeft, not only are they swapped,
but also dy has to be -dy, okay?
In other cases, there are other cases like FaceUp and
FaceDown. Those are orientations. In those cases,
there should be no gravity going on. So I'm gonna say dx
= 0, dy = 0. Okay, because my thing is flat or whatever.
Now, notice I'm modifying dy and dx in here, but I said
if let, just to remind you all you can change this to var,
if var. Exactly the same as if let, it's just that
these will now be vars that inside here you can modify.
Okay, everybody got that? Okay, so
let's try that. All right,
here we go. Drop it, it's working! Look at this.
Dropping some more things, I have my thing face up.
Okay, now I'm going to turn my thing upside down.
Let's see if they all fall down. And they do! Excellent.
Okay, now I'm gonna turn it sideways. Bam. Okay,
sideways around the other way. Okay. Now,
one thing that's interesting about this is I actually have
my rotation locked. If I unlock my rotation,
then my view is gonna change. Watch this.
See? So since it switched, all the views moved to the bottom.
So it didn't actually do much. Now, I can try and
move it around without changing my orientation, but
as soon as my orientation changes,
it's gonna jump around. Got that?
Okay? All right, that's it for
today. You have everything you need to know, I hope,
to do your assignment six. If you have any questions,
I'll be here as usual. >> For
more, please visit us at Stanford.edu.