[SOUND] Stanford University. >> All right,
well welcome to lecture 15 CS193P Spring of 2016.
So today we have three major topics.
One is the Application Life Cycle.
Remember we talked about the View Controller Life Cycle.
How View Controller comes into existence and goes on and
off screen and all that stuff. Well,
an Application goes through a similar sort of life cycle.
And we're going to talk about that. And along the way I'm
also going to talk about NS Notification, which
is that radio station from the NBC that we talked about
at the very beginning of the Quarter.
And we're going to talk about alerts. And I'm going to
switch gears a little from what I had said and
talk today about Cloud Kit. Because quite a few of you
have come up to me in your final projects and said.
Well, I want to do a little light weight backend over
maybe something simple like, some sort of messaging or
the network,
something like that. and cloud kit is a pretty cool way and
pretty simple way, actually, to do that, especially for
something like your final project,
which is a proof of concept vehicle where you
just need something simple where you can make it work and
you can always replace it with something much
more powerful networking-wise later. All right.
So I'm gonna talk about those three things today. And
then on Wednesday I will demo all these things. All right?
All right. So let's talk about this in this notification
thing. If you remember back to the very first lecture or
the second lecture when I talked about MVC,
there was this little guy here on the model
that looked a little round thing right here.
Which I called a radio station model for
communication from the model to the controller usually.
Guess where it goes and so we're gonna talk about
actually how this little radio station works in code,
how we do this thing in code. Okay,
it's called NSNotification, all right? It's a radio
station, the radio station by the way is not only good for
the model communicating with the controller,
it's also good for the system IOS to communicate with your
app. So you'll see a lot of communication from IOS to your
app as a whole using these notifications as well. So
let's first of all talk about how you tune into a radio
station. In other words if you want to listen to what's being
broadcast on a radio station, how do you do that? It's
actually quite simple, you're gonna get this in instance of
this object right here the NS notification center by saying
NSNotificationCenter.defaultC- enter(), okay.
And this is gonna get to this shared NS notification center,
and then you're gonna send that
message right here addObserverForName, okay. So
addObserverForName Takes a string which is the name
of the radio station. And it takes a block down here,
the send this notification block which is the block
that's going to be executed when there are broadcasts on
the radio station. So it really couldn't be any
simpler. It returns something that's an NS object protocol.
Optional, okay, but basically it's just a cookie.
You can almost think of it as any object. You'll kind of
need the return value of this, so you can stop observing this
radio station because you're listening when you,
when you send this, to this default center there.
You start listening to the radio station, well,
you have to be able to stop listening and
to do that, you need this little return value of this
add observer. For
name, guy right there. Okay, what are the other two
arguments here besides the name of the radio station and
the block of code to execute? One is the senders,
okay, in other words, the broadcasters that you're
You're interested in. Now you can just specify nil here,
then you'll listen to any radio station with that name.
Anybody broadcasting on that radio station you're going to
listen to. But if you put an object here,
it would only be if that particular object is
broadcasting on that radio station.
Okay? So, it depends on the kind
of environment that you're listening here as to whether
it makes sense to put something there.
And I'll show you some examples.
It'll make more sense. Then there's this queue right here.
This queue is gonna be the queue,
that this closure is going to be executed on. Okay? So
often times if you're doing UI stuff in here you'll obviously
want to say NSOperationQueue.MainQueue.
Okay? You can also pass nil here. You can see the question
mark there, so this could be nil. If you pass mail here,
then it will execute this closure on the same queue
as the radio station broadcaster,
which is a little bit odd, okay,
because sometimes the radio station's broadcasting and
you're not really sure what queue they're on, but
that's what meant, so usually we're going to have NS
operation main queue in here when you're listening. Now,
inside this closure, you can see there is one argument.
The argument is an NSNotification. So,
an NSNotification encapsulates the data that's coming across
in a radio station broadcast. And, there's really only one
interesting thing inside, there's a few in here you
can look in the documentation, but the main interesting thing
in this notification, is this thing called it's userInfo,
notification.userInfo. That's a dictionary, okay,
keys are NSObjects the values are AnyObject, okay. And
in that dictionary is any information that the radio
station broadcaster wants you to have, okay. So they're
gonna have to let you know what the keys of this are so
you can look in there and then you can get certain values.
So everybody who broadcasts. On a radio station,
it's going to tell you the name of the radio station.
This string right here, addObserverForName(String.
And then they're going to tell you the keys that you can use
to look inside this notification.userinfo. Okay,
those are all things that the radio station broadcaster has
to tell you if you want to listen to that broadcast and
make any sense of it, okay. All right, so
here's an example of listening to a radio station. So
there happens to be a radio station that broadcasts
whenever the user goes into their setting and
sets their font size. This is, did you see on the right,
there's a screen in the general settings
app that's under accessibility I think,
font sizes or something like that. And you can see there's
this slider down here. You can make your fonts bigger or
smaller. Okay, well when you change this a radio station
broadcast goes out to all the apps saying the,
what's called, content size category did change.
So this is the name of the radio station,
UIContentSizeCategoryDidChang- eNotification. Okay,
that's a constant somewhere in IOS. And it is
a string that just finds the name of this radio station.
So if you wanted to find out when the user changes
their font size you would just do defaultcenter here,
addObserverForName listen to that radio station.
The sender is going to be the UI application when the system
talks to you it usually talks to you from UI application,
but you might put nill right here because if anybody wants
to tell you that the content size category did change,
you're probably interested so you might say nill for
the object there. And then main queue you're almost
certainly gonna be listening for
broadcast of this radio station, on your main queue,
because when the font size changes we are gonna do
some UI thing. You're gonna react to it and
of course we know you can only do UI on the main queue. Okay?
So here's my closure, and right here I see I'm getting
the notification user info, inside there is a key, again,
this broadcast that's, you know, in some IOS place there.
UI content size category new value key, and it'll tell you
the new value of this size category of the font,
okay? It could be for example, UIContentSizeCategorySmall.
That's one of the size categories. And
once you get that new category, then you can react
to it, okay. Redraw something, whatever you wanna do.
By the way, if you're using preferred font,
remember we switched to using system font in our early apps?
We started using preferred fonts like the body font and
You remember all that? Those fonts are really cool because
the headline font.
they automatically are going to adjust to this size change.
So if you have a UI label somewhere, and
you used a prefered body font, and the person cranks up their
size really big, cuz maybe their eyes are getting old,
age is getting up with, catching up with them Then
it's automatically going to change those for you.
So that's kind of cool feature. Okay, but
sometimes you might have something else that some other
part of the UI that depends on the size of font that you have
to adjust as well. And maybe I'll show that in a little bit
in my demo on Wednesday. Okay, now, what about broadcasting.
What if you want to be a radio station broadcaster?
How do youd do that? That's very easy too.
You just create one of these NSNotifications,
the same thing that is given to your closure when you're
a listener. You just create one of these things and
then you're gonna ask the NSNotification default center
to post that notification. Okay, and then it's going to
broadcast on that radio station. And the notification
of course has to have the name of the radio station. And
also, the object that is sending it.
That's usually gonna be self, right. Your post notification,
you're gonna usually have the self be the center.
And then here's that user info you get to provide,
okay. This is the information that's gonna go to people
who listen to your broadcast. Okay,
you just post this notification and
all the listeners will have their closures executed
with this notification object as the argument. Okay,
pretty simple, all right. Okay, so
that's it for notifications, now I'm gonna move on to, and
I'm gonna talk about notification more like in when
we talk about Cloud Kit a little later,
there's notifications involved there, so we'll talk about
this more that and then in the day we'll talk about this too
So now we're gonna do a little different topic here which
is the application lifecycle, okay. So this is what happens
to your application as it goes through its life, okay.
And it's really encapsulated in these boxes right here.
This green box right here is the kind of your application
when it's the user's focus of attention when they're running
your app. The blue box is your app is still around and
running but it's not the one the user's interacting with
right now. And then these other spaces are not that,
okay. It's not either of those cases. So let's look at this
green box this foreground box. Inside that green box there's
actually a little state here called inactive.
Okay that's when your app is running, it's the foreground,
but it's not receiving any UI events, okay.
So this is kind of like when it's just getting started up,
okay. And then it moves from there into this state
active where it's running and receiving events. Okay so
there are just two distinct states there, and you'll see
why we have those in a moment. And then down here, okay,
when you're in this background area, at the bottom,
your code might be running, for a short amount of time.
You don't usually run in the background for very long. Now,
there's a misconception that iOS, at least until recently,
is not a multitasking system. Because,
it seems like you only have one app running at a time.
in iOS nine, they introduced the ability to have two apps
Well of course,
running at the same time,
on the same screen at the same time. In on iPad,
side by side. But even before that, apps could run
at the same time. It just one would be or two or three would
be in the background and one would be in the foreground.
Of course, we know that iOS is just UNIX underneath and
UNIX is a complete multitasking operating
system so
The single tasking nature that it would appear that IOS had,
was more a UI decision for the user. The user could
concentrate on the one thing they're doing at the time and
I have a cluttered, trying to figure out what's going on,
which apps are running all the time.
So it's kind of a simplification of the UI.
Okay, but even then, apps were running in the background.
And we'll talk about why apps run in the back,
background and when and all that in a moment here,
okay. When you go down to the state
at the bottom, okay, your code, you are not running.
None of your, no code is being executed in your app at all.
You're in the suspended state. So your process still exists,
but it's not getting any cycles from the CPU.
It's just sitting there. So spend it. At any time in here,
you could be killed, okay, and you could be killed
without ever having a chance to run again. So
when you get into this state,
you wanna make sure you're ready to be killed, okay?
So that you don't have any data that's half written or
any kind of weird state, you have to be ready to be killed
down in this suspended state. Okay? And then of course,
y- you have the not running state at the top, and
how do we get out of this not running state?
So, the not running state, there's,
there's no process that's run in your app, and how do we get
out of that? Well, we getting out of it by launching.
And the launching process takes you from not running
into the foreground Thorough this inactive state and
then into active state.
Now it's also possible for you to be launched directly into
the background. Not really sure I am here but that's
possible as well. When you switch to another application.
So you are the primary application.
The user goes and switches to some other application.
Maybe by double clicking the home button or something like
that. Going back and picking something else.
What happens here is you go from the active state to
the inactive state and around to the background state. And
then after a little while, you moved to suspended, okay,
while this other app is running. Okay, so
if they go back to you, then you're gonna go back, okay,
the reverse here. Yes. I have mentioned this already.
When you're killed,
when you go through Suspended to Not running,
no code gets run in your app. So any preparation you have to
do for being killed has to happen before that. Now,
at each of these transitions happen, all these arrows,
okay, code gets executed in your application. Most notably
in your AppDelegate, okay? We know that AppDelegate file,
a file I always Move out of the way into supporting files
place that record data, and manage up the contexting was.
Okay, well, there's a bunch of methods in there since it is
the delegates UIApplication object not much methods
in there they're called as we transition through all
these states. So, we'll talk about those. So,
when you're going from not running to inactive, okay, or
this all time from not running into the background.
Okay, you could do this little path here
not running Inactive into the background. You get this
method right called in your AppDelegate called
ApplicationDidFinishLaunching- WithOption, okay, and
it's exactly what its sound. It's saying okay you have
launch, you're in the Inactive state, okay.
And here are some options and these options is a dictionary.
Okay and we'll talk about what's in the dictionary in
a second. You also are gonna get an NSNotification for
radio station broadcast on this radio station the
UIApplicationDidFinishLaunchi- ngNotification radio station.
And so if you observe on that you'll get your closer called
when the app reaches this inactive state right here.
Okay. Now, what's this dictionary all about right
here? Okay. So this dictionary is passed to you and
it tells you basically why you were launched.
Now, you always think of I get launched because someone
clicked on my icon. That's true. That's one way to get
launched but there's a lot other way to get launched. For
example, someone might want you to open URL. You might be
an app Like you're the Keynote app, okay, on iOS. And
you know how to open Keynote files. So when someone says,
I wanna open this Keynote file, the app is gonna launch
Keynote, okay. And so this is going to tell them
that that's why Keynote got launched. You might
do this because you enter a certain place in the world.
There's a way,
with core location which we haven't talked about,
to say hey,
if this person walks in this little area of the world,
these GPS coordinates, then wake my app up. Launch me,
because I want to do something when they walk into that area.
Okay? So you might get launched because of that. You
might be continuing activities started on another device.
How many people have used Da app
continuation where you start using an app like Safari or
something on your iPhone or something and
then you go over to your iPad and you just continue,
there's a little thing in the corner, okay,
only a couple of you are nodding your heads but
it's kind of a cool feature but if you go and
press that little continuation icon on your IOS and
of course it's going to launch you to continue what you were
doing on the device. Also a notification might have
arrived for you. Like push notification.
Who doesn't know what a push notification is?
Okay, so, everybody knows what that is.
It's little things that make the badges on your icon,
just basically when communication's coming from
servers out there in the world, things like that.
Well of course that might launch you. Maybe you have
some Bluetooth devi, Bluetooth device that is attached to
your computer and it wants to do something with your app,
it might launch your app to do that.
So you can see there's tons of examples and these,
this dictionary is gonna contain the information that
tells you For example, the URL it wants to open or that,
you know, that, you entered a certain place in the world or
things like that. So it's gonna give you information
about what happened that caused you to launch, okay.
One thing about this application to finish
launching with options. It used to be
that you actually built you UI here. Okay your primary UI.
Like a split view controller with a navigation controller
in the master with this view controller in it. And you
would actually build that in code inside of this. A method,
we no longer do that anymore, we use storyboards. But,
when you are doing your final project you are going to be
out searching on the internet for things and you are going
to find something and someone is going to say, Yeah,
you do this by putting code in your application to finish
launching with options. You create your split view there
and you set the delegates. Whoa don't do that That's old.
That's old IOS 7 kind of behavior but
you know sometimes on the internet when you're searching
you can't tell what's new and what's old. The good thing for
you guys is, if you search for Swift stuff, you're likely
gonna get new stuff. Swift's only been around since IOS 8 I
guess, maybe it was 9 I guess. I was eight,
I don't remember, whichever. So, so, it's new.
So you're not likely to see this stuff when you're looking
for Swift-based code. So that's good. Okay. All right,
so what about this transition right here? Okay. So you
are going out of the inactive of this, Active state into
inactive. So you were active, user was interacting with you.
And now you have been moved into the inactive state.
Now why is it important to know this state.
This I like to talk, about as the 'app is paused' state.
Okay? So for example, let's imagine a match in breakout.
Okay? This would be the you want to
pause the motion of the ball.
Remember it's Linear Velocity and Stop it. Okay,
in here. Now, you haven't gone to any of this other state,
you just move from Active to Inactive. Now,
why might you move from Active to Inactive? Well, you might
be in your way to being thrown in to the background and
then suspend it but maybe just a phone call came in.,
Okay,if a phone call comes in you move to
the inactive foreground state. The phone call gets possessed.
When the person hangs up you go back to active. So,
if you had the bouncing ball in Breakout and
a phone call comes in, you wanna stop the ball.
When the call's over you wanna continue the ball right?
So this is the pause. Think about it as pause.
So, that's what you're gonna do in will resign active. And
again, there's a, radio station for it as well, okay,
as you can find out. The radio station is nice because
you can find out anywhere in your application if you just
went to this resign, okay?
You don't have to implement some method in app delegate,
you can find out anywhere in any view controller,
just sign up to listen to this radio station, okay. Now,
when you come back active again, okay,
maybe the phone call was over or maybe you're launching and
got to here. Okay or maybe you came out of the background.
For whatever reason when you come back here,
that's kind of the unpause.
Okay, that's where you're gonna put the ball back and
resume it's linear velocity to what it was. Okay? So this is
the pause and unpause capping between these two states right
here. And the great thing is, if you paused the ball and
you went to background, that's fine, it would be paused. And
when you come back,
whether it's come back from background or whatever reason,
you unpause and move the ball again. That's fine too.
All right? Now what about this state right here. Okay,
so here you were in the inactive state and
now you're moved into the background. Okay,
this is an important one right here, because when you move
into the background, you're only gonna get to run for
a short amount of time, about 30 seconds or so,
it's not actually guaranteed how long you get to run,
but practical matter, it's around 30 seconds. and
you'd better, in 30 seconds, you'd better hurry up,
and clean up. Because, after this,
you're probably gonna move down to the state suspended,
and then you can be killed at any time, okay? So, background
is really where you wanna batten down the hatches, okay?
Close files, you know, get rid of any stuff you're not using.
Things like that. Get your network state into the state
you want things like that because you might be,
this might be a prelude to being killed.
Maybe not but it might be so
you really wanna ask that here. Now it's possible to ask
the system for more time more if 30 seconds is not quite
enough, you can ask for a little bit more time but
eventually the system will get tired of you asking for
more time and they'll stop giving you more time. Okay.
Now, other applications, run in the background as well.
If not coming into this situation from here.
Whereas, user went to a different app or whatever. But
you can actually do things in the background.
And we'll talk about that in a second too. Okay.
Now when you come back okay, so you were in the background
okay or even suspended and then you went back
to the background and then the user made you active again.
Of course you come back up around here and you find out
here that application will enter foreground. You see
how you're coming out of the background into the green box
foreground there. Will tell you that you're back alive.
And now you can un-batten down the hatchets.
Undo what you did when you got into the background here.
You can open things back up.
All right, now, what other things can you do in
the AppDelegate besides these lifecycle methods? Tons of
things, okay. So not only can you handle push notifications
here, okay. You also have a local notification, which
are notification that you set to go up at a certain time.
Like reminders, okay, it's at 10:00pm every day,
have this local notification go up and wake my app up, and
go do something. Well, all that handled through the Also,
data protection, okay.
When your, when your app or your device is locked,
then a lot of the data, pretty much by default,
all of the data on your phone is encrypted. Okay.
That's why a locked phone, no one can get in there to your
data cuz it's encrypted, okay? And so
all the locking and unlocking and giving you access of files
where they're not encrypted when you're unlocked and
encrypted when they're locked,
that's all the AppDelegate. The AppDelegate also would get
called if you were already running and
someone said open this URL, like your keynote,
and someone said open this keynote file. You can also do
what's called background fetching which is kinda cool.
Let's say your some
social media app or something like that.
A news app and you want to kinda through out the day,
go often fetch the latest news.
So when the app runs you got the latest news right there.
You don't have to go fetch on the network at that time. And
you are actually allowed to do that,
so this background fetching Let your app launch and
run in the background for the little while again not too
long okay this is another one too many apps stealing cycles
from the foreground app but it will run in the background and
you can go do some network activity.
Pull down your data or whatever and
then go back to sleep and the system manages that and
you can go look at the documentation for
UI application to find out how you set this up. You have to
enable something in the capabilities of your app.
You set this up and
you can say kinda how often you wanna be woken up and
all those kinda things. If you abuse this, of course this so
we'll stop waking you up in the background. Other Other
reasons that you might wake up in the background.
You might be a VOIP app, right. A voice over IP app and
so you're using some other application in the foreground,
but you're talking on over VOIP to someone else.
Or you're a music playing app, okay.
And the person's got their headphones on, they're
listening to your music while they're using some other app.
Of course you're of course running in the background in
that case. So there are a lot of cases where you can run in
the background and you can look it all this up in your UI
application. Unfortunately, again from time constraints,
I don't have time to go thru and
show you all the Cool thing to know in the background but
these are some of them, and
almost all of this stuff happens with your AppDelegate.
Okay the methods in the AppDelegate.
All right, let's talk about UIApplication. The actual
object UIApplication is only one instance,
obviously in your app. You get it by calling this method
UIApplication.sharedapplica- tion Right there. Okay.
And it manages all the global behavior in your app. Mostly
it delegates things to its delegate, the app delegate,
so that's good, that's why we see so much behavior there.
But it does have some useful functionality of it's own.
For example, it has a method called openURL.
You saw this in your smashtag. Right,
this is how you could click on a URL and open it up.
You call this application method openURL okay.
You can register here for scheduling these
notifications. These local notifications, right, those
things I was telling you wake up every day at 10 o'clock and
run my app kind of things. You actually register and
schedule them here in UIApplication If
you are doing the background fetching thing I talked about.
You can set the minimum fetch interval. Okay,
so how often your background,
things gonna open up in the background in run? Here is
how you ask for more time if you're in the background.
Background task with expiration handler. Okay,
there's a little spinning wheel on the upper left
corner in the status bar of your iOS device.
I'm sure you've seen it, right,
that's supposed to represent network activity. You can turn
that on and off with this bool right here in UIApplication.
networkActivityIndicatorVis- ible equals true and
it'll on start spinning. Say false, it'll turn off.
Okay, and you generally should do this anytime you're
doing any network activity so that the user knows, app is
accessing the network right now. You can also find out
a lot of things, like remember that content sides category,
the fonts, big fonts on, you can find that out,
you can poll it, of course, you could also listen
to the radio station that tells you when it changes, but
you can poll it. You can also find out how much time
you've got remaining until you're gonna be suspended
from the background state. And you can even find out
what state you're in. Am I in the foreground?
Am I in the background etc. With this guy right there.
Okay? Now let's talk about Info.plist.
We've actually seen Info.plist.
Remember, that's where we went when we tried to access URLs,
and they were HTTP not HTTPS, right? And
we had to go in here and add something to our Info.plist
that allowed us to kind of unsecurely access URLs and
in general Info.plist is for things like that.
Little settings that you're gonna set to do things like
that. You can see that there's an, kind of a property list
editor right here. Lets you go through and edit values and
even you know, if the values are arrays okay, you can
edit that in there. You can also right-click on it and
change it to be an XML view, okay? I don't really recommend
this, cuz it's easy to make a syntax error in here, and
now your Info.plist can't be read.
So I'd stick with the other view. But actually, most of
the things in Info.plist you set In the general settings of
your project. Right? All these places where we said
things like, portrait upside down or landscape left.
Which one of those are allowed?
Those are info.p list things but we edit them here.
It's just nicer. And most of the common ones we can find in
here. Okay? Now, in addition to all, all the settings there
there's also some capabilities in your app that you have to
explicitly enable if you wanna use them, okay? And you do
this in the Capabilities tab in your Project Setting,
it looks like this. Okay.
This list is always always changing. But
you can see a lot of cool features in here like iCloud,
wich I'm gonna talk about a little later in this lecture,
and the Game Centre,
Apple Pay, here the background fetching thing,
right here, Data Protection down here, Home Kit and
Health Kit down at the bottom. If you wanna use any of these,
you have to turn it on by just going to this capabilities
tab in your project settings. And just clicking this
from off to on. And when you click it to on, there's going
to be various settings for that thing. Okay and
we'll see this all in detail when we do Cloud Kit. Okay,
you can also see from this how much stuff I just can't cover
in this class. In fact, of this whole list.
Only thing I'm gonna cover is the first one, I cloud.
Okay? The rest of the stuff, I just don't have time to get to
it all. When you go start looking through the doc and
you start looking at some of the things you might do,
you can know that you have to go here to turn things on.
Okay? All right, so
that's pretty much it for your application lifestyle,
life cycle, and kind of overall settings in your app.
The next topic I'm gonna do is alerts and action sheets okay.
So these are the pop up and
ask the user something UI okay. And they're very,
very similar the API for them is almost identical okay but
their UI is slightly different so
let's take a look at these alerts and action sheets. So
alerts, always pop up in the middle of the screen.
They grey out everything else behind it. Okay.
On this little screen. Both an iPad and iPhone.
*swallow* And, it usually asks a question that has
usually one or two answers.
Either you just click 'okay' or maybe 'okay, cancel' or
'yes, no'. Possibly a third answer. But usually it's only
two. Answers. This thing is very modal,
it kind of takes over your whole UI and
just puts up this little box, so you know,
you don't wanna use it unless you really can't proceed
without the user acknowledging this information or whatever.
Usually it's used when there are asynchronous problems,
some network connection fails. There's no place in the UI to
tell them that, so you kinda have to Take over for
a moment and say the network connection failed click OK or
click here to retry or whatever. Okay, this alerts
can have text fields in it as well. Okay, and the condition
just OK or cancel or whatever you cannot type full.
So you could use it for you know, access tonight. Enter
password Okay, you can use it for things like that. Okay?
I wouldn't use it as a general text of obtaining UI, however.
Okay? Again, it's only for exceptional circumstances.
Now an action sheet is very similar to an alert, but
it has more than two choices, usually three or
four choices. Okay? Instead of appearing in the middle,
it slides up from the bottom, on an iPhone, or
it appears in a popover on an iPad, okay? And you kind of
would think of, action sheet as a branching decision UI.
Okay, the user has reached a place in there Point in their
use of the UI where they have to branch and go do a certain
task, and go a different direction, they have two,
or three, or four different ways that they can go. Okay?
Now you've seen all these UI, these things in your app,
so I don't want to go too much into it,
but let's look a little bit about how we
do the code behind it. So Here is what they look like.
An action sheet comes up from the bottom. right.
It's got a tile right here and then also a little commentary
in there some explanation. And then it's got the buttons.
And alert is, comes up in the middle of the screen.
It's, you got one or two buttons usually and
possibly. Text, so here for example I've got
a Login Required to control my Cassini I guess here and
you got to type your guided system password to
be able to get control of Cassini.
While over in the Action Sheet I'm kind of
Cassini wants to go somewhere and we're picking a branch in
decision whether we're gonna Orbit Saturn or
E=xplore Titan, get a Closeup of the Sun. Or just cancel
that branching decision. Okay? So, how's the code for
this look? Well these things, like action sheet, are just
UI view controllers. Okay? They're presented motilly,
they just instead of taking over the whole screen,
they just get drawn like this, or
as a little square in the middle.
But they're basically just UI view controllers
presented motilly. I haven't really talked about motile
presentation. I hope to get that on Wednesday, but
modal just means you can't do anything else in that app
until you deal with this view controller. K, so these
are modal view controllers so you create them but
they are initially initialized to UI alert controller,
gonna create you one of these UI view controllers.
It's a sub class of UI view controller. All you need to
specify is this title right here like Redeploy Cassini.
And the message that goes in here
Issue commands to Cassini's guidance system.
Right here. And then, the style you want,
either action sheet or alert. Okay, so that's it,
that's how you create one of these view controllers.
The next step is we're gonna configure it and
then we're going to present it modally.
So let's do the configuration part.
Obviously configuring it, we need to add actions to it,
okay, these various buttons and we do that by sending
the method addAction, okay, to the alert and the addAction
takes one argument which is a UIAlertAction, okay.
They UIAlertAction has the following
initializer arguments The title that's gonna be
the title on the button okay like Orbit Saturn or
Explore Titan whatever. The style we'll talk about what
that style is in a second and then a handler and
this is just a closure that's gonna get executed when
this button gets pressed. Got it? So could be simpler. Okay
that's all there is. So let's look at some examples of this.
Here's orbit Saturn right here.
The title is Orbit Saturn, the style is the default style,
orbit Saturn explore Titan or default style buttons. We'll
talk about the other styles in a second. And in the closure,
obviously we're going to go into orbit around Saturn.
That's what we're going to do and
we'll do whatever code is necessary to do that there.
Okay, so here is Explore TItan,
almost exactly the same. Okay. Just that the, closure here is
a little different. Notice this closure says, okay,
if I'm going to Explorer TItan that's not part of Cassini's
mission, then, so I'm going to log,
make the person log in. Okay you can send him to Saturn,
send Cassini to Saturn evidently without a password.
But you need to enter a password for Titan.
So just has a little different action there, that's all.
Okay and these are both normal default style buttons.
Now let's take a look at closing, closer, go closeup to
the sun here, okay. Closeup to the sun's a little different.
Its style is not default, it's Destructive. So if you have a,
action sheet button that is of style of destructive,
it's gonna appear red, okay. Now you should always
pick destructive if the thing the users gonna do with this
button is going to do something permanent like
delete something,
delete an entry from a database that can't be undone,
or something like that. Okay so that is a destructive here.
A close up of the sun is probably destroy Cassini so
we made that destructive, alright but
otherwise it is still going to perform this action. Okay,
and what about cancel so cancel you notice it looks
a little different it is kind of separated. You see that?
Otherwise it looks the same. Maybe the font might be bold?
Hard to tell there, I think so. But otherwise, it's just
a normal button, okay? But it's of style cancel.
When we get to iPad, you're gonna see why it's very
important that we make our Cancel button be style. Cancel
be a different style than the other thing. Okay. So you add
all your actions there to do all the things you want to do.
And then you simply call this view controller method,
present view controller. Present view controller is
the Normal modal presentation method in view controller.
When I get talk, give you the lecture on mobile view
controllers, this is the method I'm gonna talk about.
You call this method, it takes a view controller, that's what
an alert is, right? Alert is alert controller which is
subclass UIController.
Takes one of these and it presents is modally. Okay,
this is whether it's going to animate the presentation. And
this is just a completion handler, they call it,
it gets called when it has finished presenting it.
Now when it goes away but when it finishes presenting so it's
on screen. Okay, we almost never use that, by the way.
All right, so the view controller, you do that, okay.
It puts the thing up, now when these buttons get pressed,
their closures get called. Okay,
when cancel gets pressed, it goes away, it dismisses.
That's it, that's how you use the Action sheet. Alright,
now, let's talk a little bit about iPad, okay. Because,
an iPad, this thing would look ridiculous if it came up from
the bottom. Either it would just be a tiny thing here, or
if it was as wide as the whole screen It will be gigantic,
okay? So we don't have these things come up from the bottom
on an iPad, instead we have them come up as pop-overs,
okay. See how this is the same thing, but it's over pop-over.
Notice, no cancel button, okay? Why do we
have no cancel button on iPad?
Because when a pop-over comes up, you click anywhere else,
it dismisses it. That's just like hitting cancel, okay.
In fact your cancel closure will get there, okay. So what
do we need to do to make this appear in a pop over, on iPad,
okay. Well we do need to do a little bit different code.
So here's our code from the iPhone. Okay.
First we're gonna add a little thing in here, which is,
we're gonna set the,
a View Controller's modal Presentation Style to Popover.
Okay, that says present this modally,
but in a Popover style, instead of up from the bottom
there. Okay? Then we just need to get the popover
Presentation Controller, which is just It's a class.
We're not gonna talk too much about it,
but it's the thing that controls presentation.
Okay? All view controllers, when they're presented,
have a presentation controller that presents them.
Well, pop-over ones have one called pop-over presentation
controller. You're just gonna get this thing if you look for
the UI for a pop-over presentation controller,
you'll see that it has. An argument bar button item,
it also has another argument wrecked.
Okay, and if you set the bar button item this just tells
the system where this pop over pops up from. So
here this redeploy bar button item is this little bar button
item in the upper right. And so we're just telling
the presentation controller that's gonna pop over,
pop this thing over, that this is the button that it
pops over from. And that's how it knows to put it up near it,
and to put that little triangle up there,
you see the triangle pointing to, to redeploy. We could of
said PPC question mark dot wrecked equals whatever.
And view equals whatever and
then it could pop over from any arbitrary rectangle,
anywhere in a view, okay. So you can do that as well.
So that's all we're doing here.
All we've added to this whole thing for pop over's just
made our presentation saw a pop over and
told the control, the pop over presentation controller, where
we want it to pop over from. That's all we've done. Okay,
now cool thing about this is this will work on iPhone 2.
So you can put this code in here. It will do this but
iPhone will continue to do this. And
why is that? That because of this adaptive presentation
style mechanism we talk about early in the core.
You might have forgot it by now. But it's the mechanism
that says if I try to put something up as a pop-over
on an iPhone, it says op, can't, we don't do pop-overs
on an iPhone so we're gonna present this thing modally.
So it presents it modally and this is what an action sheet
looks like, one presented modally, okay, versus
pop-over style So it's back to presenting the same way. Now,
of course, it doesn't even look at
this pop over presentation controller because
it didn't end up presenting it with the pop over style.
It adapted and presented it with a normal modal style.
So this is great. You can write this one code and
it'll work on both devices. Okay.
All right, what about alerts? Okay,
so alerts are almost exactly the same as Action Cheat. You
just say the style is Alert here instead of Action Cheat.
You still do all the same thing with Add Action, okay,
your Cancel Button and Add Action for
the login button. Okay?
So just like same thing we did with the cl, closures and
all that stuff right here. One thing that's different about
the alert, of course, you've got this text field. So how do
you deal with the fact there's text fields in an alert but
not an action sheet? And the answer is
AlertController has a method addTextFieldWithConfiguration-
Handler. This only does something on alerts,
it doesn't do anything if it's an action sheet. And
this closure will be called with the text field that
you're adding, and allow you to configure it in here.
So that's all this little closure does,
is just configuring the text field. So for example,
I want guidance system password as my placeholder
text in this text field, so I've just set textfield's
placeholder to be Guidance System Password there, okay.
So this adds a text field to the alert, and
this closure just lets you configure it.
Now, what happens when someone types in here? How do you get
the text out of there? Well in the action, like for
cancel, we went away, we, we don't even look at the text.
But for log in, I wanna look at this password.
So in the action closure here for
login, you see that right there, the action closure?
I'm going to say, if I can let tf = self.alert.textFields?,
is option because you don't always have text field .first.
Okay, I only have one text field so I want the first one.
Then, I've got the text field and I could, for example,
log in with the password tf.text. Okay, so
the answer is I use this text field's bar which is an array
of all the text fields that are in this alert. Okay,
so that's it, that's it for action alert.
Pretty easy to use,
you're almost certain to use them in your final project.
That's why I'm covering them early in the final project
period here. So hopefully that gives you all the things,
everything you need to know to do that. All right, and
of course, we present this thing exact same way,
presentViewController, okay.
It's just modally presented, happens to draw in this way,
but it's still just modally presented, so we use the same
presentViewController there, okay. And
it looks the same both on iPad and iPhone. All right, so
Cloud Kit. So I'm covering Cloud Kit,
again I don't usually cover Cloud Kit. But
I'm covering it this quarter because I think it's gonna be
something really cool and powerful for you to use for
your final projects, okay. So what is Cloud Kit?
Cloud Kit is a database in the cloud, okay.
It's a feature of iCloud and it's very simple to use, okay.
And it has very basic database operations,
okay. It's over the network, so everything that you're
doing is happening real time on the network, so
it's all asynchronous, of course. Because the network
could be slow or even not available, okay.
That requires you to do some thoughtful programing,
as you have learned with everything is asynchronous,
you kinda have to like, think about what it means for
these methods to, not call you back until much later, okay.
So, otherwise, it's really nice simple, database
mechanism to use. Here are the important concepts,
okay, that you need to know. One is record type.
Record type is like an entity in core data.
We're gonna do a lot of parallels to core data,
cuz you know core data so well so know that terminology, so
record type is kind of like entity.
Fields are like attributes. Okay, so fields
are the data that's stored in a record, type record.
A record is an instance of a record type. So I've got,
just like, it's like, sort of like NSManageObject in,
core data. But of course it's so much more lightweight,
there isn't any of that infrastructure.
But it's kind of like that, so
it's an instance of a certain record. A reference is kinda
like a relationship to another entity or another record type
there, okay reference. A database is a place where you
store your records. A zone is a sub-area of a database.
I'm not gonna talk about zones, but
if you divide your database up into zones you can do cool
things like, do efficient queries,
where you're only querying over a subset of your data,
like this in-sum zone. Okay, I'm not gonna talk about that,
but that's what a zone is all about,
it's a subarea of a database for searching and
stuff. A container is a collection of databases, we'll
talk about that. A query, is a NSPredicate based search.
Of course, NSPredicates can be quite a bit simpler,
because it's a simpler database,
but, it's still, similar to core data. You're gonna use,
actually use the class and its predicate to make '.
And then a subscription is a standing query, okay.
It's, basically an NSPredicate, you can upload to
the database, and any time it changes it will send you
a push notification, which is fantastic. This is the coolest
feature of all in Cloud Kit, is that it will send you push
notifications when the database changes, okay.
And then all you need to do is just, give it a standing
query, called a subscription, and it'll do that, okay.
All right, so let's talk about how all this works,
how do we make this Cloud Kit thing happen. First thing you
have to understand about Cloud Kit is a very important thing
here called the Cloud Kit Dashboard. This is a website,
okay. You get to it by going to your project, okay,
click on your project. Actually,
I'll show in a second how you can get to this. But
you can click somewhere in your project, and
it's gonna take you to this website.
This is gonna have all your record types,
all your entities, and
all of their fields, all their attributes.
So here's an entity called QandA, it's a question and
answer thing. Here's, it's got answers,
which is a list of strings, an array of strings,
and it's got a question, which is a single string. And
these are all indexed, both for querying and searching and
even sorting, okay. Here's another one,
response, it's got some things. Over here, okay,
you can actually go to default zone right here, you'll
be able to actually see the data stored in these records,
which is kinda cool. And then it's got some other
things here like the subscriptions that you have
outstanding out there.
Maybe any users that are using the database etc.
So this is kind of your place where you're gonna go to find
out everything that's going on in your database in real time,
'kay. The dashboard also has interesting
metadata indexes, and I'm putting a slide on this,
cuz this is easy to forget. Okay, because, of course,
the QandA thing has answers and question fields, but
it also has these fields like the record ID which is
a unique ID for this QandA record. Also, created by,
that's the user who created it, that's very interesting.
The date it was created.
So these are all kind of fields you always get, and
by default none of them are index however. So if you
wanted to search and say show me all the QandA's that were
created by a certain user, that wouldn't work, unless you
go in here in the dashboard and turn on query index for
created by. Okay, so don't forget about this. This is
something easy to forget to do cuz they're automatic off and
you're like how come that they won't show me all the QandA's
by this user,
it's because it's not indexed, okay. So that,
you need to click on this little guy here,
metadata indexes, to show this. Okay now,
that schema that we're talking about there, the entities and
the attributes okay, the record types and the fields,
you can create it all in the dashboard if you want, but
you don't have to.
You can just start creating them in your code and
it'll automatically create the schema for you. Every time
you will reference an entity that wasn't there before,
it's gonna create a new entity for it. Every time you access
a field on a certain entity, you know, record type,
it's gonna create an attribute automatically. Now,
you're still gonna have to go to dashboard and turn on or
off any indexes and things like that, but
it's just gonna create it all for you on the fly.
That only happens though during development,
once you deploy your app over at the app store,
now that's not true anymore, okay.
So your app has to have its schema built in development
and then you export that schema. When you run in
deployment environment, okay? So this is really cool for
development because you don't have to do a lot of tedious
creating of things in your in your dashboard.
And you can always go in the dashboard and delete things.
And it's really actually quite flexible and cool.
Now none of this will work until you unable Cloud Kit
in your capabilities. Remember I'd show you the capabilities
earlier. You go to the very top one here iCloud and
you're gonna click this from off to on.
Okay if you don't do that none of this works. So
when you click it to on. You get this settings right here.
You're gonna wanna click this switch right here Cloud Kit.
That's all this stuff I'm gonna be talking about here in
this lecture, okay? Cloud Kit. There's also Key Value Storage
which is kind of cool, you can store like an NS user defaults
on the Cloud. That's kind of cool features.
Well, I'm not gonna talk about that. It's there if you wanna
do it and of course you can store documents in the Cloud.
Manage document Remember that from core data?
It stores all the core data stuff in the cloud, okay?
So, so you could have that as well.
But today, we're talking about this Cloud Kit right here,
all right? This button right here,
is how you get to that Cloud Kit dashboard.
This will open up your browser and take you to that thing,
for you. Kay? This right here is the containers. Remember I
said a container is a thing that contains databases.
We're only gonna talk about use default container here.
But you're gonna actually create your custom containers.
And what's cool about these containers is these containers
can be used across different kinds of apps. Okay?
In other words, you might be a company in
your shipment four different apps, and
they wanted to share data.
They can do that by creating a shared container, okay?
The default container is just to use by your one app, okay?
I'm shipping to my app, all my users of that one app can use
this default container. Okay, and that's what I'm gonna
talk about today, but you can just know that this custom
container feature is available for your final project,
the default container's gonna be plenty, okay?
All right, so let's talk about these containers and
what's in them, okay? And because we need to know that,
so we can create records in the database,
okay? So we get a database from the container.
Remember, I said container contains databases.
And the default container actually has two databases,
a public database and a private database.
The difference between these two is that the private
database can only be looked at by the currently logged in
iCloud user. Okay, so you know how on your phone, hopefully,
you're logged into iCloud, right? Okay, so,
whatever that login is, only the person logged in as that
iCloud can see the private database for that iCloud view.
So, it is exactly what it sounds like,
it is private information. The public database can be seen by
anybody, okay, anybody who is running your app. Can see
this public database. Got the difference between public and
private? So public is where you're gonna have data that's
shared between your users, private data is where you're
gonna have data that the user sees on all their devices but
the other users can't see. All right. So that's how you
get the database. Once you have the database.
You can do all kinds of things.
Create records query all kinds of stuff.
So let's starts with how to create record on the database.
Okay. You create a record first of all by distributing
CKRecord, Cloud Kit record and all you do is specified
the record type. Okay, that's like the entity name,
like tweet or Twitter user, whatever, it's just a string,
okay. If that entity doesn't exist in the database when you
save this record, it'll create that entity, okay? Make sense?
All right, so now you have this record, okay?
How do you put information into the record? Well, you use
a dictionary-like syntax. So here I've got a record,
right here. And I'm adding some fields to it by saying,
records of text equals something, records of created
equals something, records of items equals something, So,
you see how ithat looks a dictionary? It looks like
records is almost a dictionary right there And so
that's actually use it, now what are these values,
these things that I have dot, dot, dot right here,
what are these? Well, these can only be things
that implement the protocol CKRecordValue, okay? And
the only things the implement that protocol are these seven
things in green. Strings, numbers, arrays and dates.
And of course, we get the bridged Swift types, so
that means doubles, ints, string, array, okay? And
then also these three special things, CKReference,
CKAssett and CLLocation, okay?
Now array can be array of any of the other types. Okay?
The array of any of these other green things.
So you can have an array of numbers, array of strings,
array of dates,
CKReference is a reference to another record. Okay, so this
is how you do relationships, okay? So you have a record.
So again, if you had tweeter, and the tweets, okay?
The tweet record type would have a field
that is a CKReference to a Twitter user, okay?
CKAsset is for storing big things, like images, sounds,
video, okay, files basically. Now, This cloud kit does
a really cool job of when you put something in the cloud it
doesn't immediately just start cranking on the network piling
that thing up on the net, it stores it locally and
when it wants to, when there's good network connection,
whatever, it's uploading it to the cloud. And vice versa. So
It's doing all this behind the scenes and
being very efficient and
caching it etc. CL location, we're gonna talk about next
week when we talk about maps and locations.
It's just a GPS coordinate, okay, someplace on earth,
so you can store something as a GPS coordinate. Okay, so
that's it, it's super. Easy to create these records. Again as
you put these field names in here if that doesn't exist in
the schema it's just gonna add that field okay as soon as you
store this to the database. So here we've created the record
but we haven't stored it yet okay it's not it hasn't been
uploaded to the network we've only created it locally.
So how do we get the information. So we
saw how to put the information record how do we get it out
You again use dictionary syntax,
so recor|"text| to get the text out of the record. But
you have to cast, because all of these things come back as
CKRecordValues. Okay? Cuz I told you, the only things that
can go in are things that implement that protocol.
So when you get it out, it comes out,
it's a thing that implements that protocol.
So you have to cast it.
To the thing it actually is, okay. Make sense? That's why
even like records of items. That's an array of strings.
You have to say as array of string, okay, got it.
And of course, these all will be optional because as
question mark. So I might wanna say if let on all these.
Okay. Now, I've got the record creator, how do I put it into
the database? It's, actually, the real answer is, or
the full answer is you're gonna create an NSOperation,
okay? Do you remember NSOperation, NSOperationQueue?
That's the object-oriented version of the GCD, right?
Dispatch async and
all that stuff So the way you actually create
records in the database is you create a special kind of
NS operation called CKModifyRecordsOperation and
you can give it a bunch of records and you create and
NS or operation cue, okay. You could use the main cue, okay,
or you can create you're own cue. Those cues are just like
threads, okay, they're like Not like threads,
they're cues, just like dispatch under bar cue,
under bar tee things. And then you just tell that, if you put
this ModifyRecordsOperation on a cue it'll go and
execute it and
update the database. But
that's a little bit of a pain in the neck to go do all that,
okay. So there's a nice little convenience method right in
database called save record. And it just takes a record and
a completion handler. And it saves the record and
calls your completion handler when it's done. Okay, and
remember that can be quite a ways later because this is
happening over the network. Your network might be slow,
you might be out of range of network, whatever. So
it can take a very, very long time for this to come back.
It could even possibly time out but this is how it works.
S this is on the database.
Remember the public database or
the private database that you got from the container?
That's where you send this method. Okay?
Now this thing cant do everything that this whole
NSoperationQ can write multiple records at once.
It also knows how to overwrite a newer version.
Okay, this does optimistic locking right here, the save
record one. So if it tries to write something and there's
a newer version of that thing it's just gonna fail.
Report an error.
It'll come back with an error here in the handler whereas
the modify records operation knows how to
overwrite what's in there. But save record for
the most part does what you want most of the time. And for
your final project this is gonna be plenty probably.
Okay, but you're not gonna need this operation thing.
All right, this happens all asychronously.
Be very careful specially be careful with the fact
that your closure they gets cold when they save record is
finished Happens on another thread besides the main queue.
Okay, it's not in the main queue.
So you need to dispatch async back to the main queue from
there if you want to do some UI stuff when
that record is saved. It make sense? Okay, and
you also just need an architecture code properly.
You need to think about the whole design of your app
when the data that's appearing in it
might be coming asychronously. So
you need to know how to have apps that have basically blank
UIs with either spinning wheels or Loading or
something on there, so the user knows what's going on.
And, when the data comes, it populates it. Okay?
It's very similar to, you do the smash tag where
you have the little profile images, and they come up and
they were blank. And then they just started filling in. Same
kind of thing here, you have data in your database that
starts out, you don't have it and then it starts filling in.
And what does that mean for the user? Means things should
start appearing over time. So you gotta think about how to
architect your app to use asyncronity. All right, so
here's what it looks like to create
a record in the database all put together here.
So I'm going to create a tweet right here.
So here I'm letting tweet equal ckrecord.
Just created a record.
I'm gonna have the Tweets text to be 140 characters of pure
joy. Then I'm gonna get my database by saying
CKContainer.defaultContainer publicCloudDatabase. So I'm
gonna put this in the public database that all users of my
app can see. Then I'm just gonna ask the database to save
the record Tweet, right. Here's that record Tweet and
it's gonna call this closure, this big thing,
when it's done. And this closure test two arguments,
the record that it saved or
nil if it failed to save it and an error, okay.
Again, nil if it saved it, not nil if it failed to save it,
okay. It doesn't return anything and so here's why
doing my closure almost all of the time first I'm gonna say,
if the error equals nil Hooray okay,
it saved it successfully, so now I do whatever I do when
it was successfully saved. Maybe nothing okay? Maybe I do
something else, I don't know, but here's success. Sometimes
there are 29 different errors in ck error code, so
a lot of things can go wrong. Network unavailable, all kinds
of things I just showed you how you handle these by
picking one at random, which is not authenticated.
Okay? Let's say the person is not logged into iCloud.
Kay? They just never went to their settings and
logged into iCloud. Okay? So
you're gonna get this error, CKErrorCode.NotAuthenticated.
Don't forget put, to put .rawValue so you get it as
an integer because this error code is an integer. And
so if there's that then I'm gonna maybe put up an alert
code that "Please log in to iCloud" or something, right?
And there's 29 other errors and so doing this programming
really right, is a lot of error handling code. Okay, so
in your final project You know the more you do of
this the more it's kind of like you can get forming
a one-point use of Cloud kit to a two-point use if you
actually handle the error, you see what I'm saying?
I don't expect you to handle every single error and
uh-uh you get zero points, okay. Of course not, okay,
the more error you handle, the more robust you are,
the better you're a synchronize use,
the more depth point you might get working in Cloud,
Cloud kit Okay, but there's lots of other errors here.
I'll show you some other errors that were going to
handle in some other, ones in a second here.
But this is how you're going to do it. Else if, else if,
else if, or you could just switch on the error code,
to go to handling errors. Okay.
I mean, at worst, you could just either put an alert up,
because the user is saying unknown error or something, or
you could print something on the console. I don't know.
But it's usually you want to try and collect
all the errors that you can do something about, okay?
Now again if tweet the entity doesn't exist in the database
it's gonna create it, okay? If text field doesn't exist on
this it's gonna create that attribute automatically for
me. Okay, so that's it. That's how you put a record in
the database real easy. Okay? Now, there's
a special kind of error, that you can get sometimes,
where, it will actually give you a retry time interval. So,
not all errors have this, but some errors when you get them,
Cloud Kit is basically saying hey,
you know this is the kinda area you probably wanna retry,
and here's a good amount of time to try, okay.
So it's basically telling you what an appropriate retry
interval would be.
And I believe if things continue to fail it, you know,
adds, makes the retry interval a little bit longer,
until it just gives up and says don't retry anymore.
More, but here is how you get it.
Error the NSError that you get back here in addition I have
an error it also has a user info dictionary and
in that dictionary is a key CKError retry after key and
it's an NS time interval okay it's actually an NS number but
you're gonna cast it to an NS time interval there And
then you gonna wanna dispatch back to the main queue because
you gonna wanna have do a timer and
we know that we do our timers on the main queue. And so I'm
gonna schedule a timer with that retry interval I'm just
gonna call some method but will probably try this again.
Okay maybe calls a method that this is in in fact.
Okay I found So basically something might put in
any kind of error that you'd be willing to retry.
Just check to see if there's a retry interval, there's is.
Give it a go. Try it again. Okay,
and if there is no retry interval then of course,
this won't happen. You won't be doing this timer thing.
Got it? Okay, now we've got the records stored.
Now we want to get them, okay? So we basically want a query
to get them. And querying is also super, super simple here.
You're just gonna do performQuery on the database.
Just like you did saveRecord on the database you're gonna
do performQuery and give it a query.
I'll talk about in a second. This inZoneWithID,
remember I've told you there were zones, subdatabase zones,
okay. So you can specify a zone there, or nil, actually
that's an optional string, so that could be nil. But if you
specify a zone, it will put, it will search only in zone,
so you can limit your search and be more efficient, okay,
if you can sensibly Divide your database into little
zones. To keep your searches smaller it's a good idea.
That's what that inZoneWithID is.
For your final project, again you could say nil and
just put everything in one big zone, default zone. And
then of course you're gonna call a completion handler, and
look what the completion handler has.
An array of the records that you searched for, couldn't be
simpler. Okay? Possibly an error. Okay, so this is just
really straightforward. You give it a query.
It just calls your handler with the records that matched.
Or nil if there was an error, okay?
Now what about this CKQuery, that's also trivial.
It's initializer is just the entity, okay?
So you wanna search for tweets and then an NSPredicate, okay?
And so this NSPredicate is gonna specify which things you
want in your database. And this NSPredicate is
obviously much simpler than Core Data because there
are just fewer things that you can do, fewer data type,
fewer, the relationships aren't as complicated,
there's just that reference thing etc. But
you can look in the documentation for CKQuery,
it has a very good description of all the things you can do
with NSPredicate for CKQuery. It's, you know,
all the things you might think like equals equals.
But also it has some cool things like in, okay?
Where you check whether something is in and
array of other things for example. And so like that,
it also has a special field name by the way, self, and
you know, cuz you should, could have a field name like
text if there's a tweet, text contains some word.
That's perfectly valid predicate. But you can also
have self as a keyword, not just tech, but self. And if I
say self contains whatever, it'll look in all the fields,
okay, that are index, not just text but all the tweets.
So maybe you have a tweet that has text, it has hashtags,
it has you know URLs as different fields. If you'd say
self-contained something, it'll look in all the fields,
all the indexed fields to find it, okay?
So it's kind of a search text over all the index field,
okay? So this is really, couldn't be simpler,
they couldn't have made this any simpler. This is as simple
a kind of queries you can possibly imagine. Okay, so
here's an example. Here I'm looking for
a tweet that's text contains some search string so
I've a predicate which is
text contains %@ which is the search string there.
Otherwise, it looks just like NSPredicate of core data.
Okay, I'm gonna create this query which is looking for
Tweets without predicate. I'm gonna perform the query
some time later. It's gonna call my closure right here.
It's gonna give me a list of all the Tweets, okay,
that contain that. That's what this records thing is right
here. Again, I'm checking for errors. Here, I've checked for
that not authenticated error again. But,
it's as simple as that, okay? Now,
one thing, if you're gonna search on any of these things,
any field that you're gonna search on, make sure you go to
your dashboard and make sure that the checkbox query for
indexes is set, otherwise you can't query on it. Okay,
now when you create new fields automatically on
the fly like this, it automatically sets those.
it automatically turns on indexes for all of them.
It doesn't turn on the indexes for created by and
created date and all that, but it does do it for
the new field that you add. And in fact,
when you go to deploy, you probably wanna turn
some of those off if you know you never search on it.
Don't waste the database's time creating indexes that
it doesn't use. Now, there's a special kind of record
though that you get with the special method here which
is the recordID of the user, okay, the currently logged in
iCloud user. Now why would you ever want this?
Well, because you might wanna look in the database and
find records created by that user. And to do that,
you need the user. You need the user's RecordID so
that you can make a query that says user, or
createdBy, let's say, which is a built in one. User, creator,
something. Actually I'll talk about in the next slide. You
want to be able to set that. Well, to do that, you need it.
And you do this with a fetchUserRecordIDWithCompleti-
onHandler. That is not sent to the database, though.
That is sent to the container. Okay,
because the container, all the databases in the container,
the, I currently logged in iCloud user, is the user for
them. So you actually go up to CKContainer to do this,
CKContainer default container,
fetch record user record with completion handler, and
it just returns you the RecordID of the user.
Now, notice this is the RecordID, not the CKRecord,
you almost never need the actual record of the user.
You could get the record of the user, and
you could even add fields to it if you wanted,
but it's rare to do that. Usually, you just need
the RecordID because you're going to be querying on it,
you're gonna be making queries to find out if this user was
the person who created it or whatever, okay?
The RecordID has a property record name,
which is just some randomly created string that you
can use as kind of a blind username.
It's not gonna be the person's actual iCloud name, it's just
some gobbledygook. But inside of your implementation,
you can use it as a string key that means this user if you
want, okay? I'm gonna combine the two things,
the fetchUserRecord with the query here. I'm gonna find all
the tweets that were created by the currently logged in
user. Okay, so first I get the container,
I fetch the user in the completion handler for
that right here. I have the user. Now I'm gonna create
a new predicate which is the creatorUserRecordID.
Which is a built in field on all record types.
Equals the UserRecordID, a thing I got from fetchRecord.
See that thing right there.
And them I'm gonna create a query which is for
tweets that uses that predicate. Now I'm gonna
get the public database and perform the query, okay?
In zone nil, and I'm gonna get the record in error as
a return value. And so now I have this records containing
all the tweets created by the currently logged in user.
See how I chained those two? And
remember, this fetch record, UserRecordID,
that's gonna take a little while.
And when it returns, it's gonna do another query.
That's gonna take a little while, so it's gonna chain.
But since this call is inside of this other closure,
it chains them nicely there. Okay, again
you have to create, turn that Created By metadata index on
that I showed you right at the beginning for this to work or
you can't search on user. Okay, by the way,
if you ever have a RecordID and you wanna get the record,
okay, the CKRecord, you can use databases
fetchRecordWithID and that will search and
get the actual record, okay? The RecordID, though,
on its own has some interesting things
like the creator, the creation date, the record type,
and all that stuff, so that's kind of fun. All right,
deleting records from the database couldn't be easier.
Just say to the database,
deleteRecordWithID. You have to have the record ID, you can
of course get the record ID from a record easily,
there's a bar for it. And then completionHandler when it's
done, okay? Okay, now let's talk about references, okay?
I wanna, I want to store a reference. So this is
like the Twitter user as the tweeter for a tweet.
You cannot do this code right here. twitterUser equals
a recordType TwitterUser. Tweet equals a record Tweet.
Tweet, subTweeter equals TwitterUser. [SOUND] Okay,
can't do it. This thing has to be a CKReference.
So you just have to say TweetSubTweeter equals
CKReference with the record. And then you specify this
action which is interesting, it's either deletes itself or
not. This action says what to do if this thing is deleted.
Okay, when we cascade. So if I say the action is DeleteSelf,
this reference to twitterUser is DeleteSelf reference.
Then if the twitterUser is deleted, then the Tweet is
deleted as well. It cascades the delete. That's why it's
saying delete myself, okay, if this reference gets deleted.
None means don't do it. When you delete,
don't do any cascading, just delete this one thing, okay?
By the way, when you're creating a predicate,
you don't have to do that CKReference thing.
If I wanna create a predicate which is tweeter equals
something, I can actually pass the twitterUser, I don't have
to say CKReference twitterUser there. Okay, standing queries,
the last thing we're talking about, subscriptions, okay? So
sometimes it's nice to not have to be constantly
querying, you just want iCloud to tell you when a new Thing
appears in the database that you're interested in.
And that's really, really easy to do. So for
an example here, I'm going to set up a subscription so
that I get notified by a push notification any time that
a Tweet is created or
deleted. So I'm gonna create a predicate which is
true predicate which means all Tweets. Okay,
this is a special predicate, that means all.
And in core dating, you have the predicate nil, means all.
Here you have to create a predicate,
it's true predicate.
And then you create this thing called a CKSubscription
with the record type that you're interested in, Tweets,
the predicate you want, all of the them. A subscriptionID,
this is an English language string that should
very uniquely describe what you're looking for. Okay,
because this is gonna identify this subscription in
the database so you can delete it later for an example.
Okay so here I called it "All Tweet Creation and Deletion".
And then options is what kinds of actions of those tweets,
for example, do you wanna know when the tweets are created?
Do you wanna know when tweets are deleted?
You can also find out when tweets are updated,
their fields change. And you can also have FiresOnce
in here which means that this subscription only works once.
It sends you one push notification and
then gets deleted. Okay, so it's like a one time standing
query. It also has this thing called a notifcationInfo.
Okay, this is gonna send a push notification.
So this can help you configure that push notification right
here. And then you just say, database.saveSubscription.
Okay, and it'll call you back when it's done.
And that puts this subscription in the database.
And now the database is gonna send you a push notification
whenever this is changing. Okay, creation or deletion of
tweets, in this case. Okay, now I have to tell you how to
deal with push notifications, okay. How to turn them on,
and how to get them. So, to turn on a push notification,
you actually need to in your application,
didFinishLaunchingWithOptions is usually where you would put
this code, you have to put these yellow lines here.
Which is, you have to call this method
registerUserNotificationSetti- ngs.
Okay, the user notification settings just say what kind
of push notifications you're willing to receive like,
alerts, badges, or sounds.
If you're just alerting to let the code know, you don't have
to send off any of those three, okay? Alert badge and
sound means it's gonna put an alert up when things come,
okay, or a badge. It's gonna put a little red badge
on your icon, your app icon which is kinda cool maybe,
you might want that actually.
You get to specify the, what happens when the push
notification comes from Cloud Kit back in that notification
info thing that I was telling you about in the previous
slide. Subscription.notificationInfo,
one of the things in there is whether to alert badge or
sound when the subscription fires. Okay. So
anyway you register what your kind of settings you want, and
then you have to register for remote notifications.
That means I wanna hear about remote notifications.
If you don't do this, you won't get any push
notifications of any kind, let alone these Cloud Kit ones.
Okay. So now once you've done that okay,
you need to receive them. And you do that with this
application delegate method didReceiveRemoteNotification.
So this will get called any time a push notification comes
to your app, okay. When you get it there's user info
right here, okay. And inside that userInfo is a dictionary
that Cloud Kit's gonna send. And you're gonna use this
CKNotification class, right here, call it initializer,
with that dictionary to create a CKNotification.
That CKNotification, Cloud Kit notification, represents
the push notification that was sent to you. It's got all the
information you need to know about the push notification
that got sent because you're subscription. Okay? And
it's got things in there like the recordID that change
that cause it. Why the notification is happening s
it because something was created,
or something was deleted, or something was updated?
Okay, will tell you which of those things went on that
caused this notification to be sent to you and
which record was affected by it.
You can even, in the subscription notificationInfo,
you can set certain fields to be prefetched and
come along with. Okay, cuz normally it only sends you
the recordID of what changed in the database.
You might wanna actually sum of the fields, so
you don't have to go get, fetch the record itself, okay?
So that's great. Now that you've got this notification,
what do you do with it. Okay, you really need to get it
to the part of your UI, if you control it or
whatever, that's going to do something with this data
that has changed, okay. And the best way,
this is all coming to your AppDelegate, right?
Is your AppDelegate getting this push notification?
That's not that useful because usually it's some view
controller somewhere that really wants the information.
So what we're gonna do is we're gonna forward it
using the radio station model, okay?
That's is real simple way to get this thing to came to
AppDelegate and get it out to who really wants it. So
I'm just gonna create a local notification here I'm gonna
become a radio station broadcaster see in this
notification.
Here's my radio station name MyCloudKitNotificationName or
whatever. Self is this is in AppDelegate so self is gonna
be my AppDelegate but it probably doesn't matter what I
pass here as the sender of the radio station. And
then here in the userInfo, I'm gonna put that ckn,
this notification right here that I created, okay,
from the dictionary that came in the push notification.
I'm gonna put that in the dictionary
under some key name, ckn or
whatever, CKNKey, so that the people who are listening to my
radio station can get this CKNotification. By the way,
these two strings wanna be global constant somewhere.
So that the listeners and the sender are using the same keys
and radio station names, okay? And then I just post it, okay.
DefaultCenter postNotification disNotification.
And now everybody's listening to this radio station gonna
find out about all the push notifications coming
from Cloud Kit. Cause they're getting forwarded out to them.
Okay, now, if I'm an observer, what do I do? I just
do this addObserverForName, okay. So now I'm some view
controller that wants to hear this push notification, so
I do addObserveForName, I use the radio station name there,
I don't care who sends it to me, I'm going to do it on
the same queue because I know my AppDelegate runs on
the main queue, but I could put main queue here also. And
then using block right here.
This is the block that gets called.
Here's the notification that came over the radio station.
I'm gonna look in the notification look at that
user interface, user info, get that key and cast it
to be a CKQueryNotification by the way. There's another kind
of thing it could be which is a zone oriented notification,
I'm not talking about zones but most of the times it's
gonna be a query notification cuz it's a subscription.
So you can do this as query notification.
Now you're gonna check to see if the subscriptionID of this
query notification is the same as your subscriptionID because
there might be other view controllers
who have subscriptions in Cloud Kit and
they're getting notified by push notifications.
You don't want theirs, you want yours. And
you can tell it's yours because you can look in this
CKQueryNotification and find the subscriptionID that caused
this push notification to get pushed, got it? And
once I'm sure it's for me now I can go react to it.
The data's available.
Maybe I'll put it in my table view or whatever I do with
it cuz the data is here, okay? Maybe I'll query for
more information, whatever. But now I can get going.
Make sense? By the way, notice that when did out observe for
name I grabbed the return value that cookie I told you
and in this object protocol thing we did and why do I want
that, because later on when I'm done listening
to further push notifications via this radio station.
I'm gonna call removeObserver to remove this observer so
I no longer get these local notifications.
So this is something might do in our view did disappear.
And we might do this in our view will appear or view did
appear. Right, cuz only when we're on screen do we maybe
want these notifications. When we go off we don't
want them any more. When we come back on we wanna
keep getting them again. Okay? You definitely wanna do this,
by the way you never want your view controller to go away and
still be here because this closure will keep your
view controller in memory. And you don't wanna really do
weakSelf and all that because you actually wanna explicitly
remove it otherwise the NotificationCenter's gonna
always be holding onto you, okay?
So, make sure you do this, somewhere, removeObserver
somewhere. Okay, that's it for Cloud Kit. Now you know
everything about how to create records, query for
them, and even sign up to get notified.
I'm gonna do a big demo on this on Wednesday, so you can
see it all in action. Friday, No Section again. Next week,
still kinda deciding how or what works to do things.
I really wanna make to sure you get
this Segues covered right here but maps are also really cool.
I won't get to all of these next week but I'll do as much
as I can. Okay, if you have by the way something you really
like to see me do because you find a project wants to
do it. Like Cloud Kit was, let me know. Okay, that's it.
See you next time. >> For
more please visit us at stanford.edu.