[MUSIC]
Stanford University. >> All right, well,
welcome to C, Stanford CS193P spring of 2016
lecture number 16. And today it's all demo.
I'm gonna do a big demo on CloudKit to show you how,
how that works. I'm also gonna take a brief little
thing at the beginning to show you about notifications, that
little radio station thing. We talked about how you can find
out about size changes happening and
I'm gonna show you how that works. And that's pretty much
it for today. It's kinda all demo today.
Coming up Friday we're not doing sections anymore.
People weren't that interested in sections this quarter,
that's fine. And then next week,
I'm gonna be covering maps some more segues, and
then just some miscellaneous topics, not quite sure yet
what I'm gonna do there. All right, so,
let's dive right into this demo. Going to launch Xcode
here. We're going to make a new project.
It's gonna be our standard stuff here. So
what I'm gonna do is an app that is a question asking app.
So it lets you author questions with answers, and
then they're out on the cloud, in iCloud,
and people can answer the questions,
okay, and then it keeps track of how many answers people had
and all that stuff. So today we're just gonna kinda do
the start of it, which is, we'll have some UI to make
the question and we'll upload the questions to the cloud,
and then we'll have another view controller which shows
a list of all the questions that you can choose on.
And you can click, some UI to make a new question or
delete old questions. So we're gonna be able to do all
kinds of iCloud stuff there. Deleting,
we're gonna do subscriptions with push notifications,
all that stuff. Okay, so we're gonna call this app Pollster.
I'm also gonna change my unique thing here just to be
something different, how about teacher instead of instructor.
So Pollster, because you could use it to poll,
ask people questions, and get polls. No Core Data,
it's gonna be an iPhone-only application. We're just gonna
have a couple table views is all. And we'll put it in our
standard location here. So here we are in Pollster, and
I'm going to kind of clear out my storyboard to start. So
let's take this little view controller that it
comes with, let's delete its code right here.
So I'll do Delete. Move that to the trash.
Let's go ahead and put these little guys into a little
supporting files thing again, Supporting Files. And notice
I'm gonna leave AppDelegate out of the Supporting Files,
because of course, we're gonna do push notifications.
That involves our AppDelegate, so it's not really
a supporting file, it's kind of a main thing this time.
And back in the storyboard we can just get rid of this view
controller, we don't need it at all, okay.
Now, I also have some other files
here that are gonna be supporting files for
this demo, so I'm gonna drag those in right here.
In fact, I'm gonna put them in Supporting Files.
Copy them in, let's take a quick look at those.
All right, so one is, I just wanted all my structs, with,
you know, my constants in there to be pre-typed in so
I don't have to type them in all the time. And basically,
these constants are gonna be for the push or actually for
the local notification, the radio station stuff,
this is gonna be the name of our radio station and
the key in the dictionary.
And then these are the names of the entities and
attributes that I'm gonna create in CloudKit, okay?
So we're doing QandA, here are questions and answers, and
here's a Response to a QandA, and then we've got questions,
answers, we got a chosenAnswer, and
then we've got a reference qanda. So we got all that.
And then I added this little wasCreatedByThisUser.
It's a bool on a CKRecord, a CloudKit record, that just
says whether this record was created by the currently
logged in iCloud user, okay. So that's that.
Then, over here, I have this nice class here,
QandATableViewController.
It is, has nothing to do with iCloud. It's just a table view
controller that shows a question, okay, a question and
as many answers as you want. Okay, notice that it inherits
from TextTableViewController. That's a generic
view controller that just shows a table view where all
the rows are editable text. Okay, that's all that is.
It doesn't know anything about questions and answers,
it's just rows of editable text,
nothing more. We're not even gonna be accessing this API,
we're gonna be focusing totally at this MVC's level.
And here's the public API for that, super simple. Okay,
it's got this var qanda, which is basically its model,
which is of type QandA, that's this struct, and
it's a question, which is a String, and answers,
which are Strings. Okay, so it couldn't be any simpler,
it's the simplest possible data structure for
a Q&A. It's got, these other vars here is just whether
you're asking the question or answering the question.
That's cuz if you're asking the question,
you can edit the question, right? You're asking it, so
you can add more answers and stuff like that.
Whereas, if you're answering the question,
you can only choose an answer, okay? And
then if you do choose an answer, here's the answer.
So you can just get the answer as a string, okay? It might be
a nil, because maybe they haven't answered yet.
So that's it, that's the entire public API of this, and
this is the only API we're gonna use in our cloud one.
And our cloud one is just gonna be a subclass of this,
because it's gonna be a QandA, but
it's a QandA that's stored in the cloud, okay.
So let's go ahead and create that subclass of this guy, so
I'm just gonna do File > New, okay, > Cocoa Touch Class.
It's gonna be a subclass of our QandATableViewController,
okay. And we're gonna call it CloudQand, whoops,
QandATableViewController, okay?
Cuz it's basically just a QandATableViewController that
stores its question and answer on the cloud. All right, so
here it is. Let's go ahead and blast all this, just so
you can clearly see what new stuff we're adding here. So
there's our super class being a QandATableViewController.
Let's, of course, go to our storyboard and
drag out a Table View Controller, okay.
And we're gonna set its identity to be one of these
CloudQandATableViewControll- ers.
What's interesting about the QandATableViewController is,
you don't need any prototype cells at all.
It creates its prototype cells in code.
And so, if you're interested in how to do that for your
final project or whatever, you could take a look at that
QandATableViewController, actually,
you would wanna look at the TextTableViewController,
the superclass one for how you might have a table view that
creates its cells that way instead of using prototypes.
And you can see why it don't use prototypes,
because it's such a simple cell,
its just has a text view in there, that's it.
The entire cell is just a text view, nothing more.
So it didn't really need a prototype to do that,
and it makes it easier for subclasser too,
they don't have to worry about that. All right, so
we've got our thing here.
Let's also make sure that it's the Initial View Controller,
right here, where we have the arrow coming in. And in fact,
I'm gonna put this thing into a Navigation Controller, okay?
That way I can have titles on things and stuff like that.
Okay, so this is our UI to start. And
we're gonna start by just having a question up here in
this cloud TableViewController right here. So I'm gonna go to
the cloud TableViewController. Where did I put that?
Right here. I'm gonna take that out of Supporting Files,
actually. So I'm gonna go to the cloud TableViewController,
and I'm just gonna, in its viewDidLoad,
I'm just gonna give it a question. Okay, so,
super.viewDidLoad, just so you can see how this thing works.
So qanda = a QandA, and here's the constructor for it.
It takes a question, you know,
"What is your favorite color?" or something like that. And
the answer is ["Blue", "Black", "Red"],
okay, or however many we want, okay? So let's just run and
see what that looks like. We'll go ahead and run I think
we'll run this on the device, actually. Let's try that.
Okay, so this is an iPad, but it's running here in iPhone
Compatibility mode, I'm still sharing an iPad.
So here you go, what is your favorite color?
It shows to you, you can scroll up and
down and you can choose an answer, okay? Now,
that's because we're in answering mode, okay? But
if we go back to our code over here and say asking = oops,
asking = true, okay, and then run,
you'll get very similar UI. The only difference being,
we can edit it. We can add more answers and
move our answers around. Okay, so here we go.
Notice that we can reposition them, okay, so if we want one
answer to be after another, we could add another answer here,
maybe white. Okay, something like that. We can delete
an answer just by backspacing out of it. Gets rid of it.
Okay, we can change the question too if wanted. Okay,
so everyone understand what this QandATableViewController
we just inherited from does? That it. That's all it does.
Okay, now, it knows nothing about the cloud.
And what we're gonna make this Q&A thing here be
stored on the cloud. All right, so
now we're back in the CloudQandATableViewController.
And we want to make this thing work with the cloud. So
it's gonna have a different model than its superclass.
Its superclass's model is a question and answer, which is
good, but our model here is going to be a CKRecord, okay,
a CloudKit record.
So I'm gonna call this thing CKQandA,
okay, called that because it's CloudKit Q&A.
Actually, maybe we can even call it CloudKitQandARecord so
we're clear that it's a record in CloudKit. And
it's gonna be a CKRecord, is all. And of course,
if anyone sets it, just like with almost all of our MVC's,
when someone sets our model to something,
if it's public and we allow people to set it, when we
set it, we want to react to that. And what we want to do
when someone sets our record is call our superclass,
set up our superclass's model, right, that QandA. We're gonna
get the question and answer out of the record and put,
set it up in our superclass. So we'll just let the question
equal the record's, and remember that we access
the records just using dictionary-like notation.
So I'm gonna use one of those constants that I had there,
Attribute.Question. Okay?
That's over here, remember, in the CloudKit extensions.
So Cloud.Attribute.Question is this key, so that's gonna
be a key into my QandA entity right here. Okay, and notice
how I'm not going and creating this scheme anywhere first,
I'm just writing my code on the fly, and it's just gonna
automatically create these things in the database for
me as I go. Now, we also know that this ckQandARecord,
when you use this dictionary notation,
it always returns this type that you have to cast, right.
It returns a CKRecord type or something like that.
So I'm gonna have to say as a String, cuz I know
the question is a string. And by the way, if that's nil,
I'm just gonna use an empty string as my question, okay?
So that way my question's never nil here.
And then it's similar with the answers,
that's the QandARecord, using the attribute for
the answers, except for, that's not a string,
it's an array of strings. And if that's nil, then we'll
use an empty array. So now I've gotten my question and
my answers out of this record that was given to me.
Okay, this is didSet on my public API right here. So now
I'm gonna have my superclass qanda equal a QandA, okay,
where the question is that question and the answers is
that answers. Okay? Now, what about the asking,
okay, what about whether I'm asking or not?
Okay, this thing of whether it's gonna be editable or
not. Well, that depends on whether this record they just
gave me was created by me. If it was created by me, them I'm
clearly editing it. It was created by someone else,
then I'm just choosing it. So I'm just gonna say that that
is ckQandARecord.wasCreated, what did I call it,
wasCreatedByThisUser, okay? So I'm just using that thing
I showed you in that, that little extension over here,
okay? So we've got this record, now,
a couple of problems here, okay? One thing is right here.
Use of undeclared type CKRecord. Why is that? import
CloudKit. Okay? CloudKit is a different framework.
If you want to use it in any of your files,
you have to import CloudKit, okay? Still have an error
here. What's this? The old no initializers.
Why? Because this is never initialized. Okay, well,
this is kind of an interesting case, because I could just,
for example, make this be an optional.
Then it would start out nil, that's great, but really,
I don't want any external person to be giving me
an empty record, you know, a nil record. So,
I'm gonna do something kind of interesting here that you can
do when you want your public API to be non-optional but
you still going to allow,
internally, the thing to be optional or nil.
Okay, what I'm gonna do is, I'm gonna leave this public
one to be optional, non-optional, rather. And
I'm gonna turn it into a get and set, okay, a computed one.
Where it's going to be implementing its get and
set by using a private var _ckQandARecord, and this
one's going to be optional. Okay, it's gonna do all
the same things that it did, it's just gonna be optional.
And in the get and set here, the set here is just going to
set the ckQandARecord private one to be the new value.
Okay, this is always gonna be non-optional,
that's going to be great, that's gonna set it there. And
here, if someone tries to get the ckQandARecord,
okay I'm gonna check to see if my private one is nil.
And if it is, I'm gonna set my private one to just be a blank
one. Okay, and here I'm gonna use this Entity.QandA.
Okay, so I'm gonna create a blank one.
And then I can return _ckQandA unwrapped,
cuz I know I always at least create it.
So this is kind of a little tricky thing here to make sure
that it's always this way. And another good thing about this
is, sorry, you had a question? >> Could you use
a lazy initializer here? >> Yeah, so the question is,
can I use a lazy initializer here?
Like, could I have said ckQandARecord =
CKRecord whatever, or even a lazy one, I wouldn't even have
to be lazy. The reason I'm not doing that is the old problem
where didSet doesn't
get called with the initializer, right? And
I want didSet to always get called, and
this is gonna cause didSet to always get called.
So it's a little bit of a trick there. Okay?
All right, so we've got this all set up for
our public API here. What do we want to do next?
Well, let's go ahead and change our viewDidLoad,
instead of setting our superclass thing,
let's just test and make sure we're working. So
I'm gonna set my ckQandARecord equal to an empty record,
just as a test here. Okay? So we're just gonna do that.
I just wanna see if this is working. So let's run.
And it should come up an empty question, but
it should be editable, because I created this CKRecord.
Right? So here it is. It's empty, empty question.
I could type here, you know, I could say something, you know,
like, When, we'll just say When, okay. Answers, Today.
Maybe Never, okay.
And then Tomorrow. Okay, so I've created this question.
Now, as I edit all this stuff, of course,
none of this is going on the cloud yet.
And in fact, none of it's even going into the CKRecord.
It's all just being held in that Q and A, okay. So
the next step we need to do is to have this thing
write to the cloud. Now, when to write to the cloud is
the question here, okay? We could add a button,
maybe a bar button item up there that says,
Save to Cloud, okay? Or just Save or something like that.
So that, that would be one way of it. But I'm actually kind
of a fan of UIs that the user doesn't have to take extra
steps unnecessarily. So wouldn't it be cool if we just
saved this to the cloud every time someone finishes
editing one of these fields.
Now as soon as the keyboard goes away, any of these times,
boom, we'll just save whatever we got to the cloud.
Now we might also want another UI which is published,
so that it shows it to other users.
But for now users can see things in progress, okay,
just because we're starting out our app.
So that's what I'm gonna do, I'm gonna have it every time
that this first responder gets taken away from a text field,
I'm gonna have it update the cloud.
So how can we find out when a first responder's taken away
from the text view? We gonna use the text view's delegate,
it's almost identical to the text field delegate
that we talked about before. And our super classes, okay,
the QandATableViewController, right here.
It's super class is the text TableViewController and
the text TableViewController already and not surprisingly,
is a UITextViewDelegate. So it's already receiving
UITextViewDelegate message whenever any of its text
views are edited. Okay, so that's great. So all we need
to do here is implement a UITextViewDelegate, so
I'm gonna implement the one which is DidEndEditing.
Okay, TextViewDidEndEditing. Whoops,
not did change. DidEndEditing,
this one. Okay, and let my super class. He might well be
doing something there so, we'll let him do his thing.
And now what I'm going to do with just update the Cloud, so
I'm going to have some method iCloud update, okay?
And it's complaining here because I overrode this so
I need to say override. Okay, so this iCloud update is going
to take our Q&A, ship it up to the iCloud,
to the cloud kit database up there. So let's go ahead and
do that. That's private func iCloud update.
Okay, so what do we need to do, to write this thing,
to the cloud? It's actually really simple.
The first thing we're gonna do is get the stuff out of our
QnA into our record. Then we're gonna save our record,
okay? So let's do the first part of that first.
Which is let's take our ckQandARecord, and set,
for example, its Question, and
we'll set this question equal to be the Q&A question.
So we're just grabbing it out of our super
classes thing and similarly here the Q&A for
the answers equals qanda.answers.
One thing, I'd probably don't wanna be polluting the cloud
with empty question and answers.
So I'm gonna put a little if around this just to say.
if my qanda, qanda.question,
oops, question.isEmpty and
I'm also goinna make sure that my answers, Q and
A answers isn't empty either, okay?
So, in other words, if I don't have an empty question or
answer, then I'll go ahead and do this. Okay, so now that
I've updated this record. I need to save it to the cloud.
So I'm gonna actually have a different function for that.
ICloudSaveRecord I'm gonna call it.
I'm gonna pass my CKQandARecord along. Okay,
we're gonna have this little function that's going to save
things to the cloud. So, private func iCloudSaveRecord,
takes a recordToSave, which is a CKRecord. Okay,
now what's this guy gonna do? This one also surprisingly
straightforward, as you saw from the slides. One thing
is any time we're gonna save something into the Cloud,
we need a database to work with. So
I'm gonna say private let the database equal CKcontainer,
remember? Container, whoops, [LAUGH] CKcontainer,
defaultContainer public. So we're gonna put this in
the public cloud because I want everyone to
see everyone else's questions, okay?
So if I put it in the private database I'd only be able to
see my own questions, so this way I can see everybody's,
okay? So we got that. So I'm gonna ask the database here,
just to save this record. Okay, the record to save. And
here's the completion handler right here. And in this
completions handler, we have the saved record basically.
Which should be the same thing or nil and the error, okay?
And this is asynchronous. Okay, this closure is gonna
be called sometime later when this thing is saved.
Now, this is a demo so I don't have time for
us to go and analyze every realistic error that could
happen every single time we do something with the cloud.
But I'm gonna show you a few of them just so
you kind of get an idea how to handle errors, what kind of
errors will come along. So let's look at an interesting
error that might happen when you're saving a record, okay.
So this error code equals
CKErrorCode.ServerRecordChan- ged.
Okay, don't forget .rawValue at the end because we're
looking at this as an right here.
So what is this error? This error means we tried to save
a record but that record had already been saved newer
by someone else, okay. So now I've got old data that I'm
trying to write on top of somebody who wrote newer data.
Maybe it was one of my other devices. Maybe it's even me.
Maybe I'm writing so fast. I saved three of four records in
a row, okay. They all got queued up and
one of them got through the network faster than the other,
could be. This kind of approach of writing things and
just checking when you write them to see
if it's newer is called optimistic locking.
Okay, it's basically you don't check first before you write,
you just try to write and it's newer you fail. Okay?
So save record which is this convenous method on database,
really has no way to make it overwrite,
have an older thing overwrite a newer thing.
It's not even clear that's what I'd want here.
I probably do want the newer thing, to be what what gets
through. If I did wanna do do overwriting of newer things,
then I can use that whole
operation-based thing I was telling you about in
the slides. Much more complicated that this
convenience method but it can be done. But anyway for server
record change happens there is really nothing we can do or
we would want to do. So you know we can just ignore this,
okay. We just assume that the newer ones is what we wanted.
Okay, what are the kind of stuff going to happen for
writing here? How about, let's say if our error is not Nil.
Well in other words,
we got some other kinds of error. Let's check to see
if that error may be has a retry in there for us. Okay,
something we can go and retry what we' re doing. Okay? Now,
maybe why does that happen? Net, network let, latencies,
something like that. Some network problem that might
recover with a little bit of time, that kind of thing.
So, how do we do this? So, I am just going to call another
function to handle this. I am gonna call it retry after
error. It's goinna take the error whatever happened and
I am just going to give it a selector to call to retry.
Okay, and the selector here is going to be in this case since
we are saving record. I'm gonna have iCloud update,
okay, this thing up here that updates, try to do this again.
Okay? Now let's go and put this t retry in there and
we'll see what some of these errors that are.
So this is a private func retryAfterError,
takes an error, do an NSError.
And then it takes with selector. We'll have a nice
local name for that and this is a selector, okay.
So we have errors here, so what is this error. It says,
selector refers to
a method that does not expose to objective C. That's iCloud.
Now why is this iCloud update not exposed to objective C?
Well, it's because it's private, okay.
This is a class that inherits from in it' s objects, so
that's not the problem. The problem is that we have
a private method here. So we can expose it
either by making it not private or just saying OBJC.
That mean, hey, expose this to Objective-C run time. Okay?
Make sense? All right, here is now saying the call
to the method iCloud update requires explicit self, okay?
So that it knows, in our self because we happen to be
in a closure right here, okay? All references to
things in our selves Have to be explicit. Okay, so
that's good. All right, now, retry after or how we gonna
retry after. Well, if we can't get that retry interval magic
out of the error structure then we cannot do it so
that's the first thing we're gonna do.
We're gonna say if we can let retry interval
equal the errors. User info, okay so
user info is this dictionary that comes with an error that
gives you kind of interesting info.
And, the thing we want is ck error,
retry after key, okay? So
that should be an ns time interval. So if we're able to
get that retry interval, then hey, let's go ahead and retry.
And how are we going to retry here? Well I'm just going to
do an NSTimer, scheduled timer with time interval,
I want this one, let's go ahead and make this
have different lines here so you can see little better what
we're doing with the timer. Okay, so the time interval
here is that retry interval that we got out of the error.
The target is going to be our self.
The selector is the selector we passed on Here, okay?
User info, eh, we don't have any, we're just retrying, so
we don't have any extra data, and it does not repeat. Okay,
now the problem here we gotta be careful of,
we're calling retry after error in this closure,
which is executing off the main thread. Okay, so
we cannot do NSTimers on other threads. So
we need to dispatc_async, to the main queue.
Dispatc_Ge_mai_queue.
We'll do this, like that. Okay,
you got that? Cool, all right so
that's just a couple of the errors that we can do.
If it succeeds, we actually don't need to do anything.
It saved it, we're happy,
we can just move on, okay. All right, so let's try and
run this, let's just see if it happens,
let's see if it can save this thing to the database. So
I'm gonna run, all right, here we crashed,
now why'd we crash? The first place I'm always gonna
look is the console down here. So let's go take a look at
the console and see if it has a reason that it crashed and
it does have a reason. And the reason is,
this application is missing the required entitlement for
iCloud services.
So this is that thing I was telling you about.
We have to go enable iCloud,
all right. Because iCloud is server technology. Gee,
things are gonna have to be created on a server side for
this app, etcetera. So they don't want to create that for
every app, only for apps that are actually gonna use it.
So how do we do that? We go up here, okay, to our inspector,
inspect our project settings here and
we'll go to capabilities.
And we click iCloud here, okay? So you have to make sure
you pick a team, okay, cuz it needs to know who you are so
we can set up this iCloud stuff for you, okay?
Your, account, your developer account up there. So
here we have iCloud enabled, we are going to pick cloud kit
as that's the service that we want, we can pick these other
ones as well but we're going to focus on CloudKit today.
And we'll be looking at the dashboard in a little bit,
actually let's go take a look at our dashboard now.
Once your at dashboard, of course you have to log in.
Here we are, nothing has been created yet and
that's because we haven't done any iCloud where we have
tried to create any entities, okay? All right, so
now that we've done that. Now let's go back and
run, and do that. And actually create some entities. So let's
get our code back up here so you can see that. And run.
All right. So here we go. Blank question and answer.
Let's go ahead a put a question answer here again,
let's try how about what is your
favorite team? Okay,
we'll say, maybe the Sharks. Whoops. Sharks,
or maybe the Warriors, or maybe it's the Giants. Okay,
there are a lot of teams to choose from in the Bay area.
All right? So hopefully this is creating on the server
because remember every time we went to a new field,
it should be riding something up to the Cloud.
So let's go back and take a look at our dashboard here, so
let's reload, Here it is, look at that,
QandA entity got created with answers and questions.
So that's great. So that's the entity side of it.
And we can actually look at the data,
not just the entity, but the data that's been stored by
going down here to this Default Zone.
Now, we'll notice when we try to look in here for
things, it says, records can't be shown because there's no
index on the Record ID field. So you can't look at things
that aren't indexed. And so let me show you where that is.
If you go back here you see metadata indexes,
record ID not being indexed. Same thing created by.
In fact I want both of those to be searchable.
I need created by so I know which Q&As were created by me,
and I want record ID so
I can go find all the ones out there. And
you can actually see here I'm gonna go ahead and save this.
I'll show you something real quick here. So
I've changed this to have these indexes.
Now I can go to the default zone. It can find things and
sure enough. What is your favorite team? Sharks and
Warriors. I guess we didn't save the Giants one here. When
we reload, we'll see that. One thing about the car I
wanted to show you the costs thing, which is down here.
If you look at uhs where is that uhs
usage? If you look at usage right here it is going to show
you how much you using how many active users you have,
how many request per second, how much transfers you
are doing of large files. How much storage you're using. All
that stuff. And these things if you go above these lines,
start costing you money. See these red lines.
Okay, the limits? Usage? So, I'm way, way below everything.
[LAUGH] Obviously. But, you know.
So, this is basically how you get charged for it, okay?
That good? All right. So we've got our nice database is being
loaded up, it's excellent, okay? The next thing we're
gonna do in our UI here is we are going to have another
view controller that has a list of all the question,
the Q&A's that are in the database, okay?
That we can choose from, and take a look at the Q&A's Okay,
so it's just gonna be a simple table view with a list of
the QNAs. All right, so how we gonna do that,
we gonna have to create a new MVC. So lets go ahead and
do that, go file, new, go touch, this one is just going
to be a regular UI table view controller,
am gonna call it my AllQandAsTableViewController,
cuz that's what it's gonna do.
It's gonna be the table view controller, shows all my Q and
As in it, okay? And we'll put it in the same place
as usual here. Here's all Q and As. Let's go ahead and
get rid of all of this stuff. Okay,
so as always, what's gonna be the model of our new MVC?
Well, it shows all Q and A's, so that's gonna be my model,
all the Q and A's. And that's just going to be an array of
CKRecord, okay. And of course, when that changes,
if someone changes that array of records, then I'm going to
have the table view reload its data. Hopefully you're all
familiar with that after Smashtag experiences. Okay, so
it's as simple as that. So how do we get all these Q and A's?
Import CloudKit. How do we get them all? Well,
in my view, let's do it in viewWillAppear, okay,
when I know I'm gonna come on screen. I'm
going to call some method to fetchAllQandAs, okay, and
that's gonna go out to CloudKit and find them all. So
that's private method called fetchAllQAndAs.
Oops. Okay, and how's this thing gonna work? Well,
this is gonna turn out to be very, very simple. Of course,
we need our database here, so let's get that.
CKContainer.defaultContainer, again, we're looking in
the public database there. All right, we have a database. So
fetching all the QandAs really just requires doing a CKQuery.
You remember that from the slide CKQuery?
So for CKQuery, we need a predicate, okay?
And since I'm getting all of the QandA's,
every single one, I'm not searching for anything,
I'm gonna use the predicate TRUEPREDICATE. Okay, this
is a special predicate that means, get them all. Okay,
remember, in Core Data, we have nil means get them all,
but here, you can't have predicate be nil, so
TRUEPREDICATE. It means get them all. Okay? Next,
we can just create the query itself. That's a CKQuery,
okay? And we'll get its initializer here. So it
just wants to know what kind of things are you querying.
It's just like when you're doing NSFetchRequest in
Core Data. You can only query one kind of thing at a time,
one entity at a time. So here we're gonna have Cloud.Entity,
Entity.QandA, cuz that's what we're searching for,
these QandA entities, entities.
And here's the predicate we're gonna use. Now,
one thing I forgot to show you in the slides, very important,
is sorting. Just like in NSFetchRequest, you can
do this here as well. I can say query.sortDescriptors, and
I can specify how I want to sort
this query that I'm doing. Okay? So I'll have a sort,
we'll sort this by the name of the,
by the question name, okay. So
key is Cloud.Attribute.Question, and
we'll have it be ascending. Okay, and of course,
this is an array just like it is with fetch request,
you can search last name first, then by first name,
et cetera. Okay, so that's it. We've created our carry,
query, how we wanna sort it, what the predicate is.
Now we just ask the database to perform this query.
Okay? And the query is query. Now, this inZoneWithID,
I told you that there's these zones, that are like subareas
of databases. By dividing your database into zone,
you can make your queries a lot more efficient.
You can see why already, if I only am searching a small part
of my database, it makes it a lot faster to search.
Here we're not using zones, okay, so we're just
putting nil as our zone. But if you have a huge data set,
you can look into the zones feature. Okay, so here's my
closure, when the results come back sometime later.
This is the array of records that it found with that query.
And here's the error if any that it found. Okay? Now,
what am I gonna do with these records that came back? Well,
if the records is not nil, in other words,
if it found any records, then I just need to set my
allQandAs equal to those records. All right?
But be careful. This is not happening on the main queue.
So, if we're gonna do this, which is gonna cause this,
reloadData to happen, means we have to dispatc_async onto
the main queue. Okay?
So don't forget that dispatching back to the main
queue when you're gonna do UI stuff as a response. Okay? So
that's it. Okay, super easy.
The only thing we have left to do in this TableViewController
is our UITableViewDataSource. So
let's mark UITableViewDataSource.
Okay, we don't have any sections in this table, okay,
it's just all just one big section. The number of rows,
okay, let's do the number of rows.
That's just the number of things in our array,
AllQandAs.count. That's how many rows we have, obviously.
And then we also obviously need cellForRowAtIndexPath.
cellForRowAtIndexPath. So cellForRowAtIndexPath, which
we have, well, here, let's make it a little wider here.
Okay, cellForRowAtIndexPath.
I'm gonna get the cell by using the tableViews.dequeue,
whoops, view's dequeue with identifier.
So what identifier should we use? Let's say a QandA Cell.
So let's go back to our storyboard. And
have the cells of this. First of all, let's put our table
view in here. How about that? So here's a table view.
This is gonna be in between these two. All right.
This one is going to be the root view controller, and we
are going to be segueing from this one to this one which
shows them. Let's make sure we set our identity of this to be
our new allQandAs table here. Here's our cells right here.
So these cells, we're gonna have them be basic style,
cuz they just have the question.
We're just gonna put the question, so
they don't have any subtitle.
They don't need any custom stuff. And
the identifier is the QandA Cell. Okay,
hey, while were here, let's go ahead do the segues for this.
It's really simple. We're gonna segue from these rows.
Okay, anytime someone clicks on these rows,
we're gonna segue over to here and do a show segue.
And we also want to be able to create new questions as well,
right? We're gonna click on questions we got,
but we want to create new ones.
So I'm gonna do that with some UI in here.
I'm gonna create a Bar Button Item right here. And
I'll use the standard plus one, which is add, okay,
cuz we're gonna add something, this is plus.
And then we're just gonna Ctrl+drag from here and
make that show. Okay, so this is gonna do a segue, if fact,
they can do the same segue,
cuz they pretty much do the same thing.
They show a Q and A, it's just,
one of them shows whatever row is selected and
the other one creates a new one. So
we'll call this Show QandA. That's a good name for
that. And we'll call this one also Show QandA. Now,
in our prepare for segue, we're gonna have to be,
do a little bit different thing, in those two cases,
but that's basically what we're doing. Okay? So
let's go back to our code here. allQandAs.
So here's our cell index path there. Let's
just have our cell's textLabel?.text equal what?
allQandAs sub indexPath.row.
That's giving me the CKRecord. Now, out of that CKRecord,
I've gotta get the Cloud.Attribute.Question,
cuz that's what I'm gonna show,
inside that row. And of course,
we know that comes back as a CKRecord value, so
I have to say, as a String. Okay? And then we will
return the cell. Okay? Also super simple.
All right, make sense? And now let's prepare for segue.
So that's mark our Navigation. Prepare for
segue. This is also gonna be pretty straightforward. First,
we're gonna see if the identifier is our
Show QandA. If it is, let's get that MVC.
So we'll say, if we can let the cloud Q and, QandA,
oops, CloudKit Q and A table view controller equal our
segue's destinationViewController as
a CloudQandATableViewController,
okay, so we're segueing into one of those, so
that better be on the other end. If that's true,
then we need the cell, if we're segueing from a row,
we need the cell, so let's try that. So if we can let cell
equal the sender as a UITableViewCell, okay,
hopefully you guys are used to doing this, again, from your
homework assignment. And then we can let the indexPath equal
the tableView's method cell for, or sorry, index path,
PathForCell, this cell.
Okay, so here is kind of a one-liner that gets the index
path of the row that was chosen. And if that works,
then we can just say that the CloudQandA, oops,
I guess I called it ckQandATVC,
we'll set its public API, which is ckQandARecord,
okay, equal to allQandAs sub indexPath.row.
All right? That's what's, that's the record that
was chosen there, obviously. If we can't get the cell,
if we can't get the table view cell, that must be because we
pressed the + button, right? Because the plus button's not
a row in a table. So in that case,
I'm just going to set the ckQandARecord equal to a new
record, because that's what we want. Creating a new
thing here, so that's Cloud.Entity.QandA.
Okay, everyone understand that prepareForSegue?
Okay, so let's do that.
All right, so here's it showing all the ones, and
look, it's even showing, what is your favorite team,
that we already had from before.
I'm gonna touch on that, and it's not showing it to us.
Okay. Why is it not showing it to us? When we click on this,
it shows a blank one. Why does it show a blank one?
Because over here, in our CloudTableViewController,
look what we do in our viewDidLoad.
No! We always set the record to be nil.
So, let's get rid of that. And allow the segue to actually
set it. That's a tricky little bug.
Okay, so now, when we click on this,
we get to see the question out of the database. Okay? And
we can hit + and create a new one,
maybe like, what is your
favorite Stanford class?
Okay, and we'll have some answers here,
how about CS193p, or if not that,
how about iOS development. Okay,
that's a great class too. And how about the iPhone and
iPad programming course.
You can pick whatever Stanford class you'd like.
Okay? So that, when we go back now, it's gonna ask for all of
those Q&As and it's gonna show that one as well. Okay? So
that you can see, very little code we had to write here to
have it so that we're creating these things and editing them.
What about deleting them? Okay? What if I said, eh,
I don't want this one anymore, I wanna delete it.
What would be really cool is if I could just swipe on this
to delete. You've seen that in table views, right?
Where you can swipe to delete, okay? How do we do swipe,
swipe to delete? We have never covered that in class.
This is a great opportunity to do that.
So if you want to do swipe to delete,
you have to implement two of your UITableViewDataSource
methods. One is, you have to answer whether a row
can be deleted or not. Okay? That one is called
canEditRowAtIndexPath. Okay, canEditRowAtIndexPath.
Now, in our case, as long as we created this, then we can
allow it to delete it, but if we didn't create it, we can't.
So here I'm gonna return all Q&As at the indexPath.row was
created by this user. So if it was created by this user,
then I'll allow you to delete it. Okay? The other method you
need is the thing that actually commits the delete,
that does the delete. That's called commitEditingStyle.
Okay, commitEditingStyle right here,
TableView.commitEditingStyle. And so here,
there's actually two editing styles that you can have.
One is deleting and one is inserting.
Well, we do our inserting with that plus, so we don't need
the inserting style there. We only want the deleting, so
I'm gonna say, if the editingStyle == .Delete.
Okay, so if the person wants to delete my row or whatever,
then all I need to do is delete it from the table. But
I also wanna delete it from the database as well, right,
both of those. So what's that look like? So let's say,
if we're deleting, then I'm gonna let the record to delete
equal, my allQandAs indexPath.row.
Okay. Then I'm gonna save the database. Please delete this
record with an ID, and the ID is the record's recordID,
okay. Completion handler here to handle errors.
This is the deleted record, if it happened,
or error if it didn't. And so, handle errors. I'm, again,
short on time. So we're not going to do that. And
in either case, even if it didn't, you know,
even if it failed to delete, I'm still gonna go ahead and
delete it out of allQandAs. So to do that, I just say
allQandAs.removeAtIndex the indexPath.row.
Okay, so it's just gonna delete it from the thing. Now,
hopefully, this was successful and it won't come back later,
but it's gonna delete here. So let's take a look at this.
All right, so we created both of these, so
I can swipe to delete, right, either one I wanted.
So let's delete, let's delete this one.
It's gone. Okay, and we can make sure it actually deleted
it in the database by going away and coming back,
cuz it reloads when it does that. It didn't come back, so
it actually deleted that from the database.
We could also go over and look in our database right here,
in our default zone. And we can see, we only have,
what is your favorite team. We could reload just to be 100%
sure. Default zone. Sure enough, we only have,
what is your favorite team? It deleted it. Okay? All right,
so that's great. All right. One bad thing about our UI,
though is, you see this nice little table view? If I'm just
sitting here and someone else creates something, it doesn't
show me. So let's go over here on iPhone simulator here,
and I'm gonna create a new one.
I'm gonna see what happens. Okay, so it's showing,
what is your favorite team? So I'll create a new one here,
I'll say, what is your favorite color?
That's our kind of our favorite one. Red and Blue.
And black, okay? Now, I've created this but it's not
showing up over here, right? And it's not showing up there
because I'm not subscribing to that change. I'm not watching
the database. Now, if I go away from this and come back,
it is gonna show it. Because when we viewWillAppear,
we reload from the database. But it's really annoying for
the user to always to have to go away and
come back to the see the latest, thing. So,
we need to do a subscription, okay? Perfect opportunity to
do a subscription. So let's do that.
So, how do we do the subscription? Pretty simple,
it's two parts really, three parts to doing it.
The first one is we need to actually subscribe.
So let's do the subscription first.
I'll even put this in a little MARK: Subscription place here.
One thing is we need to have an ID for our subscription.
So, I'm gonna say subscriptionID.
And this is just an English language description of what
we're gonna subscribe to. And so I'm gonna say,
we're gonna get All QandA Creations and Deletions.
And this has gotta uniquely identify this subscription in
the database and
I think that pretty uniquely identifies what we're doing
here. So, let me create a private func here
called iCloudSubscribeToQandAs, okay?
And this thing is going to do the subscription. So
when you do a subscription you need a predicate that says,
what you're looking for, okay?
What you're trying to find out when it changes. So again,
we're gonna use pretty much the same one we used before
which is true predicate, TRUEPREDICATE, yeah.
Because, we are looking for any additions or
deletions of Q and A, not, not just the ones we created, or
not just ones with certain questions but
any of them, so
that's why we're using the same predicate. And then,
we just create the subscription. Okay,
CKSubscription. And, it's, this one right here.
And let's go ahead and put this on separate lines,
as I am wont to do when there are lots of arguments so
you can see what's going on, okay? So the recordType is,
what kind of thing we're watching, and of course here,
we are watching Entity.QandA. That's what we're looking for
searches for. predicate: is our predicate, okay.
subscriptionID: is our subscriptionID.
I'm putting self in there just to emphasize that
it's my subscription ID,
okay? And then, the subscription options: are what
kind of changes are we looking for? So we want ones that
fire when one's created, and we also want to find out when
one's deleted. Cuz we're showing a list of the suf,
of the Q and As, so we don't care if one gets
updated. Although, we might care if it's updated because
maybe it changed the question and
now the list should change there.
But I'm just gonna do creation and deletion here, to show you
that. Now, one thing here that I'm not gonna do, but
that you can do here, is there is a notification info
argument, or, var on subscription that you can use
to say, what happens when the push notification comes, when
this changes. Does it put up an alert? Does it put a badge?
Does it increase the badge, right? On your app icon, okay?
Does it play a sound? Bloop, things arrived. Okay, you can
set that here. I'm gonna have none of those things happening
I'm just going to behind the scenes fix up the table.
I'm not gonna put any alerts up or whatever.
But I just wanna let you know, you can do that here, okay?
So, we got that, so let's just go to our database and
tell it to save this subscription, okay.
Save our subscription with our completion handler right here,
okay. Here is the savedSubscription,
if it succeeded, and here's an error if not.
I'm gonna take a second to show you an error here because
there's a common one that happens. error?.code ==
CKErrorCode.ServerRejectedReq- uest,
okay? And what happens here sometimes is,
if this subscription by its unique name is already on
the server, then it will reject your request, okay?
So, this usually means that you ran your program,
you were developing, you, this code ran,
and then you hit stop in the debugger, okay?
It killed your app. And then you ran it again, and
it tried to do it, it's still there. Okay, the subscriptions
live forever, until you actually remove them, okay?
So quitting your app has no effect on the subscriptions.
So, this is one where usually you'll ignore that
ServerRejectedRequest figuring eh, somehow,
this thing got got already put in there. That's fine,
we'll just use it, okay, it'll continue to work just fine.
Okay and else, you know, if there's some error,
other kind of error, you know,
report that error or whatever you feel like you need to do.
Okay, so that's it, that's all that's necessary to get iCloud
to start, you know, sending us push notifications when,
any of these creations and deletions happen to any Q and
A. Now, one thing is we're subscribing here.
We also are probably want to unsubscribed and
when would we want to do those two things.
So I'm gonna have an unsubscribe as well,
Unsubscribe. And when do we wanna do this?
Probably, we'll want to, when viewWillAppear,
we wanna subscribe and when viewDisappears,
we unsubscribe. Okay, because it's no use sending these push
notifications if we're not even on screen.
Okay, especially since when we reappear we reload ourselves
anyway. Okay, so there's no reason to do that. So,
in viewWillAppear right here,
I'm gonna say, iCloudSubscribeToQandAs,
and in viewDidDisappear, I'm gonna say,
iCloudUnsubscribe, okay? Now,
iCloudUnsubscribe, what do we need to do to unsubscribe?
Very easy, I'm just gonna say to my database, please
deleteSubscriptionWithID, my subscriptionID,
okay? Completion handler to handle errors here. So
this is, the subscription that we tried to delete.
There's an error. We will not handle errors cuz we're
running out of time. Handle it, okay? So, we'll just
delete those, descriptions there and that's it. Okay, so
now we've set up our table here to get those updates but
of course, we have to be able to receive push notifications
for this to work, okay? And we do that, over in our app
delegate. So lets go back to our app delegate right here,
and look at that code that we covered in lecture.
One, in did finish launching with options,
we need to register for
the kinds of notifications
we're willing to present to our user, okay?
And the user actually can choose in settings,
the general settings, whether they want alerts or badges or
sounds or whatever, but we're going to explain here
which ones we think we want to give them, okay? So,
we do that by just creating the settings, by that's
a UIUserNotificationSettings, and for
the types that we want. And this can be like alerts,
badges, sounds, okay? And I'll go ahead and register for
all of them, although, I'm not gonna use any of them cuz I,
that subscription.notification info, remember that?
I didn't put that line in, so it's not gonna do any of these
things. But, I, I'm gonna tell the user, hey, I wanna do all
these things cuz maybe some of my other push notifications
wanted to do it or whatever. But I wouldn't sign up for
these actually if you're not gonna use them cuz it just
creates unnecessary stuff for your user, all right?
So there's the settings, so now I have to register
those settings, so I just say application.registerUserNotif-
icationSettings, those settings.
And now, I need to turn on push notifications, okay?
registerForRemoteNotificati- ons, okay?
Push notifications are called remote notifications, okay?
Boom, so now I've turned on push notifications,
they're gonna start coming, okay?
From Cloudkit, or whatever else ones that I set up.
So now I have to handle them when they arrive, and I do
that with this thing called the remote notification,
didReceiveRemoteNotification, okay?
A remote notification came in, what am I gonna do with it?
Well, I'm gonna assume that it's a CloudKit one here.
I don't have any other ones that I'm expecting, so
that should be fine. If I had other ones,
I'd have to do more code here. But I'm just gonna say,
if I can, or actually, I mean, yeah, if I'm gonna let CQ,
ckqn, that's short for CloudKit query notification,
equals CKQueryNotification, CKQueryNotification,
okay, that's not completing because, import CloudKit.
Okay, so I'm gonna create a query notification.
The only way to create one of these things is to hand
the dictionary that comes with the push notification off to
this constructor, okay, this initializer.
So I'm gonna give it that.
One thing that's unfortunate about that is that it wants
that to be a dictionary where Strings are the keys and
NSObjects are the values,
instead of NSObjects as the keys, AnyObject as the value.
Okay? So, you just have to do this. All right, so
I've got my query notification that came from CloudKit.
Awesome. Now I need to hand it out to all my view controllers
that might be interested. And as we said in lecture,
we're gonna do this with a radio station. Okay, so
let's create a radio station. notification = NSNotification,
all right, we're gonna use this one right here. Again,
I will help you out a little bit. See what's going on.
All right, so name is the name of the radio station, and
as I told you, in that CloudKit extensions,
I created something for that. So I called that
CloudKitNotifications.notific- ation,
what did I call it? So I have to go back and look here.
Supporting Files, extension, CloudKitNotification.
NotificationReceived. That's the name of my radio station,
NotificationReceived. Sorry.
NotificationReceived. Okay, so that's the name. AnyObject,
this object is the sender. Ha, that's self,
that's my AppDelegate. Doesn't really matter too much,
cuz I'm not gonna look at it in the other end. And
then the userInfo, I need to pass this ckqn on.
So I'm gonna create a little dictionary on the fly here.
And the key is gonna be my CloudKitNotifications.Notific-
ationKey. And the value is gonna be that ckqn. Okay?
So this is the thing I'm gonna pass out onto, this is
Received, this is the thing I'm gonna pass out on my radio
station. So let's go ahead and broadcast it by saying
NSNotificationCenter.defaultC- enter, post this notification,
that means broadcast on this radio station.
Okay, now everybody who is signed up to listen is going
to get this push notification forwarded onto them. Okay?
So now let's go back and sign up over here to get that.
And I'm gonna do it in my subscribe,
when I subscribe to the Q and A's, I'm gonna then go and
sign up for that radio station so I can hear the results. And
to do that, I need that little, cookie. So
private var, we'll call it cloudKitObserver. It's gonna
be an NSObjectProtocol optional right there.
Okay, I'm gonna say cloudKitObserver = and
I'm just gonna ask the notification center if I can
please listen to that radio station by saying,
addObserverForName. It's this one. Okay, again.
I'd love if there was a nice little single key to do that
for me. So here's the radio station that I wanna listen
to, which is CloudKitNotifications.Notific-
ationReceived, that's the name of the radio station.
AnyObject, I don't care. And if anybody sends me that, I'm
gonna listen, okay? I could put the AppDelegate here, but
I'm just gonna say anybody. And I'm gonna do some UI here,
so I'd better say [INAUDIBLE] NSOperationQueue.mainQueue,
okay, send me this on the main queue. And
then here's the block, okay? This argument is
the notification that's coming along in the radio station.
And I need to get the ck, ckqn out of the user info
in that notification. Okay, so what does that look like?
Actually, I'm gonna do all that in a different method.
I'm gonna have iCloudHandleSubscriptionNotif-
ication, and I'm just gonna pass ckqn on to that.
So the cq, ckqn here, we can say,
if we can let ckqn equal the notification's userInfo,
which might be nil, you have to be careful about that,
and I'm gonna get the CloudKit notification key here,
notification's NotificationKey, okay.
And that better be a CKQuery notification, or
I don't know what to do with it,
okay? So if I can get that out of the little radio station
broadcast, then I'm gonna handle it. Okay, so
how do I handle it? private func this thing,
okay. And, there, we have a syntax
error right here, this should be NotificationKey,
NotificationKey. So handling it is pretty simple,
actually. First, when handling it, I'm gonna make sure that
this is for me. I'm gonna look at the subscription,
sorry, ckqn is a CKQueryNotification.
Okay, I'm gonna make sure that this thing is for me,
to make sure its subscription ID equals my subscription ID.
Because, remember, you might have lots of different view
controllers getting push notifications from CloudKit,
okay, doing different things. So here I want to make sure
it's this one that I'm getting the answer back from.
All right, so now that I have that, I'm just gonna get
the record that changed, okay, the recordID that changed
is ckqn.recordID, okay, so hopefully some record changed,
deleted or created here, otherwise I wouldn't be here.
I can also find out what changed. So I can say,
what is the reason that I got this notification? And
one reason could be because a record
was created. Another reason might be cuz a record was
deleted, okay? Otherwise, I don't care,
cuz I only handle creations and deletions,
all right? Let's do deletion first. It's a pretty easy one.
Okay, so what happens, if something was deleted? Well,
I'm just gonna dispatc_async back the the main queue and
remove it from my all QAs thing. So
dispatc_ge_mai_queue. And I'm just gonna say,
self.allQandAs equals self.allQandAs,
and I'm just gonna filter out any records
where the $0.recordID does not equal
this recordID that was just deleted.
Okay, so filter goes through all the things in the array,
$0 is each thing in the array,
I'm gonna get the recordID of the thing that's in there.
And if it's not equal to the recordID,
then I'm gonna filter it, if it is equal to the record ID,
then it's not gonna get through the filter.
Everybody got that? Super simple. Created,
slightly more difficult, although only slightly.
So, here, I'm gonna check if I have a record,
if the record okay, let's, first of all,
we have the record ID here. To show this record in our,
in our table, we actually need the record,
not the record ID.
By the way, it is possible in our subscription to have said,
hey when you give this thing, also give me the question.
In other words, you can ask for certain fields so
that I don't have to do what I'm doing right now,
which is I'm going back to my database and
fetching that record. Database. fetchRecordWithID.
Which is kind of unfortunate that I have this record ID and
I'm having to turn around and go back and fetch it.
So, you don't have to do that if you,
in your description say just give me
that right off the bat, okay? You just specify which fields
you want. Okay. So here's the record coming back, hopefully,
not nil, and here's the error. Okay. So, if the record
is not nil, I got it back. Now I need to add it to my Q and
As, now, a slight complication here is when I put it in my
list of Q and As, I obviously need to sort it. Because my
list of Q and As was sorted by the database, but now I'm
getting this one record that I have to put in the list.
So, I have to do sorting.
So, I'll show you a little bit how to do, ahh,
sorting in here. Ahh, so, I'm gonna dispatc_async back to
the main queue. Okay.
And on here, I'm gonna say self.allQandAs, okay?
Get ready for this, equals the self.allQandAs we got so far,
plus this record. Okay. So now, this is the new thing
with it appended on to the end, but the end is no good so
I'm gonna sort. Okay? And when I sort, sort is
gonna pass me dollar zero and dollar one. And I have to say,
if dollar zero is less than or eq, or greater than dollar
one. And that's how it's gonna sort everything. So, let's go
ahead and return here. Dollar zero, which is a record,
a ck record, so I'm gonna get the, Cloud.Attribute.Question,
cuz I'm comparing the questions, quest- question,
all right. But of course, I have to do it as a string,
and I'm gonna see if that's less than $1,
Cloud.Attribute.Question, also as a String.
Okay. So, this is nice but
this is really messy code, it looks absolutely awesome,
awful here. Wouldn't it be cool if in,
like we had in core data,
where we could have the subclass and
we just use vars for these things? Well,
we can't quite do that, but watch this little trick.
I'm going to go back to my supporting files,
this CloudKit extensions thing that I did over here, okay?
And I'm going to do this extension to CKRecord
var question is a String, okay. I'm gonna return self
sub Cloud.Attribute.Question as a String. And
in fact, I want this to not be an optional. So I'm gonna say,
??, empty. So, you see I've added a var question,
to CkRecord that returns this thing.
So now back in my other code over here, all this gunk just
becomes .question. Okay, get rid of all this,
.question. Okay, looks a lot nicer, doesn't it, okay?
And in fact, we could use this .question in other places,
like down here, in cell for row at indexPath,
we do the same. A big mess right here, ,question.
Okay. Now, okay, all your attributes would have to
be unique across all of your entities or you would have to
start putting the entity names somehow, in, in this name in
this bar, but you know, something to consider,
cleans up your code quite a bit.
All right. Everyone, make sense what I did right there?
By the way, if this record couldn't be fetched,
then I'm kind of like, what the heck am I gonna do here?
So, I might wanna do something here like,
go reload my whole table, you know, do a fetch all q and
a's, call fetch, dispatch, async, and all that, but
I'm not gonna do it cuz we're out of time. Ahm, but, that's,
I might want to react to this error somehow here. Okay?
All right, so let's go back and
let's run it on iPhone. And we'll run it on our device.
All right. Okay. So let's go and create a new one here.
Let's try, how do you greet people?
And the answer is you say Hello, or maybe you say Aloha,
and you can see as soon as I typed enough to get this thing
to upload, it appeared here because it got noti, notified
via the push notification. And in fact, I can look at it,
let's see how do you greet people? Here we got hello,
the Aloha has not even, been uploaded yet, so
let's go ahead and hit the Aloha, then we get the Aloha.
Okay? And same thing with delete, if we go back here and
say, well we don't want this to greet people,
hit delete. And it deleted on our iPhone,
we don't have to wait back and forth. Okay,
I will see you next time. >> For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.