[MUSIC]
Stanford University. >> Okay, well,
welcome to Lecture 17 of Stanford CS193P
spring of 2016. This is our penultimate lecture that
actually has content. Next week we have Memorial Day, and
then we'll have our alternate final on Wednesday.
So what are we gonna talk about today?
Today we're gonna talk about segues, okay?
We've talked a lot about segues, but
there's still quite a few more segues to be talked about. And
then we're gonna talk about core location and MapKit,
which is kind of where is the device in the world. And then
I'm gonna do a demo, I'll do as much as the demo as I can,
and we'll just continue it on Wednesday.
The demo's gonna be about maps and segues, obviously,
that's what we're talking about today. All right? So
let's dive right in here to segues.
The first segue I'm gonna talk about is the modal segue. So,
this modal segue is the segue to an MVC that is gonna
completely take over your screen, okay?
You are fully responsible if you put a modal segue up for
providing a way for a user to get out of it, okay.
Because that MVC is completely in control.
This kind of UI should be used with care, okay, because you
really are locking down the UI, there's nothing else
the user can do. They can't. If they change their mind,
they can't go to another tab cuz it's not a tab bar thing.
They can't just hit back in a navigation controller,
they can't go to the other side of their split view or
whatever. They're pretty much stuck here until you let them,
out of it. And so, I don't even show you this until late
in the quarter because
I really don't want you to think of this as a go to way
to present an MVC on screen, okay? But it does have its
uses, okay? Here's an example, perhaps. Okay,
this is a contacts app, or an app that has contacts in it.
And we're showing the contacts and
the little plus button in the corner here, let's say that,
that button's going to allow us to enter a new contact.
Now, you could argue if the user has chosen to enter a new
contact. They don't wanna do anything else except for
that right now, and so
it's okay to present this adding contact view controller
modally. Modally just means in a mode where you can't
do anything else but this. Yeah,
one could argue there might be other ways to do this,
but let's, let's say that we're gonna do it this way.
So we tap on this plus sign, and from the bottom slides up
this new MVC. Now, this new MVC is completely controlling
the screen. It doesn't have a back button that cancel button
that you see right there. Is a button that this MVC is
putting in that bar, okay, it happens to cancel and
not add a new contact in this case.
Cuz it's not a push segue, it's a modal segue,
different kind of segue. And the thing about modal, as you
can actually have embedded modal inside modal, okay? So,
for example here, I am adding my contact, let's say now,
I wanna choose the photo for my contact, okay?
That's, also going to put up a modal MVC to get that. So
I click on that, another MVC slides off in the bottom so
now, I have two modal ones.
And you might think of this as a little bit like,
navigation control but
they're on a stack, but that's really not the way it is.
It's just the ad contact MVC took over the entire world and
then, it gave it to the photos one and it completely took
over the world. And until it's dismissed,
the other ones don't even really matter,
okay. Now, again notice no back button here. Also notice
by the way that cancel button has moved over from the right,
whereas on previous MVC had it on the left.
I'm not a big fun of this kind of UI, by the way.
I think, things like cancel,
if they're conceptually the same thing in two MVCs.
Especially, two MVCs that appear back to back like this,
should probably be in the same place.
So I would have put the cancel buttons both on the left here.
But whatever app this is or from where these contacts
came from, I decided to do that. But in any case,
no back button here. Right? Make sense? Okay,
so, let's cancel this and we'll see what happens to this
modal MVC. This cancel is a way to get out of it.
And when we cancel it,
of course, it slides back out. And the other MVC is still
there. Okay? Nothing has changed. And here, of course,
if we cancel this one, then we'll go back to where we were
before. And this MVC goes away. So that's modal, right?
You press the MVC. It lives, it does whatever it does.
It completely takes over the app and then somehow,
you press something to get out of it. Cancel or done, or
whatever, but that's totally up to that MVC. Right? So,
be careful is all I say about this. Don't go to modal first.
Think about whether there's a way to put it in a tab or
in your navigation stack, or something like that. Before
you jump right to choosing modal. All right, so how do we
set up a modal segue? How do we do one of these?
Just like all the other segues we've been doing,
you just CTRL+drag, from the thing that's going to cause
the modal segue to happen, to the MVC that's going to take
over the world. When you do that by the way, an important
thing to notice is that you can inspect the segue, and
a modal segue has different kinda things you can choose.
Which I'm gonna talk about, like how the modal segue is
presented. Does it slide up from the bottom or
do something else? And also, what does the modal segue
look like when it's there? Is it a take over the full screen
kind, okay, or is it some other kind.
We'll talk about what those other kinds can be. All right?
If you wanna present a modal MVC not from a button, okay or
from a bar button item.
You wanna do it from something else. Of course,
you can present it using the normal form segue with
identifier from your code. We've seen a couple of
examples of that in the demos and of course, modal, you can
do that as well. You also, if you have a view controller in
your hand, you actually have an instance of a view
controller like remember alert view controller, right?
You say new alert view controller and you get one,
now you have one. You can put it up using this method right
here, which we actually saw in one of the other demos,
alert demo there. Actually I don't know if I demoed it,
but we talked about it in alerts, which is present
view controller. And you just give it the view controller
that you have in your hand and whether you want it
to be an animated transition, which usually you do. And
then you just got a little handler here at the end,
that will get called when it has finished being presented.
You usually don't need that, but just in case, you do.
All right. So this is how you present something modally.
This is only for modalPresentations, all right?
If you have the view controller in your hand,
which is rare. Generally, it's things you got from iOS,
like maybe the camera view controller, or
the alert view controller, some things like that.
Notice that in horizontally regular environment,
horizontally regular, not compact. You there's
a modalPresentationStyle var in a view controller, that'll,
that'll specify basically how this view controller gets
presented when it gets presented modally. Does it get
presented full screen where it takes the whole full screen?
OverFullScreen which means, it goes over the whole screen but
it, the one behind,
whatever is existing on this screen is visible. So
if you had a clear view controller,
you'd be able to see through it.
So you have things underneath. Pop over, of course you guys
know what a pop over is. A pop over is just a modal,
a modal MVC, but it's kinda got some special presentation
characteristics. There's also form sheet and page sheet,
things like that, which kinda present in different ways.
You can play with those, by inspecting the segue in
the storyboard and choosing different presentation styles.
Note that in horizontally compact environments, however,
it's basically the iPhone in portrait. The system, when you
do the presentViewController will by default,
adapt to be full screen, okay?
So if you try to present something in form sheet mode,
okay? On an iPhone, it'll come up as full screen, cuz it'll
adapt to the fact that it's on the phone. It doesn't really
have enough width to do a form sheet for you, okay?
How do you prepare for a Modal segue? Nothing to see here,
okay? It's just like any other segue you've ever done.
Nothing special about it. Just check the identifier,
get the destination view controller and prepare it.
How do you hear back from a modal view controller?
You put something some up modally and it does something,
okay? You add to new contact, how do you hear back
with the results of what it did? Okay? Well,
there's a couple of ways to do this. One is that the add
contact thing might be putting the contact in a database,
some modal that is shared by the guy who put it up.
So then you don't need to do anything, okay. When the modal
thing gets dismissed, you'll come back and there'll be
something else in the database that wasn't there before.
Another way is using an unwind segue which I'm gonna talk
about in few slides here. And then another way is
delegation. And the reason we have to use delegation or
unwind or something like that is because when you present
a view controller modally, it's part of your view.
It's part of the presenting view controller's view.
So that thing can't talk back in any way, except for
those blind structured ways we talked about,
like delegation, okay? How do you dismiss a view controller,
right? So a view controller's up, and it's collecting
the new contact, and then the user puts Cancel or
Done, how do we make it go away? The answer is you ask
the presenting view controller to dismiss you, always
the presenting view controller dismisses you. All right? And
you send it the message dismissViewControllerAnimated
to the presenting view controller and
it's going to dismiss whatever modal view controller it has
presented, okay? So that's sent to the presenting.
I can't emphasize that enough. Now, in the old days,
people used to send it to the presented.
The API was a little bit different, okay?
And then sent it to the presented view controller,
the one that's actually up, okay?
And, that's wrong. For backwards compatibility,
if you sent it to the presented one,
and the presented one had not presented another one,
then it would dismiss it. But don't write your code to
depend on that kind of backwards compatibility mode.
When you wanna dismiss it, you send it to the presenting.
Now the great thing is that the presented has a var
called presenting view controller, which is the view
controller that presented it. So it's very easy for
the presented one to dismiss itself by asking
its presenting view controller to dismiss it. You see.
But that's the way you wanna write that code.
Okay, if you do an unwind segue,
again, which I'm gonna talk about in a few slides,
it automatically dismisses. So when you unwind,
you don't have to call dismissViewController.
Just automatically dismisses. So
we're talking about unwinding in a second. All right,
so in addition to how the modal view controller appears,
like form sheet or popover or whatever,
there's also how it gets transitioned onto the screen,
what animation gets used. Okay, so, CoverVertical is
the slides up from the bottom, FlipHorizontal,
exactly what you would think, the presented and
the presenting flip, are on like two sides of a card and
it flips over.
You got CrossDissolve which is all between the two.
Even PartialCurl which will partially curl a presenting
one up showing the presented behind it. Kind of just at
the bottom. It's kind of looks really cool.
You see it sometimes with map applications and
stuff you curl the map up and there's something underneath.
All right, let's talk about that wi, unwind segue.
Right, you have these MVCs,
they wanna communicate back, or they wanna jump back.
Maybe, something's on a navigation stack and
wants to jump back farther than just one pop, okay?
You can do all this with an unwind.
Now, unwind segues are weird because they violate the thing
I told you would never violate it,
which is that segues always create a new MVC. Okay, and
that's generally true if you modally segue or show segue or
any of these other kinds of segues,
it creates a new MVC every time except unwind. Because
unwind is gonna segue back to somebody who presented you,
maybe not the guy who immediately presented to you,
maybe somebody who presented to the guy
who presented to you but
you're gonna be going back to an existing view controller.
You're gonna unwind. Okay, your view controllers.
What's it good for? Like I said, good for
communicating back information after a modal one is done,
and also good for jumping back up the stack of cards in
the navigation controller more than one step, okay?
Because it can go back to guys, who presented guys,
who presented guys so it can jump all the way back.
How does it work? Okay, so instead of
Ctrl+dragging to another MVC to set up this segue which is
what you usually do, you actually Ctrl+drag to this
little button at the top. It's kinda reddish.
The Exit button. Okay, so if I have this row in this table
right here and when you click on it, it wants to unwind and
go back to one of the MVCs that presented this MVC,
you just Ctrl+drag up to this little exit. Now when you do
that, it's gonna show you a list of methods that
are implemented by other MVCs in your app, okay? They're
special, and I'll show you what makes them special but
these special things will appear in this list.
And all you do is pick which one you want. Then when you do
the segue, it will start looking up the list of MVC's
that presented you, and the one that presented that, and
the one that presented that until it finds that method.
And it will dismiss all the way back to that one and
call this method, okay? So let me show you some more
pictures to make this a little bit clearer right here.
So this go back method right here, okay,
I want, I connected to exit and
I have to go back.
Go back let's say is in the guy who directly presented me.
He could be farther up the stack but let's say he's right
here. And here's this go back method right here. Now,
what's special about this go back method in this presenter?
Well, one thing is it has to be marked IBAction, okay?
So if it has IBAction. And the second thing is,
the argument has to be a UIStoryboardSegue. So
any method that's, is marked IBAction and
has UIStoryboardSegue as the argument is gonna appear in
this list. Okay, now this IBAction,
once you kind of pick the one you want.
This segue is gonna happen and it's still gonna be a normal
segue and then it's gonna have prepare.
Now the prepare, okay, here's the prepare for segue.
It's going to be in the aah MVC that you wired the exit
button up to, the one on the right here. Okay,
so it lives down in there. And it gets to prepare for
this segue. The segue is gonna come back to this presenter.
So, the destination view controller,
here, is the presenter. The source view controller,
which you haven't seen yet,
in previous segues, is the thing on the right, okay?
The thing it's segueing from. That's the source,
this is the destination, okay? Make sense? And
when this happens, okay, when the segue happens,
you'll be dismissed, right? The source one
will be dismissed. And again, it doesn't just have to
go one level up, it could go up the stack of the navigation
controller things. Or if you had four or five modals in
a row, it could jump all the way back, it's perfectly fine.
It's just whoever implements the method. All right?
Now let's talk another kind of segue, popovers, okay?
You've all seen the popover.
Here's an example of popover here on the right.
This is probably some kind of Search for Appointment to
popover, okay? So this MVC just leaves in here.
And it's being presented modally, okay?
It's just that it presents in a way that looks like this,
like it's in a pop-over. And the popover of course has
a little arrow at the top, a little white arrow,
you can see it, that points to the thing, the UI element that
caused it to pop up. Usually that's a bar button item, but
it could also just be an arbitrary rectangle inside
some view somewhere, okay? This area out here, okay,
everywhere else except for this popover and
the keyboard is grayed out. If you click there,
it will dismiss this popover. So the one difference between
popover and other kinda modal one is that popovers are easy
to dismiss. Just click outside of them, you'll dismiss, so
you don't need a cancel button in a popover or
modal popover. But it's still modal in that obviously you
can't do anything in that grayed out area.
You can only do what this search for
appointment MBC wants to do right now.
Okay, so it's still a modal, it just looks different.
Popover is just a presentation style basically for modal. So
popovers, you think of a popover's kind of like
a navigational controller or split view controller, a tab
bar because it's putting a view controller inside another
another view controller, but it's not. You should think of
popover just as a presentation style. Dial for modal, okay?
So segue into a popover is setup the same way that you
setup a oni modal one, it's just that when you drag over,
you're gonna pick popover instead of modal, okay? When
you're in the storyboard you drag over. Now, an important
thing to note when you prepare for a popover segue,
this is what's different between a popover and
immodal encode, okay? When you prepare all presentations of
any kind of segue are done by a UI presentation controller.
You don't see this, I'm not really talking about this
in this class, it's not really kind of a introductory
material. But, the popover one has a sub class of that called
UI popover presentation controller,
and it's in the thing that knows
how to present it as a popover.
So it's the thing that knows, for example, where to have
the little popover thing point, okay. That's something
that that popover presentation controller knows about. So in
your prepare for segue, you're gonna get this UI popover
presentation controller and I'll show you how to do that.
And you're going to use it to configure how the popover
presents, okay? Now in addition to setting things
like where the popover's arrow can point,
you can also control things like how the popover adapts
to different size classes, okay? And we'll talk about
that in a second too. So here's the prepare for segue,
the prepare for a popover, okay?
All the green, except for what's in this yellow if
statement right here is the same as any other prepare. But
when we get down to the bottom here,
we're gonna get that popover presentation controller by
asking the view controller that we're putting up modally.
Please give me your popover presentation controller,
okay? So that view controller has the popover presentation
going. We get it. Once we have it, we can do things like
configure it like the permitted arrow directions.
Which direction we want the arrow to be? We can also
specify things like where the arrows are pointing,
all that kind of stuff.
Okay, everything you would imagine a popover needs to be
configured with. All right, now also importantly,
we can set that presentation controllers delegate, okay?
And with that delegate we control a little bit more
about how the popover works. So let's talk about that.
What can we do with the delegate? One thing we can do
is find out when that popover was dismissed, okay? So
the delegate will be sent this message,
popoverPresentationController- DidDismissPopover.
Did dismiss popover. Okay, so that's nice to be able to
know when that popover was dismissed. Another thing is we
can control the adaptation behavior when we're in
different size classes like horizontally compact,
okay? So when a popover comes up, as you can
imagine, maybe it wouldn't fit in a horizontally compact
environment unless it's kind of the small popover.
So by default, the system adapts to full screen.
So if you have a popover segue and it's on horizontally
compact, it gets changed to modal full screen. So it'll
take over the whole screen, slide up from the bottom.
Okay, now you might now want that. Maybe it is a small
little popover and you do want it to be a pop over on iPhone
and you can control that. And here's how you do that.
There is a method. Okay, this is a popover. This is actually
a presentation controller delegate method. And
you can see it just sends you the controller here and
a traitCollection. So that's the size class is right here
and you're gonna return a presentation style.
Now, if you don't implement this delegation method, then
in horizontally compact, it returns full screen otherwise,
it returns whatever it was setup in the storyboard,
popover or form sheet or whatever. But
if you do implement it, you could return for example UI
modal presentation style none which means don't adapt.
This is asking for, how do I adapt to this trait
collection. If you say none, that means don't adapt.
Just do the same thing on every single platform.
Okay, and so if you do this, then your popover will appear
as a popover on your iPhone. Look just like on an iPad but
it better be small coz it didn't have a lot of room.
So this is how you can control that adaptation behavior,
okay. But here's a problem, let's say you
do that, okay, let's say you don't do that. Let's say
the popover is too big and it comes up full screen,
how do you dismiss that popover, okay? Because it used
to be a popover I could click somewhere else and
it will disappear. But now it's full screen.
I can't click anywhere else. How do I dismiss it? Okay,
that's a problem. What would be really cool,
is if you could put it inside a navigation controller and
then add a little done button, right at the top? And
this method is how you do that. So, if you implement
the delegate of the popover presentation controller, and
you implement this thing, view controller for
adapter presentation style, it allows you to return
a different view controller to present. For example,
you might, preser, present, return a navigation
controller. Whose visible view controller is, the actual view
controller that was inside the popover, you see. And
you could add a done button to it or whatever you want. So
here you can return, if you return nil here
it's going to just return the thing that was inside,
gonna be inside the popover.
But if you return the navigation controller or
whatever, it'll put that up In the modal adapted. And this is
only happening in the adapted case, right? View control for
adapted presentation style, okay? All right,
very important issue about popover is its size, okay?
iOS implements its size in a very object-jointed way,
which is that when you have an MVC that's gonna be put up as
a popover, the system asks that MVC what size would
you prefer it to be?
Okay, because that MVC obviously knows what the best
size for it to be is, and it does that via this var
preferredContentSize is a CGSize and you can either
set this preferredContectSize. The MVC can set its
own preferredContectSize to something reasonable or
you could actually even override it. And
have it return its correct size, its prefered size.
It's called preferred by the way because, obviously
the system will try to fit it on screen but if, for
example, it's on horizontally compact and the adaptive thing
is turned off then it might have to jam it in there,
it might have to be a little smaller than preferred wants
it to be, kay? So this is not guaranteed to be this size,
this size is preferred. Okay, the last segue I'm gonna talk
about is embed segues, okay? These are really,
really cool segues. Basically you could take an MVC,
take its view, you know, the top level view, and
put it as a view inside the view hierarchy of another MVC.
Okay it'll look just a view in another MVC, it's just that,
it's completely controlled by an MVC,
okay? Really cool that's why it's called embedded.
You're embedding an MVC inside of another one.
Xcode makes it really easy to do this.
Just go down to your little object pallet down there where
you get your buttons and stuff. And look for
container view and drag that into the place that you want
this thing to be embedded. It will look just like a view,
you can do auto layout constraints on it.
You can put it as a sub-view of anything else you want.
It's just a view, okay. And when you do it,
you're gonna see this kind of cool look where it puts what
looks like a Segue way thing.
Okay, here's the thing in the container, what I dragged out.
This segue right here and here's the NVC. Okay so
here's the normal NVC like in your storyboard anywhere else,
and it's got this little segue here, so kinda seem like
a segue and it is in the sense kinda segue to it.
It's just that instead of doing it modelly or something
that, it's just going to put its view right in here.
Okay, make sense and you can prepare for that segue,
it's a perfectly normal segue. One thing to be careful
about this though is the View Loading Timing.
Remember that when you're in prepare for segue,
none of the outlets of the MVC are set. And that's true with
embed as well, all right? So might have this embed segue,
has all this cool UI but none of its outlets are set up. So
a lot of times in the embed, when you're preparing for
an embed segue, you're just grabbing the MVC and
holding onto it with a pointer. And
then later like in your own viewDidLoad,
okay your MVC will be loaded by then, then you can go and
set whatever you want to the embayed, the embedded thing to
look like okay. So just be careful of that.
It's just standard thing here that prepare for
segue outlets aren't set in the destination MVC but for
embed it comes, it's even more obvious, kinda,
it bites you more often. Okay, so that's segues. Okay,
that's all the segues there are. Okay, Ben, now you can
cover. Yeah, question? >> So, so in, in that segues,
if you have an existing view controller,
can you connect into the inside or
does it have to look funny like, you know?
>> Yeah so the question is can
I connect just a regular mvc from somewhere like maybe my
Cassini image view controller for example. It's just
sitting around there. Could I embed it? And the answer is
yes you can. Okay the mvc has embedded nothing special about
it whatsoever okay it can be embedded just as easily.
All right. Core Location is my next topic.
Okay we're done with segues now we're moving on to
Core Location and map kit here. So Core Location and map
kit are really two part pieces of the same puzzle here.
Core Location is the non-UI way to find out about your
location. Okay? And then map kit is the bunch of UI to show
your location on maps and stuff. So when you talk about
correlation first because it has a lot of the intrinsic
stuff that you need to understand the map kit stuff.
All right. The basic object in core location is called
a CLLocation. Core location, location. CLLocation has
the coordinate latitude and longitude, altitude,
the horizontal and vertical accuracy of this location,
because sometimes depending on how you got this location,
it might be highly accurate,
you know, within a meter or so, or
might be very inaccurate, maybe it's a kilometer.
Okay? Timestamp, when was this thing was taken, you'll see
that that's really important. A speed if the system detected
that you were moving at this time that this thing was
taken, and a course will tell you what direction you were
headed in if it detects that you were moving at this point.
So that's the basic collection of stuff is in CLLocation.
The CL, coordinate, this coordinate thing right here is
a CLLocationCOordinate2D which is just a latitude and
a longitude struct.
The altitude is a CLLocationDistance,
which is meters. Okay? Now let's talk about
the accuracy thing, okay? When you are asking for
a location and when you get a location, in both cases,
you're gonna specify an accuracy, okay?
Specifying the accuracy is going to determine what
mechanism your device uses to get the accuracy. And
then when you get the accuracy back It tells you, kind of,
how it got it, somewhat. Okay, so, we're a little bit
abstracting the hardware away from the concept of
an accurate measurement of location. Here
are the different accuracies that it can have here,
best for navigation,
best nearest ten meters, hundred meters, kilometer,
or three kilometers and as you can imagine best for
navigation. It's really really really really accurate.
It's also really really really uses a lot of battery, okay.
And basically you can almost rename these things as
lots of battery usage,
a little bit less, medium battery usage, not so
much battery usage, very very battery efficient by the time
you get to the bottom. Okay? It's really batteries are big
deal when it comes to getting your location. Now,
how does the system get these different accuracy locations?
Well, there's three different ways really at least for
now that the system could get location and
you don't know which one is using. Okay,
all you get to do is specify the accuracy you want and
it will get the locations as best it can and re-tell you
what accuracy it got. But the three ways it knows how to do
are GPS which is very accurate and uses a lot of power.
Okay, then there's WiFi nodes. Believe it or not your phone
can, as you walk around, see what WiFi nodes are around.
It's got a huge database on the network of all the WiFi
nodes and where they are. And so based on which ones
are close to you, which ones you're getting good signal,
it can figure our generally where you are.
Which is kind of a cool feature, right?
Pretty low power, WiFi is fairly low power not as
low-power as cellular towers which is the next one, and,
but certainly a lot less power than doing GPS. And so,
it can find, you know, these kind of medium accuracies
by doing that. And in fact, if you walk around at Stanford,
it can be very accurate because there's an incredible
number of WiFi nodes around Stanford campus. You
are probably in range of 50 of them at almost given time.
Certainly 20 so, we pretty much know almost exactly where
you are. And then last one is cell tower triangulation. So
same way with the WiFi nodes it can look around to the cell
towers. Now there's fewer cell towers than there are WiFi
nodes okay, and they tend to be farther away from you.
Okay, so triangulating them is a little more iffy okay.
And sometimes there's not one for
very very far distance from you, a kilometer or more. So
that's why you start getting these really low accuracies
out here but the cellular radio is incredibly low power.
Super super low power, okay. And
your cellular radio is also automatically being turned on
and off and used as, you know you walk around and
you're making phone calls, or receiving phone calls etc. So
the cellular infrastructure's very low power but
low accuracy. Okay? Got all of that? All right
there's other things you can find out in the core location,
your speed, your course, that timestamp.
The reason the time stamp is important is that there
are a lot of ways to ask the system to give you
CLLocations, not in real time. In other words it's not going
to give you the location right now. Like you might be going
out for a run and you put your phone in your pocket and
it goes to sleep it can still collect locations. And
then when it wake back up it will send them all to you. And
when it does you're going to want to know the timestamps so
you knew where you were at the time.
So time stamp is an important part of the CLLocation.
All right. So how do we get a CLLocation? Well, you get it
from a CLLocationManager usually. Just like we had
a core motion, we have the CM motion manager. Well,
in the core location, we have the CLLocationManager. And
it has a delegate that's going to generally give you,
locations. What's really cool about it is you can actually
test in the simulator by simulating yourself being in
different locations. If you go down near the debugger bar,
there's a little guy there and that you can even upload
with the GPX file. The GPX file is just
a file with a bunch of waypoints in it, okay.
GPS locations can have other stuff in there like actually
URLs for photos taken at the location, stuff like that. But
it can have these location you can upload it and
have whatever testing you want in here okay. So
the CLLocationManager.
How do you use it? Similar to the CMMotion manager. First
you're going to check like to see what hardware's available.
Okay and then you're going to create a CLLocationManager and
set as delegate so that you can receive updates.
Then you're going to configure the manager to say what kind
of location you want. And we'll talk about what that
means and then you're going to start it going.
And once you start it going it's going to start sending
your locations based on how you, what you asked for,
all right. How, what kind of location monitoring is
available in the system? Well one is accuracy based
continual updates. This is what you would normally think.
You set an accuracy that you want. Okay, I want
highly accurate best for navigation or low accuracy and
the system will start sending you locations based on that
accuracy. So if you ask for best for navigation it's
gonna be sending you locations all the time and
they're gonna be highly accurate. If you ask for
every three kilometers. You could walk for
20 minutes before it sends you another location because it
notices another cell tower and can figure out its location.
Okay? So that's one way to do it. Another way is you can
get notified only when a significant location change
happens, okay. This is basically, I'm not talking
about how it's implemented here but I kinda am.
But it's basically when it sees a new cell tower. Okay.
So that's a significant enough change that it'll probably
send you one. So
this is not highly accurate locations necessarily. Okay.
The other one is region based updates so you can define
these regions either little circular areas in the world or
even where beacons live. Okay? Little bluetooth beacons and
you can get notified when you get close to that beacon or
you get real close to the beacon or
when you walk inside the circular area. Okay? And
then you also can have your heading monitored if
you change direction, it can send you a new location.
All right, so let's talk about how we use CLO,
CL location manager, and then we'll talk about how to make
each of those things work. First we want to find out what
our, hardware can do. One of the most important things
to find out about hardware is whether you're authorized to
get the user's location. As you can imagine, users might
not want you to know where they are, tracking their every
move out there. It's kind of a sensitive subject, okay. So
you have to make sure you're authorized to receive it.
And you can do this with these various things I'll talk about
authorization, on the next page. By the way, anytime you
in detail,
have an authorization status of any kind, not just for
location, you notice there's the states Authorized, Denied,
or Restricted. What Restricted means right there is,
it's denied, and the user can't change it.
So don't put up an alert that says, you, I'm not authorized
to get your location. Please go to Settings and change it.
Okay because they're not allowed to. There are ways
in enterprises inside companies where companies can
configure the phones of their employees. So for example,
they can't do this location service or other services.
Okay so be careful about the restricted state.
It's restricted just accept the fact you can't do it.
All right. And then you can also check for certain
kinds of monitoring like can you monitor for beacons or
can you monitor for circular regions? Most new hardware can
do all of these stuff or if you have an older phone maybe
it doesn't have the same capabilities to do that.
Alright? So let's talk about
this authorization piece though because it is
very important interesting piece to do it.
There's couple of steps you have to do to make it work.
One is you have to request authorization, okay.
This is ASynchronous, okay. You send this to the CL
location manager and you're gonna request one of
these two different kinds of authorizations.
In Use Authorization or Always Authorization. So
InUseAuthorization means you only wanna be allowed to
get the location when it's the foreground app the user is
using. Okay? When the user is in the background or
anything else, you can't find this location.
Users are fairly comfortable with that level
of authorization cuz they know when you're getting their,
their location. AlwaysAuthorization is you can
get their location anytime even the background and
that's very invasive of their privacy. So
you know a lot of people, users won't do this.
They won't give you that authorization, okay? So
the system might be putting up an alert asking the user if
it's okay, they're checking in their settings to see what
settings are there, things like that to find so
that's what its asynchronous. Eventually a delegate method
will be called in your CL location saying,
okay, here's your authorization task.
It was denied or it was accept, it was allowed. Okay?
Now, when you go off to request this authorization,
you have to have the user in their setting,
if they go into settings and
look at location services, your app will be there,
there has to be a switch they can click that says,
yes I'll allow my, this app to have always authorization or
in use authorization. To put that UI in the settings,
you have to put something in your info P list. Okay?
Which is this key right here NSLocation when
in use description or
NSLocation always use a description. This is a string
explaining why you want this particular authorization.
And if this key exists then, in settings,
the user will be able to have a switch to turn this on or
off. So if you don't put these in here, these things on top,
these funcs will always fail. Because there's no way for
the user to set that in their settings, so
they'll all just always fail. Okay? And
the system can't put up an alert even asking if it's okay
because if they said yes there's no way,
there's no switch for the system to turn on.
So you'd just be always denied, so
you need these two steps to get authorization. All right.
Now, how do you then get the CL location from the location
manager? Of course you can pull, but
like with motion manager we say that's not a good idea.
But what you can do you can just ask the location manager
please give me the current location. And
it will give you the location with whatever accuracy it has.
Okay but really the way we do it is we set this var
in the location manager called desired accuracy.
That's one of those accuracies like best for navigation and
all those things. And then also a distance filter which
is how far the user has to move before we're gonna give
a new location. Okay? So, if you take ten meters,
you just gotta walk ten meters down the way before another
location will come. And
those two things together will give the system a good idea of
how hard it has to work to get the users location. Okay. So
you set those and then you say start updating the location.
And as soon as you say start updating location, as long as
you've set these, you're going to start getting locations
appropriate to these settings up here. Now, be sure,
just like with the motion manager,
in fact even more importantly than the motion manager,
to stop them when you're not gonna do anything with
the results. If locations are coming, and you're ignoring
them, you should have stopped it because this is basically
turn on battery save. [LAUGH] Okay. If you turn, turn,
if you don't stop updating location and
you're not using it, you're just draining your battery for
nothing, it's probably the number one way to drain
their battery, actually. Okay. And you people will rapidly,
you'll get it on your app store thing on the comments
it'll say drained your battery don't buy this thing.
Okay? So you want to be really careful not to do that. Okay.
So once you turn it on you're gonna start getting this
delegate method sent to you. Did update locations is plural
which in a, within array of locations.
Now, why is that an array of locations instead of
just sending you each location one by one.
Well, it's that running example, you got for a run,
your phone goes to sleep, it collects a bunch of locations
and I'm not gonna talk about how you'd set that up but
you can look in the documentation. And when you're
pick your phone up and then and say, how was my run. Boom!
You're gonna get all these locations as an array here.
Okay, with time stamps and all that, so you'll be able to
reconstruct the run. Okay, similar APIs this, for
heading, if you wanna just monitor the user's heading.
Error reporting is important and
easy to miss because you have to implement another delegate
method here, which is locationManagerDidFailWithEr-
ror. But you definitely do want to be looking at this.
Okay if you have,
if you are using a location you have to implement this.
Because for example the user could at any time go to their
say no I don't want this guy using my location.
settings and
In which case you're gonna start getting this denied.
And if you don't look for this, your output's just gonna
go into some wacky state because it's not gonna know
what's happening. Okay you need to what's happening.
Also, error location unknown. If from some reason, it,
we can't find the location. Maybe you asked for best for
navigation, it just can't find any, thing to give you your
location, so you wanna know that as well, okay?
So definitely wanna look at this thing.
If you're doing location manager in your final project,
you got to implement this, okay? All right,
lets talk about getting your location in the background,
verses about getting your location in the foreground.
Okay, so when you get in the foreground it's all
the things we just talked about.
There's a bird in here with it.
When you're in the background, though,
things are a little different because you know that
generally you're not allowed to run in the background.
You kind of go quiet, and then you get in those cycles. But
there are ways you, you remember when we went and
enabled iCloud in that capabilities thing? Well,
there's things in there where you can enable backgrounding
for locations, okay? Now if you do this
you will continue to get stuff in the background.
You can imagine it's even more important to be sure you're
not sucking the battery at this,
in this situation, okay? And this is the kind of thing,
if you're sucking the battery in the background there,
your App Store app might not get approved, okay?
That's how important it is not to be sitting there
sucking the battery in the background, okay? Now,
there are other ways though, very battery-efficient ways,
to get your location in the background, so
let's talk about those. One is that significant monitoring I
thing I was telling you about where you're walking around,
and it notices a new cell tower so
it's very kind of large grained.
That's an awesome way to get locations for
very low battery, uses almost no battery to do this. And
what's more and really cool about it, if you're app is in
the background. You'll get the notification if it's not even
running, it will get launched and told this information. So
this a very powerful telling you where the location is.
And when it gets launched, by the way, if,
if they're using some other app, it will launch it and
launch you in the background.
So you can figure out where you are and
decide if you need to do something.
Okay, so this one is really cool, really low power,
the only problem with it, it's large grained. Now,
once you get woken up, that you've significantly changed,
you could start doing more close location, KGPS location,
try and find out a little bit exactly where you are,
if you want. Although be careful not to take too long,
when you get launched for
this in the background because the system will stop doing
this. If you, you know starts consuming a lot of resources
in the background there, okay? So be careful with that.
Similarly is the region base monitoring, okay?
Where you specify a circle or beacons,
okay? That also will wake you up and even launch your
application if it notices you going into that region. Okay,
and run you in the background. Also low power, you know,
really nice way to do it. So if that will meet your needs
as well, that's a good one to do, okay.
When you enter a region, either beacon or
circular region, you're gonna get these delegate methods.
didEnterRegion, didExitRegion, and
monitoringDidFailForRegion. Also here's the error handler
for that one, okay? So that's kind of a fun one.
Region-monitoring works when you're not running because all
your regions are named, okay? They all have to have unique
names, and so when you get launched you'll know which one
fired by its name. You also, there is by the way a maximum
limit to the circular region called maximum region
monitoring distance, you want to look at that.
You can't say when I enter the United States,
okay that won't take that big of a region.
It has to be much much smaller,and this will tell you
how big it can be, okay? This is the beacon thing.
When you're looking for beacons,
what you're really interested in is how far from the beacon
am I? Okay, am I close to it, like really, really next to
it? Or a little bit far away or across the ways. So
beacons are used for things like, you're going to a coffee
shop and when you get right up to the register.
Maybe it offers you a coupon or something like that,
well it needs to know you're right near the register.
But maybe when you just walk in the store it just gives you
an advertisement or directs you to some display, okay?
So the beacon would be sitting maybe near the register and
so this thing is telling you. That's why we call it ranging,
start ranging these beacons. Now these beacons could be
other iOS devices, could serve as a beacon, okay? Or
you could even buy these third party stand alone eye beacons
basically that will act as beacons. If you wanted to be
a beacon, okay, that's beyond the scope of this class.
I can't really tell you how to do that, okay.
You need to get the Core Bluetooth Framework involved
here and check out CBPeripheralManager.
It will show you how to do it but it's a little more
complicated than I can show in a couple slides so.
So that's it for core location. Let's now talk about
Map Kit which is the UI way of showing location.
MKMapView is a UI view that displays a map, okay?
Looks just like the maps app, on iOS.
A map can have annotations, like this little red pin
down there, okay? Each annotation has a coordinate,
obviously the GPS location where that thing is, and also
a title. And a subtitle, okay, there's no subtitle shown
in this one right here,
okay? The annotations though can also have this call out,
this white area. That's not part of the annotation view,
that's a call out that the annotation view brings up. So
we're going to talk about the components of this callout
in a second as well. Actually it's talking right now.
[COUGH] It's got a left accessory view and
a right accessory view.
And these are usually things like UI image views or
maybe UI buttons things like that, okay. So this is how
we're going to build our map UIs out of these components.
So how do you create with MapView?
Really easy. MKMapView or MKMapView with a frame,
initializer, or you can drag it out in your storyboard,
which is what we'll do in the demo. And MapView, what
does it, how does it basically work? It's got an array,
this var annotations which is an array of MKAnnotation,
okay. MKAnnotation is not a class, it's a protocol. So
anything could be an annotation on a map as long as
it implements this protocol. What is that protocol?
It has coordinate, title, and subtitle,
okay? If you implement those three bars, boom,
you can be thrown onto a map. You will be an MKAnnotation.
They're all get, see? Var title is an optional string by
the way but it's really expected to be implemented.
Don't ever leave this nil or system does not like that,
okay? I'm not sure why, it's optional, should be and then
the core location coordination coordinate remember that's
cllocation coordinate 2D, latitude and longitude Ok,
so that's it. So it's got this array of annotations but
you notice this array is read only. So to add annotations or
remove annotations you have to use these methods, add or
remove annotations.
It's generally a good idea from a performance perspective
to add all of your annotations that you know about up front.
And that's because the annotation views,
those little pins. Get reused just like in a table view,
okay? So you might as well add them all upfront and
let the system reuse the pins as you scroll,
scroll around the world. Okay, can reuse them. What do
annotations look like on the map? Well we saw it before,
right? If you use an MKPinAnnotationView, which is
a subclass of MKAnnotationView you get a little pin.
It can be red or purple I think or maybe another
color. But it does allow you to even change this image. If
you don't like a pin, you can change it to something else.
And when you click on the PinAnnotationView,
you get this call out. And
that's what the call out looks like, okay? So what happens
when you press the pin besides this call-out coming out? And
by the way, this call-out only comes out if canShowCallout is
true on the MK annotation pin annotation view.
So you have to have that be true. So this will come up,
but in addition to this appearing, a delegate method
will be sent to the map views delegate. It's called
Map view did select annotation view, okay? And so this
is important little method right here because if you're
gonna show anything expensive in your call out, like so
you're gonna go over their network and grab an image or
something like that. You're gonna wanna wait to do it
until didSelectAnnotationView. Because if the user never
clicks on this pin, he's never gonna see that image. So you
don't wanna waste your time fetching it. Okay? So this
is a place where you're gonna do expensive stuff that's
gonna show in the call out. You also, though,
might segue out of this. When someone clicks on a pin,
maybe you wanna go segue to some other view, I don't know.
Okay, but this is the target action of MKAnnotations.
All right, so how are these AnnotationViews, these little
pins created and associated with those annotations?
Because we know MKMap View only has this array of
annotations. So how do those pins get there to show them?
And the answer is from this delegate method right here,
MapView, viewForAnnotation.
This is very much like self or roll in index path in table
view. Okay? So in there, you're creating a cell which
is a view. Okay, UI table view cell. Here you're creating
an MK annotation view like the Pin annotation view. Okay. So
let's go through this and see how we do it. First we're
gonna dq a reusable one using some identifier but
if that fail, okay and view is nil if we can't dq one
then there's no prototype like there is in the table view so
we have to create the prototype in code. So
here I'm creating the prototype by saying,
view equals MK pin Annotation view, okay? But I'm specifying
that sam reuse identifier that later I might come back and do
this reuseable with, you see? So that's how they get done.
And then can't show call out either set to true or false,
whichever one you want. Okay.
Then we're gonna whether we created the view or
not, we're gonna wanna set the view's annotation to be
the annotation we're creating, this view for. And then,
we're gonna wanna prepare this view with anything else.
Like if it's gonna have a left call out accessor view,
which is an image view,
this is the time we would add the image view. This might not
be the time we actually go fetch the image to put there,
you might wait until didSelectAnnotationView for
you to do that but we're not gonna wanna put the UI image
view in there so that it's ready to go in the call out.
Okay, and then we're gonna return the view then
the system gonna use this view to show that pin.
Okay, interesting properties on UIAnnotationView,
we already talked about the left and
right CallOutAccessoryViews, which are just views.
There's also whether it's enabled or not. This image is
the image of the pin, not the image that's in the callout,
it's the image of the pin. Also you can
make it draggable, setting draggable to true. If you do
that your MKAnnotations, the coordinate property would have
to be get and set. Obviously if you're gonna drag it around
you have to be able to set the property as well.
Okay. This cool property or
delegate method right here calloutAccessoryControlTapped
will get sent to your map view delegates If your left or
right call out accessory is a ui control.
Basically a ui button okay? So if you put a button
at your left or right call out accessory when it gets touched
you're gonna get this call out accessory control tapped
method which is pretty cool.
In did select annotation view we talked about the fact
that this is where you might want to create your image or
even fire off a thread or q, on a different q, fire off
a request to go get the image. When it comes back later
you'll have to load it up into the accessory view. Okay?
Just like when you're scrolling around in a table
view, realize that if you're scrolling around on the map
you might fire off a dispatch async here to go get this
image, and when it comes back that image is no longer being
displayed in this call accessory view because it gets
reused, reused right by other ones. So be careful about
that. The map you can configure the way it displays.
This is a var on MKMapView. You can do standard,
satellite, or hybrid. So standard is like streets and
things like that, satellite is like Google Earth type thing.
And then hybrid is a mix, an overlay of those two things.
You can also show the user's current location. On the map
just by saying this Bool to true and it will show it.
I think the users current location is blue or maybe it's
purple, I don't know. But it will just show in there.
You can also get the users location as well.
As MKUserLocation which is just thing that implements
the MKAnnotation protocol. You can also restrict scrolling.
Okay, maybe you don't want. The 3D mode.
If you don't want 3D mode, set pitch enable to false and
it won't pitch up to show you 3D maps. You can control
the camera if you do allow 3D you can control
where the camera is pointing using this, API right here,
that's kind of fun. You can also say what part of
the world is being shown with the MP coordinate region which
is just a latitude longitude and a span okay which is
number of meters. Okay? So it shows that will show that part
of the Earth. Actually it's not it's not even meters.
The span is a delta of latitude and longitude.
How many degrees of latitude and
how many degrees of longitude to show.
Okay? What else we can do here?
I just want you to note that there's a whole bunch of
C-like functions, they're swift global functions,
they're not methods, that you can do to convert
like from map coordinates to view coordinates and
things like that. So make sure you take a look at these and
understand all of these. There's probably about 15 or
20 of them that will help you do conversions.
There's also some methods that will do it, as well,
in MKMapView. There's a cool method in MKMapView called
didChangeRegionAnimated.
Okay? So, if you tell the mapview to
show a different part of the world like New York, okay.
It's going to animate going there. It's going to
scroll over there. But if I'm in San Francisco and I say,
show New York it's gonna go whoo, okay, you're not even
gonna see it. Nebraska, you'll never see it okay.
In Nebraska, you can go by so fast. You'll never see it.
What would be really cool is if you said,
I'm in San Francisco, show New York, first you said
show the whole United States then show New York.
Right then you get this cool animation. San Francisco to
the whole United States down to New York.
Wouldn't that be cool? Yes it would. And so
the way you do that is you first of all set your location
to the whole United States or
middle of the United States with a large span and it will
go up to there and as soon as the animation of that finishes
you'll get sent this. Okay cuz it's a did change region.
It finished the change region.
As soon as it sends you this now you animate to New York.
So essentially chaining you see.
And now it will [INAUDIBLE] New York. So this is the way
you can chain animations to make the animations kind of
fly around the world nicely. MKLocalSearch I'm not going to
really talk about it but it's a way that you can put normal
English language descriptions of places like Ike's, and
it'll go and search. This is asynchronous,
cuz it's gonna go out on the internet to look this up. But
it'll come back and give you a bunch of,
locations that might match this search. Okay? Okay.
Similarly you can asked for the directions you can
say I wanna go from here to here and I'm gonna drive,
give me directions, and it will give you this thing
called MKRoute with also have turn by turn directions.
And also have an MKPolyline which is an object which will
draw this blue line right here Okay, and
how do you get this blue line showing on here?
You're gonna use another feature called overlays, okay.
Overlays are very much like annotations, but instead of
you have view for annotation, you have overlay view for
annotation or renderer for annotation.
Okay, and this renderer could be something like a polyline
renderer, and if you have a polyline renderer, and
you give it an MKPolyline that comes from that root thing,
you can draw that root, okay?
You also use overlays for your on own thing,
if you wanna draw a bounding area around something, or
you wanna draw your own path of where you went, you can do
all that with overlays. Okay if you wanna do that in your
final project, it'll count as not covered in lecture,
cuz I'm not really covering it,
I'm just telling you it's there, okay?
Same thing as local search and
all these things I've kind of glossed over here, okay?
These are some of the built-in renderers, polyline,
also circles, polygons, tiling, etc. Okay,
so that's it. Now we're gonna start a demo that's gonna last
across both lectures here, and we're gonna start by just
doing a simple app that takes some waypoints and throws them
on a map, so we can see how to do that. Also on Wednesday, in
addition to finishing up this demo I'm gonna cover the last
topic of the quarter which is persistence,
which is basically how to store things in the file
system, right? Opening files and all that business. Okay,
so let's go start a new app here.
We're gonna create a brand new one. We'll create on iOS app,
Single View, as usual. We'll call this one Trax, okay?
Cuz it's gonna keep track of where you have been.
We'll make it a Universal app, so it works on iPhone and
iPad. There we go, we'll put it in our standard location.
All right, so here's Trax. In the storyboard right here
I'm going to, do my standard thing. We're gonna move,
some of these things off to Supporting Files here.
Supporting Files.
We're not gonna be needing to do anything in AppDelegate, so
I'll move it off to Supporting flies, Files here.
In my storyboard, I actually don't want my ViewController
here to be called generic View Controller.
So I'm gonna rename it to be GPXViewController,
cuz what we're gonna do is take a GPX file which,
like I said before, is just a file that contains a bunch
of GPS coordinates, and we're gonna put it on our map.
So we're gonna call this our GPXViewController, so
I'm gonna rename it here as well,
and also in my storyboard and go here to
the Identity Inspector change this to GPXViewController.
Okay, now let's also go ahead and build our UI here.
Our UI is gonna be all map, all the time. Okay, our entire
UI is just gonna be a gigantic map. So I'm gonna go down to
my object palette down here and try and find map,
actually, I'm gonna search for it by just typing map.
Here it is, a Map Kit View, and you drag that out and
put it here. Make it fill the entire MVC scene.
Of course, we'll do Reset to Suggested Constraints, and
we'll jump over here to our size inspector and make sure
it did the right thing. Sure looks like it did. Let's go
ahead and make an outlet to this from our controller. So
I'm just gonna Ctrl+drag in here. I'll call it my mapView.
Okay, you can see that it's a type MKMapView right there. So
we have our Map View. Let's go ahead and when our mapView
is set, let's go ahead and configure our mapView what we
want it to look like. So how about the mapView's, mapType.
And see it's not doing escape completion here.
Why not? Import MapKit.
Okay, just like CloudKit, it's a separate framework.
We need it, or it's not gonna know any of these types.
So we'll set our mapType to be Satellite, okay,
satellite images. Let's set our delegate,
of course. Nothing works in a mapView without a delegate, so
we absolutely have to use delegate, and
that means we'll have to be an MKMapViewDelegate.
All right, so we have our mapview set up here nicely,
oops. Okay, so now we need our model.
What's gonna be our model to this thing?
It's going to be a gpxURL. Okay, so this is gonna be
the URL to a GPX file, a file that contains coordinates.
And we're just gonna open that file,
look at all the GPX coordinates and display them.
And in fact, let's go ahead and in our viewDidLoad here
just load one up. So let's see, gpxURL equals,
how about this one right here, a string, which is
http://cs193p.stanford.edu/Va- cation,
oops, Vacation.gpx. Okay, so that's just a,
a URL I have around there that we can look at. Now this
is an http, so we'd better go over to our info.plist,
right here, and do the thing we always do here where we add
our App Transport settings right here.
Let's add Arbitrary Loads allowed, and we will
say YES. Everyone understand why we're doing that,
same thing we had to do with smash tag there. All right, so
we're all set up here, what are we gonna do when this is
set? Okay, so when our model is set, when this URL is set,
what are we gonna need to do here to make this work? Well,
if they set the URL equal to something, so
they didn't set it to be nil let's say. Then really what
I need to do is parse this file, this URL somehow. And
to do that, I'm going to introduce a little class that
I wrote called GPX, which will parse a GPX file and then give
you all the waypoints. Okay, so let's go ahead and
grab that file. It's right here, it's called GPX.swift.
Copy it in. Take a brief look at this thing,
what it does. All right, here's GPX, let's go ahead and
look at it just at its generated interface
here. No need to look at the code there.
All right, so here's the GPX, this class. And
the main thing it has is this, this var waypoints,
which is a array of GPX.Waypoint.
Let's go look at the GPX waypoint, that's right here.
So, the Waypoint is latitude and longitude, of course,
kind of some information about this waypoint, the date
the waypoint was captured. And it's also an entry,
this Waypoint is also an entry, which is this thing.
The entry can have any number of hyperlinks. So these would
be like URLs to photos or video that I might have taken
at this location when I was on my trek or whatever. Also it
has a name, which is the name of this waypoint, okay? May or
may not have a name, but if it does this is the name. Okay,
these links by the way, these GPX links is right here.
It's basically just URLs, hrefs, here,
okay. All right, so that's it. That's all this thing does is,
main thing is this, this array of waypoints, okay? So let's
go back to our controller here. So we do this GPX.parse.
Notice that this parse method in GPX is asynchronous.
It parses that file, and then later it calls you back.
It's a very nice asynchronous method in that it always calls
you back on the main queue, okay, so
we don't have to dispatch async or anything here. And
the only argument that's given when you do it is a GPX, which
is an instance of this class, and it has those waypoints.
So, what are we gonna do with these waypoints when they come
back? Well, if the, if it was able to parse it, basically if
this thing came back and it wasn't nil, then we're going
to add these waypoints to ourself. Waypoints,
okay, so we're gonna have to add, do this method here.
Also every time someone said that I'm also gonna clear any
waypoints that I already have. So I'm gonna implement these
two methods right here. Okay everybody cool with that? So
we're just getting those GPS waypoints out of this GPX
file. So we're gonna implement these two methods. So
let's do private func clearWaypoints. Okay, so for
clearWaypoints I just wanna remove all the annotations off
my map, remember the map just shows annotations? So
I'm gonna remove them all.
I'm gonna say mapView removeAnnotations which is
the mapView's current annotations, okay,
whatever the mapView currently has. Notice I'm doing this
MapView question mark here, that's because if this happens
in like a perform, prepare for segue or something like that,
then my mapView wouldn't be wired up yet.
So I don't want this to fail, I just want you to do nothing.
So that's why I'm doing MapView?. Okay and
then we have the addWaypoints, private func addWaypoints and
this one is going to take an array. Waypoints,
which is an array of these GPX.Waypoint objects. Okay,
so what do we wanna do in addWaypoints?
Well, we just want to add them as annotations. So I'm just
gonna say addAnnotations, these waypoints, right?
MapView, the other thing I'm gonna do is there's a way in
the MapView to say, show me all of these annotations.
You say showAnnotations, showAnnotations, and
it takes some annotations, and
I'll just give those same waypoints. And
I'll say animated true, and
what this will do is zoom the map to show these annotations,
okay. Now, a couple errors here. What are these errors?
Cannot convert value of array of GPS Waypoint to
expected argument which is array of MKAnnotation.
Ha! Right I said that the mapView takes MKAnnotations,
and these are GPS Waypoints. They're not MKAnnotations. But
we can easily turn a GPX Waypoint into an MKAnnotation
as long as we get it to implement those three methods,
right? So how are we gonna do that? Well let's create
another little file and we're just gonna add protocol
conformance via an extension which I talked about earlier
in the quarter but we haven't seen it actually happen. So
here I'm gonna create a Swift file.
I'm gonna call it mkgpx because it's MK annotated,
map kit stuff having to do with this GPX class right
here. And I'm going to import MapKit, MK, yeah MapKit.
All right, and what am I gonna do,
I'm gonna create an extension to GPX.Waypoint, and
it's going to implement the protocol MKAnnotation.
That's what this extension is going to do. So
this is how we can implement a protocol via an extension.
Okay now all you need to do is implement these things.
Remember there's coordinates that we have to do which is
a CLLocationCoordinate2D. We have to implement title, which
is a String, optional but we have to implement it and
then there's subtitle which can be any subtitle
information we want, okay, which is also a String.
So we just have to implement these three things and
then we will have successfully,
added the MKAnnotation conformant to Waypoint.
So how are we going to implement these things?
Okay well coordinate this is not coordination this is
coordinate okay? The coordinate is easy to
implement because the GPXWaypoint knows latitude and
So I'm just gonna create a new LocationCoordinate2D okay, and
longitude.
it's gonna have latitude which is the latitude,
it's green there, you see? Because it's a var,
in this class, and then longitude. Okay, so
that was easy. How about the title?
Well, all these GPX Waypoints have that name, so
I'm just gonna return the name of the GPX Waypoint and
then they also have this thing called info, which is just
kind of information about the Waypoint.
That would be a good subtitle, okay? So just like that I've
turned GPX Waypoints into MKAnnotations and
this is how you use the map. You take usually something
you already have and make it implement this.
Now you could create a new class that all it does
is implement MKAnnotation that's fine too, but
generally, usually have something lying around that
you can turn into an MKAnnotation. And
notice as soon as I do that, no more errors here, okay,
because this is now an array of MKAnnotation, okay,
all right. So let's go ahead and run this,
see what happens, lets go here, iPhone6, run,
see if it can open this GPX file up and
show us these waypoints. Up, sure enough there it is,
and it even did that showAnnotations right here,
okay. That zoomed to where it is so
it's showing all the annotations
it found in that GPX file. Let's see if we can see where
we are here. Zoom out. Looks like we are in what, what is,
anyone know where that is? Recognize that coastline?
Canada! Yeah, there's the United States, here's Canada.
Okay? So here we are, we got these things in Canada. Now,
if we click on some of these. Let's click on some,
see what happens. So I click, notice we get the name and
the info right. The title and the subtitle got it.
Now I happen to know that this GPX file has URLs of photos
that were taken at all of these locations, okay?
So the next thing we'd like to do is see those. Okay and
what I'm gonna try to do is put them as a thumbnail image
inside my left accessory view of these call outs.
Now to do that we're going to need to override or implement
that method viewForAnnotation. Notice we didn't implement
viewForAnnotation which is like self erode index path,
and when you don't you get this really simple call
out that has no left or right accessory view,
just has the title or subtitle, okay.
But we need to implement it so we can put a left accessory
view which is going to be a button. I'm gonna have it be a
button because I'm gonna want to be able to click on it in
and segue to show me the image later in the demo probably
next lecture. All right, so how are we gonna do this?
Well we have to implement that method viewForAnnotations.
So let's see if we can find it. There it is, okay.
MKMap viewForAnnotation, okay? It's asking us to provide
an annotation view for this annotation. So first, I'm
going to see if I can get it, and I'm actually gonna do
something kind of interesting here. I'm going to type this.
Now, normally you would say why are you putting a type
here. Because you could just say view equals something and
it would automatically infer the type. Well the reason is
cuz I want it to be implicitly unwrapped. Okay if I didn't
put this here, okay, then it would be an optional
because the thing I'm going to call returns an optional, but
I want it implicitly unwrapped so
the rest of my method method looks like.
The code and the rest of my method. Okay so
I'm gonna do here. I'm gonna ask the MapView to dequeue
a reusable annotationView with an identifier.
Now to be nice I have some constants, so
let's put them on the bottom here. Okay so
here's my constants that I have and I have a constant for
the reuse identifier here. Call it waypoint and say
Constants.AnnotationViewReuse- Identifier.
Okay, so that's de-queueing it.
Now what if this is the first pin it's ever doing? It's not
going to be able to de-queue. There's no pins to reuse.
There's none that were used and
are now left over. So now we're gonna have to say if
the view Equals nil we have to create this thing because
there's no prototypes like table view. So I'm going
to create the thing by saying I want an MKPinAnnotationView.
And the arguments to initialize here
are the annotation which is this annotation right here.
That's the annotation we're creating a view for. And
we wanna use the same ReuseIdentifier right here,
because in future, we want this one that we're creating
to be in the reuse queue, okay? And
I'm also gonna say that we can show callouts.
Okay, because by default, I believe,
if you create an MKPinAnnotationView,
it won't show the callouts when you click on it.
So I wanna make sure it does show the callouts,
cuz that's where my left accessory view is gonna be.
Otherwise, if I was able to dequeue one here then I need
to change the annotation in it to be this annotation here.
Okay? All right,
now we've got this view, this is basically exactly what's
happening if we don't implement this method. Okay?
And in fact, if I run this, if I just return this view and
run it, you're gonna see it looks exactly the same,
okay the system basically will do exactly this for you. See?
If you don't implement it okay? So it's doing exactly
the same thing. So now,let's add this left annotation view
which wants to be a ui button. So how are we gonna do that?
Okay well, let's just first of all let's set the left
leftCalloutAccessoryView to be nil. I'm just going to put
this little button in there if the GPS point has a photo.
If it doesn't have a thumbnail image,
I don't want that button to
be there empty. So, first of all,
I'm going to clear it out.
Then I'm going to say if I can get the waypoint, which I
should be able to because it's just the annotation
As a GPX waypoint, right? That's what the waypoint is.
This annotation, all of our annotations are that. So
as long I'm able to get that waypoint,
which I should be able to, then if the waypoint has
a thumbnail URL, if that doesn't equal
nil Now this is something I'm gonna have to implement okay.
Because it doesn't have that method, so
I'm going to have to implement that method.
Then, I'm gonna set my left column so AccessoryView
to be a UI button. Whose frame is this constant.
Unfortunately I have to do a constant here for
this and I'll show that in a second. The constant for
this is 59 by 59. This is one of the few cases
in IOS where you're gonna use a magic number. But
unfortunately, they're just doesn't seem to be anyway,
at least that I've ever found, to ask the map views and
notation view how big is your call-out so that I can make
the thing the right size. So, I just Know that 59 by
59 works. I hope Apple doesn't change the size of that
callout in the future, cuz it might break this code.
That's why you never want magic numbers,
but unfortunately, we're kind of stuck with one here.
So, we have this error because thumbnailURL is not
implemented. So, how are we gonna implement thumbnailURL?
Well, I told you that every GPX waypoint can have
a number of links associated with one of them,
one of my view thumbnailURL. So
I'm gonna go back to my MKGPX right here and
I'm gonna add this var thumbnailURL, which
is gonna be an NSURL. And this is gonna be optional because,
it might be that it doesn't have one. Which is fine,
now I just want to show this little side button. And
to implement this, I'm gonna implement a little method
here, a private func, which goes through the links and
tries to find one of the type thumbnail. So it's gonna be
called getImageURLofType. It's gonna take a certain type,
which is just a string like thumbnail or something like
that. And it's going to return an NSURL possibly if
you can find such a thing, and
I'm just gonna go through the links in the GPXWayPoint. And
if the links type equals the type am asking for then am
just gonna return the links URL, and if I can't do any of
that I'll return nil. Okay? So this gets an ImageURLofType,
so here I'm gonna get the ImageURLofTyp.
So if it's able to get a thumbnail image, woo hoo,
we're good to go, otherwise it'll be returning nil here.
While I'm here I'm gonna have another one called imageURL
which gets the URL of the image large.
Okay, not a thumbnail of it, but a big, large image of it.
And so, that's the type large. Okay, so these are just types
associated with that link in the GPX file, okay? So
now we have these, we can go back here, and do this now.
Notice that we, Sorry.
[LAUGH] Create this leftCalloutAccessoryView here.
I'm actually gonna give this some space, but
we don't actually set the button's image. And
I'm not gonna set that image until the user clicks on me.
Okay? Soon as they click on my pin annotation view,
it makes our callout accessory
is gonna come up. Then I'm gonna go get the image.
Cuz getting the image is gonna be expensive.
Cuz I'm gonna go get it off the internet somewhere. Okay?
So let's do that and we do that in this method here
called did select annotation view.
Okay, so mapview delegate method here tells us when this
annotation view was selected. And so I'm gonna have to
extract some things here, like I need to get that thumbnail
image button from the left accessory view. That's just my
left call out accessory view and it better be a ui button.
So I'll that's what I'm doing if let here.
I'm also going to get the url which is the gpx waypoint
which is the annotation as a gpx waypoint okay?
It's it's thumbnail URL that method we just implemented.
Okay, I also need to get the image data.
Now I'm gonna be a really bad man here and I'm going
to do this on the main queue okay. Blocks main queue.
You would never do this in your final projects for
example okay. And now, I'm going to get the UI image that
corresponds to that data. All right?
So now I've run the gauntlet of all of these if lets and
I have the image and I have the thumbnail image button,
so I'm just gonna say thumbnail image button.
SetImage to be that image for the State. Remember
buttons have different states like highlight and state and
whatever so I don't want the normal state which is kinda
the default state, okay. So let's go and run that.
Right, here we go, a click on it and sure enough now we're
getting this thumbnail in here To that, okay? So
that's all we have time for today.
What we're gonna do next time is I'm gonna click on this
button, and we're gonna Segway to the image view controller
we have in Kissimmee. It's gonna Segway and
show us the full size image, the large image of that thing.
So once you have segue. Then, we'll go on and do some more
stuff to show off some other little features. All right?
So, see you next time. >> For
more, please visit us at stanford.edu.