[MUSIC]
Stanford University. >> Okay, well,
welcome to Stanford CSI93P Spring of 2016.
This is our last normal lecture.
The only lecture we have left is our alternate final, next
week. Today we are going to have a demo of all the stuff I
talked about on Monday. So, mostly that's segues.
Including ma, modal segue, popover segue, unwind segue.
And even we'll talk about the adaptive presentation,
how we adapt to horizontally compact, all that stuff. And
I'll throw a little bit of bonus in there.
We'll talk a little about visual effects, like Blur.
You'll see a lot of Blur in the UI occasionally and
I'll show you how to basically do that. And
I think that's gonna take most of the time but
if I have any time left like maybe five or
ten minutes left I'll try to do a quick tour through
persistence because creating files in the file system,
stuff like that is something a lot of people are gonna wanna
do in their final project. So I'll try and cover that. No
demo for that unfortunately, but at least maybe I can get
through the slides if the demo goes on a good pace, okay?
So here's our demo those all the things we're gonna cover.
So it's quite a quick demo, it, it, or
quite a involved demo. It's gonna be an extension of Trax,
okay, the thing that we left off with last time.
I'll run that really quick just to remind yourself,
in the last two days, what it did. So, remember that it went
out on the Internet, it grabbed a GPX file, which is
just basically a file that contains a bunch of waypoints
and possibly hyperlinks attached to the waypoints.
And it puts them on the map here so
we can scroll around and zoom in and out on them. And
we made it so that if we clicked on them,
the callout had a left accessory callout
view right here, this left accessory callout view.
And put a thumbnail that it found in the GPX file for
each waypoint, okay? So now, what we'll do today,
the next thing we're gonna do is learn how to segue from
a map, because it's a little unusual trying to segue from
a map because when you look at it in the storyboard it's
just blank, this big blank map view,
so that you can't, it's not like a table view where you
got a row you can Ctrl+drag from or something. So
we're gonna have to do this segueing from a map in code.
And what we're gonna do is make it so that when we
click on this little thumbnail button right here, it segues,
okay. And puts an image view controller that will show you
the full large image of this. And we're gonna get the UI for
doing that imagery control,
we're just gonna steal that right out of Cassini. I mean,
you're gonna see the advantage of building these MVCs that
have very clear public models. It makes them quite reuseable.
So we can reuse that MVC we made in Cassini with
absolutely no changes. Gonna just drag it in and
set up its public API and it'll work perfectly. So
let's go do that right now, let's go over to Cassini.
And where is Cassini? It's here in Developer > Cassini.
We open Cassi, Cassini here. So remember, you'll
remember Cassini here. And we, it's the one that showed the,
the image of Cassini, what it was doing. So
I'm just gonna grab this ImageViewController,
right here, this class ImageViewController. And
I'm gonna pick it up and drag it into my app over here and
I'm gonna copy it in, okay? But I can do actually more
than that, more than just grabbing that MVC,
I can actually go to the storyboard and find the place
in the storyboard, down here actually, where Casini is
using the ImageViewController. And I can copy that scene from
Casini and then bring it on over to our storyboard here.
We'll zoom out so you can see this. Okay, and we can paste.
And that actually dropped an ImageViewController there,
with the scroll view already in it and wired up. And
it has the proper identity, right, ImageViewController, so
it's all really nice. So don't forget that, in storyboards
you can copy and paste scenes between storyboards and
it'll bring it all.
And it brings it all by name, remember, so
you have to have the classes with the same name or
outlets with the same name for it all to work. Okay, so let's
go ahead and build the rest of our UI that we have here.
We want to segue from this map view over to this scroll
view, but we don't really anything to Ctrl+drag from
here cuz of the callouts and things like that are all come
up from programmatically. So we're gonna do a manual
segue, which we've already seen and the way we do that is
we Ctrl+drag from the View Controller itself just to
create a segue with a certain identifier, okay, between
the two MVCs. So let's just get these both on screen here.
And I'm gonna Ctrl+drag from here over to here.
We're gonna put this inside the navigation controller.
So this is gonna be a show segue right here.
And we'll give it a name. This is gonna show an image, so
we'll call this Show Image segue. Let's be sure to go
ahead and embed this in a Navigation Controller. Okay,
oops, so let's zoom out and take a look at our UI. So
here's our UI. We could even do some other things like here
I'd maybe this, we wanna give it a title, we'll call it
Trax, or something like that. And this title we'll set
programmatically depending on which waypoint we're
looking at, we'll put whatever the name of that waypoint is
so we'll do that in the code. All right, so how are we gonna
in at the top,
fire off this segue right here from the code?
Where's a good place to do it in the code? Well,
we know we wanna do it when we click on that left accessory
view button right there. And if you'll remember from
lecture, there's a really cool map view, MKMapViewDelegate
method, I'm just back here in GPXViewController
here. So this is a really cool MapViewDelegate method
that will get called when an accessory view is tapped on
and that accessory view is a UI control like
a UI button, for example. All right, so let's put that in
here. That thing is called a callout accessory, there it
is, MapView, annotationView, calloutAccessory view Tapped,
okay? Let's give ourselves a lot more room here.
This is this method. And all we need to do here is look at
the control that was tapped, and see if it's our left
AccessoryView, okay? So if the control == our views,
leftCalloutAccessoryView, okay, then we know someone
tapped on that left side. And we wanna do this segue, and
we know how to perform a segue from clo, from code.
We just do performSegueWithIdentifier.
Okay, the identifier is that "Show Image", I actually
created a constant for that right here, okay just so
my code would be nice. So constants.ShowImageSegue.
And what about the sender? Well, when this segue happens,
we're gonna need to know which of our many waypoints we wanna
show the image of, okay. So we need to pass a sender on
to prepareForSegue that can identify it.
And a simple thing to do here, okay, this argument
that we get right here is the annotationView. Okay,
that was, that this callout has a left accessory view
for, so we'll just pass that along.
So we'll just pass that as the sender, which makes sense,
the annotationView is the sender.
And from the annotationView, we're gonna be able to get
the waypoint that we want. Okay, so that couldn't
be simpler right there. Now what about the navigation? So
let's put in some navigation here, the prepareForSegue.
Because any segue needs to be prepared. In this case,
we're going to have to prepare that ImageViewController with
its public API, which, if you'll remember,
is an image URL. We have to give it the URL of an image,
okay? So prepareForSegue, let's do that,
prepareForSegue. And what do we need for prepareForSegue?
Well, first of all, let's collect some information here,
like, let's get the destinationViewController.
That's the segue's destinationViewController.
And actually, I'm gonna do that contentViewController
trick that we did where we have a little extension,
contentViewController here,
a little extension to UIViewController.
So that if the thing is in a Navigation Controller,
we return the visibleViewController,
otherwise we just return self. You remember this from From
before, this is so that if we're in a split view and
we happen to put the detail, for example,
inside a navigation controller,
we can get the thing that's inside. All right, so
we'll do the content view controller. Here, so
that's the destination of, this, segue.
Let's get the annotation view, which is the sender,
okay this sender any object, should be an annotation view,
so let's go ahead and get that.
By saying the sender as an MKAnnotationView. Okay.
Let's also get the waypoint that we're talking about here.
Okay, all these segues are gonna be segueing from
something that has a waypoint. So what is that?
That's gonna be the annotationViews annotation.
And it has to be a gpx waypoint, which they all
should be. All the annotations that we add to our map view
implement the MK protocol, so they're all gpx waypoint.
So this should always come out true.
So we kinda got these little things that we need.
So now lets just say if the segway identifier equals
the Constants.ShowSegue, ShowImageSegue, okay?
So we know we're going the show image. Then if we can get
an ImageViewController as the destination, so
if the destination is an ImageViewController,
then we can just load it up by saying it's imageURL equals
the waypoints.
Image URL, right remember image URL,
we added that when we put this little extension on here that
did the thumbnail URL we also added the image URL. Its just
gonna look in the gpx file information to find an image
url that's got the type large verse the type thumbnail.
Okay? Cuz we obviously wanna show the large image,
when we segue to it. All right? All right, so
that's good. While we're here, let's go ahead and
set the title of this, thing to be the waypoint's name. So
that'll give us a nice title at the top,
of our MVC. Okay? Makes sense? All right so
let's go to run see what this does. See if it works for us?
All right, so here is all of our little waypoints here. So
let's click on waypoint, like this one, still working okay,
we got the picture in here but now hopefully if we click on
this, we'll seque. Sure enough here we go. My image view
controller is not quite as nice as the one you did in
your homework in terms of the white space management but
it works. Notice it's got the title up here as well.
The title of this thing, Panorama,
got passed along there. Okay, so that was pretty easy.
The next thing we're gonna do is make it so
that in our map here, we can add a waypoint.
Now, this is a demo, I'm not gonna go so far as to actually
rewrite the gpx file to add this waypoint to it, but I'm
gonna show you how to at least add the waypoint to the map.
Now, the UI I'm gonna use here is long press.
I don't know if you've seen a long press gesture, but
basically if you just press with your finger and
you hold it down long enough,
it'll start looking like a long press, to iOS.
And when you long press, I'm gonna drop another pin there.
A new pin. It's gonna be a new we, new waypoint. All right so
let's put that in our UI first,
let's go, back here to our story board and
we're just gonna add a long press gesture to this map, so
i'm gonna go over here down to this, I'll even search for it
and make it even easier, long press. Here it is right here,
so I'm gonna add this long press the map view is the one
that is gonna recognize it right there, to it.
And now we're go ahead and make this long press send
action to our con, view controller. So let's get them
on the screen at the same time here. All right go automatic.
Okay we'll put it let's put it right down here. Okay? So
I'm just gonna Ctrl+drag from the long press gesture
into here. Its going to be an action, we will call this Add
wayPoint because that is what this gesture is going to do,
its going to add a waypoint. OK, lets go ahead and
go back here. All right, so we have got Add waypoint right
here. What do we need to do when we add a waypoint?
Well, first we're going to do it as soon as we
recognize the long press. So soon as it
starts recognizing this long press, we're going to do it.
Now a long press is actually a continuous gesture.
If you hold the long town press down,
it'll keep firing. Okay fire over and over and
over. We don't want that we don't want to add
a whole bunch of waypoints we just want the first one.
So as soon as we recognize that it's a long press
we're gonna drop the waypoint and we don't care what happens
with the press after that we're ignoring. Okay?
So we've got to get the coordinate
okay that CL coordinate 2d right the latitude and
longitude of this thing that's dropped. And to do that,
we're gonna have to take the coordinate from the gesture,
which is a view coordinate, and turn it into longitude and
latitude. Well luckily Mapview knows how to do that,
Mapview has a method called convertPoint,
two coordinate from view, you see it right there,
the first one, Convert point to coordinate from view. So
the point it wants to convert is the gesture recognizers
location in view, okay. And what view?
The map view itself. So
we're gonna get the location to gesture in the map view and
we're going to turn it into a coordinate and the coordinates
we're, converting from is the map view also. Okay.
So now we've got the latitude and longitude that the long
press happened at. So now let's create a wave point, and
we're going to do that by just saying GPX.wavepoint, latitude
and longitude. Right? So the latitude is the coordinates
latitude, and longitude is the coordinates longitude. Right?
This coordinate right here,
that's this coordinate we just created. All right. So we got
a waypoint and we can give the waypoint a name, let's give it
a default name. We'll call it Dropped since we just dropped
this waypoint onto of the map. Now let's go and add that as
an annotation, to the map, and we know that this is legal for
us to do because addAnnotation takes an MKAnnotation and
we know that GPS. Way,
GPX.Waypoint implements the MKAnnotation protocol, so
this is perfectly legal for us to do, right? All right, so
let's go take a look see if this works. All right,
so here we are. I'm just going to let's say right up here is
a little airport here, so let's hold it down and
drop and sure enough, it dropped a pin there, okay.
We drop another one over here, another one over here. Now,
if I click on this, I'm just gonna get dropped. Okay?
Also, what if I put this in the wrong spot and
I wanted to pick it up? 'Kay, there's no way to pick it up
and move it and that's because these pins are not "dragable."
And if you remember from the, la a, slides,
to make a pin dragable you have to take that coordinate,
ma, var, you know we have this coordinate var that we added
when we were implementing MKannotation we added this.
This has to be read and write. To make these things
obviously dragable if they're going to be dragable when they
drop into a new place we need to set the new coordinates.
So we need to have a editable or
one of these that has a get and a set. So
I'm actually going to do that by creating a subclass of
GPX Waypoint called editable ed it a ble waypoint,
okay. It's just gonna sub class GPX.waypoint and
in that sub class I'm gonna make coordinate.
B read right VAR. So coordinate, CL location,
coordinate 2D is gonna have a get and
it's also gonna have the set. Now for the get, I'm just
gonna do super. coordinate. Okay? We should note
that we are overriding this bar from gpx waypoint, okay.
And for the set, we've got this new value which is
a coordinate and I need to put that into the GPXs data
structure which is latitude and longitude right?
So, I'm just gonna say here that,
our latitude equals the new value's latitude and
our longitude equals the new value's longitude.
Okay, so we're setting the latitude and the longitude in
the GPX waypoint from this new coordinate value that we got.
Okay. So, we'll do that. Everybody get that.
Everyone understand what I what I did there?
So, I have this new class now, EditableWaypoint.
Yeah, I probably could have done that here,
put in the extension but it's actually nice as you're
gonna see to have a whole class that we know that this
is an editable waypoint by looking at its class,
actually. All right? Okay, so let's go back now to here, and
instead of creating a GPX waypoint here now when we add
waypoint, I'm gonna create an editable waypoint. Okay.
So that, so that it can be moved around.
Now, the other thing I need to do to make it an draggable
is to go here to where I create my annotation view for
annotation which remember,
is kind of self row index path for map view.
Here's where I create the left call it accessory.
I also need to say whether it's draggable. Okay?
And that's just going to be, whether or not the annotation
that we passed on here is an editable waypoint. Okay?
If annotation is of class editable waypoint,
then we know it's editable, and so it's dragable.
See how giving that in a separate class was kind of
cool? Makes our code read kind of nice there.
All right, so we should be able to drag this around, so
let's see if it works. All right,
so you going to drop one right here, here it is,
we can see this is dropped. Can we pick it up and drag it?
Let's see. Yes, we can put it somewhere else pick it
up again put it over here. Okay so
that's kind of cool. So, now what are we gonna do? Well,
it's kind of annoying that this just says dropped, okay.
We don't want it to say dropped,
we wanna actually edit it and so,
you know if I put it over here on top of this little
airport right here, I probably wanna put airport in there.
Okay? And so how are we gonna do that? Well,
this is a good opportunity to show you a modal segue.
Okay, cuz what we're gonna do is we're gonna create a little
MVC to edit the name and the description there of
the waypoint and we're going to modally present that MVC,
okay? So, how we're gonna do that? Pretty straightforward.
Let's start here by figuring out how we're gonna get
that modal MVC to appear and
what I'm gonna do is you see how I'm using over here
at the left accessory view. Now, I'm gonna use the right
accessory view on these and I'm gonna put a detail
disclosure button in there. That's the little blue kinda
looks like a blue round circle with a carrot in it. So,
I'm gonna put that kind of button in here and only on
that editable way points will I put it there. And
when you click on that, it's going to bring up this modal
panel that lets you edit the name and info. Okay. So, let's
go ahead and do that, let's change our UI to make our UI,
that's how we gonna do that.
We're gonna have to add a RightCalloutAccessoryView.
Just like we added a leftCalloutAccessoryView here,
so I'm gonna do the same thing where I clear it out first
because if it's not at an editable waypoint we don't
want it in there. And remember we're reusing these things,
right? DQ reusable. So, we have to clear it out from
previous uses. And so, here I'm just gonna say,
if the waypoint is an EditableWaypoint,then I need
to add this rightCallout AccessoryView which is just
going to be a UIButton(type: .DetailDisclosure).
Okay, so I'm just going to put it on.
This is only going to appear on editable ones which is
exactly what we want. Now, how do we make it so that it's
going to Do this modal segue whenever we're gonna do it.
We're gonna do the exact same way that we did for
the left call-out accessory, which is what we're gonna do
it in this call-out accessory control tapped.
Okay, cuz now this the right side one. So, I'm gonna say
else if the control equals the right call-out accessory view.
Okay? Then, I need to perform a segue, the different one.
This one's gonna be called, let's see what I call down
here in the constance. I call it edit way points,
the Edit user way points segway, right? Edit user way
points and the sender still gonna be the view because we
still wanna know which way point we're editing, okay? And
of course, we have to fix or prepare for segway to do that
as well. Let's take a time out from doing our prepare for
segue and go into our storyboard and add that new
MVC. All right, so here we are, I'm going to make this
a little zoomed out a little bit. So,
I'm going to put this new view controller just by dragging
out an empty view controller on to the top up here.
This is where we're going to put this thing.
It's of course, going to need it's own Custom Class so lets
go file New. Create a subclass of UI View Controller. Okay.
We'll call this our Edit Waypoint View Controller
because that's what it does. Edit a waypoint.
I'll put it same place as everything as usual.
Here it is, we'll go ahead and get rid of all this stuff.
Yeah, so that's clean. Let's go ahead and build the ui of
it, okay what's the ui of this thing gonna look like here?
Well, it's gonna be a pretty simple UI,
it's gonna have two fields, one for
the name of the waypoint and one for like the info, right,
the little description of the waypoint. So,
that's gonna be easy to build, let's just go down here and
grab a text field or two, there's one text field,
there's another one, let's grab a couple labels okay for
our name and description. So, all right so
this is the name of the waypoint.
This is the description of it which is called the info field
in the GPX structure. So, we'll right align these
because they're gonna be names. We'll go ahead and
put these in a stack view here. So, let's embed these in
a stack view. Hopefully it'll figure out it's horizontal.
It does. We'll put a little spacing in there,
maybe eight or something like that.
Same thing here, let's put those in. Okay.
Also, eight. Now, let's put these in vertical stack view.
Okay, maybe we'll also do 8 here as well.
Okay. Now, these aren't quite looking like what we want,
this, this kind of, this is in the center.
We don't really want center alignment here,
we'd like it to fill the entire space. Also,
we'd really want this and this lined up, which really means
we want Name and Description to be the same width. So,
I'm actually going to control drag between these two and
make them be equal widths, okay? Make name and
description be equal widths and also it's gonna,
let me take it back in a second here I think.
Let's also put it in position.
We're gonna put this leading edge, we're gonna put this
the top edge, we'll put this to the trailing edge and
we'll put this to the bottom edge. Okay? Now, where we
put these is a little weird. Okay, this one is our standard
thing here where we want this to be zero or standard value.
So, there's no standard value so we'll make it zero.
That makes it nice and wide. That's good. This one right
here, I actually don't want this one to be zero cuz
I really want name and description to sit at the top.
So, you might argue I don't even need a constraint on
the bottom here, but here's the thing when I put this
on screen, okay the size is gonna change I always wanna
make sure there's at least the standard issue thing from
the bottom. Get a standard space from the bottom and
you'll see why that is a little bit later. So,
I'm actually have the constant here be greater than or
equal to the standard value. Okay,
so just remember that I put a constraint on the bottom to
make sure it's greater than or equal to the standard value.
We we'll see that later. So,
equal widths. Thought I had done that. Okay, anyway, so
this looks pretty good for our UI, okay? Using the space,
etc. It's kind of lining things up nicely. So
let's go ahead and create a couple of outlets to pl,
plug into these two things, all right. Let's
make sure we set the right class for this. We don't want
to be in GPS Waypoint view controller, we wanted to be in
Edit Waypoint view controller. That's why we're not getting
the right class here when we try to do our list.
Let us drag our outlay here.
This outlay is going to be NameTextField. And
this one is going to be, call this the infoTextField.
All right? And so we kinda set up our UI here how we want it.
What do we wanna do here in terms of a let's
make this over here. Let's look at our edit wave.
Okay, what do we want to do in terms of a public model here,
so that people can set it?
Well, that's obvious, we want the a- waypoint to edit. 'Kay?
GPX, sorry, editable waypoint. Let it be optional.
So that's the public API. If someone sets this waypoint
then obviously we're going to have our UI show it. And when
the UI is changing, it's going to be changing this way point.
So, when it gets set, we're gonna have to update your,
our UI. So we'll call updateUI and make a method that does
that. Probably here when these well we'll talk about
that in a second, so let's get our private funk update ui.
So what do we do to update the ui?
I'm just gonna have the name, text fields, text equal
the waypoint to edit name.
And similarly the info text field Text equals
the Way PointTo Edit info. Okay. So
that's updating that. Probably also we should View Did Load.
And View Did Load will also update our UI.
That way when we're sequeway to it or
something if we set this before our outlets are set,
later on or. Now this is great for transferring information
from the waypoint to our text fields.
What about the other way? We edit in the text fields,
we have to edit our waypoint. So how are we going to that?
Well, there's actually a number of ways
to do that. I already showed you
in textfield how to do that with delegate messages.
I'm gonna show you how to do it now with radio stations.
Okay? Text fields actually broadcast on a radio station,
and one of the things they'll broadcast is my text changed.
So you can listen to that radio station, and
every time the text changes you can update whatever
thing you want to update. Now, before we do that, we
also need some things from the text fields delegate, however.
Like, I'd like to control the keyboard a little bit.
So, every time you press return in the keyboard,
I'd like to remove the keyboard,
just to clear it out of your way. So, how may I do that?
I'm gonna make sure that I am the main text fields delegate.
Okay so let's go ahead and
make sure we are a UI text field delegate.
Do the same thing with the info text field here.
All right, so now with the delegate.
What are we going to do here on that famous text
field should return target method right here.
I'm just gonna say text field, resign your first responder.
'Kay. And I'll return true,
'cause it can do whatever it wants there.
We don't have, you're not gonna have any action setups.
That's not gonna matter anyway. And, in fact,
another thing I'd like is when this NDC first appears,
I'd like to keyboard to appear. Okay I wanted it to
come up don't want to make the person touch in there.
So I'm gonna say let's do the name text field. Become
first response responder. Okay so that means when we reload,
we're gonna become the first responders.
Question. >> Sir,
did you say that the textfield should
return because this one said the textfieldShouldReturn?
>> Good catch, okay so
this is not supposed to be textfieldShouldClear,
this should be textfieldShouldReturn.
Okay, good catch, that's why you guys are here to catch
these mistakes. Yeah, so there we go, textfieldShouldReturn.
All right, so that's gonna manage our keyboard, but
now what about those radio stations? So let's go ahead,
and when, our view appears on screen, okay?
When we get viewDisappear,
we're gonna start listening to those radio stations. And
when we get viewWillDisappear, then we'll stop listening, all
right? So viewWillappear, or else you can do viewDidappear.
Super.viewDidAppear(animated).
All right. So we got viewDidAppear,
and so I am just going to say listenToTextFields Okay,
we'll make a little private func that does that. Okay,
so how we gonna listen to the text fields? Let's go ahead
and get ourselves the center, okay, the NSNotification,
NotificationCenter.defaultCen- ter. And
let's get the q that we want, we're going to do all of this
on the main Q. So ns operation q dot main q. All right now
that we have those two things, two little variables here,
I'm going to ask the center to listen to this radio station.
So I'm going to add observer for name. Return here, so
you can see this again, this is what we did last time.
All right, what's the name of the radio station?
It's UITextFieldTextDidChange, you can see it's got a couple
of other radio stations there too for begin end editing, but
I'm gonna get the one where every time the text change.
Every single character It's going to update.
The object here okay this one I'm gonna be listening to
the Name text field. Okay, and
we'll do it on the main queue. And here's the block.
So what's our block going to do here? We actually don't
even need to look at the notification, because we know
this is the Name text field right here this change. So
I'm just gonna say here, if I can let waypoint equal our
waypointToEdit, so if our waypointToEdit is not nil,
basically, then let's go ahead and
have the waypoint's name equal the nameTextFields.text,
all right? So every time this nameTextField changes,
we're going to update, our name. Okay. And
this needs to be self, because we're inside of closure here.
Okay, we'll do the exact same thing for the info text field.
One thing we could have done by the way, is have the object
we're listening to be nil and get all UI text and
then look at the text field that is sending it to us and
find out which one it is. But, what if we had other text
fields, other places in our UI that were listening, and
maybe they weren't good and that they kept listening even
when they were off screen, and all that getting all these.
This is a little bit more code in terms of alliance
right here, but it makes these closers really,
really, really simple. Okay? So, this is gonna be
the inform text field, update, now in viewDidAppear here,
we're listing the textfields, in viewWillDisappear,
We need to stop listening to these, okay so how do we do
that, okay we just ask the notification center.
DefaultCenter() to remove the Observer,
okay, that is this guy right here.
And same thing, we'll have to do another one for this.
So this is where we have to use the return value of this
addObserverForName. It actually returns something.
We'll call this one ntfObserver.
And this is just basically a cookie that represents
this radio station going here. So
we'll need a couple of private vars here. ntfObserver.
These things are of type NSObjectProtocol. Which
basically just means they're Objective-C compatible things,
they're part, they're visible to the Objective-C runtime.
Okay, and so we'll have info text field observer also.
Okay, so we'll let the ntfObserver equal that,
we'll have the itfObserver equal this. Okay, now
that we have these cookies, we, we wanna remove them here,
okay? We can just put them in here. But we wanna make sure
they're not nil, so I'm gonna say if I can let observer
equal the ntfObserver, then I will remove that observer.
And same thing down here. If I can let observer
equal to itfObserver,
then I will move that. Probably
could have made a nice little function that did this, so
that I don't have this kind of same repeated code style here.
Also, actually probably want to put these in another
private func. Maybe call it private func
stopListeningToTextFields. Put that in there, and
we'll call that from here. Okay? Arrange this
a little bit better. Put this down here. Okay, so basically,
listening and stop listening. So everyone understand that?
See how we're using radio stations to find out what's
happening in the text fields?
So it's kind of a, a fun way to do that. All right,
so the last thing we need to do here is our prepare for
segue, right? Over here, we, when we do this other segue,
this segue, this modal segue, we need to prepare for it. So
let's do that. Say else if segue.identifier ==
EditUserWaypoint. Okay, that's the name of that, identifier.
Then in here we just wanna get that editable waypoint.
So I'm gonna see if I can
let the editableWaypoint equal the waypoint as
an EditableWaypoint, so make sure it's editable. It always
should be or we wouldn't be here. Let's put a comma here.
Then we can let our editable Waypoint view controller
equal the destination as EditWaypointViewController.
Okay, then we just set the EWVC's waypointToEdit, which
is its public model there, to the editableWaypoint, okay?
Now let's go back to our storyboard here and
take a look at how we're going to create the segue
right here. Because right now, there's no segue,
this thing is free as a bird out here flying around, okay?
So we want to edit it, so we're gonna do the same thing
we did here when we created this one, which is,
to drag from the, view controller, oops,
not that one, from this view controller right here.
We're gonna drag from this guy up to our new MVC.
So let's do that. Ctrl+drag up here. Now, this time though,
we're gonna do something new. This one's gonna be presented
modally. So instead of saying show and
having it appear inside this navigation controller,
we're gonna do present modally and it's gonna take over
the whole screen while we're editing the waypoint.
So we do present modally. Now let's go ahead and
take a look at this, sorry, let's make this a little
easier to see here. Okay. Let's go ahead and take a look
at this segue that was just created in the inspector.
Okay, so you obviously will need an identifier.
I think I called this one Edit Waypoint.
I hope that's what I called it. Let's go take a quick
look, make sure we get it right in our constants. Yes,
Edit Waypoint. That's what we called this segue right there.
And you can see it's got Present Modally here,
okay? And we'll take a look at these presentation styles down
here a little bit later. Okay? But for right now,
we just wanna present modally. So let's go ahead and
see what this does. All right, so
here we go, we're gonna drop an editable waypoint, okay?
It says Dropped, we can pick it up and move it, okay,
to anywhere we want, like to that airport again. And
hopefully, we press this i, we're gonna get this
modal segue to this new MVC. So hit the i, there we go,
modal segue. Now, we've got some problems here.
Looks like we've got a little problem with our
auto layout there. We'll have to take a look at that. And
in fact, we've gotta fix that, or we're not gonna be able to,
to edit this. So let's go back to our storyboard here and
take a look at what the problem,
probably was that thing where I said same width.
Somebody has the same width who shouldn't, I believe.
Maybe one of these stack views.
Let's take a look at this guy. So I'm just gonna,
when you get a problem with your auto layout,
it's kind of a good idea to make a little tour through
your various things.
You can even see, I've got red here, conflicting constraints,
so we know there's problems. And sure enough, look at this.
When I said, tried to make the description equal to the name,
I made this whole stack view equal to the name.
You see that? Equal width to name, this whole stack view,
so that's not good. So I don't want this, so I'm just gonna
delete that constraint. And now this has probably fixed
the problem, because you see I have no more warning
of conflicting constraints. Okay? So let's go try again,
see if that makes our UI look a little better. All right.
We'll drop here. Edit. That looks a lot better.
Okay. And you can see that it passed from the prepare for
segue, it passed our existing name and info,
which is just dropped with no info, into here. And
it also put the keyboard up, was nice. And if I get rid of,
hit return, it makes the keyboard go away. And
if I make one of these first responder, it comes back.
All right. And I can edit this.
Let's say, I'll say, I love it when people, do something,
okay. And how about, the fact is your name.
Okay, so here's our basically name of our waypoint and
the description. And so, uh-oh, how do we get out of
here? It's like, we can't get out. So this is a problem I
was telling you about. Modal, you have to provide a way for
your user to escape once they've edited whatever they
want to edit. Okay? So how are we gonna do that? Let's go
back to our storyboard. The simple way to do it
is to put this inside a navigation controller and
put a done button up there like we saw in the slides.
So let's do that. Let's go here,
Edit > Embed In > Navigation Controller,
it puts it in a navigation controller right here. And
we're just gonna put a Done button right there.
So let's go down here. We'll search for bar button item.
Here it is, a Bar Button Item. We'll put it right up here.
I think there's even a standard system one for that,
maybe. Yeah, there's a Done button right there, okay, for
clicking Done.
And then we'll just make this done button call a method
in this view controller, by the way, so
you can see our stack view frames are a little off now.
We can fix that clicking on here and
doing a update frames, moves that down. But
let's make this so that it sends a message to ourselves,
and then we'll dismiss ourselves. Okay, so
let's do that. We get here, we'll put this.
Let's make it a little more space for you there. Okay,
we'll put that dismiss, how about, I don't know,
right up after our view controller lifecycle here.
Okay? So I'm just gonna Ctrl+drag right in here. This
is gonna be an action. This is my done action, I'll call it.
Okay, BarButtonitem is gonna be the argument. Here it is.
Now remember, again,
let's go twofold width here. Remember, here,
we don't want to say just dismissViewControllerAnimated.
We want to get our presentingViewController.
That's the view controller that presented us and
ask it to dismiss us, okay. And we don't care when that
happens. Okay, so don't forget that.
I'm kind of putting this self here just to let you know I'm
talking about my self's presentingViewController but
you don't need self there obviously,
okay? Understand that? All right, so let's see that.
See how that makes this work. All right,
so we'll drop this. Go here, we'll edit it. Comes up,
we've got our Navigation Controller, it's there.
We probably should have put a title called edit waypoint or
something like that. So let's go ahead and edit this again.
So let's say the best thing. Okay, that's what our name is.
And the description is, the only way. All right, so we got
the best thing and the only way there. And we hit Done.
And it still says, Dropped, okay? Now why is that?
Well, that's because that callout was put up, and
when it's put up, it's loaded up with the waypoint's
information. And it stays that way all the time,
okay? The only time it changes is if it goes away and
comes back. When it comes back, it came back, okay?
Now we got a bug somewhere in our code cuz it should have
our subtitle there. But that was really annoying for
our user that they went and edited this and
when they came back it still said Dropped, okay.
So let's fix the bug so that this the only way,
which I think was the info was yeah, so here we go.
This should be info = the infoTextField,
okay? So how are we gonna fix that? Well, one thing about it
right off the bat is that when we click on this little i,
I'm gonna take this callout off the screen. Because I know
it's pretty much invalid right away because if I go over here
and change this to anything else,
that thing is no good anymore. So let's do that as step one.
Let's just take that callout away when we do this
performForSeg, performSegue. So
let's find where we do that performSegue,
it's in this funny little calloutAccessoryTapped, right?
Here's where we perform that segue.
And when we perform that segue,
we're going to remove that callout when we do that. And
so, we do that by saying mapView.deselectAnnotation
because the reason that callout is up is because this
annotation is selected. So, if we deselect this annotation,
it will remove that callout. And what do we wanna do?
We wanna remove the annotation in the view that our
callout is currently accessory control tapping.
And sure, we'll, we'll animate it, although it probably
doesn't matter that it's animated because we're gonna
put a modal thing right on top of it. But
maybe it'll be fading out as that's sliding in, that might
be kinda nice. Okay, so let's see if that fixes our problem.
All right, here we go. Put this on the airport here.
We'll click there, there's Dropped. We click.
Okay, we go to Dropped. And we'll put something in here.
Say I'm so excited, that's good.
Description, the fact is. Okay, and
we'll hit Done and hopefully, it's not showing it.
So at least it's not saying dropped, so
that's the improvement, right? But if we click on it, it's
showing it. So really what we'd like is when we come back
from that modal segue, we'd like it to put this thing back
up with the new information. Okay, so how are we gonna do
that, cuz we don't know when that modal thing goes away,
okay. It's just getting dismissed, right? So this is
a good opportunity to show you unwind. Okay, so we're gonna,
instead of hitting Done and having it dismiss ourselves,
we're going to do an unwind segue back to
our GPXController. And when it gets that message,
that special message, it'll know I'm gonna put this thing
back up, okay. So let's do that, so how do we do that?
We know that when we unwind, we always wanna create one of
this special methods, okay? And those special methods,
first of all, they're always IBActions, okay?
They can have any name that we want, so we'll call ours
updatedUserWaypoint because that's what happened, okay?
When the unwind happens, the user update waypoint
got updated. And the other thing that's special about it,
the argument has to be a UIStoryboardSegue, okay?
So this is the special method and this is all we need to do
to create one of these special message, methods.
We'll call it a func. All right, and
so now anybody can unwind to this as long as there's
something we presented. Any MVC that we've presented or
that was presented by somebody we presented,
etc., can now unwind back to us here.
Now what are we gonna do when we unbind back to here?
Well, we're gonna reselect that annotation that we
deselected when we left. So let's do that.
I'll create a little function to do that called sec,
selectWaypoint. Okay, and selectWaypoint, we gotta get
the waypoint we selected, it's a little tricky, watch this.
I'm gonna get the segue's sourceViewController. That's
the view controller that is sending us this unwind.
So that's gonna be the modal segue, right?
That's the source of the unwind. So
we're gonna get that sourceViewController.
And actually we'll get its contentViewController,
okay? And it has to be an EditWaypointViewController.
And if we're able to find that,
then we'll just get its waypointToEdit. Okay,
that's obviously the waypoint that we want to select.
So we need to, this method selectWaypoint. Let's do that.
func selectWaypoint takes a waypoint
which is at GPX.Waypoint, point. We'll
even make it optional if you wanna pass it in there. And
we'll just say if the waypoint != nil then we are gonna go
to the mapView and tell it to select an annotation, which is
the waypoint. Okay, remember that all of our waypoints
are annotations, so we can directly ask the mapView. This
is what's really nice about having some data structure
that we already have in our app, like a GPX waypoint,
implement that MK annotation protocol.
Because we're not having to constantly create these other
little things that contain all the waypoint in you know,
the MK notation information, we just get it directly from
our waypoints. Okay, so this is gonna select it.
So now we have to unwind to this instead of doing Done.
So let's go back to our storyboard here. Okay,
we've got this Done. I'm gonna disconnect Done
from this done method, right. So I'm just going here and
disconnecting it. So now it's not gonna send Done. And
in fact, if we go back to our EditWaypointViewController,
we can just delete this done method entirely whenever it
is, oops, there it is. Okay, we're not even gonna use that
anymore. Instead of doing that, we are going to unwind.
So let's go back here and unwind. So, how do we unwind?
Everyone remember? Ctrl+drag to this Exit button. Okay,
this is how you unwind. This is saying I want this Done
button to unwind, okay? To exit this MVC and
go back to one of its presenters. And look, when we
click, look what we see in the list! updatedUserWaypoint.
That method we put there with the special
IBAction in this segue as an argument,
okay? And every method in every MVC we ever
would've put in our entire app that was like that would
appear here. Yeah, question. >> Does the unwind only work
in a Navigation Controller? >> So the question,
does unwind only work inside a Navigation Controller?
And the answer is no, it works anywhere.
So you could have just a non-navigation controller MBC
present another one modally which presents another one
modally, and then you unwind back to either of those two.
So it has nothing to do with navigation controller.
This is not pop you now back or anything.
This is really just take this MBCs off until you get back to
the guy who implements this method, okay?
Now it would work in a navigation controller as well.
It would pop back from that as well, but it works in any
any environment basically. All right so I'm gonna click that
and that's gonna make the done button unwind to that method.
Okay so that method is gonna get called. So let's ugh. We
looking at this method when it happens. Let's go over here.
All right so drop the pin right here gonna click.
It says dropped right here. We're gonna go edit it.
Change it to something here,
how about the fact that you have to,
and we'll call this I'm so
happy, okay? So we're gonna hit done here and hopefully,
we're gonna see that call out, show up,
without having to click on anything and, sure enough,
it does. Okay because it unwind back, called this code
right here which selected that annotation.
This is back in our TPX view controller here, see? Okay,
everybody got the unwind there? All right,
the next segue we're gonna look at is popovers. Okay,
let's take a look at our app on iPad. And
to do this I'm actually gonna do it on my device over here.
So let's go up here, this is device and run this.
We made this to a universal app so it should work fine
over here. Sure enough there it is, zooming in to where we
are, okay. Here's our stuff we can zoom in here and
we can click on these things just like we could before. And
we can segue to see this. Okay all that stuff is nice.
And we can also add new pins, so I'm just long pressing.
There's a pin. Okay, let's click there, okay dropped.
We're going to edit it. Whoa. Okay this is pretty ugly UI.
Okay do not do this in your final project.
I cannot tell you how many final projects
think I've made it work on the iPad with this kind of UI.
Okay, this kind of UI looks ridiculous.
You're never going to have the name and description be that
long, okay. So you don't want that. There are other ways of
presenting modal NBC's that look a lot
better on iPad. So let's go pick one of them, let's go
back to our storyboard here, oops. Let's go back to our
storyboard and we're just gonna change our segue here,
this is the modal segue okay. That puts this thing up,
okay we're gonna inspect it and I'm gonna try a different
presentation like for example form sheet. So form sheet is
much more appropriate for the iPad. So let's go ahead and
run this. See what form sheet looks like. The form sheet
modal presentation. It's just a different presentation than
take over the whole screen.
It still takes over the whole screen,
it just does it a little more space efficiently here.
All right, so I'm dropping a pin there and
we're gonna edit it. And
you can see this gives a much more sensible looking space.
Now the background here on the side, the grey on the side,
okay, is not active. I can't do anything with it so
it's still modal, it's still completely taking over,
it just presenting it a little nicer here. Okay, and I can
still do all the things that I would do here. Ya know, hello.
Okay so, that's nice but, really on the iPad, what would
be really cool is to do it in a little pop over right there.
Okay to have the name, and info just be in that small,
little pop over pointing right at that little pin,
that would be a much better UI. And so it's great because
we can learn how to do pop overs. So lets do that, how
are we gonna do popovers? So a, and when we have a popover
we're not gonna want this Navigation Controller in here,
okay? We'll zoom out so you can see it.
Okay if when we have a popover to do this we wanna get
rid of this Navigation Controller here.
So I'm gonna delete that. So we have this, okay?
Now, I'm just gonnato create a popover in the same way,
as we created all the other ones, okay?
Which is control drag from here up to here. But
this time, I'm gonna choose present as popover. Okay and
this creates this right here and you can see here's the pop
over segue. Now we of course need an identifier for it.
We're going to do the same identifier cause we're
going to have the same prepare segue as we have for
the mog modal one which was edit waypoint. All right.
Notice popover has some extra things down here. Okay, and
this mostly has to do with when I put this popover up,
okay, where do you want it to appear? And part of where
it wants to appear is where you are going to allow
the Popovers little arrow to point, point up, or left, or
down, or right that's gonna to kind of position it a little
bit. In our case we'll let it point any direction.
So, depending on whether your weight point is up in the left
corner, in the right corner,
we'll let the pop over be above it, below it,
whatever the system thinks is best. But the popover also
needs needs an anchor, which is when I come up I've gotta
point at something. And we're not bringing this up with
a bar button, or something we can point to. We're bringing
it up by clicking on this little annotation thing. So,
we really want the anchor to be those pins. Okay so
those pins are in the map view so
I'm going to have the anchor right here be the map view and
then in code I'm going to specify a rectangle in the map
view which contains that little annotation view. So
the way I make the map view be anchor is I Ctrl+Drag
over to this. Okay, from the little circle. Like that and
you can see it puts the map view in there.
So now it's saying okay, I understand that
I'm gonna point up pointing to somewhere in the map view.
In your code you better tell me where and
we're gonna tell you, tell it where, okay?
Okay, okay, all right.
So where are we gonna set that little rectangle, okay?
We're gonna set that in our prepareforsegue, for
this segue, that's where you set up all your popover stuff,
is in the prepareforsegue for that segue.
So here is that part of this prepareforsegue,
write the edit user waypoint, part of the prepareforsegue.
All we're gonna do here is get the popover presentation
controller. So if we can get that, we get it from the MBC
we're presenting. So in this case it's the EWVC, the edit
wavepoint view controller. We get it from that.
And we get it from this method,
pop over presentation controller. Now if we're now
popping over this would be null. This code won't execute,
excellent, okay? But if we're doing a popover, then it will
not be null. So in here we configure the popover
presentation controller and you can go look at the doc,
but one of the things you can do is the source rectangle
that it's gonna point to in your anchor view, okay? And
what is this gonna be? Well that's easy for
us, that's just gonna be the annotation view's frame. Okay,
the frame of the little pin,
that's where we want the popover to point. Make sense?
All right so, so, let's run this, see what it looks like.
All right? So, we'll drop this here, click on it and
whoa! Well, hm, okay we're makin progress but I
don't think we're quite there. So what's wrong with this?
Well, one thing is that thing is huge!
Way bigger than it needs to be! Why is it so big?
The answer is because no one told it what size it was
supposed to be. Okay, and you remember from the slides,
we do this in an object-oriented way.
The system wants the MVC that's being put up to say,
what size do you want to be? Now, what's really cool is,
I'm gonna calculate that size using Auto Layout, okay?
I'm basically gonna say, make yourself as small as you can
and still obey the Auto Layout rules, okay? And you can do
that with one line of code. So it's really cool. All right,
so where am I gonna do that? So I'm gonna do that in my
EditWaypointViewController. Okay,
this is the view controller that's coming up there. So
it's the one responsible for
setting its preferred size. And I'm gonna do it in
the view controller life cycle method viewWillLayoutSubviews.
Okay, so, I know that in viewWillLayOutSubviews,
my balance is gonna be set to whatever the latest thing is.
So I know I'm gonna have some good, bounds situation.
So I'm just gonna, in here, I'm gonna set my,
preferred content size, that's the size that I prefer to be,
to be the following thing,
view dot, okay, and all views implement this cool method,
systemLayoutSizeFittingSize, okay.
So that's basically saying, use Auto Layout and
tell me what size will
fit in this size the best. And there's a really cool size,
predefined size, called the UILayoutFittingSize.
There's a ExpandedSize, which means, make me as big as you
can and obey Auto Layout, and then there's CompressedSize,
which is, make me as small as you can. Okay, so, I'm gonna
go for CompressedSize, okay, and it's going to give me
a size that fits as small as possible using Auto Layout.
Okay, so this is a really cool little method,
it's how you get Auto Layout to calculate a size for you.
All right, so let's see, now that the size is right,
let's go see if that's going to fix things. I don't think
it's gonna be quite right, but it's gonna be close.
All right, here we go, drop a pin. We're gonna click on it,
oops, I clicked on the side of it. Okay, and edit it. Okay,
now, this is really close. Okay, it's really nice.
See how it's making it just the right size?
The problem is, the text editing part is pretty small.
Because look what it did, it sized it to the word Dropped.
Okay, and why did it do that? Because in our Auto Layout,
we didn't tell anything else about what size it should be.
So it put the contents in there, and
it made it as small as possible and fit the contents.
So we actually wanna go back to our storyboard and put
a minimum, reasonable minimum size for those text fields so
that they will give the person room to type something in.
Okay? The other thing is, the background is white.
This may be hard for you to see on that screen. But if you
look where the little arrow is pointing next to the word
description there, that's actually semitransparent.
And then also where the name and
description is is a white box. Okay, so it's actually
possible to have the whole thing be this semitransparent,
so that we can kind of see that we're on top of a map.
It won't feel so kind of obnoxious, this white box. And
the way to do that is just to make this MVC have
a background of clear. Okay, then it's just going to appear
clear on top of the popover's background,
which is semitransparent.
Okay, so we're gonna fix both those things at once.
So we're going back to our storyboard here. Okay, so
we're gonna make it so that these text fields right here,
okay, are a reasonable minimal, minimum size.
So what would be a reasonable minimum size?
Let's go here to our width here and height. And so
we could say a width of maybe, I don't know, 250 points?
This is something that you could play with in your UI.
I really only need to set one of these, because these
are already gonna be the same width. And so
that's gonna force these to be the same width. But actually,
I don't want it to be exactly 250. I want it to be at least
250, okay. Because if the name is really long, and
it'll fit without going off the edge of the screen, sure,
you can do it. So I add the constraint here to be 250.
And you can see that it makes it exactly 250, but
I don't want that. So I'm gonna go over here to my
dimensions inspector and look at this width 250. I'm gonna
edit it and change it to greater than or equal to 250,
okay? So understand that Auto Layout is pretty configurable.
You don't have to make things always be exactly certain
sizes, okay? So we'll go ahead and adjust our frames here.
Okay, got that? Okay, now what about the clear? That's really
simple. I'm just gonna click the background view here,
and instead of having it be white, okay,
this background view, I'm gonna have it be the default,
which is clear. Okay? So let's run it again.
Okay, yes, so that's working.
All right, so let's drop a pin. Okay.
We're gonna edit it, here we go. Boom. Perfect. Okay,
give us a little extra space to work with.
We can see, can you see that?
Yeah, you can see it's kind of a little bit see through.
You can see it's a little bit green behind that, looks a,
a lot nicer. Okay so, excellent.
Wow, popovers are great. I'm sure this didn't do any damage
on the iPhone side. Let's go take a look, okay?
iPhone. Sure the iPhone looks just great.
All right, here it is. We'll drop a pin.
All right, there it is, all right, here we go. Oops.
Ugh. Okay, well, clearly we totally broke, and
understandably, broke our iPhone side of this.
So what's wrong here, what's going on? Well, first of all,
we took it out of the navigation controller, so
we lost our done button, okay? So we're done, okay?
[LAUGH] Second one is, we made the background clear, so
it's looking into the void. Because, we know that when
it adapts, okay, first of all, why is it coming up this way?
Well, the system knows this is horizontally compact, so
it adapted from popover to full screen modal, okay.
Full screen modal completely covers
the thing underneath it, doesn't show anything,
doesn't show through, it completely covers it.
And it covers it with the void, the great void, okay.
And since we're looking clear into the void, it's black,
okay, the void happens to be black. All right, so that's
why this looks so terrible. So what are we gonna do about
this, okay? There's a number of things that we can do
to make this a lot better. So, actually, before we do this,
let's do one other quick thing. I wanna show you one
other quick thing. Let's go back over to our,
look at our iPad here, okay? We're back on the iPad there.
Okay, so when I change this, let's say I change something
here, like, you know, let's change it to, I'm not going,
okay, I'm not going, and I hit return. And now,
how do we dismiss a popover? We just hit somewhere else,
right? So here we go, tap. Look at that. It didn't
show it to us. Remember, when we had it on the iPhone,
when I clicked Done, it showed it. Now it's not showing.
Now, if I click on it, okay, it worked, that's great. But
no, we want it to show just like it did on the iPhone.
So how are we gonna fix that? That's pretty easy to fix.
We're gonna use, over here in our GPX controller,
this same popover presentation controller.
We're going to implement one of its delegate methods.
Okay, so we're going to set ourself as the delegate
of this pop-over presentation controller, which means,
of course, we have to go up here. And say that we
are a UIPopoverPresentationControll-
erDeligate, okay? And that, all right. So we're
PopoverPresentationController- Deligate. Which
PopoverPresentationController- Deligate method are we gonna
implement here? We're gonna implement the one where we
find out that it dismissed, dismiss pop over.
Okay, so this message gets sent to
the pop over presentation controller's delegate,
when the pop over is dismissed. A perfect time for
us to reselect that waypoint. Okay, we have that method
still, stay select waypoint, so let's go ahead and
do it. How do we get it this time? Well, we're going to
get this from the pop over presentation controller. Okay?
We're gonna get it's presented ViewController, okay?
That's the controller its presenting which is our
editable view, waypoint view controller. And it better be
an EditWaypointViewController, okay? And if it is,
then we can just get the waypoint to edit, okay? So
now, we're on this. Okay. So we'll drop,
click, go up here, change this to something, random words.
The only thing is tip away, and we got it. Okay.
So that's a great use of that little delegate. But
there are even better uses of that little delegate.
And a lot of them have to do with this adaptation
behavior, okay? The way that the system is adopting to that
horizontally compact environment and
putting that thing up on our iPhone
in this really obnoxious way. Okay so let's go and
fix some of these things. One thing we could do to fix this
is we could make it not adapt. Okay? We can make it just so
that it uses popover on iPhone. It doesn't do this
whole putting a modal one up instead. Okay so
how would we do that? All right, that one we're gonna
implement a different delegate method here.
Popover delegate. This one is called the,
note here, adaptivePresentationStyleforP-
resentationController. Okay, this guy right here. Okay,
adapt to presentation style for presentation controller,
actually we want a different one,
we want the one that gives us the trade collection.
AdaptivePresentationStyle, it's this one. Okay?
So this one is basically asking us, let me make it so
you can see it a little better here. Okay?
It has two arguments here and it returns
a ModalPresentationStyle. So this is saying, for
a given trait collection like horizontally compact or
whatever how do you want to present this
thing in when you're adapting. Now if I don't implement this,
what it does is, it looks at this tray collection, says,
is it horizontally compact? Yes? Then return full screen.
That's how this whole adaptation thing works.
Well, I can fix that by just saying return none. Okay,
that means don't adapt, okay? So now we will never adapt,
now if I run on the iPhone,
you'll see that it's not going to adapt because I set
the presentation style for, adapting style, to be none so
it's never going to adapt. Go here, you click this.
Sure enough we get that. Now look how terrible this looks.
Okay? Clearly horizontally compact is not wide enough to
show this popover. Okay? It's, smashed it in there,
tried to obey the 250 point wide for the text field.
The name and description got cut off. It just not you
know couldn't quite point to the [LAUGH] the pin prob
is a big mess. So this is not the solution to this problem.
It seemed like it would be a good solution to this problem.
But it's not. So, lets go try and solve some of those other
problems we had. Okay, one is, we had no done button, okay?
So how can we get the done button back? Well,
we need to put that thing back in a navigation controller,
but only when we're adapting. So, first of all,
I'm going to comment this out so
that we're back to adapting. And I'm gonna input another
delegate method here which is called view controller for
adaptive presentation style. Here it is. Okay,
again I'll show you the arguments here. Okay, now look
what this one returns. This one returns a view controller.
This is basically saying, okay, I'm trying to adapt
to a certain style, that's gonna be the full screen style
here give me a View Controller to show
when I adapt. Now if I don't implement this, it's just
going to use the edit waypoint view controller, okay.
But I'm going to fix this to return a navigational control
that has an edit waypoint controller in it. Okay. So
let's do that. I'm going to say, first I'm gonna let,
well first I'm gonna say, if the style that we're adapting
to is full screen. Okay, then I'm going to create
a navigation controller, let navcon equal a UINavigation.
I'm just creating it with its constructor, right,
its initializer. And the rootViewController of it is
going to be the controllers. PresentedViewController,
remember we used that in the other one, okay,
that is the EditWaypoint,
EditWaypointViewController that we're trying to present,
that's what it is. And so now I'm just gonna return this
navigation controller instead. So it's gonna use
the navigation controller instead of this. If we're not
adapting to full screen then I'm gonna return nil and
let it do whatever it does by default which is you know
use the popover or it's not adapting so it doesn't matter.
All right let's see if that fixes anything here.
All right here we go. Drop it. Click on it,
boom. Wahoo! Look at that we have a done button back.
Now that done button, by the way, you might say,
where'd that come from?
Okay, well that's because we put the done button into that
NBC back when it used to be a navigation controller.
When we removed the navigation controller it kept the done
button. It wasn't able to display it because it wasn't
in a navigation controller until now. Again, but it kept
the Done button. Remember that all the things that appear
in a navigation controllers title bar, the buttons and
stuff are associated with the NBC inside, okay. And
when you remove, put something in, embed in, or
take out of a navigational controller in NBC,
it keeps all it's things so that's why we kept the Done
button. Okay, not only kept the Done button there,
it's still going to unwind. Okay?
Cuz it's still hooked up to that to unwind there. Now,
we still have this black background. That's not so
good. Okay? How are we gonna fix that? Well,
I'm gonna do that in a cool way, which is to stop
having it basically cover up the the thing underneath, and
let it show through. Okay?
I'm gonna have this modal view controller come up. But
not cover up what's behind, okay, and
that's really simple to do. Actually,
we're going to use the same method we did back here, okay,
but instead of saying return none, okay,
we're just going to say let's just return. If the trace
collection here collection, okay trait selection,
horizontal size class, equals compact, then we're gonna
return this new style which is over full screen.
So over full screen is like full screen but
it's over the things so the things shines through. Okay
that's the only difference between full screen and
over full screen. Otherwise, we're just going to not adapt.
Okay, we're only gonna adapt in the horizontalSizeClass
Compact. Okay, so let's see what that looks like.
All right, here it is. Drop one, click, bring it up.
All right! Okay, it brought it up. But, it's kinda weird that
we can see all the way through it kinda makes it think that
we could click on this things. Also having the word
description be on the dark background makes it hard to
see it. Okay. I also noticed that maybe our 250 is a little
too wide of a minimum. Maybe we wanna go down to 200.
But, what were really cool is if we could actually show
what's behind slightly blurred. Just like the popover
one does. Right? The popover one it showed the name and
description, but it was only kinda the slightly see-through
semi-transparent blurred thing.
Well we can do that ourselves. Okay? There's a view, okay,
we can talk about in the slides. But there's a view
which essentially presents whatever's behind it blurred
okay, tha's what the view does. so were gonna poke one
of this views right at the top of the navigation controllers
view hierarchy okay. Even behind the things
like this bar at the top of the navigation control
everything. Okay, we're gonna be really right at the top, so
it's gonna blur everything behind. And
the navigation controller's gonna be on top of this nice,
blurred thing. Okay? So, how do we do that? Well,
we create that navigation controller right here. So
all we need to do is to create this little blurring view
doohickey, which is called a visual effects view. And
also, by the way, we're gonna wanna put here if the style
is OverFullScreen so that we can do it in both cases there.
So, we're gonna create a visual effects view,
visualEffectsView, we'll call it and
it's UIVisualEffectView.
That's the name of the class. VisualEffectView. I guess
it would be VisualEffectView cuz it's a single effect. And
you just specify what kind of effect you want. Effect, and
I want a UIBlurEffect. And the style of
it is I want a ExtraLight okay which is a really
extra light ver, blur. And the reason I want extra light is
cuz I'm gonna be putting black text on top of it and
things like that so I really want that to stand out. So
there's extra light blurring.
Now I'm going to set the visual effects views frame
to equal the navCon bounds. Okay.
So navCon is a view controller. It's just
a regular view controller like any other view controller.
It's got a view which is it's top level view. So I'm gonna
put my visual effects right at the top of its hierarchy, so
I'm gonna have it fill the entire thing. Now,
I'm also gonna do a little bit of magic here which we didn't
talk about at all, which is, there's
a really kind of an old style way of doing auto layout where
you can specify just a couple of things.
And, I'm going to have this visual effect view
always stick to the same size as the nab cons bounds.
And the way I'm gonna do it, is by using these old style
constraints where I basically say that the width and height
of my visual effects view is flexible. So, as things change
it tries to stick to its super view. Okay? Don't worry
too much about this magic It's just a little easier way than
doing this than trying to show you how to do it with
the new way.
So I just basically say that's auto resizing math is flexible
width and flexible height.
If it's superview changes it's size than it sizes with it,
using the rules keep your width and
height flexible. Okay?
So now I'm just going to take that navcon top level view and
insert a subview, which is a visual effects view.
And I'm gonna put it at index zero, which is all the way at
the back. Remember subviews is ordered int he subview list.
All right, so let's take a look at that.
All right. Drop it here. Up. There we go.
Okay, see how it, you can kinda see the,
I don't know how, how good the projection there is, but
you can kinda almost see the valleys here.
The mountains and the valleys. In there. When you get this
we'll go run it at home you'll see it a lot clearer. Okay? So
that's it we only have three minutes so
I'm not going to the slides on that. I will post on
how you can learn a little more about that. And
that's it. So, that's everything there.
You learned a lot about map view and
about all kinds of segways there, so
hopefully that will prepare you for
your final presentation. So,
next week is just the alternate final,
there's a holiday on Monday, so there's no class then,
and Wednesday is the alternate final. And,
if you have any questions I'll help you here as usual. For
more, please visit us at stanford.edu.