Stanford University. >> Okay,
斯坦福大学
well welcome to lecture number three of Stanford CS193P.
欢迎来到斯坦福 CS193P 课程第三讲
This is spring quarter 2016. And today we
这是 2016 年春季
are going to mostly talk about the layer under the UI.
今天我们主要会介绍UI层
Okay, so we're gonna talk about Swift the language.
我们会讨论 Swift 这门语言
We're gonna talk about this foundation framework that
我们将会讨论位于核心服务层顶部的 foundation 框架
lives on top of Core services. So we're not going to be
所以我们不会讨论一整天非常多关于 UI 的内容
talking about the UI very much at all today. I do have a demo
我有一个用演示作为结束
towards the end. So I will finish off the slides and
我会完成这些幻灯片然后我们把这个演示做完
then we'll do the demo to finish. Okay, all right, so
好的
first thing I want to talk about is optional's,
首先我想介绍的是 optional
by the way, everything I am talking about today is
顺便说下 我今天介绍的所有东西
in your reading assignments. Okay, I'm just, the things I
都在你们的阅读作业里。好的
am talking about today I want to emphasize. I mean these
我想强调我今天介绍的东西
are things that you really really want to understand.
我的意思是这些东西你们真的真的需要理解
So if you see me mention it today and then you're reading
如果你在你的阅读作业里读到我今天提到的东西
it in the reading assignment, be sure to pay close attention
确保密切关注好吗？
all right? So as we learned in the last lecture,
那在我们上节课学的内容中
optional is just an enum, okay? It's a generic type kind
optional 就是一个 enum 是吧？它是一个有点像数组的泛型
of like array. It's got this little angle bracket T,
它有个小尖括号
which just means an Optional can be an Optional of any
这意味着 Optional 可以选择任何类型
type. And we know that to be the case. We can have
并且我们知道的情况
Optional strings or Optional even Optional optionals.
我们可以有可选字符串或者任何可选类型
We can have any kind of Optional we want. And so
我们可以选择任何我们想要的 Optional
it's an enum with two cases. The None case which is the not
所以这是一个有两种情况的 enum。
set case and then the Some case, which is the set case.
None 情况是没有设置东西，其它情况是设置了一些东西的
And in the Some case it has an associated value. And you
在一些情况下它有相关的值
learned all about enums last time. So this, syntax should
你们最近学过的关于枚举的内容
look completely, familiar to you. So let's look at some
所以这个语法对你们来说应该是完全熟悉的
of the little question mark, exclamation point stuff. And
让我们来看看这些小问号，惊叹号
what that means in terms of optional behind the scenes. So
在这些场景背后它们和 optional 的关系是什么
if you had a constant x which was of type optional string,
如果你有一个常量 x 它的类型是 optionl 字符串
right, string question mark.
对，字符串问号
And I set it to nil, then that's the same as saying that
然后我把它设置为 nil ，这等同于是说 x = Optional.None
x = Optional.None, right? Obviously, and same
对吗？显然， 的情况一样
thing if I had an optional string that was set to hello,
如果我有一个可选字符串设置成 hello
that'd be the same as x=Optional.Some
那就等于 x=Optional.Some
with the associated value, hello. Okay,
关联的值是 hello。 好的
everybody cool with that? And similarly, if I unwrap,
大家都觉得这很酷吧？类似的，假如我拆包
if I said, var y=x unwrapped, that just means switch x,
如果我说，var y=x 拆包，那就意味着开关 x
because we know that the way we unwrap Optionals and
因为我们知道我们那样子拆包 Optionals
get their associated value is with switch, so
所以我会打开 x 并用开关得到相关的值
I'm gonna switch on x. And in the case of Some, I'm gonna
在一些情况下，我会用 let 值
do that let value thing so I can grab the associated value.
因为这样我可以抓取相关的值
And then I'm just gonna set y equal to that value.
然后我要设置 y 等于那个值
In the case None, I'm gonna crash.
在空的情况下，我的程序会 crash
I'm gonna raise an exception, okay, because that's what
我要提出一个列外
unwrapping an Optional that's not said is supposed to do,
因为拆包一个 Optional 不意味着它应该这么做
it's supposed to crash, okay? And of course, in the case
它应该让程序奔溃。
where I'm doing if let, then I'm just gonna switch on x,
如果我用 let 这么做，然后我去 switch x
and I'm, the case of .Some, I'm gonna grab that y, and
在 .Some 情况下我用 y 拿出 x 的值
then I'm just gonna put some code, whatever my code is in
然后就会执行我放在下面的代码
there, and if let to happen there. And in the case None,
然而在 None 的情况下
I just break out of the switch, I do nothing.
我会直接跳出 switch 什么都不做
Okay, sound good? All right, so that's Optionals.
听起来不错？ 这就是 Optionals
Hopefully Optional now should start feeling very,
希望现在开始对 Optional 的感觉好点了
very comfortable to you cuz, as you found out,
在这些 API 里面
it's everywhere in these, in the API. Now Optionals have
你会发现到处都有舒服的提示
some more syntax, okay. That question mark and exclamation
现在 Optionl 有更多的语法了。你看见的那些问号和感叹号
point stuff, as you're seeing, is just syntactic sugar.
都是语法糖
It's just to make the, your typing it in easier and
这是为了让你写起来更舒服并且更好看
look nicer. It has a little bit more syntactic sugar.
它还有更多的语法糖
One thing is that Optionals can be chained. Okay, so
比如 OPtional 可以是链式的
this is the case where, for example,
如同这个例子的情况
in our calculator, we have the display, and
在我吗的计算器例子里，我们有显示，
lets say we want to get the text out of the display. And
让我们把一些想要得到的文本显示出来
then we want to send another message like hash value which,
然后我们想传递一些信息，比如哈希值，
strings understand this message hash value,
这些消息哈希后的字符串
how would we do that? Well of course we would say,
我们该如何做呢？
if let label equal display to unwrap the display. And
我们会这样，如果让 label 等于 display 这样去拆包 display
they we would say if let text equal the labels text,
然后我们会让 text 等于 label 的 text
and unwrap that. Then we would say let x equal the text hash
拆包之后，我们在让 x 等于 text 哈希后的值
value, okay? So that is how we would unwrap it.
所以，这就是我们如何去拆包这些信息
Well there is a lot easy way to do it which is this,
当然还有很多更容的方法来做
you just say display?.text?.hashvalue,
你可以这样 display?.text?.hashvalue
okay? So if you use question marks when you're, not when
如果你在这个时候用 ？ 而不是在声明 optional 类型时使用
you're declaring the optional but when you're actually using
这基本上意味着
it, that basically means, try and unwrap this and
尝试去把它们拆包
if you can then use that value to go to the next thing.
拆包后的值是否可以让你去到下一部分
If you can't, just return nil from this whole expression.
如果不行，整个表达是就返回 nil
Okay, this whole display question mark,
这个 dispaly 后面所有的问号，
that typed question mark, that hash value,
那个 哈希 值
that whole expression will return nil if at any point
如果它们当中有任何一点在拆包的时候返回了 nil
any of these things that were changing unwrap turns out to
这整个表达式就会返回 nil
be nil. So, if the display is nil or if the display's text
所以，如果 display 是空的，或者 display 的 text 是空的
is nil then this whole thing is gonna be nil.
那这整个就会变成 nil
So you see let x equal up there? What type do you think
所以你看见让 x 等于它们
x is right there? >> [INAUDIBLE].
这里的 x 是什么类型的 [讨论]
>> Int, almost.
[大概是 Int]
Optional int, exactly. It has to be optional int, because
对，可选 int 类型
any of those things could fail and it would return nil.
因为任何其它东西都可能失败并返回 nil
So it has to be able to take nil. So
所以它可以是 nil 值
that would be an optional int, cuz hash value returns an int,
因为它可以返回一个 int 的哈希值，所以它是一个可选 int
okay. So you're definitely gonna wanna use this,
你肯定会想用这种链条一样的方式去编程
chaining, it really makes your code read beautifully, okay.
它真的让你的代码看起来漂亮了
And the starts make Optionals make a lot of sense why we use
当我们开始使用可选类型的时候会有很多场景去使用它们
them so much. Okay, but there's more.
好的，但是还有别的用法
Here's another Optional syntaxtiture which is ??
这里是 Optional 的另一种用法叫做 ？？
Okay, and this is basically providing a default value
它基本上是在 case 为 nil 的时候提供一个默认的值
in case something is nil. Okay, so let's add an optional
来添加一个可选字符串 s
string here s, okay. I could say if s is not nil,
我可以说，如果 s 不是空
then I'm gonna set my display to be s, okay.
然后我会把我的 display 设置成 s
So let's say I'm setting the display in my calculator, and
这意味我在我的计算器上设置了显示
I never want it to be nil. At worst, I want it to be just
而且我不想让它是空的，最差也得是个空格字符
a space character. Because you might have noticed,
因为你可能注意到了
some of you when you're doing your homework,
当你在做你的一些作业的时候
that if you put nil into a label,
如果你往 label 里面放了 nil
its size will go to zero. Okay,
它的尺寸会变成0
cuz there's no text in there to have a natural size for. So
因为没有文本它就不会有一个天生的尺寸
sometimes you might want to have a code like this where if
所以有时候你可能想要一些这样的代码
you want to put nothing in the display,
如果你往 display 里面放了空的东西
you put a space character, so at least there's something in
你就放一个空格字符，因为这样至少这里有东西让 label 有高度
there for it to have a height, okay? Otherwise your display
否则你设置成 nil 的话
would keep disappearing if you kept setting it to nil. So
你的 display 可能会消失
we can do this, if s does not equal nil then display equals
那么我们可以这样，如果 s 不等于 nil 就让 display 等于 s
s, that should be s exclamation point right there,
用 != 表示不等于
otherwise display equals a space. Okay, well,
否则就 display 就等于一个空格
a much simpler way to put that is with this,
有一个更简单的方法
defaulting operator, which is to say the display.text
让 display.text = s
= s Okay? And that means if s is not nil then unwrap it and
这表示如果 s 不为空，就把它拆包
use that value, otherwise use space.
然后就使用拆包后的值，否则就使用空格
Got that? Everyone understand? I don't see any nodding heads
懂了吗？每个人都懂了吗？我没有看就有人点头
on that one. Make sense, okay? So this is, again, just
理解它，好吗？ 在说一遍
a simple way to have a default value in case an optional is
这是让 optional 在 nil 的情况下有一个默认值的简单的方法
nil. All right so let's talk about another thing, tuples.
继续介绍另一东西，元祖。
All right tuples are a type, okay? In Swift they're really,
really cool. They're basically a way to build a type out of
other types by grouping them, okay? And
you can use it anywhere you can use a type, a tuple can be
used anywhere types are valid, okay? So, here's an example.
I'm going to create x, okay? This let x, x is a constant.
It's type is a tuple, with a string, int, and
double. So, even though tuple has the sound, to, in it,
it's just not two things. Any number of things can be in
a tuple okay? So x there is a tuple with string int and
double. And I'm even setting it to a value,
which is just parenthesis, a string, an int, and a double,
okay? Now how do I get those values out of the tuple?
Well there is two ways to do it.
One is to say, let and then three, identifiers. These
are basically three local variable names, equals x,
okay? And that's gonna extract the three values and put them,
assign them to word, number, and value, which are gonna
be local variables in this context, okay? Now, if you
tried to say let word, comma, number, closed parentheses,
equal x, the compiler will complain, because word, comma,
number can't match a string in double tuples. Okay? So
this particular syntax is just putting names on the things in
the Tuple so you can use them, so now you can print them out.
Print word. Print number. Print value.
Value would be of type string. Number would be of type int
and value would be of type double. Okay,
another way to do it is when you create the tuple, okay,
you can name each of the things in the tuple. So
here I'm letting x, this time be w: String i: Int v: Double.
I'm giving the names w, i and v to the things inside
the tuple. I'm still assigning it, just like I did in
the version above. But now if I want to get at the values,
I can just say x.w, x.i, and x.v to get at the tuple
values. See the difference between those two cases?
One, you're kind of naming it when you declare the tuple,
the other one is you're taking a tuple that you got and
you're just extracting the values. And you can mix them.
For example I could say let = x.
Even though I defined it x to have w, i and v,
I could ignore the w, i and v and instead just do
the syntax from the top okay and call it wrd, num and val.
Okay? So, tuples are cool because you can return
multiple values from a function with a tuple. Okay?
So, we know that returned values are arrow and a type.
Well, since a tuple can be a type, you can go arrow and
a tuple, and return values. Yeah?
>> Can you ignore some of
the values? >> So, question,
can you ignore some of the values?
Absolutely you can, if you use under bar. Underbar and
swift is the universal I'm ignoring this character, okay,
so you can put underbar in there. So yeah, so
here I'm returning this tuple weight and
height, obviously straight forward how we do that.
So tuples are perfectly valid return values, okay? So
you can return multiple things from functions. All right,
range. So range is quite important, actually,
in Swift. It's essentially just two end points,
okay, of anything that can be representative consecutively,
okay? So range, the type, is generic, like array,
so you can have a range of ints. You can have
a range of indexes into something or whatever it
really conceptually just has two things, a startIndex and
a last index, okay, endIndex. An array's range, okay.
If you wanted to get an array, arrange into an array,
it would be a range of ints,
because an array is indexed by ints.
So you would have a range of ints. In fact you know,
you, there are methods in array where you can say, give
me this range of yourself, and you specify it as a Range.
A string's range is not Int. Okay, if you wanna substring,
you cannot use a range of Int. It's actually a range of
String.Index, which is a different type than Int. And
you're gonna need to read all about that in the assignment,
okay? One of the section's in assignment is
indexing into arrays in the ring assignment.
And you're gonna wanna understand that, okay?
It's a little bit complicated. I'm not gonna spend
lecture time but just I'm pointing it out to you,
so you could go look at it. Okay? Now, there's special,
just like with optionals we've got question marks and
exclamation points. There's some special syntax for
ranges, okay, which is this ...and ..<.
You see them right here? Okay the... ..<!--? Okay?
This means a range right here, okay, that goes from 2 to 3.
This is a range that goes from 2 to 3 but does not include 3.
Okay? So that would be just the number 2, right there.
Okay? Now, see this 4 right here?
4 loops in swift all are 4 in like this.
So if you wanted to go for I equals 1, 2, 10 I plus plus or
whatever you would so that with these, ranges like this,
okay, for IN 27 to 104 or whatever. Okay? And
you can make ranges that are more powerful than just direct
ranges. I can't talk about that really on time wise, but
again check the documentation and
you'll see out of the ranges, okay? So that's when you see
that. Okay, let's talk about data structures in Swift.
I'm talking about classes, structures and enums.
Okay, you've already seen them in the example. I'm gonna
talk about the similarities and the differences.
So what's similar between class, struct and enum,
they're declared the same way, right? Just a keyword,
the name of the thing and then curly braces.
They all serve like that way. They're also similar and
that they can also have properties and
functions. Okay? So you can have functions on there,
and you can have properties. Enums cannot have stored
properties. Only structs and classes can have stored
properties but enums can have computer properties. Okay?
The storage of an enum remember is the cases.
It's a discrete value thing so it's the cases and
their associated values that's the storage.
All right they all can have initializers.
Okay, we haven't talked much about initializers yet.
We're gonna get that today. Eh, so they're all allowed
to have initializers except enum. Okay,
obviously enum doesn't need an initializer because you just
set it to the discrete value with its associated values.
Okay? All right. Differences. One, inheritance. Okay?
With classes, you can inherit, structs and enum you can't.
Value types, I talked about this before, okay? Structs and
enum are value types. They're passed around by value.
Class is a reference type. You pass pointers to it around. It
lives in the heap. Okay? Let's talk a little more about value
versus reference. Value means that it's copied when passed
as argument to a function, that's kind of obvious. But
it also copies when you assign it to another variable.
If I say varx=y if y is a value type,
x will be a copy of y.
A copy, so if y is an array y might be an array. Okay? And
you say, x equals y. And then you say, x append this thing,
that thing will not be appended to y. Because x
was a copy of y. You see what I'm talking about there? Okay.
So that's a big difference with value semantics.
Even just assigning them, is a copy of them. A value symantec
thing is immutable if it's signed to a let variable.
Okay? So if you have an array okay,
since that value symmentic cuz an array is a struct.
If you assigned to a let, let x equal an array you cannot
append things on to that array cuz it is immutable. Okay,
same thing with the dictionary or whatever. Okay. Remember
the function parameters. All of them are constants so
of course you'd copy them into there, you can't modify them.
Because of the way copy symmentics work, Swift makes
you when you do have a struct or enum you have to mark all
functions that might change that thing. Mutating functions
with the keyword mutating. So like mutating funk whatever.
Okay? If that function could change that struct.
And the reason for that is when Swift copies it
it doesn't want to actually make a copy. Okay?
It gets another pointer to it but as soon as you try to
mutate it then it's gonna have to copy it. You see? So
it's kind of a performance enhancement. So
any time you have a struct that has a function that
changes the values, any of the values of the struct,
you have to put mutating in front so Swift knows
that you're doing that. Okay, reference types, okay.
This is what you're used to,
probably. Things are stored in the heap.
You have a reference to them. Those references are counted
automatically. That means there's no garbage collection
in Swift. All right, there's no mark and sweep in
the heap. Every single time you create a new pointer to
something in the heap Swift keeps track of that and
it keeps incrementing a count. And when that count goes down
to zero because maybe the last pointer that's pointing to it
goes out of scope or maybe you assign that last pointer to
point to something else. Nothing points to it.
It immediately removes that from the heap.
Okay, predictably removed from the heap immediately.
So, it's very different than garbage collection, where
garbage collection is kind of going on in the background,
and it might collect a whole bunch from the heap,
all at once. That's been sitting around for a while.
This is predictable,
memory management and it's all managed for you. Okay,
there's only one way that you participate in that, which is
the weak and strong, which I'll be talking about later,
okay? Let's see, constant pointers.
Okay, if you have a constant pointer to a class,
obviously it's a pointer, so you're still mutating it,
right? It's not like a struct where if I say var y = x and
then I add something to y, it doesn't modify x.
If I say var y = x and they're classes, then if I send
a message to y, it's sending a message to x because they're
the same thing. Right they, that same thing lives in
the heat. There's no copying, so let, all let means is that
pointer's not going to change. It doesn't
mean what the pointer points to won't change.
Okay obviously so when you pass a pointer to a class
as an argument, then it does not make a copy, it's just
passing a pointer. Okay. Now how do you know which to use?
Struct versus class, specially.
Okay, enum is pretty obvious. But struct versus class well.
Usually you're gonna choose class over struct.
Okay. Because this is object oriented program.
You use to do it and that's going to be fine.
Struct is gonna be used for more fundamental types.
Okay, things like strings and doubles, and ints and arrays
in dictionaries, and also for drawing, points, rectangles.
Do you see what I'm saying, smaller things that
are self-contained, that it makes sense to copy by value.
You want the value semantic, that's gonna be your primary
reason for choosing struct as you want values
semantics when you're passing this thing around. Otherwise,
you're gonna choose classes, okay? Anything big is almost
certainly gonna use the class, all right? Okay.
On the methods. So now we are gonna talk about the syntax
of methods. Okay, I showed you this in class a little bit but
I'm gonna talk about the full semantics here of it.
So interesting about the naming of functions, so
here is someone defining a method and here is someone
calling this method. Okay? Okay, so watch this colored
stuff going on as I talk about these various things going on.
So all parameters to functions have an internal name and
an external name, every single parameter.
So here's the first parameter, here's the second parameter,
they both have an external name and an internal name.
Okay? The external name comes first. Internal name comes
second. The internal name is the name of the local
variable that's gonna be used inside your method.
All right? So that's this one right here,
internal name. Shows up right before the colon. Okay?
First and second. You can see how first and
second are the names I used for those inside my function.
Don't appear anywhere here. Notice first and
second do not appear in the funk bar call. Okay,
cuz those are the internal names. The external name
is what the caller uses when they call this method. Okay,
so you can see bar down there. It says externalFirst: 123,
externalSecond: 5.5, right? Okay, it's using the external
names first and second never appear but
first and second are still used in the implementation,
those in the internal names. Okay,
you can put an under bar if you don't want callers
to use an external name at all for a given parameter. Okay,
so if you put underbar as the external name then there will
be no external parameters. So you see it says foo(123), not
foo(externalFirst or anything, it's just nothing, 123. And
in fact, this is the default for the first parameter.
The first parameter defaults to under bar, you don't need
to put an under bar there when you're creating a function.
Just by default an under bar would be put there for you,
okay? Now you could specify an external name for the first,
it's legal. Okay, I'll show you that in a second. But
by default under bar is the external name for the first
parameter only. All the other ones. Okay? The default is
the internal name. So, if you don't have an external name,
then it defaults to being the internal name. Got it?
Okay. Any parameter's external name can be changed, okay?
You can change even the second one to be underbar, so
that the second one has no name, okay?
But don't do this, okay? It's very anti Swift
to either remove the second parameter name or
to add it back to the first. Adding to the first is
probably less anti Swift, there is probably some case
where that might actually make some sense. Removing them for
subsequent ones is probably really bad. Okay,
I don't think I've ever had to do that in my entire life of
writing swift so.
All right now, methods are obviously overriddeable,
this is object orientated programming. Right and the way
you do it, you just put the word override in front of
the func or var. Both properties and functions can
be overridden right, so you put override in there. It is
possible to mark a method or a property final in which case
no one can subclasses. Okay, there won't be a list,
a subclass can't say override that thing. The compiler won't
let them. Okay, you can also mark an entire class final,
and then the whole thing is not subclassable. All right?
Now, both types and instances can have methods and
properties. What does that mean? So, so
far in all the demos we've done,
all you've seen is instance methods and
instance properties. In other words,
they are properties that you get from an instance of
the thing. Okay, an instance of the calculator brain.
Someone actually created a calculator brain in the heap
and you send it messages, okay. Those are instances
messages, Instances methods and instances properties. But
it is possible to have methods and
properties on the type itself, so calculator brain,
the type can have functions, okay? And here's what
it looks like to call them. So here I have a little example.
Here I have a var d which is a double, okay?
And it's set to some value. So this d is an instance of
a double. It is an actual double that has some value,
all right? And here I'm checking by sending a message,
an instance method right here. Or probably a property
actually. Instance property on D, where I'm asking
if it's signed is the minus sign, I'm just making this up,
there's probably not even such a method on double.
But that would be an instance property or method and
I would be sending it to D,
which is an instance. If it does have a minus sign,
I'm going to use a type property. Or type function,
rather, of double here, to change its probably absolute
value, so it'd probably change its sign there. Okay.
Notice the syntax here, Double.abs, okay.
This is the name of the function abs, okay, and
I'm accessing it by saying Double. So in other words, I'm
putting the name of the class. Not an instance of a class,
not a variable of that class, but the actual name of
the class, dot abs. Okay, that's it's gonna be defined,
that abs, will be defined like this. Static func abs.
This would be in the class double. And you put this word
static and that says that you don't send this to double
instances. You send it to the Double class by saying capital
D Double dot. Okay? Why do we have these things? Okay these
are usually utility functions kind of global functions but
they're really strongly associated with the class. So
we put them as class methods, okay?
That's what they're for, mostly. Maybe you have a class
method that creates Shared instances of a class, okay.
Something like that, we'll see a few of these.
Once you start to see them in action,
you'll start to understand. But I just wanna make sure you
understand that there is a difference between these two
and this static that makes a difference on declaration,
okay. That's also in the reading assignment, make sure
you read that carefully. In the homework assignment,
I even say be careful to read this carefully. All right,
properties, okay. Properties are really cool.
In Swift we're only just scratching the surface so
far of what they can do. But one really cool thing about
them is that you can observe changes to a property, okay.
And you need to do that by, here's your var, okay. This is
a stored property, this is not a computed property,
it's stored, okay. It stores in ints, its value is 42. But
I'm putting the curly braces after it, not because I'm
gonna do get and set, I'm not computing it. But
I'm gonna add willSet and/or didSet, okay. So willSet and
didSet, this is just code in here that's gonna get called
whenever this thing gets set. Okay, before and after. Before
it gets set, after it's been set, okay. And inside there
newValue is going to be the value it's going to be set to
in willSet. And oldValue is this value it used to have in
did, when you're executing in didSet, okay. So, pretty cool.
And you can do that for stored properties, you can do it for
inherited properties, properties you inherit even,
okay. And you can do it for computed properties as well,
okay. Also here, this will be,
one thing to note about this is these willSets and didSets,
if you mutate a value type they will get called,
okay. So, operations here from our calculator brain,
dictionary string operation that is a value type,
dictionary is a value type, right. So
if you add something to this dictionary,
this will get called. willSet and didSet will get called,
okay. That's not true if it's a reference type, okay.
If that if this property isn't a class and
you change the class somehow, it can't detect that, so
it doesn't do willSet and didSet, okay.
You have to change the pointer itself. All right, okay.
One very common thing to do in these willSets and didSets is
update the UI. You got a method in your controller.
You set some value in controller that changes
the way the UI would look. You ask your view to
draw itself again, okay. Very, very common.
We're gonna be doing that up the wazoo in the next lecture,
okay. All right. Lazy initialization. So, this is
a little bit of a cheat code of Swift right here.
You can declare vars to be lazily instantiated.
Which means that, their value, this equals calculator brain,
will not actually happen. That assignment will not happen
until someone asks for the brain, okay.
If someone tries to send a message to this brain or
get a property to this brain,
then it's gonna get initialized.
So in other words, it's lazily instantiated, okay.
And you can do it like that, okay. Just lazy var brain,
calculatorbrain. You can do down here, okay.
Lazy var myProperty = self.initializedMyProperty.
So, I'm calling a method on myself to initialize one of my
properties. Normally, this would be illegal
without the lazy. The reason this would be illegal
without the lazy is that you cannot send any messages to
yourself or access any of your properties until you're fully
initialized, okay. And this is part of your initialization,
so it's a catch 22, you can't do it. But
if you make this lazy, now you can. Because it's not actually
going to happen until after you're fully initialized and
someone comes along and tries to access myProperty, okay. No
one can access myProperty for your initialize anyway. So,
once you're fully initialized, I'm gonna access myProperty,
lazy, boom. This method will get called to initialize you,
got it? And how about this one in the middle here,
some property of this given type equals a closure
with open parentheses,
closed parentheses on the end. This just means,
initialize this by executing the code inside this closure,
okay. It's very similar to doing
self.initializeMyProperty but you're putting the code
in this closure instead of putting it in initialize
myProperty, whatever that method is, okay. Now,
normally inside here, okay. If this weren't lazy,
you would not be able to access self in here.
Because again, this is a part of initialization, you can't
do anything with self until you're fully initialized. So
if you tried to put self in here,
the compiler will complain. But if you make it lazy,
now you can access self in here. Got it?
Call your own methods or whatever you wanna do, okay.
So that's lazy. The reason this is kind of a cheat code
is that this lazy business satisfies the requirement
that all your vars have to be initialized, okay. So even
these, though these things are being initialized lazily,
they're still being initialized for
the purposes of that rule that all your vars have to be
initialized. This kind of will often keep you from having to
write an initializer. You won't need an init,
because of this lazily do it, okay.
That's why I say it's kind of a cheat code a little bit,
okay. One thing about lazy, they always have to be var.
So there's no such thing as lazy let, okay. Lazy var
only, okay. You can also use laziness to get around some
dependency issues, if you have one var depends on another. If
you can make one of them lazy, then that'll be fine, right.
Cuz the lazy one will call the one that gets pre-initialized,
okay. All right, let's talk about array.
Okay, I'm not gonna spend much time on this cuz array you're
used to array, you know what array is.
In other languages, it's pretty much the same in Swift.
So I'm just gonna try and cover the syntax a little bit.
One thing is we've been using this kind of syntax for
dictionary, right, dictionary angle, extreme colon
operation, remember that? This is the formal
syntax for an array but this square bracket,
string closed square bracket is more informal and
it's the one we use, okay. So as we go forward, we're gonna
use [string] to mean the type array of string, okay.
And similarly for dictionary, [key:value]. That is
dictionary with keys of this and values of that type, okay.
Now, this is the type,
so the open parenthesis close parenthesis on the end just
means that I'm calling the initializer with no arguments.
Same as up here. So don't get confused by that, okay.
So that just means I'm initializing,
I'm creating an instance of an array of string, okay. That's
what both of those mean. So, I can also create arrays and
initialize them by just saying some variable like animals
there which is constant let animals = [ list a bunch of
things ]. That creates an array of those things.
And notice I don't specify any type here.
Why, why do I get away with that? What does Swift do?
It infers type. So, we would look at this and say string,
string, string, string all right.
This is an array of string. Now if I went giraffe, cow,
three, bird, then Swift would complain, can't infer the type
of that array, because it's not all the same type.
Okay, so we'd infer it here. Now, notice this
animals.append("Ostrich"), if I put an Ostrich in here,
this will not compile, okay. Compiler will say no,
that's because animals is let, it's a constant.
So this is a constant array, it can not be modified.
If I put var right here, no problem, it would work, okay.
Now, if I say let animal = animals[5].
That's gonna crash my program. Array index out of bounds,
just like most Programming systems do. It's one
of the few cases that you can crash your program in Swift.
We know unwrapping optionals is one, this is another one.
If you array index out of bounds,
it will crash, okay? How do you enumerate array?
I wanna look at everything in an array. Yeah, I could do for
with a range 0.., the length of the array, right?
0.., less than sign, length of the array. But
that's not how you would do it, you would just say, for
animal in animals, okay? This is gonna loop through, and
this local variable is gonna be assigned each
of the animals, okay? That's how you enumerate an array.
All right, interesting Array methods.
Okay, I'm not gonna spend a lot of time on this slide.
But I really want you to understand that these methods
are here, okay, and you're gonna wanna use them.
They will really clean up your code.
They'll keep you from doing a lot of code, this like for
enumerate through my array, do this, if then, this then,
collect it in another array, all that kinda stuff you can
put in one liners, okay? So what do these things do?
These things use closures to operate on arrays. So filter,
okay, is a method in Array. You send it to it.
You provide a closure, which takes whatever type is in the,
in the array and returns a bool. And it just
executes that closure on every single element of the array,
and it includes the ones
where you return true from your closure. And it excludes
the ones you don't, until filter returns a new array,
which is only the things that match your closure, okay? So
here for example, let bigNumbers = this
array.filter, here's my closure,
$0 is this thing that's gonna be for each of these,
called on each of these. If $0 is greater than 20,
I'm gonna return true. So this returns an array, bigNumbers,
that only has 47 and 118, cuz those are the only
two things greater than 20, got it? Okay,
there's another one simpler, similar, which is map.
Map takes your closure and your closure converts each
element in the array to something else.
So if you had an array of ints and you wanted it
to be an array of strings, you could do it with this,
okay map, closure. Notice, by the way,
no parentheses here. You see, map, okay,
map takes an argument, which is a closure there. But I have
no parentheses after map around the curly braces like I
had up here with filter. I put this in here to show you that
those parentheses are optional when a closure
is the last argument to a function, okay?
When a closure is the last argument to the function,
it can be outside of the function's parentheses, okay,
and live on its own out here.
Okay, here's another function, okay, called reduce.
This reduces the array to a single result. Okay, so
this particular one, you can convince yourself of it later,
it adds up the numbers, okay. It just reduces,
starts with zero, and for each one it takes the amount so
far and adds it to the next thing in there, so
it adds up the numbers.
Notice this one has two arguments,
an initial and a closure. Okay, see this closure here,
an initial? And notice the closure also is still living
outside of the parentheses. The first argument is inside
the parentheses, but the closure is living outside.
This one had no first argument.
It only had the closure, so it has no parentheses here. This
one does, okay? This is called trailing closure syntax, and
you almost always wanna use it, it looks really cool,
reads really nicely. Okay, dictionary.
All right, so dictionary, similar to array,
it's just looking up keys and values.
Again, we're gonna use this more informal kind of syntax,
okay? [String:Int] means the type dictionary where
the strings are keys and ints are values, all right?
So if I have pac10teamRankings here, and
I had Stanford at number 1, Cal number 10, and I let the,
I guess it's Pac-12 now. I should update this,
should't I? So, okay, Cal 12 and so if I say here, let
ranking = pac10teamRankings ["Ohio State"],
that's obviously, no Ohio State in the Pac-12.
So the ranking here has to be an Int?, right, it's
an optional Int, we already saw that in our, calculator.
Okay, anytime you dereference a dictionary,
it's gonna return an optional of whatever type is
the dictionary's values are, okay? The way you enumerate
through a dictionary is using a tuple, okay, for (key,
value) in pac10teamRankings, inside here, key is
gonna be the key. And here is gonna be the value for each of
the things in the dictionary, okay? Pretty cool. And again,
you could put under bar here if you just wanted the keys,
or under bar here if you just wanted the values. All right,
String. String is a little complicated in Swift because
it's full Unicode.
And I mean full Unicode. All right so,
it supports all kinds of languages. Languages where
one character might be many, many different codes, okay.
So characters are no longer single codes anymore. Okay,
so, that's why, when you index into a string,
you're not indexing by ints. You're indexing by
indexes that know how to move along in a string past things
like emojis that might have multiple codes, okay?
So you're gonna wanna read about this, so
I'm not gonna cover it all in lecture here. But
one interesting way to look at a string is by calling
this, String.CharacterView, okay? If you call character
view on a string, you'll get the characters
in what looks like an array of character, okay? It looks like
an array of characters, not actually array of character.
It's a character view. But it can be indexed with ints,
okay, and you can get at the characters. So that's one way.
Another way, you can actually create an array,
one of the initializers that array will take is a string,
okay. And then it'll be an array of characters.
Okay, not quite as efficient as this character view, but
you could do it that way, especially with a long string,
you probably might not wanna do that. Okay, but that's
a little easier way to get at it, otherwise you have to
understand what it says in the reading about string indexes,
okay. String.index that class and
how to use it to get things out of a string,
okay? There are a lot of other cool methods in String,
though, like hasPrefix will tell you whether one string
has the prefix of another string. You can capitalize and
lowercase and uppercase these strings.
You can even do sophisticated things like,
get me all the components in this string separated by
this other string. So
this is a method you send to a string. This might be a comma,
let's say, and this, right here like this, and it will
extract all the strings that are separated by a comma.
Okay, kinda fun. So make sure you familiarize yourself with
a lot of the methods in String so that you don't waste your
time writing this method which already exists, okay, or
similar methods like it. All right, other classes that
are here that you have to think about. One is NSObject.
This is the base class of all Objective-C classes, okay.
Now, we know, in Swift, it doesn't have a mandatory base
class, like CalculatorBrain, no superclass, okay.
Perfectly legal in Swift. But
all Objective-C ones have to be subclasses of NSObject.
Now, there are some APIs, they're fairly rare and
I'll tell you which ones they are when we get to them later
in the quarter, that are Objective-C APIs, okay.
And when you use them in Swift,
you need to have a class that subclasses from NSObject. So
in Swift, it's perfectly legal to subclass from NSObject,
not required except for in these few cases I'm gonna talk
about later in the quarter. But legal and it really won't
hurt anything, so you could do it if you want. Some people
just get in the habit of always sub-classing for
NSObjects in Swift, if they're not sub-classing from
something else, because why not, okay. Then their classes
are always ready for whatever these weird old APIs are,
okay? NSNumber, okay in Objective-C,
there's no such things as well structs
in Objective-C are not like structs in Swift.
They're not this nice value type semantic thing.
Okay, structs are more like C structs okay, so double and
int, string, array,
dictionary. In Objective-C these are classes.
Okay, sorry, array and diction are classes.
Double and int are C-double and int. Not even objects,
okay? So that brings a problem in Objective-C,
what if I wanna put a bunch of numbers into an array? Okay,
you can't do it, because an array is an array of objects.
And doubles and ints are C primitive types,
in Objective-C. So this class NSNumber,
is how you wrap a primitive type into an object.
So you can put it in an array.
Now in Swift we don't need that, because in Swift arrays
and dictionaries will accept structs, and double and
int is a struct. Okay, so this NSNumber not necessary for
that, okay. Now there are iOS APIs that take,
for example, arrays of ints. And
in Objective-C, they're gonna be arrays of NSNumber and
in Swift, they're going to be Swift arrays of Swift Ints.
And you might ask, how is that ever gonna work?
Cuz you're talking about a struct filled with struct
versus an array class filled with these NSNumber classes.
Well the answer is, those things, array, dictionary,
then int double, and NSNumber are all bridged, magically and
automatically, okay? As you call functions that require
one to be one way or the other. It just automatically
works. Okay, there's a lot of magic going on in Objective-C
runtime to make that work. Okay, and we're gonna take
advantage of that bridging in a couple of slides here.
NSDate, brilliant important class to know about. If
you wanna put a date in your UI, you need be very careful.
Because dates are represented in a different way all over
the Earth. Date date class knows all about those ways and
it has a lot of companion classes like NSCalendar,
NSDateFormatter, NSDateComponents to help you
put dates on screen in a way that's gonna work when you
translate your app to Chinese. So NSDate is an important
class to get familiar with and understand what it can do.
Okay, if you're ever gonna put a date in your UI,
you're gonna need to know about NSDate. NSDate can also
tell you the current date and time. All right NSData,
that's a bag of bits. Okay just unstructured bag o' bits.
We use it to pass things around,
sometimes over the network like image data,
things like that. It's pretty self explanatory,
bag of bits doesn't have a lot of methods on it.
It's basically just give me the bits and here's some bits.
Okay, now let's talk about initialization, I'm gonna kind
of blast through this pretty quick. There's a really
good explanation of this in your homework in your reading
assignment. For this coming week but I'm gonna try and
give you the 50,000 foot overview of it quickly so
that you kind of have an idea what's going on as you go and
read that very detailed description, okay?
So when is an init method needed? We're talking about
initializing structs and classes okay? They're
not needed that often because of course we can say equal
something in the var. We coud use those lazy instantiation
things to get around it. Properties might be optional,
so, and they can just start off being not set.
So there's a lot of reasons you don't need an init, okay?
And frankly, most people try to design their classes and
structs so they don't need an init, okay? So you can just
create them with an init with no arguments, right,
which you get for free. Or a string in a struct case maybe
you just do what we did in demo where you just init it
with the values of all the things in the struct, okay?
So but sometimes you might find yourself needing an init
because you just can initialize things using those
mechanisms, all right? Now, you do get some free inits,
okay? We know about in classes you get the init with no
arguments for free. That's how CalculatorBrain got an init,
so we could create one. And
we also know that structs have a free
initializer to let you initialize all of the,
all of its vars. Now, One thing to know about,
[COUGH] both of those cases is that you,
if you start providing your own initializers,
then you stop getting the free one, okay?
If you provide even one initializer for your struct
you no longer get this free one, the one that does both,
okay? All right, what can you do inside of init?
What is legal to do? You can set any property's value,
even one's that already have default values.
Ones that you said equal something,
you can reset them to something else if you want.
You can set any property's value,
okay. You can even set constant properties, okay.
So if you have let something, so you have a constant in your
class, like a constant instance variable basically.
You can set that in, even though it's let,
you can set it in the initializer. Constant
properties are fairly rare. You know, why would you have
something that's constant? You might, though, you might have
something that's determined in initialization. And
then it never changes,
okay? You can call other init methods from your init,
you actually can call one other init method from n init,
okay? And you can call superclass inits, okay.
You can call your superclass initializers, but
there are rules for calling inits and they are rather
complicated. And I'm gonna go through them quick and
you're gonna read the documentations,
it's gonna give you all the details, okay? So
there are requirements inside of init, things you must do.
The previous slide was things you are allowed to do,
here's the things you must do, okay? By the time any init is
done, okay? By the time the init is finished,
all properties must have values. We know this, right?
But in Swift, all, by the time initialization is done,
all properties have to have values, and again,
optionals must have a value too, but
it could be the value not set. That's fine, okay? Now,
there are two types of init methods in a class.
Convenience methods and, convenience initializers and
designated initializers. Designated initializers
are not marked with the word convenience. Okay,
convenience initializers say convenience init whatever,
okay, in their declaration. A designated initializer must,
and can only, call a designated initializers
in it's superclass, its immediate superclass, okay?
So a designated initializer can't call a convenience
initializer in its superclass, and it can't
call a convenience super, initializers in its own class.
It must call a superclass's designated initializer. Okay,
you must initialize all the properties that you introduce
in your class, before calling a superclass's init.
Okay, so by the time you call super init to let your super
class initialize you must have all your properties
initialized, all right? You must call a superclass's init
before you can touch any of your superclass's properties.
See the order there? You do yours, call the super,
now you can touch theirs, okay? That makes sense.
You gotta let them initialize theirs before you can touch it
and you want yours initialized before they come along and
start doing their stuff. A convenience initializer must
and can only call an init, either can be user designated,
in its own class, cannot call super. Okay,
a convenience initializer cannot call super initializer.
A convenience initializer must call that in it, before it can
set any property values. It's own, or it's super classes.
Okay, in other words, it must let a designated initializer
initialize your own properties first.
And that thing is gonna call supern,
it's gonna initialize it, so by the time a convenience
intializer gets back from the emit, all the property values
will be set and it can reset them to something else,
okay. It's just a convenience. Calling other inits
has to be complete before you can access any properties.
Access I'm talking about, not set. Access any properties or
methods in yourself. So you can't say self.anything.
You know, you can't access any of the properties or
methods in yourself until you're fully initialized.
Okay, so you'll have to have called the other inits first.
Yeah? >> If you're building
an imperative class why would you
ever need convenience inits? >> So
the question is why would I ever use a convenience init?
The answer is I have a reasonable default for
some of the arguments to a designated initializer, and
it's actually possible to default things in swift.
You can basically say, equal something. But let's say you
wanna default into some calculative value, maybe based
on the other argument. A community initialize,
initializer you could create would have fewer arguments and
then turn around and call the designated one.
Okay, it's truly for convenience,
that's all these are for, phew is right, okay.
There's a lot of rules there. And it's a lot to think about.
And when you start writing your own initializers you're
gonna bump up against these all the time.
You're gonna be like I can't, I can't access that one until
I do, yeah, I gotta call supren, okay, believe me.
So try to stay away from doing your own inits,
is my advice to you. Okay, inheriting init.
Now, if you don't implement any designated inits,
you'll inherit all of your superclass's designated inits.
But if you in, if you implement even one designated
init, you don't get any of your superclass's designated
initializers, okay. If you override all of your desig,
class, superclass's designated inits, or
don't implement any of them, then you will inherit all of
the convenience initializers from your superclass, okay. In
other words, the convenience superv, initializers in your
superclass are all kinda dependent on the designated
initializer in your superclass being sensible and
making sense together. So you have to get them all
by overriding them all, or by overriding none of them. For
the convenience one to inherit,
to make, for sure make sense, okay. If you omit no inits,
you get all of your superclasses inits,
convenience and designated, okay. Any in it that
you inherit by these rules count on the previous slide.
All right, the previous slide says things like you have to,
convenience has to call a designated in your own class,
blah, blah, blah. Well, if you inherit it,
then it is in your own class. Okay, so
chew on that okay. Required init, different topic.
It is possible to mark an init with the keyword required.
That means that a subclass must implement this init.
Okay, it is not optional for it, it must.
And it can inherit if it follows these rules above.
But it must implement it, it's required, okay. UI view, for
example, which we're gonna do on Wednesday.
It has a required init.
Okay, and we're gonna see that. All right,
failable initializers, it is possible for init to fail.
We saw this double if you pass a string to the initialize,
if a double has an initializer it takes a string.
If you pass a string. That's not a double,
then it will fail, then return nil, okay.
So failable initializers cause optional versions of the thing
to be returned and you specify them with this little question
mark. You put in a question mark in there, that turns
this ititializer into the kind of initializer that will turn
an optional of this class whatever it is. Okay? And
to fail, you just return nil. Inside this initializer,
if something goes wrong, return nil, and nil will come
back to whoever's trying to get this thing. Make sense?
Okay, failable initializers are pretty rare. Images, for
example, UI image,
image named, if it can't find an image with this name,
it returns nil. Okay. So that's why this image right
here Let image. This image is an Optional UIimage. And
we probably use if-let here, if let image if we can like
this image equal to UIimage name foo, then whatever.
Okay? All right. Creating Objects All right,
usually you create an object by calling its initializer
with the appropriate arguments using the type name. So
CalculatorBrain, we've seen that,
ComplicatedObject with a bunch of arguments to create it.
Or here's let z = the type array of String initializer.
Okay, that creates an empty array of string.
It's constant, so it's gonna be empty forever, okay? But
sometimes other objects will create objects for you.
They can call a method and it will create an object for you,
give it to you, right? But
when you're creating objects from scratch, this is the.
Syntax you're using, you're used to that, right?
No questions about that, it's a kind of obvious slide. Okay,
now AnyObject, little more complicated here.
AnyObject is a special type, it's actually a protocol, but
we haven't talked about it yet, but anyway,
it's a special type. You can leave it as a type.
Protocols are types, I guess. It is used Commonly, or used,
used to be, for compatibility with Objective-C APIs,
because Objective-C, for those of you who are trying to learn
some Objective-C along the way here, Objective-C has a very
important type called ID. Okay, the type ID.
Which means pointer to a object of unknown class.
Okay. So that's a very open-ended type. [LAUGH] Okay,
Swyft doesn't do things that way. Swyft is strongly typed.
Okay, it infers types but it's strongly typed. However,
Swyft has to work with all those IOSAPIs, so
it introduced this type called AnyObject.
So AnyObject in Swyft means A point or two an object of
unknown class, okay? It only works for objects for
classes not for. So it means the same thing as objective C.
IN iOS 9 they fixed objective C. So it has almost none of
these, okay? They're still a few but very very few. So
nowadays It is more used as an opaque type. Okay?
When you want to have a point or
two in the object and you are not sure what it is or
you don't want anyone to know what it is okay?
So let's talk about how we can do this okay? So classes only
and no structs. There is another type by the way. It is
what is called any, which is anything. Could be a struct,
could be a class, anything. We almost, in fact, this class we
will never use Any, okay? You probably never wanna use it.
It's in there, I think, for just language completeness.
But I can't even think of a good explanation of why you
would wanna use it. So we're not even gonna talk about Any.
But we are gonna talk about AnyObject, okay?
So where will you see AnyObject? You'll sometimes
see it in a method where one of the arguments Truly can be
more than one different kinds of class, mm kay? For
example, you'll see on Wednesday, prepare for segue
which is a thing that prepares for transitions from one NVC
to another, okay? We're gonna have multiple NVCs someday.
We're gonna wanna transition from one to the other, prepare
for segue prepares for that transition. Well the sender,
in other words the object that initiated the transition could
be lots of different kinds of objects.
It might be a button you collect on,
it might be a roll in a table, it might be some custom code
inside of your controller. Okay? So this sender has to be
any object. Okay, cuz we don't know what it is. We
don't know if it is a button or table row or what it is.
So AnyObject. Okay. So this is a case where he is an object,
it could be many things we don't know what it is.
So we have to type this as AnyObject.
Okay? Another example of that is touch digit. If we haven't,
when we control dragged,
remember when we changed it from any object to UI button,
Okay. If we hadn't done that, it would have created a touch
digit with sender AnyObject and then touch digit could've
been sent by a UI button or maybe by UI slider. Okay. Or
something else. And we didn't do that because the inside
touch digit we wanted sender to be a UI button so
we just send it current title and other button things, but
it could have been AnyObject, all right? So, another use for
AnyObject is when you wanna return essentially a cookie,
okay? A cookie is something
you give back where you're giving it to someone,
they don't know what's inside of it,
you're not gonna tell them, the only thing they can do
is give it back to you, okay? So the cookie just saves some
state, remembers something and you can give it back. So
browsers have cookies, right? You go visit a browser site,
the site stores some stuff about itself and about you in
their cookie. When you go away and come back to that site,
it looks in the cookie and it can interpret it, okay?
But it gives the cookie to the browser.
The browser has no idea what's in there. Okay.
To pick with AnyObject as far as the browser is concerned.
All right. So how do we use a variable type AnyObject when
we don't know what the heck it is? Okay. And the answer is we
have to convert it to a type that we do know what it is.
Okay. Now this conversion might not be possible.
All right, because that thing might not be of that type
when we try to convert it. So
we use this as keyword in Swift to try to convert it to
the other type. Okay. In other words, try to treat that
AnyObject as something else, optionally. So this is an op,
this returns an optional. Okay, we usually, usually use
it with if let, this as thing because it ensure an optional,
right? So if I have this local variable here,
AO which is in AnyObject and I was tying it to something,
some class I don't know what it is, okay? But I wanna try
and use AO as if it were of class SomeClass, okay,
AO might be of SomeClass, and I'm gonna see if it is, and
if it is I'm gonna use it as some class, I say if I can let
foo equal AO as SomeClass, then in here there's gonna be
a local variable foo, which is not gonna be AnyObject, it's
gonna be of type SomeClass. Got it? Just to that symbol
essentially casting if you wanna use that terminology?
Casting any object to be some class conditionally, okay?
So that's how we use something of AnyObject either that or
we don't know what's in there we just pass it around. Okay,
just pass it around to people who know what to do with it.
We don't know what to do with it if it's a cookie, okay? So,
what would code look like let's say on touchDigit.
If we had touchDigit and we had any object instead.
We probably say if we can let sendingButton equal the sender
as a UIbutton, then we'll treat it as a button,
get its currentTitle and go. Other wise else if
we can let sending slider equal to sender as UI slider,
then we'll let the digit equal the sending sliders value
which is a double, we'll convert it to an int and
we'll convert that to a string, okay? That's how we
get the digit. Did you see how we're doing kinda if let else,
if let else? With this optional thing, that's how we
would use that AnyObject. All right, another use
of AnyObject is Property List, okay? So Property Lists are,
essentially any combination of array, dictionary, string,
double, int, NSData, and NSDate. Kay, if you build
any data structure out of only those classes,
you got a property list. So it's just a word. It's just
a term we use to mean that. Kay, that's what it means.
And you might feel like, wait a second. Array,
AnyObject has to be a class, it cannot be a structs.
But string, array, dictionary, double, those are structs.
So how could this ever be in a property list. How could it
ever be any object. And the answer is the bridging, kay?
We got this automatic bridging to Objective-C, kay?
It automatically treats them like NSDictionary, NSArray,
NSNumber, which are all classes. And allows them to be
AnyObject, kay? Now these property lists
are passed around blindly. The people who are looking in them
are only knowing that their dictionaries and
arrays of strings and dates and stuff.
They don't know anything about what that data means, okay.
They're just being passed around, so
let's look at an API and iOS that uses a property
list to understand it better. It's called NSUserDefaults.
What NSUserDefaults does, is it takes a property list and
makes it persistent on disk. So when your app quits and
runs again and you look it up again, it's there.
So it's basically a database of property lists,
a database of structures with dictionaries, arrays, dates,
okay, that's what it is.
It's a small database so don't use it for big things.
You wouldn't wanna store like a dictionary of the entire
English language in there. It's for
small things like settings and things like that. The API on
it is very simply just say, setObject, property list here,
forKey, string. And then you can look it up and
get the property list back. So here you can see how you're
just passing it around. You're storing it as a cookie and
it's user defaults has no idea what's inside there.
It just knows it's only array is dictionary strings,
ints, etc, okay. It can also restore smaller things.
Like as I said a double, and it will make a little property
list out of a double because a double by itself Is a property
list, right? Because it's one of those classes, okay?
Just like array is. How do you use user defaults?
You create a shared one using this class or type method,
NSUserDefaults.standardUserDe- faults().
This gives you the shared instance of standard, of user
defaults. And then you just say To it. Get me a certain
property list, write this property list out. The changes
you make will automatically be saved eventually, but
if you wanna force them to be saved on disk, you can do
synchronize, which returns a bool, which we almost always
ignore because not clear what to do if it fails.
It would probably only fail if your disk were full.
Not sure what you're gonna do at that point, but any way.
We usually ignore that return value, okay? Another example
of property list might be in our calculator brain and
I'm gonna show you a demo of this.
Really quick here, which is, what if we wanted to get
the program that it's in the calculator? Right now,
our calculator could be programmed by saying
five times four times three equals, let's put a program
in the calculator, right? Five times four times three.
It's kinda simple program. It'd be cool if we get
that program and the person who got it,
it doesn't know anything about our internal data structure.
So it's AnyObject to them. And then later,
they could come back to the CalculatorBrain and
say. Run this program that you gave me earlier, you see? So
we use AnyObject as kind of this opaque program.
Okay. Now this doesn't seem very variable right now.
But it's gonna be really valuable in assignment two,
when you're gonna add variables to your calculator.
You're gonna be able to say three times X times five
equals, where X is a variable, and
then you can run this then you get this program using this
code I'm going to show you here, the property list, and
then later you can, they can set the variable x and
run it again. Maybe set the x to something else and
run the program again and again and again, you see?
So this would be a good use of AnyObject, because
the calculator brain doesn't wanna give away its internal
data struc for how, structure for how it represents
a program. But it's happy to let someone have the program
and give it to them later and they'll run again it later.
Make sense, see why we want it?
Now why would we make it a property list?
Because it'd be nice to store it in user defaults, right?
I've got a program? I'm gonna put it in the user defaults.
Next time my program runs, I can pull it out and
ask a calculator brain to run it. You see,
it's just more flexible to be a property list.
So that's what we're gonna do. We're gonna create a var
called program in our calculator brain.
It's gonna be gettable and settable. When you get it,
it gets the current program in, that the calculator brain
has just run, and if you set it, it runs the program, okay?
All right, so I'm gonna do that as the demo. I'm gonna
finish off the slides here first. One thing about this
casting, you can cast other things besides any object,
okay. So you, for example, you can look at this slide later,
but you could have a class that's a subclass of another
class, okay? And you can try and cast using as to get
the subclass. You're not sure whether it's a subclass, but
you can cast and as will tell you whether it is, okay?
In this case, for example, if I have view controller
the base class of our view controller, we can't say
vc.displayValue cuz this is a CalculatorViewController
thing. But if I went and as'ed it, okay,
if I took this VC and as'ed it to CalculatorViewController,
now I could use displayValue. Okay, so as is for
more than just any object.
Okay, and yes, you can force with as!,
it'll crash if it can't do it. Assertions I'm not gonna talk
about cuz we talked about it in the debugging section.
You can look at the slide or the reading assignment to find
out more about assert. And that's it. So coming up on
Wednesday I'm gonna start talking about custom drawing.
On Friday we don't have a section for this week.
And next Monday I'm gonna start talking about gestures,
multi-touch gestures, okay, pinches and swipes and
stuff leading up to your assignment three,
which is you're gonna be doing a lot of drawing and
multiple MVCs and all that stuff. Your assignment this
week is going to be the variables thing, okay?
All right, so let's do that program var, okay?
Just gonna go back to our calculator here, all right,
and leave off exactly where we were. All right,
so here's my controller, right here.
I'm not gonna change my controller to do this.
This is purely a brain thing, okay, here's my brain,
calculator brain. So I'm gonna add a new var.
Let's put it I don't know, down here, okay?
It's gonna be called program. It's AnyObject.
Now I'm gonna make it be AnyObject, but I'm also gonna
make it be a property list, cuz it's more useful.
People can put it in as user defaults or whatever.
So I'm gonna use a cool Swift thing called typealias.
typealias lets you create a type, a name type,
that's exactly the same as some other type. So
I'm gonna create a type called PropertyList which equals
AnyObject. So PropertyList is now a type in Swift.
It's exactly the same thing as AnyObject.
Now why would I create this? That's because
I'm gonna change this to say PropertyList. So
I'm gonna cha, make the type of my program be PropertyList.
This tells anyone using my program that yeah,
it's AnyObject but it's also a PropertyList, okay?
This is documentation. I'm essentially documenting here
that this AnyObject is PropertyList.
I could have also just put some comments in my code that
says it is, but this kind of really hammers home the po,
the point here that this is a PropertyList,
okay? Now I'm gonna have my program here be computed,
okay? So I'm gonna do the get set thing, right? And
so now I need to have my program internally,
I mean, internally store my program, so I'm actually gonna
go up to the top and create another private var
which is my internalProgram. And
so I have to think about how I'm gonna store my program,
you know, all the operands and operations, internally. And
I'm just gonna store it to show you the power of
AnyObject. I'm gonna store it as an array of AnyObject,
okay? And the objects in that array are gonna be a double if
it's an operand or a string if it's an operation. So
I'm gonna have an array that has a mix of doubles and
strings, okay, and that's gonna store my program.
I'm just gonna put operands in as doubles and I'm gonna put
operations as strings. So that's another power of
AnyObject here. So how do I implement my internalProgram?
Real simple, okay. When I set an operand, I'm just gonna
tell my internalProgram append that operand, oops.
Okay, now normally this is AnyObject.
Operand is a double, that's a struct. That normally wouldn't
work, but the bridging, the Objective-C bridging,
will make this work. Okay, I told you everywhere in the UI
where you have this compatibility,
it's gonna automatically bridge.
I don't, look, I don't have to do anything or say anything.
It just automatically always bridges when necessary.
Okay, similar down here in my operation.
When someone performs an operation, I'm just gonna tell
my internalProgram append the symbol for this operation.
Okay, that's a string. Again, a struct but
it's automatically bridged to NSString and
thus can be an AnyObject. Okay, that's it, that's
the entire implementation of my internalProgram.
I'm just remembering every operand and operation.
So now I'm just gonna return that internalProgram here,
okay, to be the program.
Now you might be freaking out, whoa, you're returning
your internal data structure here to a public caller. But
what kind of type is an array? A value type. And
what happens when you return a value type? It gets copied.
Okay, so I'm not returning a pointer to my internal data
structure here, I'm returning a copy. Okay, that's, again,
a cool thing about having these things be value types.
All right, so now we have to do the set. So someone can now
get my program and they can give it back to me later and
I have to run it. Okay, so how am I gonna do that?
Well, when someone sets my program, first I'm gonna clear
whatever's in my program. So you, you guys probably
implemented something like this for your homework, but
I'm gonna, see clear my accumulator. I'm gonna say
that I have no pending binary operation. And I'm gonna
clear my internalProgram that I currently have out.
Actually I'll just removeAll items from my internalProgram.
Okay, so that's clear cuz I'm running a new program, so
I wanna clear all my stuff out.
Right, make sense? Now I'm just gonna say if
the program they get me, gave me is an array of op,
operands and operations, so I'm gonna
say if I can let arrayOfOps equal this newValue that they
just gave me as an array of AnyObject, which it has to be.
If it's not that, I can just ignore this. Someone gave
me a program which was not one that I gave out, so I'm
ignoring it, cuz it's gotta be an array of AnyObject or
I can't figure out what it is. So if it is, now I'm just
gonna go look through at all the ops in there,
all the operations and operands. Okay, an arrayOfOps.
Okay, that's how we loop through an array, right, for
in. And for each one I'm gonna check and see what it is.
Now what type, if I can Alt-click on this,
what type is this gonna be? >> AnyObject?
>> AnyObject, exactly.
See, AnyObject. So I can't do anything with AnyObject,
so I have to try and see if I can make it something else.
So I'm gonna first try and make it be an operand by
saying op as a Double, okay? So if I get to here,
then this op,
the next thing I looked in the array was a Double. Excellent,
then I can just say setOperand to be that operand, okay,
cuz I'm running the program. So I'm just gonna replay,
basically, my operands and operations. Otherwise,
if I can let, let's say operation = op as a String,
okay, then I'm going to perform that operation.
Okay? Done, okay, very simple, I've done it.
Now you're going to have to really make sure you
understand this, because you need to enhance this for your
assignment number two. Because you're gonna have variables,
you're gonna have to deal with here too. You're gonna have
variables in your program, not just operands and operations.
Now, let's see this thing in action.
We've got this code and we wanna make sure it works, so
let's put something in our UI that actually checks
this program business.
So, I'm gonna go back to my storyboard.
I'm gonna steal a couple of buttons here. I'm gonna make
this be the save button and this be the restore button.
So I'm gonna have the save button, save the program, and
then I have the restore button, restore the program.
Okay, so you can see how it would look like to use that.
So these are not operation buttons anymore, so
I'm gonna disconnect using right-click,
all these perform operations. Okay,
then I'm gonna wire these up. Let's make some room. Wire up,
down here. All right, so I'm gonna wire up save first.
Put it right here. I'll call it save. It's an action.
It doesn't need an arg,
I don't need the sender this time, this is the first time
we've seen where we don't need the sender. Okay,
at least the first time not in your homework.
And here's restore. And restore is also an action, and
it doesn't need an argument either. Here we go, there's
save and restore. Okay, how am I gonna implement this? Well,
I need the saved program, so I'm gonna have a savedProgram.
Its type could be any object, but
I'm actually gonna have it be CalculatorBrain.PropertyList.
Just to be clear to myself, this is a property list, and
if I wanted to save this into NFC or default,
I could. Okay, but I'm not going to, but I could.
All right, so how do I save?
And I'm gonna make this optional because,
of course I might not have hit save yet.
So it's gonna start out as nil,
as soon as I hit save it's gonna have a value. All right,
so how do I save? Well, I'm just gonna say that this
savedProgram = the calculators brain.program.
Okay, that's gonna store it in there, really good, you see?
How about restore? Okay, well, if I have a savedProgram
!= nil, then I'm just gonna set the brains.program
= savedProgram. Okay, I have to unwrap it,
cuz it's an optional. And then I'd better update my display
value now because the brain is gonna have a different result.
It's got a new program, it's gonna have a different result,
got it? Okay now, this code,
you don't need this in your assignment. This is,
I'm only putting this here just to demonstrate program.
You will need the other code in CalculatorBrain,
but you will not need this code. Okay, let's go ahead and
run this. All right,
here we go, make this a little bigger. All right,
let's rotate so that our restore button looks better.
All right, here we go. So let's put a program in here,
4 x 5 + 1 =. Okay, that's 21. Okay, let's save that program,
now let's do pi square root. Okay, that's good, + 8 =,
something like that. Now let's restore. What should happen to
our display when I restore? >> 21.
>> 21 cuz it's gonna rerun
that program. And sure enough, there it is.
Okay, 14 divided by 7=, restore. Okay, we, we,
we've run that program, and that's the result in there, so
we can say x 2 =. Okay, we could save
it again. Okay, 47 divide 8 =, and now when we restore,
we'll get 42, which is the meaning of life, the universe,
and everything, and so we're done, okay. So
get that program to code into your app, okay.
You'll need to add that to your assignment one, and then
I will be publishing, I might actually publish assignment
two before Wednesday, okay. It goes out on Wednesday,
due the next Wednesday. But for those of you who want to
start a little early, cuz you know everything you need to
know now to do assignment two as well, okay. So
I'll probably publish that earlier, maybe tomorrow.
>> For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.