[MUSIC]
>> Stanford University. >> Okay, well, this is
lecture six of Stanford SC193 P Spring of 2016. And today we
are gonna dive in more into this topic of multiple MVCs.
If you remember, last lecture I talked a little about
multiple MVCs and how we can combine them with tab bars,
split view controllers and navigation controllers. And
we showed a little bit how to wire them up. Well, today, I'm
gonna talk a little about how we transition between them,
right? It's one thing to wire them up in our storyboard, but
as the user navigates our user interface, clicks on buttons
and stuff, we want to navigate between these MVCs, okay?
And then, time permitting at the end, I'm gonna talk
a little bit more about this view controller lifecycle, the
thing that I always delete. Okay? Those two methods.
There's a few more methods in the view controller lifecycle
that I'm gonna talk about, and again, time permitting,
I'll do a quick little demo at the end. All right.
So, segues. Okay, we've wired up these controllers of
controllers like tab bar split fuse navigation controllers,
and we've got all of our nice MVCs, and
now we want to transition between them.
We call those transitions segues, right?
The word segue in English means a transition. And
there's really four major kinds of segues.
I'm gonna talk about some more rare segues towards the end of
the quarter, but the main segues that you're gonna wire
up in a story board, one is called a show segue.
So, remember the navigation controller that's the stack of
cards, right? The settings app I showed you where you're
putting more stacks on the card. Well, transitioning to
put a new card on the stack, okay, is done using a show,
what we call a show sequeway cuz it shows another MVP or
MVC. I'm thinking about Steph Curry, I guess, okay?
MVC. And then, show detail is if you have a split view,
okay, and something happens in the master and
you want to show an MVC, a different MVC in the detail,
okay? Show detail, that's the detail of a split view.
Show detail also works in a navigation controller,
okay? So, if you do show detail, it's this really
the same as show in a navigation controller, unless
that navigation controller is inside of a split view, okay?
Show and show detail would be the same. But
if a navigation controller's inside a split view,
then show means show it in the Navigation Controller, and
Show Detail means show it in the Split View Controller,
right? Show the detail. Then there's Modal and Popover,
I'm not gonna talk about those today. Modal is basically
segue into takeover the entire screen with another MVC, okay?
And a popover is almost exactly the same except for
instead of taking over the entire screen,
it still takes over the entire screen in terms of input, but
it draws it in a little popover window and
everything else is kind of grayed out and
you can click on the grayed out to dismiss the popover.
Okay? So those are the major kinds of segue that you wire
up in your story boards.
So, we're gonna talk about navigation controllers,
split view controllers, tab bar today.
So, for navigation and split view controllers,
we're talking about show and show detail, okay?
So, we're gonna talk about today. All right. It's very
important to understand that segue virtually
always create a new MVC. Okay? If you segue to an MVC,
it's going to create it. You rarely, extremely rare,
there's only one kind of segue where you're gonna segue to
an MVC that already exists. Okay? So, segues create new
MVCs, okay? Super important to understand. That's even true
in a split view. If you do a show detailed segue,
it replaces the MVC that's in the detail side.
That's why we sometimes call a show detail a replace segue,
okay? That's kind of its old name. All right? So, how do we
make these segues happen, okay? Just like we always do,
we control drag, okay? Just like we
control drag to wire up our MVCs to our split view
control, navigation control, we're also gonna control drag
to determine how they segue up to each other, okay? How they
transition. It's also possible to make segues happen in code.
There's a method you call that says do this segue,
perform segue, it's called, okay? So
here is something wired up as of our last lecture, here.
I've got a split view controller,
and the detail is this little graphing thing at the bottom.
And the master is a navigation controller with
your little calculator view controller right there, okay?
That calculator view controller up there,
looking at this side today, that calculator up there might
be exactly the same MVC as the one you're building in your
homework, okay? All right? So, if we want to add a button to
the calculator that caused this graph to show,
maybe graph what's in your calculator. Wouldn't that be
cool? Then we would Ctrl-drag from that little button.
Can hardly see that button, but it's there. Ctrl-drag to
the MVC we wanna segue to. Okay? So, that's how it works.
You would just Ctrl-drag to. Now, when you Ctrl-drag to,
it's gonna put up a little black window here,
which I'll zoom in on, which is going to ask you what kind
of segue do you want. Do you want a show? A show detail?
A modal? Or a popover? Okay? So if you want this to appear
as the detail in a split view, you're gonna pick Show Detail.
Otherwise, it's just in a navigation controller,
you're gonna pick Show, okay? Again, we'll talk about
the other two later in the quarter. All right?
So, you've got that wired up. As soon as you do that,
you've get this little guy appearing here,
this line with a little thing in the middle here.
This is the segue. Okay? And this segue,
just like a button or anything else, is inspectable. So
if you go over here to the inspector and inspect it,
it's going to let you set some things about the segue.
The most important thing is its identifier, okay?
Every segue needs an identifier, because in your
code, you're gonna have to refer to that segue,
and you do it by name. By this identifier.
That's how you're gonna refer to this in your code.
So it's critical that you give your segues names, okay?
This identifier thing. And
we'll see that in the demo. And the name of
the identifier should probably describe what the segue does.
It's usually a verb, like a verb phrase like show graph,
do something. Cuz that's what segues do, they do something.
So it's usually some kind of verb phrase. Okay. So, what,
so, where in our code are we gonna use that identifier for
the segue?
It's really two places. One place that we don't use too
much is when we want to make that segue happen from code.
And we can do that with this method in UI view controller,
okay? You have your controller.
You all know what that is, okay? It's called perform
segue with identifier. You give it the identifier, and
then you can pass any object you want as the sender, okay?
The sender is the object that is causing the segue to
happen. Often that's a button, okay? But when you're doing it
from code, you can send any object really that you want.
Okay? And you'll see why we need that in a moment. Okay?
So that's one reason you need the identifier.
But a much more important reason is because when a segue
happens, the MVC your segueing to,
usually needs to be prepared to come on screen. Okay?
It needs some information.
Maybe it needs it's model to be set. That's a common thing.
Maybe it needs some of it's drawing attributes to be set,
okay? So that is happening in this preparation.
So, this is so important.
I'm gonna talk about the preparation in detail. Now,
the preparation happens with a method that is sent to
the view controller that is causing this segue to happen.
Not the view controller on
the other end that's being created, but
the one that is causing it to happen, okay?
That view controller is gonna be sent this message,
prepare for segue. Okay? And it's job in this method is
to prepare the MVC that's being created by the segue to
do what it wants to do. Now, it's really important to
understand with this multi-MVC world, that it's object
oriented in that each MVC kind of has it's own world.
Okay, they don't really wanna be talking back to each other.
And the MVC on the ender end of a segue is really part
of the view of the MVC that's causing the segue. Remember
those graphics that I told you? So we really can't talk
back to the one causing the segue. We would have to use
some kind of blind structured communication because the view
is not really allowed to talk to its controller, except for
in these structured ways, right?
The controller can talk to the view,
no problem. And he's going to here. This is going to be
the controller talking to its view by preparing
that MVC. But
you really wanna think of MVCs as living in their own world,
self-contained, they have some public API,
you set things in their public API, and they do what they do,
okay? It's very tempting when you're writing code,
especially maybe a lot of the code that you've written so
far in classes, to think, well, I can just put a method
here and a method there, and they can all call each other,
and it's all fine. But it's not, you need to start
thinking in terms of programming interfaces, okay,
encapsulation, true object oriented programming here.
Okay, I made you think about that a little bit in your
calculator brain and the calculator view controller,
assignment with
right? The calculator brain has a public API,
it's very clear what the public methods are,
those are the only methods a controller can use, okay?
Hopefully you didn't write your assignment,
where they're each calling, private messaging each other,
or things like that, okay? There's gotta be well-defined,
what those objects encapsulate, okay.
That's object oriented programming. So
same thing here, but at the whole MVC level, right?
We want the MVCs to be well-defined in what they do.
All right, so let's talk about prepareForSegue here and,
how you make it work, what all the parts of it are, okay? So
what it does,
first of all, you have the arguments here for
prepareForSegue. The first argument is the segue. So
this is a instance of a class called UIStoryboardSegue.
And it contains interesting information about the segue,
most notably the identifier.
Okay, that identifier we typed in the inspector, and also,
the controller of the MVC that you're segueing to.
It just created it, and you can, cuz remember,
segue is always created an MVC, so it just created
that thing, and you can get a pointer to it
from this segue argument right here, one of the properties on
UIStoryboardSegue is the destination view controller.
Okay, this other argument here, sender,
it's the same sender as was in perform segue with identifier.
This is just who caused this segue to happen. Usually,
it's a button, okay. But it could be any object if you,
if it started in code with perform segue with identifier,
okay? So we'll, we'll see this in the demo sometimes why you
would wanna know who this is, okay? All right, so
here's the identifier,
I'm getting it with the, var here called identifier,
right, the property off of the segue thing.
I'm checking here to make sure it's not nil. Because someone
might have created a segue in the storyboard, and
they forgot to set the identifier or
they didn't set the identifier. So
it could be nil, so
I'm checking to make sure it's not nil here. And then
I'm switching on it, okay? So I'm gonna switch on it.
And in this case, I'm gonna look for Show Graph,
which is in my previous slide, that's what I called,
that's what the identifier for that thing was.
And when I see that this is a Show Graph segue, then
I'm going to try and prepare the destination of the segue,
assuming that it is some sort of graph controller, right,
some code controller,
controller of an MVC that shows the graph. So
I'm gonna have to prepare it, I'm gonna have to prepare it,
okay. So the first thing that I'm gonna do is I'm gonna look
at the destination view controller of the segue, where
we're segueing to, okay. And I'm gonna see if it's a graph
controller. And it better be, because that's the only
way I know how to prepare for a segue called Show Graph. So
this thing better be, but I am doing if let with as to,
to see if it is, because destination view controller,
its type is just UIViewController, okay. So
I need to cast it with as just like I cast any
object sometimes with as.
Here I'm gonna cast this view controller, if I can,
to be a specific kind of controller that I'm expecting
this segue to be segueing to. Okay, so in this case,
some sort of graph controller of some sort. All right,
now once I've done that, now VC right here is gonna be
of type graph controller. Okay, that's what if let
this as that does, right, inside this curly brace,
vc is gonna be of type graph controller. And so I can start
sending messages and setting properties, public ones only,
of this controller in order to prepare it to do its job. So
if it's a graph controller, I don't know,
it might wanna know the axes, the range of the axes.
Somehow it might wanna know what function it's graphing,
I don't know. Okay, but that is happening in here,
where I'm preparing this graph controller that just got
created cuz of a segue to do what it does. Okay, questions
about that? All right, so it's really important
to understand, and that's why it's in red here, I don't put
things in red very often. But it's in red that when you're
doing this prepare of that destination view controller,
it was only just created just now, okay, femtoseconds ago,
okay. So its outlets have not been set, okay. This happens
before its outlets are set. This is quite annoying, okay,
because usually when you wanna prepare a view controller,
you wanna set things up in its outlets, like a calculator
one, you'd want to set something in the display or
something like that. But you can't do that, okay,
unfortunately, you can't do that.
This is happening before your outlets are set, so
you have to just give it the data it wants, and you're just
gonna have to hold on to that data. And then after its
outlets are set, it can start parceling that out to its UI,
okay? You will, at least once this quarter, get a crash,
because you'll start preparing some view controller.
You'll start accessing its outlets, it goes out with your
still nil, and you're gonna get optional nil was
accessed, okay. I'm gonna do it in my demo just to show
you it happening because it can happen so much.
All right, okay, so that's preparing,
super important part of segues, okay, so preparing.
Now there's a method you can also implement in your view
controller in addition to prepareForSegue called,
shouldPerformSegueWithIdentif- ier, okay.
And that is basically gonna return a bool, whether or
not that segue should happen. So you can prevent it, for
example, let's say in your calculator,
let's say you had a button that did a graph, and
let's say it was a partial result, so
you couldn't really graph it. This might return false, okay?
And maybe you'll see that on your homework. All right, so
the demo I'm gonna do is I'm gonna take FaceIt,
that we have so far that draws that face, I'm gonna add
a second MVC, okay. And this MVC's gonna have some emotions
listened in it, and when you click on them,
it's gonna show a face that reflects that emotion, okay?
So I'm gonna have two MVCs, and
we're gonna hook them up. Okay,
so here we are back in FaceIt, exactly where we were.
I haven't, added anything or changed anything, right?
So we've got our face view controller right here,
it's got its model, which is a facial expression. And
then it's got its view, which is this face view thing right
here. We add some gestures, we update our UI when this thing
is first set, our update UI just takes the model,
all these things out of the model, okay? And
it turns them into things in the view,
and and these are just the handlers for
these gestures. And that's it, so
that's all we have in our controller. And our story
board is really, really simple, it only has this one
view controller, okay, this face view controller. And
what I'm gonna do right off the bat is add another MVC.
So how do you add another MVC to your storyboard?
Well, you go over here to your object palette, and just like
from your object palette, you can do things like, adding
buttons and labels, you can also add entirely new MVCs.
And the way you do that is by grabbing this thing called
view controller at the top. In dragging it out into your
storyboard, okay. You can put it right there.
You can move things around wherever you want. Okay, so
now I have two MVCs in here. One really interesting thing
to note is that an NVC always need to have a custom class.
Okay, if it doesn't have a custom class,
where are you going to put your outlets and actions and
all that stuff. So just like this view controller,
if you look at it's identity inspector, remember we changed
it's identity and the identity inspector to be face
view controller, okay. So that makes it so
that this class is the controller for that thing, so
it has a model and outlets and things like that. Okay we need
to do the exact same thing with this view controller.
It needs to have a custom class. So the way you create
classes, you'll remember just like we did when we created
Face view for example. Is we do new file here. Okay so
I'm do new file. It's going to be iOS source, It's going to
be Coco Touch class because it's going to be a sub class
of UI view controller. Just like Face View controller was.
So I'm gonna double click here. Here, subclass of,
this is good, okay. Remember we did UI View before,
now we want UI View controller as our class. We don't want
to call it view controller, that's a very generic name, so
I'm gonna call it Emotions View Controller because that's
what it shows. This view controller shows emotions,
okay. Put it in the same place we always put it,
right here, same same as all our other code.
And here we go. Here's our emotions view controller,
again I'm going to remove these few controller
life cycle methods for now. But
notice also when I created this,
I got this little method. What is this method? Prepare for
segue. Okay, segues are so important to have in multiple
view controllers. That when it gives you a blank one, it
always gives you prepare for segue commented out, but it
knows you're almost certainly gonna want to prepare for
segue. Okay, that's how important this is. And indeed
we are gonna have to implement this if we want clicking on
emotions to go to our other MVC and do things, okay?
But we're not going to do this right now. The next
thing we're going to do, and you'll forget this step, okay?
You will for sure forget this step multiple times.
Which is we have to remember to go here and set in
the identity inspector, the class of this thing to be that
emotion's view controller. A lot of times you will create
that emotion view control, you just dive right in,
you start programming, and you forget to do this, and then
you cannot connect any of your outlets, and you are like,
what is wrong with this thing? Okay, well this is why.
You forgot to type your identity, here,
okay? So, now I have two, you see? This one says emotions
view controller and this says face view controller, so
two NVCs. Notice this little arrow right here.
You see this arrow? This arrow tells the app when it runs,
start with this view controller. So
if I were to run right now it would show the face, but
if I wanted to show my new view controller first I can
just pick this arrow up and drop it on this one.
Okay, so let's go ahead and run actually to verify that.
We should get a nice blank screen. Okay?
Here it is. Nice blank screen, working perfectly. Now,
one thing to notice, also is, it, I got a warning here.
Look, see this warning? Scene is unreachable due to lack of
entry points. It's talking about this scene,
okay? By the way, we call these MVCs in the storyboard.
This is called a scene. Okay? A scene. So this scene
is unreachable, because this arrow doesn't point to it.
And nothing in here segues to it. So you can't get to it,
okay, which makes sense. So
it's good that it's warning us about that. All right let me
build the UI of this guy right here. Okay? As I said it's
just gonna have some emotions in here that you can click on.
Normally you probably wanna do this with the table view.
Okay a table and extensible list of them.
But I can't I'm not teaching a table view until next week.
So we're gonna use buttons. All right?
So I'm just drag out four buttons here to be my
the four emotions that I am going to have here.
Sorry, put this in here.
And when I drag it out, it does not really matter where I
put it because I am going to stack view them. So
let us go ahead and make the font a little bigger here, 40
point. And so what buttons do we wanna have here? How about
an angry button and we'll have three other buttons.
How about happy and how about worried? Is that a,
an emotion, worried? I don't, I don't know.
It's good to make a face of it though. How about mischievous?
Mischievous, is that how you spell that?
Again I'm not sure that's an emotion, but
it makes a good face. Okay so here I have my things,
I'm going to stack view these.
Just going to select them all and go embed in stack view.
I don't want them left aligned like this, so
I'm going to change their alignment to fill the space.
I'll do fill equally although they're all the same font so
they're all gonna be the same height anyway so
it doesn't really matter there. So,
I want these words to always be in the middle of my screen,
even if I'm rotated like if I'm in landscape or
portrait, I always want them in the middle. So I'm gonna
use the dash blue lines to put it right in the middle.
And now you're going to do the same trick we did before,
which was rest to suggested constraints and
it's going to use those blue lines
to suggest some constraints to constrain this stack for
you on here. And let's go look what it suggested,
remember to do that we go over here to the size inspector.
We go down to where it says constraints, and sure enough,
align the center in the x-axis to superview and
align the center in the y-axis to superview. Perfect,
exactly what I want. So now if I run, it's gonna center this
horizontally and vertically. Okay, even if I'm in
landscape. Okay? So now, I've built this UI. Great,
it's exactly what I want. And I had now have two NVCs. Now,
I'm gonna show you all three ways of combining NVCs, tab
bars, split view controllers, and navigation controllers.
Let's start with tab bar controller, okay? How would I
put these two things one in its, each in its own tab?
Well, I'm gonna go down here, okay? To our object pallet.
And if you look, about six or seven down, there's this.
Tab bar controller, you see that? And if I drag this
out here, okay, it'll put this tab bar out here.
It unfortunately also brings some extra MVCs here,
these little blank MVCs that I don't want. So I'm just gonna
click on those and delete them. So get rid of that one.
And get rid of that one. So all I have now is my tab bar
controller. If you can read that, I'll zoom in a little.
Okay see tab bar controller and then I've got my two
MVC's here that I created. My emotions view controller and
my face view controller. Now I for sure want
the app to start with the tab bar controller, so I'm going
to move that arrow. This is another thing you'll forget.
You'll forget to move this arrow. Okay. And
now I just want this to be in one tab and this in the other.
I just do that with control drag. So control
drag to this one, I'm going to hook up this view controllers.
Remember the view controllers
property in a tab bar is just an array of all the tabs.
Okay, the MVCs is there in the tabs and do this one also,
that in the view controllers array, okay. You can even see
it's already starting to put the tabs on the bottom.
If you wanted to edit what's in these tabs, like the names,
you think, you double click down here something, but no,
because this is the Tab Bar Controller and these titles
and images are all set by the MVCs inside. Okay,
in an object oriented way, right. So, if you wanted to
set this you would actually go to each one of them.
And you can even double click right here and put in whatever
you want. You can also click here and inspect them, okay,
if you go to the inspector, you can set images and also
a bunch of system ones. Okay, so that's how you set that.
So this is what our Storyboard looks like right now and
if we run this. We'll see that we get a tab bar.
See, it's got two tabs at the bottom here. And
if I click between them, I get my two MVCs.
Now this is completely inappropriate to what I'm
building here because I would never want, if I clicked on
one of these, for it to switch over to this tab, okay?
That's because when you do a tab bar UI, listen closely,
the user owns which tab is showing, okay?
They get to choose by clicking on those tabs. You don't get
to choose by throwing them over to one, okay?
That is not appropriate for tab bar. Everyone got that? So
things in a tab bar UI tend to be independent things,
things that don't segue from one to another,
you can't even make a segue from one tab to another, so no
such segue. So we don't want to do a tab bar controller
here, so I'm just going to delete my tab bar controller,
okay? Now one thing you'll notice when I deleted my tab
bar controller is, where's my arrow? Okay, it's gone. So
now it's not going to, if I run, I'm actually going to get
an error in the console saying I don't know where to start
in my storyboard, basically. So how do you get that arrow
back? Just click the one you want
the arrow to be on, inspect it, and go right down here,
very top, is initial view controller,
if you turn that on, the arrow will come back there, okay?
And you can move it, okay, down to here if you want.
Okay? All right, so let's talk about split view controller.
We haven't even done anything with iPad at all in this class
yet. So this is our first time doing it and we're gonna put
this in split view controller where this is the master and
this is the detail, makes sense, right?
Because we're clicking in the master,
this will be the detail that's shown from clicking on this.
So how do we do a split view controller?
Same way as tab bar. I'm gonna go down here, right below tab
bar is split view controller. I'm gonna drag that out,
I get a whole bunch of junk with it. We'll zoom out so
you can see it. Okay. See, I got all these extra things, so
I'm gonna, click on these extra things and
delete them, don't want any of them. Okay. So I just have
the split view controller and my two guys here.
Of course I want the split view controller, again,
to be the start so I'm going to put the arrow there. And
then, in order to hook up master and detail, Ctrl+Drag.
Master, Ctrl+Drag, detail. Okay,
so that's how we set it up, couldn't be simpler. So let's
run, but let's run on iPad, so I'm gonna, on iPad 2 here,
we'll run and hopefully this will show up as a master and
this will be the detail. All right. So here's the iPad.
Here's the detail. You notice that when it's in portrait
it fills the screen with the detail,
and you get the master by dragging out from the side.
See that? Okay? That's how you get the master. And
if you're in landscape,
then they're both onscreen at the same time. Now, if I click
on these, I want this face to show me angry, show me happy,
show me worried, show me mischievous, okay?
So how do I do that? This is where the segues come in.
Okay? This is where we have to have this view controller
segue to create a new one of these and
when it creates this, it's going to create it with
the proper facial expression, okay? So it's going to prepare
it with a facial expression and show it. Okay? So
let's do those segues. The way we do segues, also Ctrl+Drag.
So, let me zoom in here so you can see this. All right?
I'm gonna Ctrl+Drag from whichever of these buttons
I want to segue from. I'm gonna segue from all four, so
I'm gonna have four segues. So like angry here I'm
just gonna Ctrl+Drag down to this MVC. And let go.
And it says, well what kind of segue do you want?
Show, show detail, modally or
pop over. Well, we're in the split view controller here so
I want to show detail, right? Split view. Master detail.
Show detail. Bam. There it is right there. Okay?
Created this little thing here. That's my segue. And
this segue can be inspected. You can see it up here, okay?
This is the attributes inspector. And it's got
the kind of show detail, also known as a replace segue.
It animates, it shows that this segue is going to happen
in an animated fashion, so it's going to slide in or
whatever. It's not always makes sense to animate but
sometimes it does. Class and module, don't worry about
that. That's for creating your own custom segues,
which we're not going to talk about in this class.
A little bit too advanced. And then, here is the all
important identifier. So here, we have to give any string
we want that identifies this segue. So I could call this,
for example, the angry segue, maybe I'd want a verb
phrase like show anger or something like that but
it's fine also maybe to have a nice simple word like anger.
So that's my angry segue right there.
Okay. And so now let's wire up the other ones, Ctrl+Drag this
one down here. This one is also going to be show detail.
They're all going to be show detail. I'll do worried also.
Show detail, oops, not present modally, get rid of that.
Alright. Then here. Show detail.
Mischievous. Show detail.
Okay, now I need to set the identifier for all of these.
What's really cool is if I click on one it'll tell me who
the sender of this segue is. So there's worried, okay.
Worried. Here is happy, and
we'll call this my happy segue.
This one, angry already set up. This one, mischievous,
okay. Mischievous. Hopefully I spelled that right. Okay, so
now we've got these segues set up so let's run and
see what happens here. All right, angry, happy,
still nothing's happening. What is the problem here?
Okay, well, it is actually segueing here.
It's replacing that face with a new MVC, but
that new face has not been prepared to show the emotion
we want so it's just showing the default emotion,
whatever happened to be in our storyboard, right?
This face right here just happens to be, or or
it's actually what happens to be the default our model is is
that. Okay, so we need to, in all these segues, prepare
the MVC that we are segueing to. We do that in the source
view controller, that is the emotions view controller.
This is the thing that implements Prepare for Segue.
So I am just going to un comment out the comments here,
okay, for my Prepare for Segue. Make lots of space.
Alright, so here we have Prepare for Segue,
we get the two arguments, the segue which tells us a little
bit about which segue it is and
what the destination view controller is and then we have
the sender. That's going to be those buttons,
like the angry button, the mischievous button.
That's what this is going to be,
it's going to be the UI button. Okay?
This is any object because it is allowed to be any object.
In this case it's a button, but
it's allowed to be any object. All right.
So what do we do here in preparing for
segue? The first thing I'm going to do is get a hold
of the destination view controller, and
make sure that it's a face view controller.
Cuz if it's not, I don't really know how to,
the segue so I'm just going to do nothing in that case. So
to prepare for
I'm going to create a little local variable, okay?
I'm going to call it destinationvc, destination
view controller. And that's just equal to the segue,
destin, segue, destinationViewController,
okay? Now this is a UIViewController, okay,
of some sort, it's some sub-class of UIViewController.
I suppose it could even be UIViewController itself.
There's probably a subclass of it, and so I need to get
that subclass, I need to get this variable, in some way,
so that it's a subclass of it. Or I can't work with it.
Right? Because, UIViewController, I wouldn't
be able to send any of the face view controller messages
to it, because it's just a generic UIViewController, so I
need to get myself a faceview controller so I'm gonna say,
if I can let facevc, which is a new variable,
equal the destinationvc As a FaceViewController.
Then I'm ready to rock here. Okay, now I have
a FaceViewController, okay? So I've just casted.
They're similar to how I can't work with any object,
I really can't work with a generic UIViewController.
I need the subclass. Otherwise how am I going to set its
model, okay? I have to be able to talk to it. All right. So
now I have this destination view controller.
Now I need the identifier. So here I'm gonna say, if I can
let the identifier equal the segue's identifier. Okay,
so here I'm just checking to make sure it's not nill.
Now it should be angry, or mischievous, or happy.
One of those identifiers that I put in the stored word,
right? And I could do something here like,
switch on the identifier.
And if it's angry then I'm going to have my face vc's
expression be a facial expression that's angry, blah,
blah, blah. I could do that but
that's going to be allot of if then, blah, blah, okay, mess.
So instead I'm going to do one of my favorite ways to
program, as you're probably getting the,
idea about which is use a dictionary. Okay, so
I have this dictionary I'm gonna type in real fast, okay,
and this dictionary has keys which are the identifiers, and
it has values which are the appropriate facial expression.
Okay, got that, so
instead of doing all of this switching on the identifier
thing, I'm just going to say if I can let the expression
that I want equal these emotional faces up here.
Tha's this dictionary up here. Index by the identifier.
Okay? Then I know the expression that I want.
And now I can prepare my face VC okay, by setting its
expression equal to this expression. Okay, and remember
FaceVC.expression, that is just FaceViewControllers model
which is a public bar. This View Controller allows
its model to be set externally, publicly,
okay, which makes sense given this kind of model.
Not all, and doesn't make sense always for
every MBC to allow it's model to be set but often it makes
some sense. Alright, so now I've prepared this Faceview
controller to do what it needs to do. Everybody got that? OK.
So now let's run it and see if it's working. Okay.
So here we go, we have our iPad here, let's try angry.
Crash a roo. Hmm. Wonder why that crashed? Well let's look,
let's use the debugger. Okay, we haven't used the debugger
much in these demos but let's do it here. Seems like,
okay, whenever I have a crash, I always look first in
the console, okay, because the console is always going to
tell me something about what happened. And here it says
unexpectedly found nil while unwrapping an optional value.
Okay, well this is probably the number one crasher you're
ever going to get, it's one of the few ways actually to crash
Swift code is to have unwrapping and nil.
So it is happening on this orange line of code.
I am looking here. Does anyone see an optional here? No?
Nobody sees an optional on this line of code?
It doesn't look like it, does it? Because you do not see any
exclamation points. I am not unwrapping anything.
What is going on? Well actually what is face view,
what's its type? Anyone remember? Our outlet,
that's our outlet remember here? Right, it's a optional
face view, okay? It's implicitly unwrapped okay,
but it's still an optional. And I told you in the slides,
that your outlets are not set at the time you're preparing.
So this face view right here, okay, is nil, let's look.
Okay, here's where our variables are down here,
clicking on "self", face view, sure enough nil.
So my pointer to my face view has not been set yet by iOS
and that's always gonna be the case when you're preparing so
be prepared for that happening okay. So what can we do about
it here? Okay well one thing we could say if face view does
not equal nil then we'll do all this updating UI stuff
right? K, by the way why is this happening,
why are we on this line of code? If we look over here on
the left it'll show us how us we got here.
Okay, so we're in this place right here,
okay, and let's see how we got here by clicking here. See,
we set our model which makes sense and it called up DUI, so
why are we setting our model, okay, let's go up more. Sure
enough here we are preparing. Okay, setting our model.
So this is right, preparing for segway, goes in here set
to our model. Wants to update UI, it's great.
Unfortunately our view is not been connected via outlet.
All right, so this is one way we could do it. By the way,
there is another trickier way to do it which is to
use question mark here.
You know that question mark works for optional chaining,
right, on the right hand side of an equals?
It also works on the left hand side. If you put a question
mark there, that's and you can put as many of the question
marks as you want on the left side of an equals. And
if any of the things that you put a question mark are nil,
it just ignores the whole statement.
Like it didn't even happen. Okay. So, that would be
another way. But we would have to put a question mark on
every single access of faceview in here. So,
we might as well just check to see if it's not nil. Now, is
this going to fix our problem? And the answer is, yes it is.
Because we do update UI when our model gets set, but
we also do update UI when this outlet gets set, remember?
So when the outlet later, after the prepare is done,
when the outlet comes along and gets set, boom,
our UI will get updated with the model that we set during
prepare, okay? So it's going to work fine, okay?
But this is part of the reason why when our outlets get set,
we update UI and when our model gets set,
we update our UI because the order of them happening can be
you know can vary. All right. Sound good alright.
So we fixed that, we checked this so
it's not gonna crash anymore, so let's run and
hopefully this is all working like a charm now.
All right here we go ready? Angry,
happy, worried, mischievous.
Okay. All right? So it's working great. Okay, and
let's try it this way. Slide out. Angry, happy, right?
Working like a charm. Okay? Okay, all right.
Now, what about iPhone? Okay, this is great on iPad.
Let's try running this on iPhone, and see what we get.
All right, here's our thing. We got it here. Let's try
happy. All right, we're happy! Actually, now we're not so
happy because we're stuck. Okay, there's no way for
me to get back to choosing something else. Okay, I could
try rotating. No. I can try sliding out from the left.
Nope, no. OK, split view does not split on an iPhone.
Only on the iPhone 6 Plus, which is
the only one big enough to really do it,
okay? So we're stuck here. So this UI that we have in our
storyboard is no good for iPhone, okay? Now we can still
make our guy blink, okay? But that's all we can do.
So unless we're happy just watching him blink all day
we need to fix this. So how are we gonna make this work on
iPhone? Okay. First we have to ask ourselves what would be
an appropriate UI on iPhone. Okay,
and this is where navigation controller comes in.
Navigation controller would be great here because
you start the stack of cards with the angry mischievous
worried MVC. And then when you click the face it puts
a new card on top which is the face. And then if
you want a different one you just hit back, throw that card
away, and you are back to the angry mischievous worry choice
again, right? Okay, so it's perfect, okay,
navigation controller would be a perfect UI. So we need to
put navigation controller into our story board, okay. So
let's do that. Let's go back to our story board over here.
There's a lot of space here.
So where I'm gonna put this navigation controller? Well,
you really need one navigation controller around the root.
View controller. The base card, cards at the bottom.
Okay? So I can put a navigation controller here in
the same way I put these other things by going down here. You
can see there's a navigation controller right here.
I could drag it out. I could control, drag,
etc. There's actually a cooler way to do it, which is select
your route MVC which is this guy. That's the card that's
at the bottom of the stack and go up to editor and
just like you did in bed and stack view, do embed and
negotiation controller. You can also do it for
tab bar by the way, but do a navigation controller.
Now watch what happens here, boom! You put this
inside a navigation control automatically wired it up.
Now whats kind of interesting about this is, it also made
that navigation controller be the master of the split view.
In other words, it kind of wrapped the navigation
controller around the root con, the root view controller
and kept that pointer to the master. So
now the master is actually a navigation controller,
with this as it's root view controller. Still all these
segways are still here. Okay, these segues are still,
they didn't it didn't undo any of these segues. And
this is still the detail of the split-view controller.
>> How did I put it in there?
I selected this, which is my root-view-controller,
and I went to editor, embed in, navigation controller.
Okay? So, now this is an interesting set up right here.
Let's see if just fixed it, maybe it will just work.
Because, you know, I hear,
I got this, in a navigational controller, right now, so
it should just work on a iPhone, right?
Let's try it. How many people think this going to work?
Raise your hand if you think this is going to work.
Nobody thinks it's gonna work. It is going to work! Gotcha.
Okay. So here I am in my navigation controller.
I'm going to go back. Here is my stuff. Let us try worried.
He looks worried. I am not worried though cuz I know it
is going to work. Okay so this worked fine, exactly what
we want on iPhone. Now my question to you is,
is this still going to work on iPad? Okay.
Let's go look at that. Let's go back to iPad.
How many people think it's going to work on iPad still.
One. Two. Three. You guys are getting smart. Yes.
It's still going to work on iPad.
Okay. It's pretty cool the way they made this work so you can
build one storyboard that'll work fine on both platforms.
So here we go, this is iPad, we can turn it around,
here it is, it is in a navigation controller,
you see? Which is actually kind of nice, cuz I can put
a nice title in here for this MBC, okay. But when I click in
here, it's not going to slide a deck onto the deck of cards,
it's going to do the show detail, right, angry, happy,
worried, mischievous. Okay? Everyone got that,
how we do that? Now this kind of structure,
we have split view, navigation controller, and
then the content for your master, and
then the detail right here. Very common to build this,
because if you're building an app that works on both,
this is what it's gonna look like basically. All right,
so I'm gonna show you one
last thing here of interest, which is these titles, okay.
So we have this little space for a title up here, so
I'd like to put a title here, okay. And how do I put a title
up here? Again, remember that's object oriented, okay.
That title comes from whatever MVC happens to be showing in
this navigation controller at the time. So
I go to the storyboard, to that MVC, which is this one,
and could just double click on it, okay? So
we'll call this one Emotions, okay. So now if I run,
I get a nice title up here,
Emotions. What if I wanted a title over here? Okay,
how would I do it if I wanted a title over here?
Well if you look on the iPhone,
okay if we go back and oops, run this on iPhone.
Since both MVCs are in that navigation controller,
they both have titles Okay, so if I go here, here's emotions,
angry. Look, there's room for a title up here. But
back on the iPad, that's not the case because the detail,
when you replace the detail it doesn't actually put it
inside the same navigation controller that the master is
in. So the master is in a navigation controller, but
this is not. So if we wanted a title here,
we have to put this guy in a navigation controller.
Even though we're not going to use the navigation controller
for anything except for the title on the split view case.
We would still have to do it.
And in fact, iOS makes it so that just works, okay?
So I'm going to go here. Down to this guy. Okay and
I'm going to embed him in a navigation controller okay.
So just have this, I have the face selected,
embed puts him in there, okay. Now this
almost is going to work, okay, if we look at what this looks
like. Okay? There's a little bit of an issue here because
these segues are now going to this navigation controller.
But let's take a look at what it looks like anyway. Okay,
on iPad look, they're both in navigation controller.
So I've room for a title here now, okay? And if I click,
it doesn't work anymore. Okay, so I broke it by putting this
in a navigation controller. Now why, and by the way,
does it work on iPhone? Yes, still works on iPhone. So
it did not break it on iPhone because iOS is smart
enough to know this is already in a navigation controller, so
I'm just gonna ignore this navigation controller and
put this in here. See? So this looks the same, no change,
still in a navigation controller.
iOS didn't put a navigation controller inside a navigation
controller, in fact iOS never puts a navigation controller
inside another one. Okay, if it sees and
encounters another one, it just ignores that one,
okay. It's like you're either in one or you're not,
you can't be in two at the same time. So
it worked great on the iPhone. So why did it break though?
Sorry, it worked great visually but it still,
I didn't show it there but it didn't work to click.
Okay, just like in the iPad it didn't work to click. And
why didn't it work to click? Well, we have to understand or
prepare a little bit better there, okay?
And in fact, let's take the time to do this.
I'm gonna go in the debugger and show you this.
So I'm gonna set a break point right here, okay?
In prepareForSegue because prepareForSegue is not
properly preparing that thing. So let's see why it's failing.
All right, so here we go. I'm going to hit happy. And
it's going to break, okay, at this prepare.
So it's trying to prepare that thing to be happy. And
what is, let's look at this destination VC right here.
Look what its type is. It's a UN navigation controller.
And that kind of makes sense, right?
Because if you look at our storyboard,
these segues are going down to this navigation controller.
Okay? So that's just a little bit of a twist.
A little bit tricky. And all we have to do is look at this
destination VC and if it's a navigation controller,
then let's get moving inside of it. Okay. And
work on that. Okay. So I'm just going to say here,
if I can let Navcon, which is a local variable,
equal the destination VC as a UI navigation controller. So,
if the destination happens to be UINavigationController,
then I'm gonna let I'm just gonna set the destination VC
equal to the navcon.visibleViewController.
Which is optional, so I'm gonna,
actually I won't even unwrap it.
I'm gonna say if it's visible view control and
if the navigation control doesn't have a visible view
control then we'll just leave it to be the destination view
controller. This'll have to be bar. Okay? So
here all I'm doing is, I'm just saying if I'm preparing
to segue to something and it's a navigation controller,
then instead look inside the navigation controller and
segue to that instead. Okay? Prepare that instead. Okay?
Everyone understand what I'm doing there with these, this
little Three lines of code? >> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Yes, so you're
saying, could I go
back here in the storyboard and
have all these segue things go down over this way instead?
You wouldn't actually want that,
because when the segue creates the MVC that it's gonna show,
you want it to create a navigation controller. So
you actually want it to go into this navigation.
It's just that, when it comes to preparing it, you don't
really want to prepare the navigation controller,
you wanna prepare the thing inside. So
that's why we're in this code just looking inside
the navigation controller to make the destination
that we're preparing be the thing inside. Okay?
So little trickiness. You'll often have this little code.
I'll actually show you later in the quarter kind of
a little more sophisticated way to put this in there.
You can put it there with one syntactical element,
it's possible, but this I want to leave explicitly so
you understand what's going on here. So now when we run it's
going to work because when we segue to something
that's navigation controls, it can look inside. See, angry,
happy, worried, mischievous. And the last thing I wanna do
is set this title right here. Now this title was fixed.
This is always the emotions MVC.
But this MVC, its title kinda depends on what it's showing
here, doesn't it? Alright like if we are showing angry it
would be nice if this title would be angry.
It would be nice if this title were worried.
Okay? So where can we get the appropriate title here?
we'll we can get it form the button that's asking us
to segue. Right? If this angry button asks us to segue then
let's set this title to be the title of the angry button.
Right? So, looking back here, in our "prepareForSegue".
Is that title of the angry button available to us here?
Where? Where can I get it? From "sender", yeah, exactly.
Okay. You guys are getting it. That's really good.
Sender is the button that's causing the segue to happen.
That's gonna be the angry button. So, it's any object.
So I'm gonna have to cast it to be a button. But that's no
problem. I'm just gonna say if I can let the sending button
equal the sender as a UI button, okay? And
if not, if I'm segueing from code or something here,
then this is not gonna work.
But so what. Okay? We just won't get the title we want.
On our Face View Controller. But if it is then I can just
set the Face View Controllers navigation item. Does everyone
remember what navigation item is? It's kind of just a bundle
of things like a little bag of goodies that the navigation
controller looks inside of when that MVC is showing.
To get information like the buttons or the title, okay.
Equals the sending button's current title,
okay. So this little bag of goodies, navigation item,
here let's look at it in the documentation, okay.
I'm going to go here. The I View Controller,
it's like a navigation item.
You can see it house things like the title to show
when this MVC is showing in the navigation controller.
Back bar button item to use instead of the default one.
Left bar button items and right bar button items.
You can put you know things on the top, left and right.
That's what's in this little bag of goodies. And
this bag of goodie is only looked in when you are on top
the of a navigation controller stack.
All right, so let's see if that works.
All right, here we go. Let's try angry,
there it is, angry, happy, worried, mischievous. Okay,
and let's make sure that it's working on iPhone.
All right, let's go back here. Angry. Yes.
Look he even got the title right. Happy.
That's definitely happy. Worried. Okay?
All right, everyone got that? So this is how we can build
these nice apps that work on both platforms, okay? They
work in split views. They work in navigation controllers.
Now if you were building an iPhone only app, you could do
this exact same thing but you wouldn't need the split view.
You could just take this view and
move your start Your little starting arrow right here.
You just move right up here to this navigation controller,
and you wouldn't need this navigation controller either,
okay, because you don't have this issue where this whole
thing is in a separate space like it is on iPad and iPhone.
They'd all be inside the navigation controller.
Okay? Now not surprisingly for you're homework I'm going to
ask you to do pretty much exactly this. Okay?
You're going to have a calculator.
You're going to have a calculator graph,
have to write the code for. So you're going to have two MVC's
which you're going to
and you're going to have to put it in the situation like
this that works on both iPad and iPhone. Okay?
And now you know how to do it. All right back to the slides.
Okay the View Controller Lifecycle.
So I've been mentioning this and we delete
those methods in there for the View Controller Lifecycle. So
now let's talk about what this View Controller Lifecycle is.
So View Controller Lifecycle It's really just a set of
methods that gets sent to your view controller as your
view controller goes through it's lifetime. Okay,
meaning it's lifetime is it gets created, it does things,
it dies. Okay, and as it goes through that life,
you get sent these nice messages. Okay? So the start
of the lifecycle is obviously the creation of your MVC. And
MVCs are almost always created out of storyboards I'd say 99%
of the time okay? That's how you've seen us do it and
that's how it's done, okay? It can be done in code but
I'm not even gonna show you how to do that in this course,
It's rarely done, okay?
The great thing about putting in a storyboard is that people
looking at your code can see what you intend visually,
okay? In terms of your MVC and
their layout and their segways to each other. So
that's why we try to do stuff in the storyboard. So 99% of
the time these MVCs are being created out of the storyboard.
After they're created they go through the following steps,
one they get prepared okay,
they get segwayed too they get prepared so that first.
Then outlet setting happens that's why we had that crusher
because outlet setting happens after prepare.
Then they appear and disappear. Okay,
now this can happen over and over. This thing is gonna
appear on screen, go away, appear on screen, go away. For
example, when we had the iPad version of our demo here, and
I would pull out the master, and then I would hide it, and
I'd pull out the master, and then I would hide it.
Okay, it was appearing and disappearing. Alright?
Then as this is all happening, geometry changes can happen to
this thing, mostly due to rotation from
portrait to landscape, changes the geometry. And then,
very rarely you can get into a low memory situation
where your view controller may be asked to participate in
freeing up some memory, super rare.
Alright So let's talk about all these methods, okay?
After instantiation and preparation and
outlet-setting, you get a very important method sent to you
called viewDidLoad. Okay Load refers to loading up your
outlets, okay? So viewDidLoad is an awesome place to put
initialization code in your I view controller.
It's why you almost never have to override View controller's
init method. Okay it has a very strange init method.
You don't even wanna think about it's so weird.
Okay? But luckily you never need to override because you
got viewDidLoad. Okay? You put all your initialization code
almost all into viewDidLoad, okay,
it's kind of like your init for view controllers,
it's awesome. And it's great there because you're prepared,
and your outlets are set. So it's like, whoa,
you are ready to really get initialized, okay, and
of course all your instance variables are initialize,
or you wouldn't exist, okay? One really good thing to do
here is to update your UI, so you notice we had update UI in
the outlet setter property observer for
face view, okay? More likely you'd put update UI
in your viewDidLoad, okay. Cuz you know by viewDidLoad,
everything is ready to be updated.
Okay, now you're still gonna want it in your models,
didSet, because someone might change your model after
you've been loaded, okay?
But no one's going to change your outlets after you've been
loaded, your outlets get set up and now you own them, okay?
So they're, no one's gonna set it to point to something else,
okay? Now one thing to be careful about viewDidLoad,
though, is geometry, okay? The geometry of your view is
still probably the square, okay, of your storyboard. So
it's useless to do any calculations in viewDidLoad,
that have anything to do with your geometry.
If you're looking at your bounds and trying to make
a calculation is a waste of time, because it's a square.
It's not, it hasn't been updated to the portrait or
landscape of the device you're running on. Okay,
so this is the one think you don't do in viewDidLoad.
The other thing I wouldn't do in viewDidLoad is
anything that's going to kick off something expensive, okay?
Computing expensive or network intensive, whatever.
There's a better place to do that.
That's because viewDidLoad, kay,
your view controller got created. There's,
it's not a 100% guarantee it's gonna appear onscreen.
It might or might not. Depends on what the user touches in
your UI. So you wouldn't wanna kick off something expensive
until you know you're gonna be onscreen. And that brings us
to viewWillAppear, kay? So, viewWillAppear is called right
before you get put onscreen. So you are sure when this is
called that you're going to be put onscreen.
This is a great place to start something expensive.
Now you're gonna learn starting next week that iOS
apps, you wanna build them multi-threaded, okay?
Multi-threaded means, you're gonna have multiple things
going on at the same time in your app. They'll be sharing
the processor, time sharing the processor basically,
unless you have multi-core I guess,
which I guess that's formed is a basically running multiple
things at the same time. Your UIs gonna be running in one
thread at a very high priority and then other things
like accessing the network or things that block, things that
take a long time, we are gonna be running another thread.
And we are gonna be running simultaneously,
because we never want our UI to be blocked. Okay,
when user touches on something it should immediately respond.
I don't care what you're doing. Okay, you don't wanna
touch on something and it does nothing, because you're out
trying to fetch something from the network and
the network is slow. That would be a nightmare,
okay? So viewWillAppear is we would, you
would fire off another thread to go do something expensive.
kay, now your view is going to instantly appear on
screen without that data that you tried to get,
or whatever the expensive thing is.
So you have to learn to program in iOS, so
that multi-threading works.
And mostly that's a matter of putting UIs on the screen
that might not have all the information yet. Okay,
they might be fetching some data from the network so they
have a little spinning wheel or something loading dot,
dot, [LAUGH] dot. Something that tells the user, yeah,
I know you wanna see this data. I'm working on it, but
it has to come on screen instantly, okay?
You can't block, wait to get you one and then come on.
It's just, you can't do that, it doesn't work especially
iOS. Like the network can be really slow and
it might be stall. All right, cell network can be super
slow, so you can't do that. So the viewWillAppear
is a good place to kick off that kind of stuff.
Now, geometry is more likely to be correct here,
because you are just about to come on screen. But,
I still wouldn't put geometry calculations in here.
There is a better place for
that as well. There is also a viewDidAppear.
This gets sent right after you have come on screen.
This is a good place to do things like start
an animation. Okay, cause now you know you're onscreen,
boom, you can start an animation or something like
that. Okay, similarly there's viewWillDisappear, okay
usually viewWillDisappear, you're going to undue
the things you did in view will appear, so here you might
stop your animation. Or stop looking at the gyro, okay,
because things, things are going to disappear, so
there's no point in looking at the gyro anymore And there is
also a viewDidDisappear. Okay. This is where you might free
up something you fetched from the network in viewWillAppear.
See how they kind of a mirror each other, the will did
appear and then they will and did disappear. Kinda do and
undo things as it goes on and off, and these appear and
disappear could be viewDidLoad is only called once.
Okay one time. This could be called repeatedly as your view
controller comes on and off screen, appears it disappears,
appears it disappears, so this could be called repeatedly,
okay. So you wouldn't wanna do something in here
like if you're gonna fire off a fetch on the network
that's expensive, you wouldn't wanna be doing it over and
over if you already have the information from the last time
it appeared. Kay, so be a little careful about that. So
if the geometry, if you wanna do something based in
geometry, where do you do that? Well,
there's lifecycle methods specifically for
that, viewWillLayoutSubviews and viewDidLayoutSubviews. So
every time your bounds changes and sometimes when it doesn't
change, be careful, you'll get these two messages.
ViewWillLayoutSubviews and viewDidLayoutSubviews. Yeah.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Great question, so
the question is, would my bounds change if for example,
I added a navigation bar at the top or
maybe the tab bar at appeared in the tab bar or
I'm in the split view? And I appeared on the other side,
in other words, can it change due to the environment I'm in?
And the answer is, it can,
now it doesn't usually change with the navigation case,
because action that navigation bar is layered on top of
your view, it's kinda semi see through, if you look. If you
go look at navigation items,in the navigation bars, they're
actually kind of translucent and the thing is behind it, so
your bounds actually wouldn't probably change there.
But they might change if you're put into a tab bar,
because that space at the bottom might not overlap.
Okay, but the main time your balance changes when you
rotate, but it can happen other times too.
So between viewWillLayoutSubviews and
viewDidLayoutSubviews all that auto layout is gonna happen,
the stuff based on the constraints.
Remember all that blue dash lines and all that stuff?
That's gonna happen between.
So you can do stuff before all the blue lines, the autolayout
stuff is happening, or you can do it after, okay?
You rarely need to do anything here,
because usually the constraints are making all
the decisions about what to do with everything, okay? But
it is possible sometimes, you know, not in assignment three,
maybe in assignment six in this class. Maybe you might
wanna do something in viewWill or DidLayoutSubviews. But this
is the only place you wanna do anything that's geometry
dependent, okay? Yeah, one thing about these methods,
don't think that these are only gonna
be called when you're bound to actually changes.
The system is allowed to call these any time it wants, and
sometimes it might be drawing something to an offscreen
buffer to prepare to do an animation and so
it calls this, okay? But, and
then it actually draws on the screen and calls it again.
And the bounds have not actually changed, okay? So
don't expect that every single time this calls the bounds
will be different. If you do something really expensive as
a result of a bounds change, you might wanna keep track of
what the bounds were the last time you did that expensive
thing. And when this gets called,
make sure the bounds have actually changed, okay?
Again, you're not gonna need any of this for
assignment three, but it's good to know.
This can be recalled all the time, repeatedly, over and
over. Even if your bounds have not actually changed. Okay, so
auto rotation. Usually what happens in auto rotation.
When auto rotation is when you turn your phone from landscape
to portrait, it automatically changes your bounds to be tall
and skinny. And then wide and short, okay?
So autorotation is usually just a bounds change, so
you're just dealing with it in view did layout sub views, or
more likely, you just have constraints, and
the constraints just work, okay? So
there's really nothing to do, but it is possible to
get involved in autorotation, specifically in the animation.
If you watch an autorotation really, really closely,
you'll see that the views actually move. They move from
their position in portrait to where they are in landscape
in an animated fashion. They don't just jump there,
they kind of fly across the screen. And you can fly things
across the screen, too, if you want using this,
life cycle method called will, viewWillTransitionToSize. And
it's basically telling you, this is going to transition.
It has this thing called a transition coordinator.
You can look up the documentation on it. But
the main thing the transition coordinator has is a closure
that you can provide that will be executed alongside
the animation that it's doing to animate your,
your, rotation, okay? You won't need this in this class,
but I just wanna let you know this is here. Okay,
in low-memory situations, didReceiveMemoryWarning, okay,
this is only gonna happen if your app uses a lot of memory,
okay? iPhones today have so much memory,
it's ridiculous, okay?
So this is not really gonna happen, likely. But if you had
a memory leak where you're leaking videos in memory,
or images, huge images, or
something like that, it's possible you might get this.
When you get this, you should throw out any pointers to big
things you have in the heap that you can recreate, okay?
So you can re-download them from the web or
from your file system or something.
You should throw them out when you get this one. Okay,
going back to the very beginning of the lifecycle,
there's another interesting method called awakeFromNib.
Okay, awakeFromNib is sent to you really early before
preparation, before outlet setting, before all that, but
only if you're coming out of a storyboard. Okay, so it's this
really, really, really, really early method that gets called.
And it actually gets sent to every object that comes out of
a storyboard, not just view controllers,
okay? Now I mention it at the end here,
because I really don't want you using it that much, okay?
You're much better off putting things in viewDidLoad,
viewWillAppear, those kind of places than awakeFromNib,
okay? Some people find out about this, and they just put
all of their initialization junk into awakeFromNib, and
it's not really for that. It's for
really kind of exceptional circumstances,
where you really, really early you need to do something for
some reason, okay? Set, you're gonna need to set yourself
as a controller of some other object that something's
happening early, whatever. But I just wanna let you know it's
in there. Okay, so here's the summary of the lifecycle.
You're instantiated, usually from your storyboard.
awakeFromNib is then called.
Segue prep happens if you're being segued to,
which you almost always are when MVCs are being created.
It's because you're being segued to usually. Then
your outlets get set, okay, the things like display and
the calculator get set. Then viewDidLoad gets called, and
you can do a lot of nice initialization here that's not
geometry related. Then viewWillAppear and, and
DidAppear and then viewWillDisappear and
viewDidDisappear will be sent to you as you appear and
disappear on screen. Meanwhile, at any time,
whether you are onscreen or not,
whether you've appeared or not,
you can be set viewWillLayoutSubviews and
viewDidLayoutSubviews. Okay, and that's where you're going
to react to geometry changes if nec, if you need to outside
of constraints. Okay, usually constraints will just do it
for you. And if your memory gets
low at any time, you could get didReceiveMemoryWarning.
If you get didReceiveMemoryWarning and
you don't clean up your memory,
the system will probably kill you, okay? Just probably
your app will appear to crash to the user. Okay, so
I have a short demo here for View Controller Lifecycle,
and I'm just gonna throw some print statements into all of
those Lifecycle methods. Okay, that's all I'm gonna do. And
then we're gonna run our FaceIt, and we're gonna see,
as view controllers appear and disappear and
get created, what's happening in the Lifecycle,
okay? So that's all this demo is,
it's very brief. Okay, the way that I'm going to,
kind of print in the console is I have this, a little
extension here called, VCL, View Controller Lifecycle,
then I'm just gonna add to FaceIt, copy it in, and
I will post this, so you can look at it if you want.
But it's basically, it's just extending these classes to
override all of these, things. And
one thing that's cool is it will show you, the log which
instance of the Face View Controller, which instance of
the emotion controller, okay? So, that's kind of fun.
All right, so let's go ahead and run this, let's do it on,
iPhone first. All right, so this thing appeared,
all right, and it's showing the face, okay, this is kind
of like on the iPad, it would be showing the detail here.
It's showing a face, but we haven't chosen an emotion. And
let's look over here what happened. Both an Emotions
view controller and a Face view controller have been
created and instantiated, okay? Now that's because
the Emotion view controller is at the bottom of the stack and
a Face view controller is on top of it.
So they're both on the stack, that means they both exist.
However, notice that while the Emotions 1 has had viewDidLoad
called, because its outlets have all been set and
all that stuff, it has never appeared.
You see Emotions 1 never gets viewWillAppear,
because it never has appeared. We've never seen the angry,
mischievous, that has not appeared on screen. So
it hasn't appeared, whereas the Face 1 has, so
it's gotten viewWillAppear. It got, it laid out, okay,
viewWillLayoutSubviews and DidLayoutSubviews.
And then it got viewDidAppear, and sure enough,
here it is. Now I'm gonna press Back, the Back button,
and let's watch what happens, okay?
Face 1 got viewWillDisappear because of course,
it was gonna disappear. Emotions 1, that's this one,
got viewWillAppear cuz it's about to appear.
Then Emotions 1 got laid out a couple of times here.
Let's see some more here, there we go. Okay,
so Emotions 1 got laid out a couple of times here,
see if you will ask at the same exact size. So this
is why I'm saying be careful, that can happen multiple
times. Why might that happen? Again, maybe the system was
preparing to animate that thing sliding in, and
so it was drawing off screen, then it was drawing on screen,
and it was laying out both times,
it's called it both times. You don't know why,
you don't care why. You just have to be prepared for
the fact that it could call it multiple times. Then Face
1 got viewDidDisappear because the face disappeared,
it slid off. And Emotions 1 got viewDidAppear, because it
got replaced on top of it. Then notice Emotions 1 got lay
out again. Okay, even though it was already on screen.
Why, I don't know. Maybe this is the layout for
it actually appearing on screen. It's not clear. Okay,
everybody got that? Now I'm gonna click on one of these,
I'm gonna click on Happy, and let's watch what happens.
Okay, now most important thing to watch here, okay, is that
Face 1, that first face that we showed up is gone, see?
No more reference to Face 1. It has created a new face,
came out of the story board. Okay, this is what I'm talking
about. When you segue, it creates a new NVC.
That first Face 1 is out of the heap, it is gone, okay?
Every time you segue, you get a new one. But Emotions, okay?
The root, it's still Emotions 1, okay?
Since it sits on the root, the base of the card stack,
it never comes off. So, it just sits there forever, okay?
New cards come on and off, on and off.
But it's at the root, so it just sits there. So
it's always gonna be Emotions 1, okay? And then, again you
can see it goes through willDidLoad, viewWillAppear,
got laid out, Face 2 finally did appear, okay? And notice
that Emotions 1 did disappear because it got covered up
by this one. Okay, again if we go back and
I click a different one like Mischievous,
now we have Face 3, okay? Face 2 is gone forever but
still Emotions 1. Everyone understand that?
Okay, now let's run this on the iPad.
Okay, so here, okay, we're seeing the detail, okay?
Notice here that even though the master does not appear
on screen, it gets created. Not only does it get created,
it gets laid out. But it never got viewWillAppear and
viewDidAppear, because the master has never appeared,
okay? Whereas Face 1, it did get appear, and it appeared,
Now watch what happens if I rotate, okay, I'm gonna rotate
right?
to landscape. Okay, now when I rotate to landscape,
all of a sudden the master, Emotions 1, it got that
viewWillTransitionToSize thing.
That's the auto rotation thing I was telling you about, okay?
And Emotions 1 also got laid out and
told it would appear, and then it did appear, okay? Now Face
1 also got to participate in that rotation. See,
animatingAlongsideTransition. Okay, and
then here's Emotion 1 appear. Notice that inside here, okay,
there's no viewWillAppear or viewWillDisappear for Face 1.
That's cuz it was already on screen,
okay, so even though its bounds changed, okay, and
it got viewWillLayoutSubviews, it never got viewWillAppear,
it already was on screen. That make sense?
And now interesting. I'm gonna click on one of these, and
what's gonna happen to Face 1? Out of the heap. Okay,
watch this. Angry, see Face 1 gone, now we're on Face 2.
So even in a split view where it seems like,
you know with the cards, it's really obvious that yeah,
I'm throwing the card away, I'm making a new card. But
even here in a split view,
I'm throwing away the detail,
I'm making a new one. Plopping it right in on top, okay?
So all of these segues create a new MVC, even if they're
a split view navigation controller, whatever.
The only ones that don't that you've seen is in tab bar. All
those things in the tab bar. It's too bad I don't really
have a tab bar, I wanted to show you this VCL thing.
But those ones get created when you click on the tab for
the first time and they live forever. Okay,
they never go away. And when you click on the tab,
it comes back, it's still exactly the same way.
It's not a segue,
in other words the tab bar is not segueing.
Navigation control and split view are segueing, tab bar,
notice we never did anything there to do a segue, okay? So,
yeah, notice here also that even though when I clicked on
here to show this, look what happened to Emotions 1,
it got laid out a couple times even though its size did not
change. Here I'll do it again. We'll go to happy. Okay,
I didn't change, this did not change size in the least.
Okay, and yet it got viewDidLayoutSubviews,
viewDidLayoutSubview. Okay, so you have to be prepared for
that being called all the time, okay? And so here is
Face 3, it's getting pulled out of the storyboard. It's
kind of interesting that it gets a viewWillDisappear here.
I'm not sure why it gets that right there. Kind of strange
I've noticed this,
and then it loads, it gets a WillAppear it lays out,
it gets DidDisappear, and then DidAppear. So I, this is
strange, I don't really understand why it goes through
that shenanigan right there, but the good news is that
once viewDidAppear happens, it has appeared so
that's good. It's just kind of strange, so be prepared for
that. Now you'll have this code of mine,
this little logging thing. So
you can always throw this in your own app, okay, change
the name to the classes. And then you can see if
somethings not going the way you expect and the lifecycle
method is not getting called at the time you want,
you can see when it's happening exactly. Okay, all
right, that is it for today. Your assignment is posted.
I already explained what it's gonna be.
It's due next Wednesday before class. Hopefully you've
finished up all of the reading for the Swift thing.
All that Swift reading, you're really gonna want to have that
in your memory bank as the rest of the course happens.
So if you're a little behind there,
make sure you catch up as soon as possible. All right, I'll
be here if you have questions. >> For
more, please visit us as stanford.edu.