[MUSIC]
Stanford University. >> All right well welcome to
lecture number seven of CS193P,
Spring of 2016. So we've got a lot of different topics today,
a couple of demos interspersed with it.
Here are all the topics. A lot of these are kind of,
I don't want to say advanced Swift features, but kind of
important Swift features that we haven't talked about so
far. And then towards the end
we'll talk a little about an iOS kind of concept,
that comes over from the objective C world,
that we have to deal with in Swift, called delegation, but
it's super important. It has to do with our whole NVC
model and how we do that blind structure communication and
now I'm gonna finish off with scroll view.
Okay, very important class, because these devices
are really small and you want to look at something big.
So you will need to be able to scroll and zoom in on it,
okay. All right, first topic, Memory management. So I told
you already, that reference classes, or reference types,
which are classes, live in the heap, all right. And that,
that memory is automatically taken care of for you, okay?
That's called automatic reference counting,
because it's a reference counting base scheme. It keeps
track of how many pointers are pointing to something, and
when that count goes to zero, it immediately freezes, right?
Which is different from, like, garbage collection,
where you're basically going through the heap and
marking it, trying to find things that aren't pointed to,
and then sweeping through. Marking or sweeping and
then clearing out. So
you know, that kind of memory frame can be intermittent and
it's not really predictable, whereas, ARC is completely and
utterly predictable. Normally you don't think about ARC,
you don't think about memory in the heap at all except for
there are, there is a small way that you can influence ARC
the way it works.
And that's with these three things right here. Strong,
weak, and unowned, okay? So we're going to talk about each
of these three keywords that you can put in Swift.
And all of them you use when you're declaring a variable,
okay? It's all for declaring variables. All right, so
strong, you don't even see the word, strong in Swift,
because that's the default. Strong is normal
reference counting. Basically a pointer that is strong,
forces whatever's in the heap to stay in the heap,
until that pointer no longer points to it. Okay, so
it strongly holds things in the in the heap, so that's
the default. Okay, if you go round creating pointers,
they are strong pointers, gotta get rid of all
the pointers to something for it to clean up. Okay, but
then there's weak. So if you have a weak pointer, it means,
if no one else is interested in this thing in heap,
then you can get rid of it in the heap and set me to nil.
Okay, so it's kind of like, yeah, I'm pointing to
the thing in the heap, but I'm not that interested in it,
if it goes away then just set me to nil. Now for me to be
set to nill that means I have to be an optional pointer,
okay? So weak only works for optional reference pointers,
okay? So basically optional pointers to classes,
all right? A weak pointer never keeps things in
heap, okay? It's up to strong pointers, pointing to things
to keep them in the heap. So, a good example of this,
that you've already seen, is outlets, right?
Remember your calculator, you have an outlet to the display,
that UI label. That's weak, okay,
it automatically got set to be weak. Why is that weak? Well,
because the view hierarchy, okay?
The super view, for example, of that UI label,
it has a strong pointer to that UI label. So your outlet
doesn't have to keep it in the keep, in the heap, cuz it's
going to be kept in the heap by the view hierarchy. But
if the view hierarchy ever gets rid of that UI label,
in other words, it's no longer part of the view,
then you're probably not interested in it as an outlet
anyway, so just set the outlet to nill. Now you notice when
you make an outlet you can over at the bottom switch over
to strong, meaning that even if the UI label comes out of
the view hierarchy it'll still stay in the heap. Okay, maybe
you wanna do that because maybe you wanna put it back in
the view hierarchy after it got removed from the view
hierarchy, okay. That'd be one of the only reasons I can
think of that you would have a strong pointer through
an outlet to something in the view hierarchy.
Right, cuz maybe we are going to take in and out. Okay,
everyone understand weak? Optional reference pointers
can be weak. Okay, and you just declare it when you say
var, you say weak var whatever optional pointer, okay?
And then the last one here, unowned, unowned kind of means
don't reference count this, which is very dangerous. If
you have an unowned pointer, it means that reference
counting is not going to track it. And so this pointer is
always going to point to that little place in memory.
And you better be sure that the thing you point to
stays there. Okay, until you don't use that, this pointer
anymore, okay? And if you have an unknown pointer and
you later reference it, and the thing that you're
reference got thrown out of the heap, because there were
no more strong pointers to it, then you will crash, okay?
Which could be memory reference error.
Now you might say, why do I ever want this unowned thing?
And I will show you a little example, later in this
lecture, of a way to break a memory cycle between objects.
One object points to another,
which points back to the first one, directly or indirectly,
keeping them both in memory. You can break it with unknown,
but often times you'll break it with weak.
But you'll see that coming up. Okay, so this is the only way
you can influence arc, is with these three things. And you
almost never really use this, it's very rare to use these.
Weak, occasionally, strong, never, 'cuz of the default,
and unowned, next to never. Okay, all right, let's talk
more about closures. We did closures in our first lecture,
our first week of lecture.
Remember we had those closures like $0 times $1.
That's a closure, a closure is just an inline function.
And one thing that is interesting about closures,
they are stored in the heap as well, okay?
So closures are essentially a reference type, okay.
Cuz you remember that closures are just functions,
functions are types, or just normal types in Swift. So,
they're stored in the heap.
Now it has interesting ramifications for the way
things work, because inside of a closure, you can reference
all kinds of variables that were in the scope around it.
Okay, cuz remember it's an inline function, so
you might reference variables that are local variables in
that inline, in the function you're in,
or maybe instance variable, properties of the class,
if you're inside a method you declare the closure.
It's perfectly legal to access all of those things, and not
to only access them, but you can access them read-write.
Okay, well now we know, from the calculator,
that sometimes a closure lives a long time, maybe it gets put
in a dictionary, like we did in the calculator, right. And
so that dictionary can live for a long, long time.
And that closure keeps getting pulled out and called,
called, so what happens if you put a local variable,
you captured a local variable In one of these closures and
you put it in there.
Well that local variable has to be kept around too,
and Swift automatically does this, okay? Anything that gets
captured inside a closure that you use inside a closure
gets moved, or if it already is in the heap, it gets
a strong pointer to it from the closure, otherwise, it
gets moved to the heap. Okay, so everything get in the,
stays in the heap, okay? Everything that closure and
everything it references internally in its
implementation, all of that gets in the heap, okay? So,
what is the problem with that? Well, there's no problem,
it generally just kind of works how you would think,
except for memory cycles. Okay, so
let's go through why a memory cycle can be created and
what's bad about memory cycles. Okay, what's bad about
them is, you have a closure pointing to an object, that
object is pointing back to the closure, they're pointing to
each other, they have strong references to each other.
How can they ever leave the heap? Never. Right.
Because they each are pointing to each other.
They always are gonna maintain a strong pointer to each
other. There's no way, unless you set one of those pointers
to nil, okay, or something else.
There's no way they can stop pointing to each other. Okay?
So let's see how this can happen with the calculator.
Let's say with my CalculatorBrain I added
a new method called addUnary function that took a symbol
and a operation, right.
A function that takes a double or turns to a double.
And basically I'm making it so that the user of my
CalculatorBrain can add their own functions. Right now our
CalculatorBrain just has this built-in table of functions
and operations. Well what if I added this method and
I just let people add them? That would be really cool,
right? And so let's say we have our View Controller. And
we wanted to add a Unary function which is the same
as square root except for that it would turn the display in
the calculator red. Okay? So I call it red square root, okay.
It's just square root but
it's gonna turn the thing red when the result comes back.
Well how would we do that? Okay, well we would just call
this addUnaryOperation. Now one thing I just wanna
remind you a little bit of the syntax here.
You see here's UnaryOperation, it has two arguments.
There's the symbol, okay.
Here's the operation which is this closure. Of course,
because of type inference I don't, well, first of all,
I don't need to do this comma second. Second argument.
Here, I can actually put this closure after the end, right?
So I can take this second argument and
put it after the end.
Remember that's the trailing closure syntax,
everyone remember this?
Okay since the closure is the last argument we can do this.
Also I don't need any of this type stuff in here because it
can infer that. Okay, so I can just take that away and
use $0 down here. Okay, everyone remember that?
All right, so here I am adding this UnaryOperation.
Notice that it sets the display color.
This is in my View Controller, my calculator View Controller,
right? It sets the display color to red when it does
the square root. Okay, this is gonna be UnaryOperation.
Everybody understand what this is doing?
It's really super simple. Okay,
well this code will not compile. Okay,
why will this code not compile? It's interesting.
It's because, and when you look at the warning,
it's gonna say, you have to put self.
In front of this. Which normally you don't have to do,
you can just reference your own properties with display,
why do you have to put self.? Well you have to put self.
There cuz the compiler wants you to realize that this
closure is going to capture this self. And
keep a strong pointer to it forever, for
as long as this closure lives. Okay? And
this closure's gonna be put in a dictionary in another class
so it's gonna live a long time. It's gonna capture self.
So self now has a strong point to it, it can never leave
the heap until until this closure leaves the heap. Okay?
But this closure is never gonna leave the heap because
it's in the CalculatorBrain which the View Controller has
a strong point or two. So, who will leave the,
the heap first? Neither of them, okay? So they're stuck.
So, that's why swift forces you put that there so
you realize that you are implicitly capturing and, and
making a strong point or two self. All right?
Now, how do we deal with this? How do we break this loop, so
that we can have these things leave the heap normally?
Okay? There's a couple ways we can do it.
First, we have to realize that there's a cool syntax in
swift. That allows you to, declare variables to
use inside your closure. Right at the beginning. All you do
is a square bracket tier and you just put the names
of the variables you want and
their initial values. Okay? Put it right here.
For example, I can create a variable called, me. M-E.
And, I'm gonna set it to self. Okay. And so
me is now local variable only inside this closure and
its value is self. Okay? And sure enough look I can change
self right there to be me because me is just a local
variable. But this will have no effect on the the closure
problem because me is still self and it still gonna make
a strong point in there. To self and hold it in memory.
But I can use those unow, those unowned weak and strong
things with this variable, so I'm gonna say unowned me =
self. Now, we've broken that cycle. Okay, because unowned
means don't reference count this, which means that swift
is not going to make a strong pointer to this me in this
closure. So now this closure does not point strongly to
self. Self still points strongly to this closure
through the CalculatorBrain through the dictionary.
To it, okay. But it does not now strongly point back to.
It's not gonna keep the View Controller in memory.
Now the danger here, is if this closure lived longer than
the View Controller lived, which is pretty much
impossible because this is in the dictionary that's
in the brain that the controller owned. But
if some wackiness happened and this lived longer and we tried
to execute this longer after the View Controller is gone.
This will crash. Okay? Because me would be pointing
to something that got free from the heat. But
another way to do it besides unowned is weak. So
we could make self weak, okay? This will work great.
This will also break the cycle.
Because weak things don't keep things in the heap. However,
self inside this closure now becomes what?
An optional UIViewController. Okay, so this self right here,
this local variable self has the same name but
it's a different variable than the outer self. Okay?
And this is weak so this will not work, anymore. This won't
compile because display is not a message you can send to
an optional, you can only send it to our View Controller;
calculator View Controller. So how do you fix this?
Well the simplest way is to use this optional changing and
just put a question mark in here.
Remember if you put a question mark on an optional,
on the left hand side of an equal sign, it means if any of
these things or the question mark are nil, just ignore this
whole line. Okay? Bailout. So this is perfect. Weak self.
If this self ever were nil, this would just bail out and
not do it. Okay? So now this code would work even
if the View Controller got thrown out of the heap. And
since this is weak,
we're using a weak self in here, it won't keep the,
the View Controller in the heap. Now,
when we do this weakSelf, here, we almost always declare
a different name here. Almost always. WeakSelf. Okay? So
weak variable weakSelf = self, and then we'll
put that in there. And that tells people reading our code,
yeah, I understand I'm making this weak. So
don't worry about that, that possible memory cycle. Okay so
that's closure in memory cycle.
I'm gonna do a demo on this, okay. Which is I'm gonna do
that red square root and let's see what this looks like
in the calculator. To do this. All right so
I'm going back to our calculator
[INAUDIBLE] There we go. Okay so here's our calculator as we
left it off. This is not your homework calculator. This is
lecture four or whatever our last time. We just have
this blank calculator right here. I'm going to now that
you're comfortable with things like navigation controllers.
I'm going to actually add another View Controller here.
Okay, and I'm gonna put a button in it. Oops,
make this bigger. Put a button in this. I'm gonna make it
bigger. We'll make it 40 point, I would say. Okay,
I'm gonna change the title to be Calculate.
Okay, and this button is going to cause this calculator here
to appear. So let's go ahead and Reset to
Suggested Constraints. Notice when I did that, look,
I got all kinds of constraints I didn't really want.
You see, because, that's cuz I didn't have this thing be
in its natural size. So let's go over to the size inspector
over here and look at our constraints. And
we see, it's constraining the width to be 204.
I don't want that. I wanna it to be its natural width. So
I'm just gonna select this constraint, constraint and
hit the Delete. Same thing here,
it's constraining it to the top by some magic number 203.
I don't want that because I want it to be aligned center x
and y. So it's okay in here just to go ahead and
delete constraints you don't work want. Now of course now
this is yellow, so we're gonna go down here and
say click on this. All right. And go down here and
say update frames, and that's gonna move the frames to where
they should be, and now everything is cute. Okay,
a little quick review there of constraints.
Also, I don't want the entry point to be my calculator,
I want it to be this thing. Okay,
this is going to be my first thing, and I'm going to put it
inside of a navigation controller. So, I'm going to
put this inside a navigation controller with embed in,
oops, select this again, embed in navigation controller,
and now I have a nice little UI here. That has a navigation
controller in this and I'm going to make it so
that this button, when it's clicked,
segues to show a calculator. Okay, so let's do that.
Control, drag over here, we're going to do a show because
we're inside a navigation controller. This is not for
iPad, this is for iPhone only, so I'm just going to do Show,
and here's our show now. I'm not going to set an identifier
here because I'm not gonna prepare that calculator. I'm
just gonna let it come up in whatever its state is. I'm not
gonna prepare it. So, no need to put an identifier here.
Okay, so this is what our UI looks like. All right, so
let's go ahead and run this, see what this looks like.
Okay, so here's our calculator.
We're inside a navigation controller. Hit Calculate,
it shows it, go back, hit calculate, it shows it.
Now remember in a navigation controller,
every time we segue what happens? We get a new MVC. So,
we're getting a new calculator MVC every single time.
In fact, I'm going to prove that to you by going back here
to my calculator view controller.
And I'm going to have it print every time it creates a new
one and every time it leaves the heap. Okay? So,
let's start with every time that it creates a new one,
we can use viewDidLoad() for that, okay?
So, here's viewDidLoad().
Remember in our ViewController life-cycles we always need to
call super, so I'm calling super.viewDidLoad().
I'm going to create a global variable here,
which is my calculatorCount Start out as zero.
That's how many calculator instances are currently
existing in the world. So when I do a viewDidLoa,
which I know happens only once per MVC, I'm going to take my
calculator account and increment it by one.
And then I'm just going to print out, loaded up
a new calculator and I'll tell you what the account is at
that time, and that's going to be calculator count, okay?
So, every time we create a new MBC where it's gonna get
a message, now how do we find out
when something leaves the heap? Anyone do the homework,
the reading homework and tell me? Special method?
What? Nobody? My gosh, okay.
Deinit. Okay, this special thing deinit gets called just
before you leave the heap, okay? So, in here I'm just
going to say the calculator Count minus equals one because
this is leaving the heap, and I'm going to do a print here,
I'm gonna say calculator left the heap and
now show our count. Okay? So now,
when I run, we're going to see our count of calculators.
And what happens to it as we keep clicking that calculator
button, and keep having new MVCs, all right? So,
here we go, let's calculate. There it is,
loaded up a new calculator, count equals 1, looks good.
We go back, calculator left the heap, count is 0,
go back again, loaded up a new calculator, count is 1.
Go back, count to 0. So, this is proving what I was
saying before. That every time we segue,
it's creating a new one. Every time we go back,
it throws it out. Everybody believe that now? Okay. So
now, let's go ahead and do our red square root. Okay?
Let's do our red square root button. I told you,
I was gonna go to calculate the brain and
add a new public function here called addUnaryOperation. It's
gonna take a symbol which is a string, and it's gonna take in
operation that goes along with it, which takes a double and
returns a double. Okay? And adding a Unary operation
is really easy because all we all have
to do is add an Unary operation to this table right
here, okay? So, I'm just gonna say operation some symbol,
okay? This is the symbol that the person wants this under.
We're gonna set this equal to the operation.
We can't really do that, though,
because we have e nums in here. So we need to wrap
a operation dot unary operation around this thing,
okay, and the associated value is a double takes a double so
that works. And that's it. So, I just added a unary operation
to my operation table. Okay. Now that we have that feature,
then let's go back to our view controller and
use it. We might viewDidLoad.
Right here. I'm going to add a unary operation, oops,
add, and my brain, I'm gonna add a unary operation. And
I'm gonna say I'm gonna have it symbol be the letter Z, but
we could make it a nice red dot and a square sign,
but faster to type z, and
the function is going to be a closure. Okay.
And again, I can use the trailing closure notation
to do that right here. Okay, and as we said in the slides,
I'm just going to set my displays text color
equal to UI color, red color. And
then I'm gonna return the square root of $0.
Okay, and as promised I have an error right here.
It says reference to property 'display' in closure requires
explicit 'self' to make make capture semantics explicit.
Okay? Hopefully that with that warning it makes perfect sense
now. Links wants you to be clear that you are going
to capture self, it's gonna get a strong pointer to it.
So, I'm gonna do the fix right here,
which is insert self, fixes that problem.
And now we have [INAUDIBLE] operation. So,
let's go to our story board and add that somewhere here.
We'll replace, how about we replace our old square root
with our new z square root and
run? All right, so here we are,
okay, I'm gonna hit calculate, loaded up a new calculator.
Let's do 81 red square root, it's working perfectly, okay.
It took the square root and it turned the display red. And so
let's go back. We did't lo--, we didn't leave the heap,
that's weird. Le's go back again. Wait,
now we have two calculators, wha's going on, or three.
No, we're collecting calculators.
Now, these calculators are not very big, they do't have
a lot of storage so probably not gonna kill us. But
what if these had an image? Right or even like a video or
something in there, and w're collecting these things, and
they were building up in the heap never to be freed. Okay,
that would be a problem. Okay, so how can we make it so that
it goes back to where it was where when we left it would
free up? Well all we have to do is go here to this and
fix a problem that this self is being held in memory so
that a view controller can't be freed when it comes off.
Okay? So we can do exactly what we talked about before.
We can create, for example, unowned. Me equals self, how
about that one? Okay? Don't forget the in right here.
Okay? All this stuff has to go before the in, all right?
A closure in. So if we do that, and
now we say, me, okay? So me, right here, is unowned.
So, it's not going to keep anything in the heap.
All right, and we know it's safe here because we're
the view controller. We own the brain. So, there's no way
that we're gonna get thrown out before the brain. So,
let's run it again. So, here's calculate,
81 square root, okay, the red is still working,
back, left the heap Okay, working good. See that?
All right, now another way we could've done it here instead
of unowned is we could've said weakSelf = self, okay.
So, this is a weak variable right here.
It's going to be an optional. In fact, if I look at it, see,
it's an optional view controller,
you see that? Optional view controller, so
right here it's complaining, you can't send display to,
oops, this was weakSelf, it would be complaining. You
can't send display to weakSelf because it's an optional, see?
And it's asking do you want to put exclamation point? But
I'm gonna be more conservative and just put a question mark
right here, just in case this ever did get to be nil,
I just want this line of code not to happen. Okay, so,
let's see if that fixes our problem. All right, Calculate,
Back, Calculate, Back, Calculate, and Square root.
Still turning it red. Okay, now, you are probably going to
be using functions. I would imagine your assignment three
and closures too probably. I'm not going to require that you
not have memory loops. In other words, you are allowed
to have these memory cycles in your assignment three, but
if you want to try and fix it in your assignment three,
you are welcome to. Okay? I never ask you to do anything
in your assignment that I didn't teach you
in class before I gave you the assignment.
So this is after I gave you the assignment so
it's totally optional if you want to fix it. But
otherwise it's likely you probably will have a memory
cycle in your assignment three. It's possible you won't
but likely you would if you don't do this. Okay?
Any questions about that? All right,
back to our slides. Okay, the next thing we're talk
about is a cool little Swift feature called extensions.
Okay, extensions allow you to add methods and
properties to other classes, even if you don't have
the source code to the other classes. So, for
example you can add it to classes in UIkit.
Okay. You could add a method to UIbutton or, in this case,
I've added a method to UIViewController. Okay. So
when I add this method, it's available all throughout my
app. All view controllers will now have this method. Okay,
now what this is example this method I did right here? Well,
remember and when we're doing prepare for segway and
we wanna handle the case where we put the detail of the split
view controller into a navigation controller. And so,
when the segue happens we have to look inside the navigation
controller. Remember that? And we had this
little code right here if let navcon equal
the destination ViewController as NavigationController,
then return the visibleViewController
remember all that business?
Well I'm just gonna add that inside of a method here in
ViewController called contentViewController. So,
if I ask a ViewController what's your
contentViewController? Well if it's a NavigationController
it's gonna give me the visibleViewController. Okay?
If it's any other ViewController it's looking
to be itself cuz itself is the content.
That way, whether it's in the ViewNavigationController or
not, I'm gonna get the thing that I intend, the content
that I'm trying to get at. Everyone understand that?
So that makes you prepareForSegue instead of
looking like this where you got this destination and
all this you can actually make this into a one-liner.
You can get rid of all this and make a one-liner. So,
let's see if we can understand this. Ready? Here we go. We're
going to save the Segue's destination ViewController,
it's contentViewController, as, my ViewController.
If I can do that, then I'm good to go. See, so,
you see how this simplified this code really nicely. Now,
extensions you got to be a little careful with.
They could be abused. Okay. You start adding all
these wacky methods to class, it makes no sense.
You're still object on your programmers if you're gonna
add a method to UIViewController,
it better makes sense as a UIViewController method.
Okay, it shouldn't be some calculator method,
okay this has nothing to do with calculators.
It has everything to do with UIViewControllers, okay.
So, if you use extensions, use them wisely,
use them in an object oriented fashion. Okay? Now,
inside of an extension, notice that you can refer to self.
Self of course means the UIViewController you sent
this to. Just like self would mean if you had a method,
in UIViewController that was in that class.
Okay? Couple of interesting restrictions on
extensions. By the way, you can extend classes,
structs and enums. Okay, all of them are extensible.
You can't re-implement any methods or properties. It's
not re-implement thing, okay? It's an additional thing.
You can add methods, but you can't re-implement.
Okay? Also any properties that you add have to be computed
properties like that content view controller was.
You can't have any storage with your extension. Okay,
extension is purely for adding code, no storage.
All right, this feature I say is easily abused because you
can add all kinds of non objected oriented methods and
stuff like that, but actually this feature can be really
powerful for organizing and structuring your code.
Okay? And it's really beyond the scope for this class for
me to show you how you could use extensions in terms of
building your kind of code infrastructure in your app,
but know that it's possible.
Because if you go out there in the real world and
you start building big apps, extensions are a great way to
kind of divide up big complicated classes,
into sensible sub-pieces that are each extensions.
Also, if you have protocols,
which I'm going to talk about later in this lecture,
extensions are a great way to implement a protocol
in a class, so you'll see what that means in a minute.
Okay, for now you can use extensions in your homework or
whatever, but use it more along the lines of the content
view controller example right?
Small utility functions that make sense,
that kind of thing okay? Maybe for your final project if you
want to read up on how you can use extensions to build your
code base you can try it then,
but on your homework assignments let's stick to the
little stuff, okay? All right, so I mentioned protocols,
let's talk about protocols. Protocols are a way to express
an API more concisely, okay? Protocols are another type,
their the last type I'm going to talk about, okay?
We've talked about classes, enoms, strucks,
now we're gonna talk about, and functions, those are also
a type, now we're going to talk about protocols, okay,
the last type. What a protocol does is it lets you have
an API where instead of having to specify the full class or
struct that you're going to be using to do whatever
you are going to do. You can just specify what it is about
that class or struct that you actually need, okay, and
you do this with a protocol. And a protocol is simply
a collection of method and property declarations. Okay,
so it's just like a little bundle of methods,
and you can have part of your API that says I want something
that implements this bundle of methods. And
it can be any kind of struct, enum, class, whatever as
long as long as it implements those little methods.
Okay, and that's what the protocol is all about.
So, it's a type, anywhere you can use
a type, you can use a protocol. So, any like I might
have an argument to a function that takes a UIViewController,
it could also take a protocol, okay, that has a few methods
in UIViewController that I needed. So then it wouldn't be
so restrictive and have to be a UIViewController,
it could just be something that implements those methods.
Okay, anywhere you can use a TYPE you can use a protocol.
Okay, the implementation of a protocol happens in the class
that implements the protocol. The class or struct or
enum that implements the protocol. Okay,
the protocol itself doesn't have any implementation.
The protocol itself is just a declaration of the properties
and methods. Okay? Now, it is possible however,
to use extensions to implement some or all of a protocol.
So, you just say extension, protocol,
instead of saying extension class name.
Whatever, you say extension protocol open curly brace and
implement some of the methods. Or properties in the protocol.
Okay, now protocols just like extensions can have
no storage, okay. Protocol can have no storage and
extensions can have no storage either. So there's no way to
implement some of the protocol with any storage, no vars,
okay. You can have vars but they have to be computed.
Okay, so no storage in protocols or extensions.
All right, so there's four aspects to using a protocol.
One is the protocol declaration.
That's where you declare what methods and
properties are in this protocol.
Then there's the declaration where a class, a struct or
an enum says, I implement this protocol. So,
it's not good enough if you're a class or
struct enum to just implement the methods or
the property there.
You have to actually declare I implement this,
then you have to go implement all the methods and
properties as well. Okay, and we'll show you how to do that.
Then there's the code that implements the protocol and
that's usually going to be, in the class structure enum that
said it was going to implement it.
But it could also be in an extension, okay?
It can either be an extension to the protocol or
it could be an extension to the class, struct or
enum. Okay? You could have implementation in there.
Again, no storage though.
So if you need storage to implement it,
that's gonna have to be inside the class, struct or enum.
All right. Optional methods in a protocol.
This one's a little bit tricky, okay, in Swift,
protocols all the properties, all the methods are required.
If you say you implement that protocol, you must implement
all of the protocol. You ca't just pick and choose.
However in Objective C, it had something called protocols.
Okay, and in Objective C things could be optional. So
in Objective C, you could put the word optional in front of.
So you could say like optional func, whatever.
And it would mean that in this protocol,
you could still say you implement this protocol and
you don't have to implement this one. It's optional, okay?
That was Objective C only. Now, I was used Objective C.
It was written in Objective C and
uses this optional protocol stuff a lot. Okay, and
I'm gonna talk about how it uses it in a moment here. And
so Swift has to have this mechanism. And so the way
it does this is it lets you declare protocols to be @objc
compliant. You just say @objc space protocol, whatever.
And that means this protocol is an objc compliant one. And
inside that kind of protocol, you can use the word optional
in front of any of the funcs or vars in there. To say this
is optional so that someone who implements that protocol
does not have to implement those optional things, okay?
This is used in iOS for something called delegation
and we'll talk all about that. One thing that's interesting
is that any optional protocol implementing class.
So if you're class and it implements a protocol,
an Objective C protocol. With these optional things must
inherit from NSObject, so this is the second time I'm telling
you. Sometimes a class can't, a Swift class cant
inherit from nothing, you have to inherit from NSObject or
from a class that inherits from NSObject. Okay? So
cuz it's all part of this Objective C runtime and
that class has to be available in the Objective C runtime.
Just like the protocol has to be available in
the Objective C runtime,
okay? So that's the optional thing there.
All right, so here is what the syntax looks like, here I'm
declaring a protocol, it's called some protocol. Okay?
See it has, looks just like doing a class, right? Class,
someclass, enum, someenum, protocol, someproperty.
Exactly the same. And then there's the curly braces and
then there's these methods inside. Notice that you can
have inheritance, in fact multiple inheritance for
protocols. All right? Now, Swift is a single inheritance
model for classes, but for protocols, it's multiple
inheritance. What does it mean for a protocol to inherit from
another protocol? Well, it just means that some property,
okay, some protocol, anyone who implements some protocol
also has to implement all of these protocols as well.
InheritedProtocol1, InheritedProtocol2,
it's gotta implement those as well. So it's required,
the requirement goes all the way through, okay, that's what
multiple inheritance means there. Okay, inside here when
you have a var, okay, remember this has to be, in here you
have to specify whether it's a get only or get and set. You
can do that with this little curly brace syntax here,
it could either have the word get in here or get space set.
There's no such thing as a set only property, okay? Get or
get and set. Any functions that are mutated,
they will mutate this thing.
They're expected to mutate it. Have to be marked mutating and
this is because struct can be allowed to implement these
protocols. And we know that structs that have methods that
mutate themselves have to be declared mutating. So
we have to do the same thing in the protocol here as well.
Now it is possible to restrict your protocol by the way to be
only for classes. In other words, enums and
structs are not allowed to implement it. You do that by
putting colon class comma right after the protocol
before all the inherited ones, you just put class comma.
Okay? That means this protocol is only for classes.
Then you would not need mutating, okay,
cuz we don't use mutating for classes. You can even
specify initializers in your protocol. And
that's basically saying anyone who implements this protocol
has to have an initializer that looks like this, right?
Okay, now, you have this protocol declared with all
the vars and funcs in there. How do you implement it, okay?
Well, a class or a structure or
enum comes along and it says at the end of its, after,
in the class' case after it says what its super
class is. It puts a comma and says here's all the protocols
I implement. And when it says these other protocols
over here, it's promising to implement them. And
the compiler will not let it get away with not implementing
them, it will complain, okay? So simple as that.
If you have an enum or structs,
like here's an enum, there's no superclass obviously, but
otherwise it looks the same. Right? So this enum is saying
I'm gonna implement these two protocols. Same thing with
this struct, it's saying I'm gonna implement these. And
obviously if there are any mutating ones in here,
it's gonna have to be mutating in there. Okay?
There's no limit to the number of protocols that a class or
struct or enum can implement, can do as many as they want.
If you have a init as part of the protocol and
a class is implementing it, it has to make that init
required. Okay, that's because you wouldn't want
this class to have a subclass that doesn't implement this.
Now it would not implement the protocol anymore. And yet
it inherits the fact that it has to implement the protocol.
So, there's init,
that's why you have to have this be required, okay? You
are allowed to add protocol conformance via an extension.
So you could have extension to something, let's say this is
a struct or a class or an enum colon some protocol and
then put the methods in here. So now I'm extending that
class or struct or enum to implement this protocol. And
that just allows you to put this code off in another file,
for example, you don't have to put it in the same file. Or
you might be, this might be a class
you don't have the source code for.
Maybe this is a UI kit thing,
maybe you're extending UI button to implement some
protocol. You could do that with an extension, you see?
And that saves you having to for example,
subclass UI button to add protocol conformance. Just use
an extension. Okay, it's all really very well thought out.
They did a really good job with Swift with protocols and
extensions. Protocols are a really important part of
sophisticated Swift programming. If you're really
gonna build powerful complex things, you really have to be
facile with protocols. Because protocols really
give it the heart of what the API contract is
between things. Okay, it's really talking about,
these are the methods and functions I expect you to
implement if you're gonna work with me, okay.
That's what a protocol all about.
And that's fundamentally good object-oriented programming,
fundamentally good encapsulation, so
you really wanna understand this.
Now, this is a beginning,
starting class in iOS so I don't expect you to
have mastered this by the end. But again, it's something you
gotta know that if you go out in the real world,
and start a program people are gonna
expect if you're gonna be a sophisticated programmer.
It's like you're gonna know how to use protocols, and
not just make everything a class.
Okay all the courses you've had before now probably,
everything's a class. Okay it's a Java thing,
everything's a class. Now in the real world out there
you're probably gonna have a lot of protocols.
Okay, question? >> In what case would you
use a protocol other than extension?
>> Okay so this question is,
in what case would you use a protocol versus just
an extension for example, and that's a good question.
You'd use a protocol anywhere you need to, specify that as
a type in some API. Right, if you need to say the argument
to this method takes something that implements
certain methods then you need that protocol type to say that
in your user data type. An extension is not its own type
it's just adding methods to an existing type.
See the difference? So a protocol is a typing and
it's for strongly typing things. Okay, so,
let's look at an example of protocols here.
I have a protocol called Moveable. Okay,
it has a mutating function called moveTo a certain point,
okay. That's its only method. And I have two classes, two,
not classes, two data types here. A Car. It's a moveable.
See? It implements moveTo. It doesn't have to say mutating
cuz it's a class. And I have a shape like a shape on screen.
It's a triangle, a rectangle. Okay? It's moveable. Okay? And
it's mutating. Okay, and it's got, they've each got other
methods like a car knows how to change the oil of a car.
And a shape knows how to draw the shape.
Okay. But, they share the fact that they're both moveable.
So I can create a couple local variables here, a prius,
which is a car, initialized to a car here.
And let's say I have a square, which is a shape,
probably this would be actually be square,
open parentheses, closes parentheses,
probably have a subclass or a different kind of, well,
let's say it's a shape [LAUGH] okay. So we got a shape here.
Both of these, okay the prius and the square, are each
a local variable of their perspective type. Now I, and
so these, this is the method that's common to them all.
Now I can create a var called thingToMove which is of type
Moveable. That's its type. Okay, and I told you protocols
could be type. And look, I can set this thing to moveTo
a prius. Because a prius is a Moveable. Cuz it's a car.
You see? So this is perfectly legal right here. And
I could even say thingToMove.moveTo, and
it'll call the car's version of moveTo, okay.
Make sense? However, I cannot say thingToMove.changeOil.
Okay? Why not? Prius is a car. Car can change oil.
How come I can't say thingToMove change the oil?
Because thingToMove is not a car,
it's a moveable. Okay? Moveables only know
how to move. Now the fact that underlying there's an actual
thing a car in there that can do change oil, that's,
that hasn't, it's irrelevant, okay. It has nothing to do it
with because this thing is typed to only be a Moveable,
so you can only send moveable things to it. Okay? I could
also say thingToMove, this same variable, equals square.
Also perfectly legal, because a square is a shape,
a shape is a Moveable. Okay? I could even create an array
of things to move that are moveables and
put the prius in the square in there.
Okay, so even though prius and
the square are completely different things,
a car and a shape, okay? They can live in this array because
they're both moveables. This is an array of moveables,
okay? Now I could have a function here for
example called slide which takes a slider or
thing to slide basically. And it's a moveable.
So, with argument type here, this function is moveable.
And inside here, I could take slider move to some position.
And I don't care wether this is a car or shape.
This function slide has no idea wether sliding a car or
sliding a shape. No idea. Cuz all it knows is it's working
on a moveable. So that's how you could use a moveable as
a type to an argument, of a function, okay.
And see, I can say slide(prius), slide(square),
works perfectly, yeah. >> You said car [INAUDIBLE]
into moveable it's another protocol.
Card could be seen as a little object as well
as the other. >> Yeah.
So the question is, I think the question is if car
was part of other protocols? >> Yeah.
>> Then could I set
some variable that's of that other protocol equal to this?
Absolutely I could. Because it is both removable and that
other thing. Independently it is both of those things.
And I can even have a protocol right here that's
two different things. Now this would mean that for something
to be passed to slip and slide through this variable.
It would have to implement both of these protocols. So
it's almost like I'm inventing a protocol in this slot.
With this syntax right here, it's almost like you're
inventing a protocol that inherits both of these.
Okay, so this means that it requires both that's what this
protocol angle bracket means okay, and
this could be any number of protocols in here. Now I can't
say slipAndSlide(prius) here, because prius is not slippery.
It's moveable but it's not slippery so it will not pass
through here, everybody got that? So that's protocol.
Super powerful, you'll start to get a feel for
as we start using more and more. Now the first important
use of protocol we're gonna talk about is Delegation.
All right? So delegation is how we do this blind
structured communication between our view and
our controller right there. And we talked about this very
second lecture, I think about how sometimes our view wants
to send message like, should I do this,
or I will do this like in the scroll view. I did scroll to
this location, I will zoom to this zoom factor. Or
if I'm some data thing like a table, I'm gonna say, well
I've got a count of 400 rows, I want the data at row 7,
I want the data at row 12 through 20. Okay? These kind
of communications right here, you can see now with protocol,
it's really easy. You just create a protocol that has all
these methods in it, and anybody can implement this.
Even though it's usually a controller, it doesn't have to
be a controller. The controller for example could
instantiate some other object that implements those methods.
Okay, it would still be a part of controller camp,
by the way, but it doesn't have to actually
be a UIViewController sub-class anymore.
Okay, so let's see what that looks like. First some
view something in the view okay this generic remember
views are generic minions okay of the controller.
They declare some protocol which is the methods,
like the will should did, or
the data add count, those things that it wants somebody
else like the controller to implement for it,
so it declares a protocol with all those methods and
properties in it. Then the view's API, okay,
somewhere in the view, it has a public property, okay, which
is weak delegate, and the type is this protocol it invented.
Okay so this is gonna be a var. Okay, that's going to
have to be an object that implements that protocol and
it's weak because the view is kind of
saying well if no one can do this will did should or can't
do the count add data well I'll just sit here empty or I
won't do what I do or I won't notify anyone of the wills and
dids. Okay, I won't ask anyone the shoulds. So it can be nil
so that's why the delegate is usually weak okay or
might even be unowned but it's certainly not strong.
Cuz you don't want the view to keep the controller in memory
right. The controller can keeps the view in memory but
you don't want the view keeping the controller.
All right, then the view uses this delegate property
any time it wants to send that will, should, did,
count, data, add. It just sends it to this
delegate, okay? Because it knows the delegate implements
those protocol methods. Then the controller
has to declare that it implements this protocol, so
it just puts it on its you know, class something,
UIV controller, comma, that protocol.
Then the controller sets itself as this delegate, so it
sets itself as this property. So now when the view talks
to that delegate it's talking back to the controller.
So that's how it plays out to use delegation here.
Now of course the controller has to implement the protocol,
has to implement the methods, but
remember this is all objective C worlds.
Right?The delegation is from the objective C world, so
all these things you're gonna see in iOS,
these delegate protocols like scroll, views delegate,
table views, delegate. Almost all the methods are optional,
okay. There's a few in there that aren't, and
that's because you might not care that the scroll
view just finished scrolling to this location. So you don't
wanna that method scroll view did scroll to point.
You don't want it, so
you don't wanna even have to implement it. Okay? So
these protocols are all gonna be Objective-C protocols,
@objc, and they're gonna have a lot of word optional in
front of a lot of the funcs, okay. All right, so
now the view's hooked up to the controller. The view still
has no idea what kind of object is doing, is
implementing the will, should, and did. It could be anything.
Any class, it could, doesn't even have to be a class!
It could be a struct or something. Although actually,
probably does have to be a class, cuz OBJC thing,
those have to be classes, and it's an object thing. So
it is a class but it doesn't know that it's a UI view
controller. Ok, it doesn't have to be a view-a UI view
controller. So it's blind. But it's structured, because
the protocol says exactly the method that had to be sent.
All right? So, this, I keep talking about this happening,
because of objective C in the history of iOS.
What would you do in Swift? Because Swift doesn't have
these optional protocols. Well, in Swift,
either you could do the same thing, ok? And just
break up your protocol into the pieces that make sense, so
you might have three or four different protocols and
you'll only implement the ones that you want.
Like you have the scroll view notification protocols,
and then you have the scroll view should protocols, and
then you have the data app protocols, or whatever.
Another way to do things like this is with closures, okay?
You don't even need all this overhead of having
these protocols do that you can just have a closure and
the closure knows what
the arguments to the closure are and
what it's supposed to return.
And that's essentially like having the protocol defined.
So in this case what you could do you can imagine saying to
the scroll view. When you're finished scrolling,
execute this closure. Right, give it a closure. So
that's another way to do it is with closures. And
you're gonna see that iOS does some things with closures and
some things with delegates. And they're not
exact substitutes for each other. Protocols are sometimes
nice because they make it really clear what this object
is capable of delegating. So that's nice.
Closures are really good for things like error
call backs and multi, when a multi-threaded world when
things are gonna take a long time and they're done later
and it wants to tell you it's done, that kinda thing. So
we'll see both as the rest of the quarter goes on. All
right, so here's an example of scroll view, right? So
scroll view, the, is a UI view subclass. It has a var called
delegate, it's weak. Its type is UIScrollView delegate
optional because you don't have to set a delegate here.
Okay. The delegate protocol looks like this.
It's in OBJC protocol. Okay. And it has all these
optional functions. It has over a dozen of them,
things like scrollViewDidScroll. View for
assuming it's scroll view which gets a view to zoom on
on inside the scroll view etc. Okay? So
a Controller that wants to work with the ScrollView
will say MyViewController is a subclass of UIViewController
and it implements this protocol. Okay?
Now most of this is optional so
didn't have to do much to do that. Okay? And then
this UIViewController is gonna say, scrollView.delegate.
This is some outlet that points to the ScrollView.
That delegate equals self and that's gonna be okay because
it says that it implements this protocol, okay.
Now the scroll view is gonna use this to talk to this view
controller. Okay, and then view controller implements
whichever of these it wants and, off to the races. Okay,
make sense? All right, let's go through and
talk about ScrollView in more detail, because this is
an important class, all right. So here's an interesting,
this is like an iPhone one or something.
Notice this very small little iPhone. But it has a cool
little animation here to show you how ScrollViews work.
Look at this ScrollView. See it can ScrollView
horizontally, and inside there can be vertical things.
So this is a ScrollView that's inside ScrollView. See that?
So ScrollView's really smart about that. Look at this one.
Okay, you've got two things, top thing ScrollViews and
the bottom thing is a horizontal ScrollView
with vertical ones inside. So you can see an old iPhone
one here or whatever it is, not a lot of screen space, but
it's very efficiently being used by the ScrollViews, okay.
So the ScrollView is super powerful. So
let's talk a little bit about how ScrollView works and
we do it mostly by adding subviews to it.
Let's first remind ourselves what it's like to
add a subview to a normal UIView. It's really simple.
I've got the UI view right here on my phone.
I just set the frame, where I want this UI view to be added,
and then I just add it. View, add sub-view.
This is probably in the view controllers so
this will be the top level view. And
I'm just adding the sub-view, this specifies where it is.
All right, everyone is cool with that? Very simple.
So a scroll view is almost exactly the same. Okay. But
the big step that's different is first we declare a content
size. This is a big area, k, that the scroll view is going
to be scrolling around and in. Okay. And we specify by size.
Okay, here I've made one 3,000 wide by 2,000 high, so
we've got a lot of room to scroll around in there.
But once I've specified the content size which I've set
this bar right here.
Now I just add sub views in the exact same way. Okay,
logo.frame here I've moved it over to 2700,
so it's way over on the right. Scroll view,
add sub view logo, okay? Just like any other view.
I've added it as a subview. Could add another one.
Let's add an aerial photo of Stanford here, okay?
Added it as a subview. So they all get added in a coordinate
system relative to this big content area right here, okay?
Now the scroll view just moves around and lets you
look around inside that content area. See. That's all
it's doing, is looking around. Now you can move the subviews
to different places in the same way you can move
them in a regular view. Right? So I can change the frame of
the aerial view to be in the corner.
I can change the frame of the logo, maybe, to overlap.
I can also come along later and change the content size.
Maybe I want this content size to be small enough to just fit
my views. Okay and again then when I'm kind of using
my finger, in the scroll view I'm just moving around in
its content area. So the most important thing to understand
about this is if you don't set your content size
you get nothing.
You can't scroll because you're scrolling over that
content size. This is the most commonly mistaken thing about
scroll view people don't understand.
They don't set their content size and so things
can't scroll. Gotta have a content size, okay? Couple of
other interesting things. If you want to find out where
you're currently showing in the content area, there's this
var inside of scrollView called contentOffset. And
it's just a CG point. Gonna tell you the X and
Y of the upper left corner of where the scroll view is
showing right as it moves around that changes.
Also if you wanted to know the whole,
what that whole rectangle is in the, coordinate system in
one of these views, like this thing or the, or the.
The logo or the, or the aerial view. You can get
the scrollView's bounds, okay. ScrollView.bound. And
use this UIView method convertRect fromView, okay?
So you're gonna convert this bounds from the scrollView's
coordinate system, to this aerial view. This is probably
the UIImageView, okay. To it, coordinate system. Now you
can find the whole rectangle in the a, in the aerial guy
coordinate system, to show what's, what's visible, okay?
Okay, how do you create a scrollView,
it's just like in the other UIView,
usually you're gonna drag it out in, your story board,
okay? You can also do Embed In Scroll View in the storyboard.
We don't usually do that very much, but you can.
That's if you just had one view inside there,
it would embed it in there and also set its content size
to the size of the thing you embedded, but usually we drag
it out. You can also create it in code, right, it's just,
it's just a view, so you can use UIView (frame:),
initializer there. Then you, add your too big UIView,
of the view that's too big that you wanna scroll over,
just by creating it and calling addSubView, okay?
Talked about on the previous slides there,
okay? Don't forget to set that contentSize,,
I can't emphasize that enough. If you don't, if you don't set
the contentSize, it's just not gonna work, okay?
All right, so, you can scroll with your finger, but you can
also scroll programmatically. And the classic way to do is
by saying scrollRectToVisible and you just specify
a rectangle in the contents size coordinate system, and
it'll scroll to try and show as much of that rectangle
as possible. It'll scoll, scroll as little as possible,
to show as much as possible of the rectangle, okay?
Here's also a ton of other methods in scrollView, I can't
talk about them all, you can go look them up. But you can
control which direction scrolling is allowed,
just vertically or just horizontally, or
if it starts being vertical, does it lock vertical?
That's how the scroll view inside scrollView works.
Things like that, you can flash your scroll bars,
all kinds of stuff there, okay.
Now what about zooming? So we talked about kinda panning
around, what if I wanna zoom in, like pinch to zoom in,
how do I do that? Okay, well, all UIViews, okay,
have a property called transform, it's
an affine transform, which means translate, scale and
rotate for, or is incorporated into to this transform. And so
the scrollView, as you zoom it's just modifying the scale
of this transform property in the view. So basically, if you
zoomed in really a lot your view would get very grainy,
because all it's doing is basically scaling the bits up.
Now, once it's finished zooming in,
you could redraw your view to not be so
grainy, okay? If you have, the ability to do that. But,
generally when it's zooming, it is zooming the bits, okay?
Using this transform property. Zooming will not work unless
you set these properties. Because by default,
the minimumZoomScale and the maximumZoomScale is 1.
Meaning no zoom, okay? So this is how much,
you can zoom size, zoom down, minimum. So 0.5
would mean it can zoom down to half its normal size. And
this is zooming out, eh, you can zoom to twice its normal
size if you set it to 2.0. Okay, so you have to set
these, don't forget that or your zooming won't work.
You also won't work if you don't implement this
delegate method, that's why I talked to you and
told you about delegates. You have to implement this method,
viewForZoomingInScrollView, okay. By the way,
notice these delegate methods, the first argument is always
the thing that's sending you the delegate method,
it's basically the sender. Okay, just so
you know which, if you had two scrollViews,
you'd know which one is asking you for the view for
zooming in scrollView.
Now this is going to return the UIView that's gonna
have its transform modified when you pinch, okay? So
you have to implement this.
If you don't implement this you get no zooming,
all right? You can also zoom programmatically, not just
with a pinch obviously, you can set it to scale, or
you can zoom to a rectangle that looks like this. So here
I have a zoom scale of 1.2 I'm kinda zoomed out a little bit,
and I could zoom back to normal.
Okay, this is 1.0 so this is the normal size of this image.
Or I could zoom back out to 1.2, so that's 20% larger,
right? I can also do the zoomToRect, let's say I have
this little rectangle here and I said zoom to this rect,
it would show as much of the rectangle as possible. Or
if I had the rect out there, and I said zoom to rect,
it would zoom it down to fit that rectangle, okay.
So that's how you can zoom in from your code, okay?
There's lots and lots of other delegate methods,
you can look at the documentation to figure out,
a lot of them are the did and
will, like here's DidEndZooming.
This is where you might redraw your thing with more,
with a finer grain, if you got scaled up really big and
you got grainy, things like that. So you can take a look
at all those. I have a demo here at the end, but
first I want to talk about whats coming up here.
On Wednesday your Assignment 3 is due,
of course before lecture you know that,
and we're gonna start talking about Multithreading,
all right? Friday this section is on UI Testing,
which is really cool and
iOS, you can actually basically record mouse clicks
and then play them back, and make sure that you're getting
the results you expect. Next week, we're gonna talk about
Table View, and Object-Oriented Database.
I'm give a little break this weekend, okay? I'm not gonna
assign, Assignment 4 on Wednesday, I'll be assigning
it next Monday. It'll be due the Monday after. So
you have no assignment over this coming weekend.
There's no more reading assignments at all. Okay,
right now, I'm gonna do a little scrollView demo, okay,
called Cassini. Any questions before I jump into that?
Okay Cassini, okay, I'm gonna create a brand new thing here.
So let's quit that, let's go, oops, over here.
Create a new project. Okay, it's gonna be an iO, I'm gonna
start going fast through these new project creations here,
Single View Applications like we always do.
I'm gonna call it Cassini. Okay all the things we
normally do there. Put it in the same place we always do.
Here is our Cassini. I'm going to do the same thing where I'm
gonna move these things out of the way, or
at least most of them. Supporting,
oops, Supporting Files.
Okay, they, that, there, I left info plist,
cuz we're actually gonna look at that today. All right,
here's my storyboard, for Cossini right here,
this storyboard has a generic ViewController.
You know, we always get this generic ViewController.
Now in the calculator, we renamed this,
hopefully you did that for your assignment. But
I'm not gonna rename it, I'm gonna do another thing here,
cuz I don't want this to be a generic ViewController.
I want it to be a subclass of ViewController, but
I'm just going to delete this instead.
So I'm gonna take this ViewController and
I'm gonna right-click and
hit Delete, just get rid of that whole class and
move it to the trash. Now my storyboard,
if I look at the Identity inspector over here,
it still thinks this is a ViewController, okay.
So I need to create the actual class,
not this generic ViewController, so
I'm gonna do that. Gonna create, a iOS Source,
Cocoa Touch Class, it's gonna be a ViewController, I'm gonna
call it ImageViewController. I'm gonna have my UI here,
what it's gonna do is just display an image, okay.
So it's just, that's just very simple,
UI is gonna display the image,
in the whole screen of the phone or the iPad,
whatever. Okay, so it's gonna an ImageViewController,
it's gonna display that. We'll put it in the same place we
put all these other things over here.
All right, here it is. Okay, you can see we have
a couple of ViewController life cycles here, here.
I'm not going to be a bad citizen, so
hopefully I won't have any memory. Then I'm gonna leak,
I'm also not going to navigate from this MVC,
okay. On Wednesday, we'll be continuing this demo and
we will be navigating to this, but not from it,
so I don't need, the prepareForSegue,
that's only for things that are navigating from, okay?
I do need my viewDidLoad() right here, so
I'm gonna leave that in here. When I create a new MVC
controller here, you gotta remember to go back here to
your identity inspector and set the class. If you don't,
obviously none of your outlets are gonna work right,
you'll probably crash at launch, all kinds of things,
okay? So I'm just using the Identity Inspector right here
to set that to ImageViewController.
Another thing I like to do when I create an MVC right
off the bat is think about what is my model, okay?
So this is an image view controller, what does it do?
It shows an image, so I'm gonna have its model,
which is gonna be public,
I'm gonna allow the people to set it, be the URL
of the image to display. Okay, so that's my model,
it's a URL. It could be a file on the local filesystem, could
be something over the network, okay, that's what it is.
Now to display this imageURL's image, I need an image view.
Now we have created all of our classes,
all our views by going over here and finding things,
like there's image view down here somewhere,
here it is right here, and we've been dragging them out.
And I could drag this out and all this stuff, but I want to
start showing a little bit how to create views in code.
So we're going to create this image view in our controller's
code, and in fact I'm just going to create a private
var for it, which I'm going to call my image view, okay?
And I'm just going to set it equal to UIImageView.
So I'm creating one right here.
I'm using the init that takes no arguments, so that's going
to create an image view that the frame is 0000, okay? Tiny,
tiny little ImageView. So I'm going to have to be careful to
reset it's frame whenever I put an image in there. Okay,
so now I have this ImageView,
that's cool. I need my viewDidLoad right down here,
okay. After I'm loaded I'm going to,
just take this, ImageView that I created and
add it as a subview of my top level view.
So I'm gonna say view.addSubview my ImageView.
Okay, so remember this view right here, this var, okay,
comes along with your UIViewController.
It's the view that's at the very top, okay?
So I'm just going to add this image view, in there.
Now, its frame is 0000 so I'm putting it up in the corner
there, okay? So right now it's not gonna show anything, but I
haven't put any image in there either, so nothing's gonna
happen. So, I'm gonna kill two birds with one stone and
deal with that and create a new private var, which I'm
gonna call image. It's gonna be a UI Image, optional, okay?
And this is gonna be a computed var, okay? And
in the set for this, this is when I'm gonna set my image,
okay? So, this var, anytime I want to set the image that I'm
showing, I'm gonna set this var. And every, and I
could also use it for getting as you'll see in a second, but
I'm just gonna set it. So
what do I need to do when I set an image, okay.
Well there's two things I need to do. One is I need to set
the imageView's image to that image,
which is the newValue right? So now I've taking
my image view right here and I'm giving it the image. But
I know I need to reset my frame, okay, to fit this new
image. So I'm also gonna say imageView.sizeToFit. Okay, so
this is a method on imageView that will size the imageView
to fit whatever image is in it, okay? Now the get is
really easy. I'm just going to return the image view's image.
So this is an interesting var right here,
it's a compute a var, that it's a computed var and
it's actually storing its data somewhere else.
It's storing it in the image view, but it's intervening
when that value gets set to do this little size to fit, okay,
everyone understand why I have this image var? So
now the rest of my code looks really cool. Anytime I want to
set an image I just say image equals whatever and
it's going to set it in image view and size to fit it.
Okay, now what else do we need to do here?
So we've got this nice image thing,
one thing we wanna do is whenever our model gets set,
we want to go load that image up. So,
I'm gonna do a didSet here in my model. And
I'm first going to set whatever image I have to nil,
so if I have an image that I'm showing,
I'm gonna clear that out. And now I'm going to go fetch
the image that the person is asking me for. And I'm going
to do that in another little method here, fetchImage.
Okay, its going to be all private func fetchImage.
And all this thing is gonna do is gonna go out and look for
this URL either on the Internet or
in a local file, okay. So how's it gonna do that?
Well let's see if that URL is not nil first of all, okay so
if I can let, oops, let the URL equal that image URL,
okay. Now I know I have a real URL and I can go get it. So
how do I get the data from the URL to correspond to an image?
Well I actually use the class NSData. Remember I mentioned
that class NSData that gets a bag of bits?
It knows how to go out to a URL on the internet and
get the bag of bits. So I'm gonna say if let imageData
equal the NSData's contents of URL it's called, this URL,
now I have the imageData. I just need to create a UIImage
out of that and I'm good to go. So let's do that.
I'm gonna set my image equal to the UIImage that is made
with that imageData. Okay, so this is an intializer for
UIImage which takes the raw JPEG data basically. So
here I got the raw JPEG or png or whatever it is data.
And here I'm just creating a UIImage out of it.
And then I say image equals,
which is gonna cause this setter to happen.
Which is gonna set the image in my imageView and resize my
imageView to fit, all right? [COUGH] And then, we're good
to go. Make sense? This code's pretty simple code,
but I've intentionally broken it down into pieces like this
to show you how you can use some of these Swift mechanisms
to compartmentalize your code and make things simpler. Like
this is very simple to set the image, because it's taken some
of the image related handling stuff out of band there.
Now we need an image to show, okay, so
the first thing I am gonna show is a little demo image,
so I actually have a little class right here with some
demo URLs. Let's go take a look at this. It is actually
just a struct with only static stuff in it, okay? So
I've got a little Stanford URL here, to show some image of
Stanford, and I've also got some NASA images, which we're
going to show when we get to this demo on Wednesday, okay?
So I'm just going to go here to my viewDidLoad, all right,
and I'm going to say that my image URL, that's my model,
all right. I set my model here equal to,
I want to say it's equal to the demoURL.stanford, okay,
this is the demoURL.stanford that I have over here,
demoURL.stanford. Unfortunately this is
a string, okay, URLs are actually classes,
okay, in iOS, so I have to use an NSURL constructor,
which takes a string and turns it into a URL.
Got it? Okay, so let's go ahead and run this.
Okay, didn't work. It's blank and I have a little
error down here. And this is a very interesting error.
Okay, you're gonna wanna pay attention here cuz it's gonna
happen when you do your. Homework next week.
It says App Transport Security has blocked a resource load
since it is insecure. By def, by default, only https,
secure http calls, are allowed to go through. If you
want insecure calls like this, okay, that's because my URL
happens to be this kind. If you want that to go through,
you have to put an entry in your info.p list.
Okay, so this is what it like, looks like to put something
in your info.p list, you just click on info.p list,
so that's showing here, okay?
And then you right click and say add row, okay?
When you add a row, you can see there's [LAUGH] dozens and
dozens of different things you can control in your p list
here. We actually want the third one down here,
which is App, App Transport Security Settings.
See that right there? So App Transport Security Settings,
Settings is a dictionary. So we click this to go down
arrow, which means we wanna edit what's in the dictionary.
And we just hit plus, and it's gonna add a key value here.
So there's two different keys can be in that one.
We want Allow Arbitrary Loads. That allows us to load
arbitrary URLs, okay. And we wanna set it from NO to YES.
Okay, so that means we're gonna allow arbitrary loads.
So you're definitely gonna need to do that, for
your homework. So now we run, we'll go out there.
There it is. Okay, just a picture of Stanford.
Now the thing is, it's kinda good, but we can't see,
we can only see the left half of the quad here, and
I can't scroll because of course,
we're not in a scroll view, all right? So how we,
how do we put this image view into a scroll view so
that we can drag it around and look at the whole thing?
Okay, now for this one, for adding a scroll view, I could
do that in code as well, just like I did the image view. But
to show you that it's not exclusive which you do,
I'm gonna put the scroll view in the storyboard,
and I'll put the image view in the code and
we can mix them, okay? So how do I do that?
I'm gonna go to my storyboard right here, and
I'm gonna go grab a scroll view outta here,
I'm gonna search for it, actually. Scroll, here it is,
Scroll View. So, you're gonna drag it out and
use the blue lines to put it in the edges here. Like that.
Okay, I'm gonna reset to suggested constraints.
I'm gonna go over here to my Identity Inspector,
which I always like to do when I do that reset, and
make sure you have trailing leading top, bottom.
Perfect, that's exactly what I want.
I obviously need an outlet to this scroll
view if I'm gonna talk to it and
be its delegate, and things like that. So I'm going to get
both of these on screen at the same time, my controller and
my scroll view. Let's go ahead and control drag here,
this right here. I'm gonna call this outlet scroll view.
Notice here's the weak, strong by the way, okay? If my scroll
view leaves my view hierarchy, it can set me to nil, I am
fine. Connect, okay, we've got our scroll view here. Now,
all we need to do is set the image view as a subview
of our scroll view instead of as a sub, subview of our top
level view. So, really, all I need to do is change this
to scrollView, okay, and it's gonna add as a subview. Now,
let's see, is this gonna work? Probably not cuz I wouldn't
have asked that question. Why is this not gonna work,
do you think? It looks like it worked,
right? Let's scroll, it's not, why isn't this scrolling?
What's going on? I put a scrollView in there. Is it,
what's wrong with this thing? Okay,
anyone have any idea why this is not scrolling?
>> Content size.
>> Bingo.
If I had a can, if I was Mehran,
I'd be throwing candy out to you. Yeah, absolutely,
no content size, so it's currently scrolling fine over
a zero by zero area, okay. And the image is just bleeding out
from the edges of it, okay? So we need to set the content
size. Where do we set the content size? Well, one place
we definitely need to set it is anytime we have an image
because we want the content size to fit the whole image.
So here, I would just say scrollView.contentSize,
contentSize = what, ever our image view's frame size is.
One thing I'm gonna do here is kinda tricky,
is I'm gonna put a question mark right there. Why might I
put a question mark there? Because this scrollView
is an outlet. If this image setting happened, for example,
when someone was preparing me, this would crash.
Cuz my scrollView wouldn't be set in prepare. Now no one,
no one is yet segueing to me. But on Wednesday,
they're going to be. [LAUGH] So I have to be careful here.
So here, if I haven't set up my scrollView and
I get an image, I'm just gonna do nothing. Well,
then I better do something when the scrollView gets set,
okay? When the scrollView comes along later, later and
gets set, I better do this content size, so
I better do it in both places here. And here,
we don't need that, okay? See why I'm doing in both places,
cuz I'm not sure which is gonna happen first.
Is my scroll view gonna get set first, or my outlet,
you know, or my, model and thus my image gonna be set
first? Okay? Okay, so now let's run, see if this works.
All right, here it is. And sure enough,
scrolled beautifully, okay, and even if we rotate and
scroll. All right, so that's great, it's working
wonderfully. On Wednesday, we'll talk about zooming cuz
we wanna be able to zoom in on this. Then we're also going to
talk a little bit about what happens if these images
are huge and take a long time to download. That's hard for
me to demo on this network cuz this network is so fast.
But I have some huge NASA images that I think will go
slow enough that you're gonna see my
UI is really sluggish as I wait for these,
things to download. And that's why we use multithreading,
Wednesday's topic, to figure out how to make it all really,
really, really snappy. Okay, that's it,
I'll see you then. >> For
more, please visit us at stanford.edu.