[MUSIC]
Standford University. >> All right,
斯坦福大学
welcome then to lecture number eight. I think it's eight,
欢迎参加第八讲。好像是第八讲。
yes, of CS193P Spring of 2016. So today, we start off
是的，2016 春季 CS193P 课程。今天，我们将
by continuing that demo that we were doing last time.
继续完成上一次的 demo
Remember we had the demo, Cassini demo with the, scroll
今天用到之前 scroll view 写的 Cassini
view in there. And so I'm gonna make it more powerful,
让它功能更加强大.
we're gonna get multiple MVCs going in there.
我们将会用到多个 MVC 的结构.
We'll start doing some zooming in the scroll view.
会用到 scroll view 的缩放属性.
Depending on how the time goes I might actually show you some
如果有时间，我会通过实际案例来
things that couple of you have asked about on Piazza.
解答有些同学对 Piazza 项目的疑问.
Like, how to when I launch my calculator app can I have it
例如，在启动我的计算器 app 的时候，
not launch and show a blank graph, right,
因为没有启动图而显示空白的情况.
how can I have it launch and show the calculator for
怎样才能在在第一次启动计算器时，
the very first time, okay, those kinds of things.
显示启动页等，诸如此类的问题.
So we'll see how the time goes and
最后，我们会根据时间安排
decide on the fly whether to do that stuff.
来决定是否要解答这些.
Then we're gonna dive back into the slides.
让我们回到幻灯片上.
I'm gonna talk about multi-threading, okay?
我之后还会讲到多线程.
Very, very important thing in iOS is how to multithread
在 iOS 上，多线程的处理是非常非常重要的内容.
your execution. And then I'll go back to the demo, and
然后我们会回到 Cassini demo,
we'll multithread this Cassini thing we're working on, okay?
为它加上多线程支持.
And then time permitting at the end I'll go back to
在时间允许的情况下, 最后还会回到幻灯片
the slides and I'm gonna talk about text fields. And
讲一下 text field. 然后
then, next week we have table views, databases, etc. And
下周会讲 table view，database 等内容.
again, remember, no assignment going out today.
今天不会布置作业.
The assignment is gonna be a table view based thing, so
作业是基于 table view 的,
it will go out after Monday's lecture, all right? So,
所以我们会在下周一课程之后再布置, 没问题吧.
let's dive back into this Cassini demo. Okay,
那么, 让我们回到 Cassini demo.
we'll start off just exactly where we left off before. So
接着上一次的内容继续完善.
we'll go to Xcode here. So I'm just gonna open Cassini,
启动 Xcode, 打开 Cassini
here it is. I'm just gonna run it real quick just
我先来带大家快速过一遍
to remind you where we were for those with short memories.
回忆下之前的内容.
Even though it's only two days ago. All right,
虽然是两天前才讲的.
here it is. So we've got, our image view, right?
好的, 我们有一个 image view.
We have an ImageView and it's inside a UIScrollView, and so
这个 ImageView 嵌套在 UIScrollView 中,
we're able to scroll around, okay, just by panning with our
所以我们可以进行滚动, 用手指滑动就行
finger. My mouse is like a finger there, so
这光标就是手指
I'm just panning around, and that's all we can do, okay?
目前就只能随意滑动
But we've created this nice UI, or
但是我们这个漂亮的界面
this nice ImageViewController, which is an MVC that lets you
或者说, 漂亮的 ImageViewController 所用的 MVC 模式,
take any image and put it on screen inside the scroll view,
能任意将图片加入到 scroll view 中, 并显示出来
that's kind of a nice reusable, reusable MVC, right?
有很好的重用性, 重用 MVC, 对吧
So now we're going to make this a multi-MVC app, okay,
接下来, 我们会做一个多 MVC 的 app
and I'm gonna reuse this ImageViewController
重用的 ImageViewController
as one of the MVCs. So let's go right to our storyboard,
也是其中之一. 让我们打开 storyboard.
see what this is gonna look like.
来看看里面都有什么内容
This is where the Cassini part of this whole thing is gonna
Cassini 所展示的内容都从这里得到.
come in. All right, I'm gonna create a new View Controller,
现在, 我准备创建一个新的 View Controller
just gonna drag it out right here. Again,
将它拖到这里就可以了
I'm gonna go fairly quickly, cuz I've done this all before,
之前我们已经做过了, 所以这一步操作有点快
so this is almost like a review, for you here.
更像是在帮大家复习
So, I have this controller.
好, controller 创建好了
It needs to have a custom subclass of UIViewController
因为需要自定义 UIViewController
so I'm going to create such a thing. Go here to New File,
所以要做接下来的这些操作. 创建一个新文件
it's iOS source, it's a Cocoa Touch Class. Cuz it's
选择 iOS source, Cocoa Touch Class, 因为
a subclass of an iOS class, which is a UIViewController in
要子类化的类属于 iOS, 这里是 UIViewController
this case. I'm going to call this CassiniViewController,
类名就叫 CassiniViewController 吧
cuz it's gonna let us look at some Cassini images.
这个类会展示更多 Cassini 的图片
That's what our app is gonna do. But just in the same place
也是这个 app 的需求. 存放路径和之前一样
as always here is our CassiniViewController,
CassiniViewController 创建好了
I'm gonna remove the view controller lifecycle methods
暂时先删除模板给出的 view controller
that it gives me right here just for now anyway.
生命周期方法
And I'm actually gonna uncomment this prepareForSegue
然后打开 prepareForSegue 的注释
because my CassiniViewController is
因为 CassiniViewController 会
definitely going to be doing, some segueing.
用到这个方法, 一些 segue
So let's now go back to our storyboard,
现在让我们回到 storyboard
now that we have this ImageViewController class, and
我们已经有了 ImageViewController
I'm gonna change the class of this controller right here
再通过 identity inspector, 将这个
with the identity inspector, to be a CassiniViewController,
controller 改为 CassiniViewController
okay. Everybody got that? I'm going to put this whole
好的, 都能跟上吧? 接下来, 我会将整个
MVC structure into that split view with navigation that's
MVC 结构装到 split view 中
over in there, the thing that will work in both iPad and
这样就能同时用 iPad 和
iPhone, exact same thing we did for,
iPhone 上, 这种处理方式我们在
the emotions view controller. So, let's do that.
emotions view controller 上也做过. 下面来实现吧.
I'm going to start by dragging out the split view controller,
接下来需要拖一个 split view controller
I'm gonna zoom way out here.
先缩小画板
Let's go get a Split View Controller, here it is. I'll
然后找到 Split View Controller
drag it out. I'll get rid of these extra things that came
拖拽出来. 删掉除了
along here with the Split View Controller because I already
Split View Controller 的其他内容, 因为我们已经
have my master and detail right here. The Cassini's
有自己的 master 和 detail 了. Cassini 是
gonna be my master and this ImageViewController's gonna be
master, ImageViewController 是 detail.
my detail right there. So I'm just gonna Control drag, hook
按住 Control 并拖拽到 master
up my master. And a Control drag, hook up my detail.
然后按住 Control 并拖拽到 detail
I'm also gonna take my little entry arrow and make it so
接下来, 将入口箭头移动到
that it enters on the Split View Controller. Right,
Split View Controller
instead of entering on my Image View Controller,
Image View Controller 不再是入口
obviously. And, I want this to work on both iPhone and iPad,
我想要在 iPhone 和 iPad 上使用
so I'm gonna take my master and put it embedded inside
所以, 我准备将 master 嵌入到
of a navigation controller, okay? And maybe I can even go
navigation controller 中, 然后我能在这
in here and put a nice title here, right here. Cassini,
给它加上 title. Cassini.
okay? All right now, what is this UI going to do?
跟上了吗? 最终, 这个界面到底有什么作用?
What's it going to look like? How's it gonna function?
长什么样呢? 怎样触发一些功能?
Well, I'm just gonna have three buttons here.
好的, 我会在这里放 3 个按钮
Similar to how I had in emotions view controller.
和之前的 emotions view controller 很像
In a demo I can only do, I can't do a nice complicated
在 demo 中也只能这样了, 不能像计算器
MVC like a calculator and then another complicated one like
一样有复杂的 MVC 结构, 也不能像
a graph view. I have to do a simple one. So I'm gonna do
graph view 那样复杂. 只能做个简单的界面了. 所以我也只好
a simple one here. Where I'm gonna put three buttons and
这样了. 之所以我要放三个按钮,
those three buttons are just going to cause three different
是因为要展示三张
images from NASA, okay, about Cassini which is a little
NASA 的图片. 至于 Cassini, 它是被
thing sent out into space to take pictures. I'm gonna put
发送到太空来拍摄图片的. 我会把
those three buttons here and then were just gonna segue,
三个按钮放到这, 然后我们处理 segue,
as we know how to do, down to here,
大家应该知道怎么做. 将 ImageViewController
which is gonna be our ImageViewController,
放到下面来
all right. So the Image View Controller's just gonna show
Image View Controller 会用来显示图片
the image, and we already know that the Image View Controller
我们已经知道展示图片的 Image View Controller 是一个
is a nice, little, reasonable MVC that shows an image.
优雅的, 小巧的, 合理的 MVC 结构.
So it's perfect, exactly what I want. So
如此完美, 正是我们想要的
I'm gonna go down here and get the buttons. So it's this
向下滚动, 找到按钮.
button right here. Let's go ahead and make it bigger,
将按钮放在这. 继续, 把它放大点,
I'll say 40 point would be a pretty good size here.
设置为 40 点看起来比较好
And, make three of them, copy, paste so
然后创建三个这样按钮, 复制, 粘贴
I get that. Okay, one of them is gonna be called Earth,
好了, 一个叫做 Earth
another one is gonna be called Cassini.
一个叫做 Cassini.
And another one is gonna be called Saturn, okay?
剩下的一个叫 Saturn, 好了吗?
And then I'm just gonna take these three things.
然后, 将这三个按钮
Of course it put them in a stack view.
放到 stack view 中
Okay, we'll go ahead and have the stack view be fill.
ok, 将 stack view 对齐方式设置为 fill.
And we'll also do again fill equally.
然后将分布设置为 fill equally.
It doesn't really matter because they're all identical,
这些都无关紧要, 它们都是相同的
they're all buttons. We'll put a little spacing in there,
都是按钮. 然后给它们加一些间隙
maybe. 20 points something like that. Then I'm gonna drag
20 点之类的. 接下来将它拖到
this into the middle use my blue lines right there so that
视图中间, 有蓝色对齐线这里
I can go here and say Reset to suggested constraints.
点击这里, 选择 Reset to suggested constraints (重置为建议约束).
And then I'm gonna go over to my size inspector and
接着看到 size inspector
double check that it did the kind of constraints I want.
再次确认约束是否正确添加
Which that looks good to me it's gonna align these things
看来这些约束能正确将
in the center, okay? So, here's our UI right here.
视图居中, 好了吗? 这就是我们的 UI 了.
Now, all we need to do is have these three things segue down
现在, 就只需要将这三个按钮的事件和下面
to here to fill these images. Now, I'll show you where these
这个关联, 来显示图片了. 之后, 我会展示这些
images come from in a minute here, but let's just create
图片从哪来, 现在先来创建 segue.
the segue. Now, I'm gonna do something a little different
这次我们处理 segue 的方式和之前不一样.
with this segue. In our last one I, each segue had
之前, 每个 segue 都有
its own identifier that was different, and
自己的 identifier, 每一个都不同
it was the identifier that let us know which emotion to
这些 identifier 使我们知道应该
show in the emotions one. Here I'm gonna have them all have
显示哪个表情. 这一次, 它们只有
the same identifier, and I'm gonna use the title of
一个相同的 identifier, 我将使用按钮的 title
the button to decide which image, okay? So it's kind of
来决定显示的图片. 所以,
a cross between what we did in the calculator and
这和我们之前做计算器,
what we did in emotions, all right? So, let's go ahead and
做表情的处理不一样.
create these things. So, I'm gonna, Control drag, okay,
下面我们来创建 segue 吧. 按钮 Contorl 并拖拽,
from Saturn down to here. This is in a split view, right,
从 Saturn 到这里. 他们都在 split view 中.
so I'm gonna do Show Detail, right?
选择 Show Detail.
That's the kind of segue I want, not show. The same thing
这才是我想要的 segue, 而不是 Show.
with Cassini right here, Show Detail. And then up here to
Cassini 也是同样, ShowDetail. 接着是
Earth, Show Detail. Whoops, not Present Modally, undo,
Earch, Show Detail. 噢, 不是 Present Modally, 撤销,
let's try that again. Show Detail. Okay, so
重新来一次, Show Detail.
we've got these three things here. Let's go ahead and
这三个就关联好了. 然后来检查下.
inspect them. I'm gonna put an identifier on them but
我准备给它们设置 identifier, 但
they're all gonna have the same identifier.
它们的 identifier 都相同.
And what that means is when prepareForSegue gets called,
那么, 这在调用 prepareForSegue 时意味着什么呢
it's gonna be called, and the same thing is gonna happen for
调用时, 他们所触发的事件都是相同的.
each one. Again I'm gonna look at the sender in
不过, 可以通过
prepareForSegue to know which button,
prepareForSegue 的 sender 来区别按钮,
but we're gonna use the same code. So I'm gonna call this
但是它们的代码是共用的. 所以, 就命名为
Show Image, cuz that's what it does, okay, when you click On
Show Image 吧, 见名知意.
here to segue, it segues to this image view controller and
点击 Segue, 跳转到 image view controller
shows an image. Okay, so let's make sure all three of
显示图片. 确保三个按钮都
them are doing that. Okay, so everybody cool with this?
设置好. 好了, 大家对这一步有疑问吗?
This is all just review, I haven't done anything new, yet
以上是对之前的回顾，还没添加新的知识点
here. K, now of course we know if we want these
如果想要这些 segue 生效
little segues here to work, we need to prepare them, so
还需要准备 segue
let's go back to our Cassini View Controller right here and
接下来回到 Cassini View Controller，
do our prepare for segue. I'm gonna show you something
准备 segue. 接下来我会演示如何
that's kind of nice to do from a clean coding mechanism,
在用纯代码来实现
which is I like to create a private struct here to
我比较喜欢创建一个私有 struct
store my constants that are strings in the storyboard.
来存放 storyboard 中 string 类型的常量
So I usually call this thing storyboard okay? And then I
所以命名为 storyboard
just put these static lets inside. So the ShowImageSegue
然后将这些静态常量放到 struct 中. ShowImageSegue
= "Show Image". So that this string, and basically any
= "Show Image". 就是这样. 在
string that I put anywhere in my story board, like in these,
storyboard 中的其他 string 也都和这个类似，
when I inspect these things down here like this string.
比如看到的这个下面这个 string
Okay? That's all collected here into this nice struct.
将这些都添加到 struct 中
Okay? So
到此，
we already know that this is what we do to do constants,
我们已经知道怎样处理这些常量了
okay? I'm just calling this group of constants storyboard.
我暂且把这个集合称为 storyboard 常量集吧
They're my storyboard constants, all right?
这就是我的 storyboard 常量集了
All right, so let's do prepare for segue right here.
然后在这里准备 segue
What do we need to do in prepare for segue?
我们需要在 prepareForsSegue 中做哪些处理？
Well first of all, we probably want to make sure that this is
首先，我们要确保 segue 是
the show image segue, so I'm going to say if the segue's
show image segue，所以先进行判断
identifier = the storyboard.ShowImageSegue.
segue 的 identifier 是否等于 Storyboard.ShowImageSegue
Okay? Then we know this is what we're preparing for.
这一步是保证我们处理的是正确的 segue
And remember,
记住，在一个复杂的 app 中，可能会有很多不同的
of segues, like we have in emotions actually, with
segue，就像我们有不同的情绪一样，它们有
different identifiers going off. So that's why we almost
不同的标识. 所以我们
always check the identifier first just to make sure
通常使用 identifier 来确保
that we are doing the right thing, and
处理方式是对的
usually we'll try and spell identifier properly. Okay.
当然，还需要正确的拼写 identifier
So now, we know this is the right segue. We need to get
现在，我们知道这里就是想要的 segue 了. 还需要
the MVC that we're segueing to so we can prepare it.
有一个 MVC 结构来准备 segue
So we know that's supposed to be an Image View Controller so
假设需要的是 Image View Controller
I'm going to say if I can let IVC, short for
所以定义一个叫做 ivc 的常量
Image View Controller,
ImageViewController 的简写
equal the segue's destination view controller as
等于 segue 的 destinationViewController
an image view controller. Okay.
转换为 ImageViewController
So if I, I don't even need the parentheses there, sorry. So
这里不需要大括号，不好意思
if I can get that destination view controller as an image
如果能正确将 destinationViewController 转为
view controller then now I'm ready to prepare this thing.
ImageViewController，那么就可以开始做一些准备了
So, how do I need to prepare it? Well,
怎样去准备呢？
it depends on which button Is doing this show image, okay.
这要取决于哪个按钮触发显示图片事件
So, I'm actually gonna look back at the button. Now,
所以，回头看看这些按钮
here's the button. Remember it prepares for segue.
这个参数就是按钮，并且是谁触发的 segue，
The sender is the button or the line in a table or
那这个 sender 就是谁，可能是按钮或者 table 的某一行
something like that that caused it to happen.
或者其他触发事件的对象
So, I need to convert this into a button. So
所以，我需要将它强转为 button
I could actually do this like this. I could say, if I can
我可以这样做，如果 sender
let the sending button equal the sender as a UI button,
是 UIButton，并解包给 sendingButton 不为空
then I can go forward here and say let's let the image name,
那么就可以定义一个 imageName
that's the name of the image we wanna show,
代表我们想要显示的图片名称
equal the sending button's current title. Oops,
并将 sendingButton 的当前图片，哦，不
not current image, current title. All right, so
当前标题.
this'll be one way to do this,
这是一种处理方式
okay, but kind of a cool way here is, this is this, right?
但是还有一种更好的方法，看这个和这个
So what if I took this, cut and
如果我将这个
put it in here like that. Okay, so
剪切到这里
I don't need this except for this is If, let. So, if I put
那就不再需要这个 if let 了，但如果
this in here, this is going to be an optional. I can't send
将它放到这里，那这就会是个可选值，不能从可选值
current title to an optional. So, how can I deal with that?
中直接访问 currentTitle 属性. 该怎么办呢？
Let's use optional chaining. Okay? So it's perfectly legal
让我们试试可选链. 在表达式返回可选值的时候
to use the optional chaining stuff on the end of some,
使用可选链来操作
some other expression that returns a possible optional.
是完全合法的
And remember, if this is nil right here,
如果这里是 nil
then this whole thing's just gonna be ignored.
那么之后的都会被忽略
That's what the question mark means, it means if it's nil,
这个问号就是表示可能为 nil
nil then just return nil and ignore it.
遇到 nil 会返回 nil，然后忽略掉
That means imageName is gonna be returned to nil. Okay.
也就是说 imageName 可能为 nil
See how I did that? This cleans up our code a little
接下来做什么呢？先把代码
bit, to do that. Less if then, if thens and
整理一下. 减少分支语句
all that, business around there. Okay? Now I'm going
接下来，要根据
to go get the image that goes with this button's title.
按钮的 title 来获取图片
Now let me show you how we're gonna do that.
让我来演示一下
This DemoURL class, remember the one that had that little
这个 DemoURL 类，有一个 Stanford 的 URL
Stanford URL in there? Well it also had these NASA URLs,
还有 NASA 的 URL
one for Cassini, one for Earth, and one for Saturn.
里面包含 Cassini，Earth 和 Saturn
Those are the three buttons we have. And
对应着我们的三个按钮
I have a little function right here that just gets the name
这还有个简单的方法，接收图片名称
of the image and looks it up in that dictionary right here,
然后在字典中查找
okay, and returns it. So this a little function called
并返回，所以这个方法叫
NASA Image Named. So let's use this NASA Image Named.
NASAImageNamed. 来调用下这个方法
I'm just gonna say right here that the IVC's image URL
在这里写 ivc 的 imageURL
equals the NASAImageNamed this imageName. Okay?
等于 NASAImageNamed 的这个 imageNames
This thing I got right here. >> [COUGH]
就这样
>> All right.
能跟上吗
And then, oops, sorry, this has gotta be DemoURL.,
接下来，哦，不好意思，要加上 DemoURL.
because it's over here in this DemoURL.
因为这个方法在 DemoURL 中
Notice this is a static function, right?
注意这是个静态方法
NASAImageNamed is static function.
NASAImageNamed 是个静态方法
So, we send it to the class DemoURL, that's why I had to
所以应该用 DemoURL 类来调用，所以
put DemoURL here. Okay, just kind of a utility function for
应该加上 DemoURL. 这只是 DemoURL 中
that little DemoURL class. And while we're at it,
的一个工具方法而已. 接下来，
you know what, let's set the title of that MVC to be that
将 MVC 结构的 title 设置为
image name as well. So that way we'll Earth or Cassini or
图片名字吧. 这样 MVC 的 title 会是 Earth 或 Cassini
whatever as the title of that MVC. Okay so this make sense?
或者其他的名字. 这就是这段代码的作用
Everybody okay now? Let's go ahead and run this and
都能跟上吗？运行程序
see if this is working. Here we go.
看看效果
Okay, there we go. So here's Cassini right here, and
运行起来了，这是 Cassini，
if I click Earth, okay, whoa. So it worked. I clicked Earth
如果我点击 Earth，有点击效果. 点击了 Earth
but nothing's happening in my app. Wait, no there,
但是 app 却没做出响应. 等下，不对啊
it's showing Stanford. Why is is showing Stanford here?
这展示的是斯坦福，为什么会这样？
Well, that's because our nice reusable image view controller
那是因为我们重用的 ImageViewController
we have over here, it's view did load smashes Stanford on
的 viewDidLoad 方法中，将斯坦福盖在了
top of everything. So, that we only put that in there as
所有视图的顶部. 这只是之前的 demo
a demo. Right, so I'm taking that out, sorry about that.
把它提出来，不好意思
Makes everyone see what happened there. So
现在来看看都发生了什么
now let's go back here. It won't be slamming a Stanford
重新运行一次，这下我们的重用 ImageViewController
in there in our reusable image view controller. Okay? So
应该不会被斯坦福盖住了
now we'll go back to Cassini. We'll pick Earth this time.
回到 Cassini 界面，选择 Earth
Again it seems like it's kinda stuck. I can't click on any of
these buttons. I can't, actually I can't do anything.
There it is. Okay. So that must have been a really big
image. It took a very long time to load and here it is.
It doesn't really look like Earth, but
pictures of people on Earth, hm. That's interesting.,
Let's try one of these others. Let's try Cassini here. Okay,
what happening? This is, basically, just blank.
What's going on here? How about Saturn? Again,
taking a really long time, you can see why we're gonna talk
about multi-threading a little later. Okay, and here it is,
okay that's not good either. All right, so
we gotta start here. We know the Cassini's not working.
It comes up blank. So why might Cassini not be working.
Let's go back here and check for example to make sure that
our segue is good. Okay, the Earth's segue. Here's
the Cassini segue. Let';s go look at its identifier.
Look at that. This Cassini identifier, no identifier.
So let's put show image in here. Okay?
So when you have a segue and it doesn't seem to be working,
like it segues to the new MVC but
the prepared doesn't happen, often you want to go back and
look at your identifier, make sure it's set properly or
set in there. Okay, so now, if we go back here.
All right, we have Cassini here. Let's click on it.
Again, it's loading. That one must be a smaller image.
It loaded pretty quick. And here it is.
It looks like it's just a bunch of outer space. Okay, so
we've got a problem here,
which is that these images that I loaded are huge. That's
created two problems for us. One, our app get's blocked.
See I can't click on anything else. I can't even rotate or
anything here. My app is just completely stuck.
You never want your app in that circumstance.
Never should your app be stuck like that. Users will just,
basically, double click on the home button and
kill your app and never run it again.
They'll think your app is totally hosed. And it is,
if it behaves that way, okay, so we really need to fix that.
The other thing is, this image is so
huge that we can't really see it. So we'd like to be able to
zoom in on it, right. So let's go ahead and
do the zooming, okay? How do we do the zooming in our,
back here in our image view controller, right?
So our image view controller has this scroll view,
right? That we dragged into the storyboard. It's got this
image view as the subview of the scroll view. Okay, and
we set our content size, so it's working nicely. And
we know from the slides last time that
to make zooming work. Okay, we need to set some other things.
What are some of the things we need to do? Well,
the most important thing is we need to set ourselves
as the scrollView's delegate. Okay, so
this is the first time you're seeing delegation demoed here.
And the way we do that,
I'd probably do it here in my scrollView didSet here, right?
The didSet for my scrollView. Probably just say that Mr.
scrollView, please set your delegate to be self. In other
words, send me any questions you have about how to operate.
Now when I put that in there I have a error,
anyone guess what this error is? Okay,
it's going to say that these types, this and
this do not match. Okay, and why is that? The type of this
is, well the type of this, not showing, but the type of this
is UI scrollView delegate. Which is a protocol, okay.
The type of this is UI or image view controller.
That's its type. Those don't match. Okay, so
that's why this says cannot assign value of type image
view controller to UI scroll view delegate, optional.
Okay, so we need to say that this image view controller is
a UI scroll view delegate. And we do that by just putting
that right after our super class there, a little comma,
UIScrollViewDelegate, and that says we are scroll view
delegate, and all of a sudden this works.
Now UIScrollViewDelegate has no methods or
vars in there that are not optional. In other words
they're all optional, so we've successfully implemented so
the compiler's not complaining. Okay,
cuz none of them are required. But, we still wanna implement
one, that zooming one, which is called
viewForZoomingInScrollView. Now, one
thing that's cool is once you say that you're a ScrollView
delegate, look what happens when I start typing view
in Xcode. It knows I'm a ScrollView delegate, so
the very first thing it offers me is viewForScroll,
ScrollingInScrollView. For
zooming in scrollView. Right? So that's kind of cool. And
what view, which of the scrollView subviews do we want
to zoom in on? Well, of course, the image view. This
is our image view right here that we store our image in.
That's of course the thing we want
to have its transform modified when we pinch in there. Okay?
Now you might think okay, that's good.
Got it all ready to go. Let's go start zooming, and
we'll go over here. Let's get Cassini, kinda small.
Let's start zooming. Now how do I zoom? It's with Pinch, so
I'm gonna hold down the Option key right here and
start pinching. And it's not working.
It's not doing anything. Okay, I can still scroll but
I can't zoom in. Anyone know why? Say
it louder. I think I might have heard it back there.
Yeah, this right now, our scrollView by default,
it's maximum zoom and its minimum zoom is 1.0.
So it is zooming to the maximum,
minimum extent we allow which is none, 1.0. So
we need to set the maximum and minimum scrolling factor or
zooming factor on this scrollView. So let's do that.
Let's do that also right here when we're setting our
scrollView from our storyboard. So
we just say that the scrollView's minimum zoom
scale. I'm gonna have this minimum zoom scale.
What did I think that worked well here? 0.03.
So we're gonna zoom- allowed to zoom way out.
So it will make the image really small, okay?
Three one-hundredths of it's size.
3% of its size. And then the maximum,
it is perfectly fine for us to say the maximum is 1.0.
Maybe we never want the thing to be zoomed out any bigger
than it already is, especially there are huge images already.
So we can set the maximum to zoom scale. We don't even need
to put this. Cuz by default, it's 1.0. But we'll put it
in here just to kinda be very clear about what we're doing.
All right, so now lets try it. All right,
so lets go get Cassini right here. All right, here it is.
Lets zoom in on it, right. I'm pinching. Yeah, look at that,
it's zooming. And sure enough, look,
there's Cassini. Taking a little trip by Saturn, okay,
let's zip it around here so we can see a little better. Okay,
how about some of these other images, go look at the Earth,
didn't look like much like Earth. Now if we zoom,
we'll see something here. All right, so here it is,
scrolling around, I'm gonna pinch, pinch some more.
Look at this Earth, okay? Same thing with Saturn.
Okay, everyone see what we do with the zooming?
Zooming quite simple
in terms of the code you have to write, but
you have to understand that delegation piece for
it to really, to make it work. And you'll see Saturn,
there's Saturn. Okay? Now let's try this on iPad,
okay? Let's see what it looks like here.
All right, so here is our master and
our detail right here. So if I click on Cassini,
hopefully Cassini will eventually really slow,
appear right here. Okay? And we can zoom in here, okay?
Now, what would be really cool here is if we could have
a title up here that said this was Cassini,
or Earth, or Saturn, right? So remember
the tricky way we did that, is we went to our storyboard, and
we just put this one down here. Also in the scrollView.
So we said embed in navigation control.
Or not in a scrollView, in a navigation controller. So
I embed it in there, so that now I have a title. Right? And
we know that if we can go and
run this, it's not going to work, right? Because these
segues are segueing now to a navigation controller. And
so our prepare is not gonna work,
cuz this line of code is going to fail. Right,
because the destination view controller is now a navigation
controller. Of course,
a navigation controller is not an image view controller.
This is the exact same problem we had before. So
I'm gonna show you now how to use that extensions mechanism
to fix this. So I'm gonna create an extension. This is
exactly what I did in the slides of UIViewController.
Okay, and in this extension, like to scroll up a little so
you can see it better. Okay, inside this extension,
I'm gonna add the var contentViewController.
Which is a UIViewController, okay?
I'm adding this var to the class UIViewController.
So, all UIViewControllers will now respond to this property
contentViewController. Okay? It's gonna be get only.
It's gonna get it. And what I'm gonna put in here is
basically that same code I had in prepareforSegue,
in a motionview controller. I'm gonna say,
if I can let navcon = self as a UINavigationController,
so in otherwords, if I am a navigation controller,
then return navcon.visibleViewController.
Okay? The only problem with this is this is
an optional view controller, because the navigation
controller might not have anything showing. Okay, so
I need to return something because contentViewController
does not return an optional So I'm gonna use this
defaulting to say if I have a NavigationController and
it has no visible ViewController, just return
self, which is to say the NavigationController itself,
okay? Otherwise, we can just return self. So if it's not
a NavigationController, then the content is myself.
Everyone understand that code right there? Okay? Good.
So, now that we have this, we can just use that method right
here. Okay? Instead of asking if the destination can view
controller is an image view controller, I'm gonna ask if
the destination controller's content view controller, and
I can escape complete, cuz now that's a method on U, I,
this is a UI view controller. This is a method on UI view
controller. I'm just gonna ask if the content view controller
is an image view controller. Okay? So now we should be able
to run an iPad and get some nice titles. All right.
Cassini again. We've got the navigation controller up here.
There's Cassini. Sure enough, there's the title, right.
We set the title right here. Ivc.title = imageName, okay?
And of course, we can zoom around, okay?
All right, any questions about that before I go back to
the slides? All right. Let's hit the slides here.
Okay, so now we're gonna talk about multithreading, so
we can fix that problem where our Cassini app,
when we click on the big image, it just froze. Okay.
When you build an app, never have it freeze like that ever.
In fact, if it freezes like that, probably you won't get
through the app store approval process. Okay. So the only
way to stop it from freezing is to use multithreading.
Okay. So, multithreading just means we're going to
have different threads of execution,
okay? Different places in, in our iPhone or
our iPad where code is running, okay?
And these, these appear to run simultaneously, but
it'll even work on a single core processor, okay,
not a multiprocessor. It works, then, by timesharing.
Okay. And so you got one thing running,
another thing running and it's kinda going back and
forth. Letting them each run a little bit and maybe if one of
them's more important than the other, it gets run a lot and
the other one doesn't get to run so much. Okay? But
that's basically what multithreading is all about.
So how many people have,
have done any multithreading programming of any kind? Okay,
so some of you have, okay. About a little less than half
of you. Okay, good. So in iOS multithreading is about
queues, okay? Queue meaning like, if you go to the movies
maybe in England [LAUGH] they would say, well,
get in the queue, meaning the line to get into the movie,
okay? So same thing here, and it's the same thing as queue
in the computer science sense, right? A queue is a thing,
a bunch of things lined up to do something.
All right. And these queues contained an iOS functions.
Okay? Most of the time these functions are closures. Okay?
That you've put in there. Okay? Blocks of code that you
put in this queue. Okay? And then, the system simply runs
along this queue, pulls the next thing off the queue and
starts it running in a separate thread, okay?
And you can have multiple of these queues and the system is
pulling them off each one and running them un, in their
own threads, simple as that, you just got multithreading.
Okay. Now there's a little bit of trickiness
here of what are these queues and
how do you put things on the queues, but
that's the fundamental way these work. Now queues can
either be serial, which means the function that's on the top
of the queue gets pulled off, it runs to completion, and
then the next one gets pulled off. That's serial queues. Or
they can be concurrent, where the system pulls the top
one off the queue, starts it running in a thread. If it's
got more thread resources, it takes the next one off,
starts it running in another thread while the first one's
still running, and
it might keep pulling a whole bunch of them off. Okay, so
that's a concurrent queue.
All right, so let's talk about the queues, how we get them,
what, what we call them, etc. The most important queue,
it's a serial queue called the main queue, okay?
The main queue is where all UI activity has to happen. And
this is super important for you to understand. That if you
want to do anything where you call something a UI kit, okay,
UI button, UI anything, all right,
with a couple of exceptions which I'll talk about later.
You need to be making those calls on the main queue.
In other words, you can't put those calls in a closure that
you put on some other queue. Okay, it has to be on the main
queue, all right? Now conversely, all non-UI
activity that's gonna take any amount of time or resources,
probably wants to be off the main queue. So it never blocks
the main queue. We want the main queue reserved for
doing our UI stuff as much as possible. Okay, now this is
not only cuz we want our main queue UI to be responsive,
okay, that's the main reason, but
also it serializes the activity on the main queue so
that our UI is presented in an orderly fashion. If,
if we allowed our UI to be on all these different queues, it
could, things would be drawing at all different rates and
overlapping, it would be
unpredictable as to what happened on screen. Okay, so
we use the main queue as kind of a synchronization point
where everybody comes back to draw on the main queue,
all right? Now the main queue can only pull a closure or
a function off of the main queue and
work on it when it's quiet. In other words,
it's not off doing something else, like drawing or
something like, like that. Now the system is using the main
queue behind the scenes all the time.
For example, you know about draw req. Right.
I told you draw req gets called by the system and
it doesn't get called, you don't call it,
you don't tell it to, you just set needs display.
Well, you set needs display and
as soon as the main queue gets quiet, it goes and runs some
function that causes that draw req to be called. So
you see how that works, okay? So that's what's going on in
the main queue. What about other queues? Okay, so
there's, I'm, in the next slide I'm gonna talk about
two different kinds of other queues that you can use to run
all your non-UI stuff. All right? So the first,
not gonna talk about this now, that'll be on the next slide.
So on this slide I'm gonna talk a little bit about how we
put something on a queue and the main way we do it is
with this function right here called dispatc_async.
Dispatc_async takes two arguments. One is the queue to
put it on, like the main queue or one of these other queues,
and the second argument is the function to put on the queue,
again, usually it's a closure. You see how I'm using trailing
closure syntax right there? Okay. This is two arguments.
One argument. Two arguments. So this is the closure you're
gonna put on there. What's cool about these closures,
they take no arguments and then return no arguments.
So they're really easy to, to [LAUGH] put into your code.
Okay? And you can put anything you want in here. Okay?
But if this gonna do UI, you better not put it on anything
but the main queue. All right, so how do you get the queue?
How do you get this little queue argument?
Well, for the main queue, you call this function,
dispatc_ge_mai_queue. Now, you might ask,
why is all these underbars and why does this look like this?
This is basically a CAPI, okay, from iOS before Swift,
and so it comes into swift looking like a CAPI.
These are Swift, these are just Swift global functions.
But the reason this is not object oriented, for
example is because this is a CAPI.
This, this is called grand central dispatch actually,
that's why they all start with dispatch,
all this multithreading stuff, and that's why it looks like
this. I'm gonna show you the object-oriented way to do
this in a minute, but actually we're gonna end up using these
C-like ones more often, all right? So, again, all UI stuff
have to be on this main queue. It's a serial queue, okay, so
nothing happens concurrently on this queue,
things happen in order in the order they go in, okay?
And, but all time-consuming stuff,
okay, or even worse stuff that might block,
like you're going out to the network to get an image,
like we are doing where that block's waiting for
the Web server on the other side to respond,
all that wants to happen off the main queue.
Now you still dispatch to that queue using dispatc_async.
You go down here and you say look at the bottom,
it says dispatc_async, not the main queue in here.
And I'll talk about where you get that queue in a second.
And then open curly brace,
so this is a closure, inside that closure you do the non-UI
thing that takes a long time or blocks. And then still
inside this closure, you dispatc_async again. This
time back to the main queue to do the UI stuff that you need,
maybe that the image you got from doing this, you now put
this in the UI here. So look how I'm dispatching within
a closure. So can you imagine this outer closure
is off running on some other thread in some other queue and
in the middle of it, it puts a block of code,
this block right here,
this closure. It puts it back on the main queue, this one
continues to run after that in fact dispatc_async,
that function always returns immediately. Because all it
does is put things on queues, it doesn't actually execute
any of the code inside the block.
It just puts that block of code onto the queue. Okay, and
then this outer closure just happily runs to completion and
it's done. Meanwhile, that inner block has been posted
on the main queue and it's just waiting for
the main queue, for it to be first in line and
for the main queue to be quiet, and
then it'll pick it up and run it. You got it? So this is why
we use the C function notation because it reads really cool,
okay? Dispatch off the queue this, then dispatch the main
queue this, okay? It reads very clearly to the person
who's reading your code what you intend. Okay, but
you do have to remember that this is async,
it's out of sync. Just because you say to execute this code,
it's not gonna happen right away.
It's just being put on that queue, it'll happen sometime
in the future when that queue is ready, okay? When it rises
to the top of that queue and the main queue is quiet, okay?
So how do we get these not the main queue queues?
Okay, that we want to run something else on.
Well there's really two ways to do it.
The most common way is to use one of the concurrent queues
provided by the system, okay? Now these
queues provided by the system there's four of them, okay?
They each have what's called a quality of service and
the quality of service is really how
much attention the system gives to them.
You can think of it as their priority. High-priority queues
get a high quality of service. They get serviced a lot, okay?
But it's not purely that, but it's generally that. So
what are the four qualities of service here?
One is USE_INTERACTIVE. So, you can get a queue, you
can call this dispatch, get global queue right here. And
you can say give me the user interactive queue. Again, it's
a concurrent queue, so it's doing things concurrently,
it's not serial. And user interactive means
the user just asked to do something.
It's gonna take a little bit of time,
so I don't want to do it on the main queue,
but I need this done as soon as possible because the user
is interacting with me right now, okay?
So, this is very high priority, but
lower priority than the main queue, okay? So, this might be
something where the user is dragging with their finger,
and you're having to calculate something to make the image
that's pretty intensive, time wise, and so
you put it off on the thread. The user continues to drag,
they're not seeing the result and
then the result comes back in and
then the user gets to see the result. So
the results a little bit behind their finger,
because it takes so much time, but
at least as their finger tracks the main queue is still
listening to their finger, okay, and responding, okay?
So that's what USE_INTERACTIVE is for.
USE_INITIATED means the user just asked me to do this, but
it's not in the middle of an interactive event so, you can
take a little bit of time but get back to me right away,
cuz the user just asked for this, right now, okay?
So, that's lower priority, than an interactive thing.
UTILITY is something that usually runs in the background
for a long time, okay? Maybe it's fetching data.
It's cleaning up some database somewhere. It's doing
something that the user didn't ask to do, but that needs to
be done for this program. It's that kind of thing. And
then BACKGROUND is even lower priority. This is the kind of
thing well it could run today or tomorrow. But you know,
it's really not something that I need done right away,
I don't really care. So, it's kind of just a,
something that runs along in the background.
It's only gonna happen when things are really quiet,
when nobody wants any other service, okay? So, you get one
of these four queues by saying dispatc_ge_globa_queue,
you specify which one you want. Then this has this
extra argument ,0 which is reserved for future use, so
you just always put ,0 there.
And that's gonna give you back a queue, a dispatc_queu_t
that you can then use as your first argument to dispatch
async, okay. So these are the, this is the cues,
these are the cues you're most often going to
put this work that needs to be done in the background onto.
Now, its also possible for you to create your own
serial queue. You call dispatc_queu_create.
You give it a name. This can be any name you want, okay?
This is usually just so you can see it in the debugger,
okay, this name is gonna appear in the debugger.
And then you say DISPATC_QUEU_SERIAL,
saying you want a serial queue.
Now you will get a serial queue of your own.
And it's gonna be a pretty high priority queue,
nothing like the main queue, but pretty high priority.
Why would you ever want a serial queue?
Let's say you had a big table that you wanna download
a thousand images to put in that table.
Small little images, okay? Well you could do it on
one of these user initiated queues or something like that.
But it's gonna fork off a whole bunch of threads and
try to download as many as it can concurrently.
Open a whole bunch of network connections.
Whereas if you do is serially it will do it one by one,
okay? So it kind of throttles, it's a throttling,
a way of throttling your access to the network,
all right? You usually don't need this.
These are usually what you're gonna use for that not main
queue queue, okay? Now, we're only seeing the absolute
tip of the iceberg on multithreading here,
okay? There's a lot more to GCD, Grand Central Dispatch.
You can look in the documentation for
all the functions that start with dispatch underbar and
you'll get an idea, there's at least a couple dozen in there.
I don't have time to cover it in this class.
You won't need it,
you won't need anything more than I just showed you for
the work that you're gonna be doing in your assignments.
In your final project, you probably also won't need
anymore than that, but at least you know where to look,
if you might need more. There is an object-oriented
way of doing all this called, there's two classes,
NSOperationQueue, which is kind of like dispatch queues.
And NSOperation, which is kinda like those closures,
right, those little functions. Why would you ever want this?
These do have a little bit of extra functionality,
that they wrap from GCD, things like, hey,
I have these two operations and
this one depends on this one finishing, okay. And so
I'm gonna put them in a concurrent queue, but
don't let this other one go until the first one finishes,
right. So dependencies, you can have dependencies and
things like that. We're not gonna talk about that.
You can look at the documentation if you want.
You can do, I think almost everything here with GCD.
This would be more if you actually are building
something where there's queue are doing queues and
these operations are doing the actual calculation. Like as
your model is doing, you're doing some scientific app and
it's actually doing all this complex calculation where
things depend on each other and all that stuff.
And so it has a lot of queues and a lot of operations going.
You wouldn't use it as much for things like, I'm fetching
something from the network and I need to put it in the UI,
and I want that fetched to happen in another queue.
That kind of stuff you're just going to use the dispatch
underbar, okay. Now, in addition to dispatch underbar,
you have to understand multithreading from
the perspective of how iOS's API uses it.
Because there are plenty of methods all throughout
iOS that do what they do asynchronously, using threads.
Okay? And the way you see this in the API, is that one of
the arguments to these methods is a block, is a closure,
right? It's gonna be a closure you provide, and
the documentation for that function will say your
closure's executed off the main cue, asynchronously.
So what kind of methods are we talking about here that do
that? Here's one that goes and fetches a URL. Okay,
from the internet. Downloads it from the internet. And
when it, and it does it asynchronously obviously.
You wouldn't wanna block the main queue waiting for
this URL to load. And when it comes back,
it calls this closure right here, okay? Now
inside this closure, you might want to do some UI things.
Like maybe you downloaded an image and you wanna put it.
But you can't put that code right inside here.
Because this closure is executed on a different
thread and on a different queue than the main queue. So
what you would have to do in here is the same thing
you have to do with the dispatc_async,
which is you have to wrap dispatc_async ge_mai_queue
around it, okay? So here's the method. This is an iOS method
downloadTaskWithRequest. It takes this last argument,
which is a closure. And inside there you're gonna have to
do this dispatch to the main queue. Because if you wanna do
something to the UI, because this is not happening,
this closure will not be executed on the main queue.
Got it? So we will talk a little bit about, you're just
gonna run into occasional iOS APIs that take these closures,
and they're asynchronous. And you just have to know that if
you wanna do anything in the UI, you're gonna have
to dispatch async back to the main queue. All right, so
let's do a demo of this where let's fix Cassini.
Okay, let's make Cassini so that it's UI's always
responsive even while it's off downloading these things.
All right lets go over here.
Okay, all this is gonna be, all this code that we're going
to have to do is going to be in our ImageViewController.
We're going to make our ImageViewController, so
that it is asynchronous, right? That it can load things
asynchronously. Before I do that actually though,
I wanna talk one other thing we should be doing here,
probably, in ImageViewController.
Notice that if someone sets our model, we immediately go
off and fetch it, okay? Now what if we never appeared on
screen? Okay, what if this or something that's in a,
gonna be in a navigation controller, it got created,
but no one ever clicked to cause it to happen on screen,
but someone set our model.
Then this wouldn't happen in Cassini, this app, but imagine
an app where you've got this image MVC and some incentive.
Really we really wouldn't want to do this
fetch cuz it could be very expensive as we've seen,
right? It goes on the network,
it's pulling down this thing if I'm paying for
cellular data, it's costing me money! Okay,
to get that Cassini image, so I probably don't want to do
this fetch image unless I'm on screen. If I'm on screen,
I definitely want to do this. So here I'm going to say how
can I tell if I'm on screen? If my view, okay,
this is my MVC's view the top level, if it's window
is not nil. Okay, that's a pretty reliable way to tell,
sorry, that you are on screen, right? Because your view,
your nbc's view will not be in a window unless it's on
screen. Make sense? We haven't talked about window much.
It's that UI Window class I told you that you really never
use it, and you don't.
You're not going to send any messages to it here. But
whether it's nil or
not will tell you whether your view is on screen.
Now what happens though if someone sets my image URL like
in a prepare for segue and then I do go on screen later?
Now I have to fetch that image, okay? Cuz now I
am going to go on screen. So how can I find out in my view
controller lifecycle that now I'm gonna go on screen,
which method? Which method in my view controller lifecycle?
Do you remember? It called. I'll put it down here
next to this viewDidLoad one. ViewWillAppear. Okay, so
viewWillAppear is sent to you when you're about to appear on
screen. Okay and we always do super.viewWillAppear in
all these view controller life cycles, all right. So,
here I'm going to say if my image is nil,
then I better go fetch it, okay? So, this is one
thing I've done to increase my performance a little bit. But
it's still not going to stop things from blocking,
because as soon as viewWillAppear happens,
and I'm just about to go on screen,
my whole app is going to freeze while I'm out fetching.
Those big huge images, right?
So I haven't really fixed the problem. I need multithreading
for that. But I just wanted to show you to be a little bit
careful about when you fire off an expensive operation.
That's what viewWillAppare, Appear is for.
That's really where you wanna fire off things like going
out on the network and stuff, okay? All right, so now let's
do our multi guiding and fix this. We're gonna do this here
in fetchImage. We're gonna make it so that fetchImage
does the actual fetching in another thread. All right, so
how are we gonna do this? It's pretty simple actually.
We're just going to take this code right here which blocks.
This blocks the main queue while it goes out
on the network, to forget the contents of this URL.
And we're going to use the GCD to
put it on a different thread, okay? So I'm just going to
say, dispatch, async, okay? Remember, dispatch async
takes two arguments. A queue and a block here, a closure or
a function do that. So I'm going to put on one of those,
concurrent cues. And I'm gonna put it on the one where
the user initiated it but it's not interactive.
The user's not in the middle of dragging or something.
They initiated it so it's pretty high priority and
so I get that by saying dispatc_ge_globa_queue and
the one I want is
QO_CLASS USE_INITIATED. This one right here, okay?
This flags is always zero, right? And now I have this
block here, so I'm gonna double-click on that.
It's really nice, by the way,
you can double-click on these things to expand the block.
I'm gonna use the clay trailing,
closure syntax here. Okay for my block, this block, you'll
notice it takes no arguments, returns no arguments.
I'm just going to put all this blocking junk inside here,
okay. So this is going to fix my problem, okay.
Except that it probably gonna make my app go all strange
because I'm gonna be trying to do this inside
a non-main queue. All right, cuz this queue, this block
right here is gonna be put on this queue, and so I can't do
this inside of here. Question? >> Can you explain
the trailing, the plot,
the trailing plot where you added the parenthesis and
what it does? >> Yeah, okay, so
this used to look like this. Okay, so this is normal.
I'm calling this function right here, okay? Sorry,
this function right here. Here is its first arguments,
see that? Here its second argument, okay.
If the sec, if the last argument of any function is
a closure, then you can put it outside of the parenthesis.
See this dispatc_async parentheses starts here? So
I just took this parentheses off of here and
I put it over here. Okay, so now this is the first
argument to this function, inside these parenthesis. And
here's the closure which is outside the parenthesis, okay.
You definitely wanna get used to that cuz we're almost
always gonna do it that way. And when people design APIs
they almost always put the closure at the end so
people can do this. All right, so
what am I gonna do about this,
okay? I need this to be back on the main queue. Well,
very simple here. I'm just going to dispatch it back to
the main queue. Now, another thing I'm gonna do here,
while I'm kinda at it is, let's get this NS data right
here. I'm gonna assign that to a local variable
here called content of URL, okay? And then I'm gonna put,
so that's gonna be happening in my other queue.
And then I'm gonna dispatch async back to the main queue,
which I get by dispatc_ge_mai_queue.
Okay, same exact thing here, okay, here's the block,
I'm gonna do the same thing. Click trailing, close your
notation, and now I'm gonna put this inside here, okay.
But now the image data is this thing that I got right there,
so that's content of URL.
Okay, now this happening on the main queue, all is well.
This image=UIImage, the UI kit thing. This is a UI kit thing,
by the way, no, not actually because of the UIImage.
That is the one UI thing you can do on a different thread.
But it's because when we say image= down here,
it's gonna do something like imageview.image=new value.
Okay, well that's the UI kit right there, so
that has to be on the main thread. So that's why I have
to do that. Now notice we still have an error here.
Anyone know what this error is? It's pointing right here.
What do you think it wants there? No idea?
It wants self there, because this is a closure. Okay,
this is inside a closure. And remember,
whenever we have a closure and we use a property on our
object, we need to put self in there to make it
clear that we understand this is being captured and
kept in the heap. So as long as this closure right here,
which it's got this closure inside of it.
As long as this is out there fetching,
it's going to keep this view controller in the heap, okay?
Now if we wanted to here, we could do the week self thing
and have week self question mark and that way if the image
came back and our MVC had been thrown out of the heap,
it would be fine, we would just ignore it.
Okay, but I'm pressed for time so I'm not gonna do that but
you could hopefully imagine doing that. Okay, so
everyone see what we've done here?
So that's really all we need to do. One thing that it's
a little, now, I told you that multithreading, it's pretty
easy to read this code and understand what's going on.
But you've got to think of the bigger picture of what's
happening with multithreading here. For example,
what happens in Cassini if I click on the Cassini,
which is a kind of a small image, and
then I change my mind and click on Earth.
Okay, so Cassini, which is small, comes back, okay?
This code is gonna put Cassini on screen. But then the Earth
is gonna come back and this code's gonna put the Earth on
top of it, okay? So I'm gonna get this flashing thing,
Cassini, Earth. Or worse, if I clicked Earth first and
then clicked Cassini, it would show Cassini and
then later Earth would come in and it would be showing Earth,
even though I clicked on Cassini.
Okay, do you see the problem, is that I'm firing off these
network things in other threads.
They're coming back at different times. So
really I want to,
If I'm gonna be a good programmer here,
multithreaded, I need to check and
make sure that the URL that I'm fetching,
that's this URL right here, is still equal to the image URL
that I ask for. Okay, then I'll do this. If it's not,
then maybe I could print something like ignored data
returned from URL, and then we'll put the URL in here,
okay? And that needs self here, of course, cuz that's
inside this closure as well, all right? Everybody got that?
So let's go ahead and run, see if this works. So
what we should have now is a very responsive UI, okay,
all the time, no matter what we click on, so let's try it.
Earth, Cassini, see I'm able to click on different things.
I can still rotate, okay. Whoops, wrong way around. And,
the it's gonna pick whichever the last one that I asked for.
It's still fetching right here. It's gonna eventually,
hopefully, get one. And maybe it's even easier to see this,
maybe. Let's stop this action, go look on our iPhone, cuz you
can really see it happening on iPhone because when we click
on them, it actually segues and comes back.
So watch this. Are we running here?
Oops, no, we want iPhone.
Okay, so we go back here. Now I click Cassini,
it's loading it, but I can go back, okay.
While this is still loading, I can go back and
change my mind because my UI is highly responsive,
even though it's loading those things in the background.
When they eventually arrive, it's gonna put them in the UI,
okay. But while they're out there fetching I can do things
like go back in my navigation controller. Make sense,
see that? >> [INAUDIBLE]
>> What happens, what?
>> [INAUDIBLE] Image each time
you click out. >> So the question is, if I
click out, and then click back in, does it reload the image?
And the answer is absolutely, because when I click out,
it throws that NBC out of the heap. Okay, it's gone.
Now actually, that NBC is not gonna immediately leave
the heap, cuz that closure that's doing the fetching is
still holding it in the heap. But once that fetch comes
back, then it'll leave the heap and the image with it. So
yeah, every time we're re-fetching, okay?
So see how we built this nice responsive UI right now, okay?
Everybody got that?
Even though it's still taking a long time to fetch things,
we can still navigate. Now, what's a little weird about
this UI, though, is that while it's fetching,
like when I'm here, it's not clear what's going on.
It looks like there's just no Earth image,
I guess. I don't know, I guess not, I don't see it. Wouldn't
it be cool if we could give some feedback to the user?
Hey, I'm working on it, okay, this image is big.
All right, and we can do that.
And the cool way to do that is with a little spinner, okay,
a little animating. You see them all in apps little thing
that spins around basically telling him yeah, yeah,
I know, I'm working on it. So let's put a spinner in there.
Turns out to be really easy to put, do spinners in iOS.
We're just gonna go to the storyboard, okay.
I'm gonna put the spinner here in this view. Now when I put
it in there, I'm gonna have to be very careful.
And this is a good chance for
me to show you more about the document outline. But
watch this, so I'm gonna go down here. The spinner is just
a thing you can drag out. You see it right here.
Now watch what happens when I drag this out, okay, and
I try to use the blue lines to put it in the middle, drop it.
It looks like, okay, that worked, that's nice.
I can even go here and inspect it up here.
You see, I can make a nice larger one. Maybe I'll even
make it blue instead of white. Let's have it hide itself
when it stops animating.
We can do all kinds of cool stuff here. But
actually something terrible has happened,
which is that when I dragged that thing out and
dropped it in the middle there,
it made it a subview of the Scroll View, okay?
In the interface builder when you drag a view out on top of
another view, it makes it a subview of that.
Now you can't really tell that here, but that's what this
little guy over in the corner, the document outline,
is really great at. If you look at the document outline,
do you see how the activity indicator is indented
from the Scroll View? Okay, that means it's a subview
of the Scroll View. Now, if you don't want that, okay,
no problem. You can just drag it up above.
Now, it's not a subview of the Scroll View. Now, of course,
it's not in the right order right now, because I want this
thing to be in front of the Scroll View. So, I'm gonna put
the Scroll View on top of it. So, now they're siblings, and
this one is in front, because remember, the subview is list,
the top ones are in the back.
The other ones go towards the front. So,
now we have this thing in the front, okay? Now,
another thing is, what if I wanna have,
constraints on this to keep this in the middle?
Well, I have to be very careful here too,
cuz those dashed lines. We're referring to the scroll view.
So if I tried to do reset to suggested constraints here,
I'm gonna get constraints that constrain the activity
indicator to the scroll view. I don't want that.
I want the activity indicator to be in the middle of its
superview.
And watch this, you can do control drag in the document
outline. So I'm gonna control drag from my activity
indicator to its superview in the document outline,
not over here, but in the document outline.
And when I let go, I can do things like, yeah,
please center it vertically and horizontally in yourself.
Okay? So now this thing is centered and middle. Okay?
So, now we've got the spinner, how do we do anything with it?
Well, we need an outlet to it.
So, I'm going to bring out my code over here, okay?
Do it automatic.
Got our image view controller here, let's give it to this,
give it to that, give it some room. Okay so
I'm just going to create an outlet from this little
spinner right here, over here. See it make sure that it's
type is activity indicator view not something else, and
I'm just going to call it spinner,
I like spinner as my name. And it's just an outlet,
it's a normal outlet just like our scroll view or anything
else is an outlet. Okay just like your display was in your
calculator there's nothing particularly special about it.
So now that we have this nice spinner right here,
we just need to turn it on and turn it off. So where are we
gonna turn it on? Well, I'm gonna turn it on right before
I start doing something on that other thread, okay. So
right here when I dispatch onto this other thread to go
do this NSData, which is gonna block, I'm just gonna say
spinner startAnimating. And I'm gonna be even trickier and
go spinner?.startAnimating just in case
I'm fetching my image like as a result of prepare for
segue, okay, because there my outlets aren't set.
So even if my app spinner's not set,
I'll just do nothing. Now where do I wanna turn it off?
Its actually two places that you can turn this off.
One good place might be down here when your image gets set.
Okay? Cuz if someone sets your image,
then you don't need to be spending anymore.
By definition, you're showing the image.
So, it will make no sense to be spinning such a good place.
Got to be a little careful though here because,
what happens when we get in here, okay?
And you get to the URL here, and
the image data wasn't able to be found, so
you never call set image, so it's never going to stop.
So you probably want to put in else spinner stop animating
here as well. Okay so this is gonna stop the spinner in
the case where it went off to the Internet to get something,
and it couldn't find it. Okay, eh,
little tricky. Okay, so let's see how that works.
Alright, here we go, let's try Earth, there it is,
it's spinning, and we can go back, let's try Cassini, it's
spinning. Now when Cassini appears it stops spinning, and
so it hides because we had, we set this switch over here
on this one we inspected it called hides when stopped,
right. And so since it hides when stopped, it's not here
anymore okay. [INAUDIBLE] Saturn,
spins okay then we can rotate. Big image, taking a long time.
There it is, okay? So see how we turn this into an app, it's
really responsive and really nice and it's being as fast as
it can. It's getting those images as fast as it can,
but from the user standpoint, it's very responsive.
You really wanna go with that way.
Okay, so now I'm gonna show two unrelated to this, okay?
But did you've asked about in Piazza. One is notice that
when we run this, let's run again, watch what happens.
When we run, we get an empty image view controller
which really doesn't make any sense. What we'd
really want it to, when we first run and this is empty,
we want it to come up showing this view controller. So
this is like with your calculator,
you don't want it to come up showing empty graph.
You want it to come up showing the calculator because
the empty graph is useless,
it just forces them to do that back thing right here for
no good reason. Okay, so how do we do that, okay this is
another case where we need to use delegation.
In this case it's the split fuse delegate. Okay, split
view controller's delegate. So what does this code look like?
I'm gonna put this in Cassini, view controller right here.
The first thing I need to do is I need to make the Cassini
view controller be its own split view's delegate.
In other words, it needs to be the delegate of
the split view it's in.
So I'm gonna do this in viewDidLoad. Okay sometimes
viewDidLoad is not quite early enough to do things for
split views. We might have to do it in a wait for even. But
this will work in beaded load. And I'm just going to set
my split view controllers remember MVC knows the split
view controller its in. Or the navigation controller its in,
or the tab bar controller its in. So
SplitViewController says what it is, might be nil, okay? But
if it's not I'm gonna set its delegate to be myself.
Of course as soon as I do this I'm getting an error because
I didn't say that I was a UI SplitViewController delegate.
So I need to go up here and
say that I'm a UI SplitViewController delegate.
All right that satisfies that error. All is good. Now which
split view controller method am I going to implement?
Okay hold on your chairs for this one, okay
by the way again on the split view controller delegate so
I can just start typing split view and you can see it
shows me all the split view controller delegate methods.
There's quite a few. Okay about a dozen of them.
And the one I want is the one that controls
the collapsing of the detail on top of the master.
Because I don't want it to collapse that detail on top of
the master if the detail is empty, okay?
If it doesn't have an image in there,
I don't want it to do that. So this thing that controls that
it's called, collab secondary view controller,
on to primary compute controller. Okay, collab
secondary view controller, on to primary compute controller.
Now, notice it returns a Bool, this Bool
you return true if you took care of this.
Return false if you want the system to do the collapse.
Okay, so this is a way where the delegate can do this
collapse if it wants, or not, and
it just lets the split view know whether it did it or not.
So that's what the bool is, let it know when it did it.
So, this is actually quite simple right here.
We just want to get the image view controller,
okay? Well first of all let's make sure that the primary
view controller, content view controller, is ourself.
Now it should be, because we're setting ourselves
as our own split view delegate, so we should be
the primary view controllers, the masters content Okay?
So we showed you that, that should not be a problem. But
now I'm gonna say, on top of that, if I can let ivc =
the secondaryViewController, that's the detail.
It contentViewController as an ImageViewController. Okay? So,
if have a ImageViewController as my detail, and
where, everyone know about where, right? You did your
reading assignments, you know about where. Where is
an additional clause that you can add onto an if, okay?
So I'm gonna say where the image view controllers
image URL is nil. So if I have an image view controller as
my detail and it's, image url is nil, then it's empty.
There's nothing in there. There's no Saturn or
anything else. So in this case I'm going to return true,
which is me telling the system, yeah,
I took care of that. Okay, I put that detail, I collapsed
that detail on top of the master, don't worry about it.
Now I didn't, didn't actually do anything, that's good,
cuz that's what I want. I don't want that
detail to be collapsed on top of the master if the thing is
nil. All right, so I just kind of lied to the system and told
them I handled it when in fact I didn't. Okay, otherwise,
we're just gonna let the system do whatever it does,
okay. Return false, we did not handle this so you handle it.
Okay, so let's see if that works. Okay, so here it is,
look at that. It came up, didn't show me a blank thing,
so it worked. Now let's click on one of these. Woop, okay,
it worked. So
it collapsed the secondary on top of the primary when I
wanted it too, okay? But if it came up nil,
then it didn't show it. Everyone understand that? I
know it seems a little, a lot of long words in here [LAUGH]
like primary view controller, secondary view controller, but
this is just master in detail, that's all this is. And
we're just checking where the image URL's nil and just
returning that, we handled it when we really didn't handle
it because we don't want it handled. Okay. One other
thing I want to show you is reusing the detail in iPad.
Look at iPad. And we have the master detail right here.
Every time we click on this thing, it's creating a new MVC
here. Okay? Creating a brand new MVC. And if there,
there's really no reason for that. Okay?
We could absolutely just reuse this MVC right here.
Okay, we don't have to create a new one every time.
So, how would we do that? How would we reuse this?
Well, if we're gonna reuse this, we can't use
segues because segues always create a new MVC.
That's what segues do, they create a new MVC.
So, we can't use segues, okay, to do that in that case. So,
lets go back to our Cassini right here. Our, storyboard.
And we're not going to use these segues over here. Okay,
see these three segues? I'm gonna get rid of them.
Get rid of, oops, not that. Click here,
get rid of that one,
I'm gonna get rid of that one, I'm gonna get rid of that one.
Cuz I cannot segue from these buttons or
it will constantly create a new one of these details.
Instead, what I'm gonna do is to use target action.
So I'm just gonna bring up my code here, some space,
all right, and I'm gonna do a target action message from
each of these that reuses the detail to show the image.
So let's do that. Let's just go Ctrl+drag here.
I'm gonna call this show image, that's a good name for
this action right here, and I'm gonna have UI button
be the center, cuz I'm gonna know which one to show because
I'm gonna look at the sender. Okay. So,
I got show image right here. So, let's go ahead and
put the code here. So, show image is a lot like,
looks a lot like prepare for seg, segue. We can only do
this if we're in a split view. Right, we can only do the show
image thing here, this trick, if we are in a split view,
sorry, let me, just so we can see what's going on here.
All right. Okay, we can only do a split view so
I'm gonna first check to see that. I'm gonna say,
if I can let the ivc = splitViewControllers,
if I have one, view Controller,
controller[1]. We know that's the detail, right.
And actually I don't wanna use sub one
because if for some reason my split view controller
doesn't have a detail, then view controllers only have one
thing so I'm actually gonna use ViewController.last.
Okay, because last returns nil if there's no such thing.
Okay, and then I'm gonna grab the content view controller as
always and I'm gonna check to see if that's an image view
controller. So in other words,
if I can get my detail as an image view controller,
then I'm basically gonna do this right here,
in here, but here I don't have to say sender as UI button
because the sender is
a UI button so I can just say sender and
it's never gonna be nil there. Okay? And do that. So see,
see what's going on here? So no segueing,
I'm not doing any segueing. So when I go over here, Okay,
and I pick something, like Cassini, or Earth, okay,
we'll say. It loads it up. Actually,
we got to do one other thing, sorry. Back here, in our
storyboard, let's wire up all these buttons to do that.
[LAUGH] Okay, we only wired up earth to do this show image so
let's do that. Let's go to automatic.
All right, so let's control,
so this one here and let's wire up this one here. Okay,
so now all three buttons are sending that same show image.
So now we can actually demonstrate this. So let's
do Cassini. Here it is showing this and once this appears, or
even before it appeared, I could hit Earth and
it just reusing this. No seugues, so there's no way I'm
creating a new MVC here. It's just reloading it, okay,
just by setting the image URL on the image there. Got it?
Okay. Now, what about back on iPhone, though?
Let's go back to iPhone.
Is this going to work over here? No, it's not
because it only does that thing if it's in split view.
Remember I said if split view controller, so if I hit Earth,
it's not working at all now, cuz it's not segueing here. So
really what I need to do back here in Cassini is I need to
say [COUGH] if I'm in a split view controller, then do this.
Otherwise, I basically want to segue. Okay, so
now I'm gonna show you how to segue from code. Okay,
you've only learned how to segue from,
by dragging in Storyboard.
And now I'm gonna show you how to do it in code,
which is you just say performSegueWithIdentifier.
And you give it the identifier. So
we'll use the Storyboard ShowImageSegue,
and the sender can be whatever you want,
I'm gonna have the sender be this sender button right here,
this button that's asking us to show image, so
it's gonna be one of those Earth things or whatever.
Now this, perform segue with identifier,
requires that such a segue exist in the storyboard. Okay,
and we got rid of all those segues.
So that's not gonna work. We need to have a storyboard with
this identifier, and the way you do this is, you actually
segue from the view controller itself. Instead of seguing
from one of the buttons, when you wanna segue in code,
you segue from the view controller itself,
from this little icon right here down to wherever you want
to segue to. So we want to segue to this, right here,
put these close to each other. Okay, so I'm just gonna Ctrl +
drag from here to here. It's gonna be, it can be show,
because we're never doing this in a split view controller cuz
split view controller we're doing the other thing. So
we do show. We've got this thing here now, this one
segue, this segue sets up the whole view controller to here.
We still need to set its identifier to ShowImage. Okay?
And now, back here in this code, when we do perform segue
with identifier, it's going to do that segue. And
we're seguing from the view controller to the other one,
not with the buttons anymore, from the view controller, so
let's see if that works now on iPhone All right, Cassini.
Sure enough it's working. Okay, so
it's doing that segue, it's back to doing the segues.
So this is a new MVC. Go back. This is a new MVC.
But it's only doing it on iPhone because if you look at
our code over here in the showImage,
if it's in a split view controller, it just reuses
the image view controller that's already in the split,
in the detail. Okay? Got all that? All right,
I think I have time to do the last bit of slides here,
oops, which is on text field, go through it pretty quickly.
All right, so UITextField. I haven't been able to show
it to you right now because it requires delegation to work.
Without delegation, text fields don't work. So
UITextField is like UILabel but it's editable.
Users can touch on it and then a keyboard comes up and
they can start typing in it.
UITextField is not really a very main stream
input mechanism on the iPhone because the keyboard is very
small, okay? So, you only want to use UITextField when you
absolutely can't get the text from the user in any other
way. You can't offer them a choice
from a list of the things, they have to actually type it
in, okay? So, be careful, this is not a desktop app that you
are building. It's a mobile app. All right so,
TextField is not a primary input source. Now,
the keyboard appears whenever a TextField becomes
the first responder, and you can make a TextField the first
responder by sending it the message, becomeFirstResponder.
And then it will become the first responder.
You can make it stop being the first responder,
in which case the keyboard will go away, by saying,
resignFirstResponder, okay?
So, the keyboard appears and
disappears purely if there's something on the screen
that wants to be the first responder. Okay, simple as
that. Now, delegation is used here primarily with the return
key. So, if you bring up that little software keyboard
in the corner, there's a button called Return.
And if you click return the TextField's delegate will
be sent this message textFieldShouldReturn. It's
called ShouldReturn because it returns a Bool about whether
it should do target/action when that return happens.
Because a TextField is like a button, if someone types in
there and hits Return, it'll do target/action, okay?
You can control drag and
it'll target/action just like a button. But
this text field should return, either has to return true or
it has to not be implemented by the delegate for
that to work. But one thing, so usually do implement this,
because one thing you wanna do in here is resign first
responder. A lot of times when the user hits return,
you do the target/action, but
you want the keyboard to go away. So, a lot of times
you'll do that here and TextField should return. So,
you just need to set yourself as the UITextField delegate,
you've got to save it to the UITextField delegate, and
then you implement this method and inside just say sender,
which is the text field that's sending this to you,
design first responder. You can also find out when editing
has ended in your TextField, meaning that the user
clicked on another TextField usually and you've resigned
first responder. Okay, any time you resign first
responder you'll get sent this and you can ask the TextField,
ok, what text is in you. Okay, so that's another interesting
one. And as I said, TextField's UIControl,
you can do target/action, just control, drag.
The keyboard, you configure the keyboard actually by
talking to the TextField.
There's no UI keyboard object that you talk to in iOS, okay?
When you wanna configure your keyboard,
you talk to the thing that's bringing the keyboard up.
In this case, the TextField. And
there's all kinds of methods in here you could look at.
This is the UITextInputTraits protocol, so
that's where you wanna look in the documentation, for
this protocol. Remember,
a protocol is just a bunch of methods and bars, that's all
these are. And these will set what kind of keyboard it is,
you're entering a URL? Is it a password thing,
where you can't see the text? All that stuff Is part of that
protocol, so you wanna look that up. One thing about
the keyboard, it comes up over your UI so it might block.
It might even block the TextField that you're
editing in, if you're not careful about how you layer UI
out. And we are gonna talk later into the quarter about
this NSNotification center. It's a way to get notified
when things happened and when a keyboard comes up and
blocks your UI, you will get notified, okay?
And when we talk about this,
you'll understand what you can do. You could move your UI
up from out underneath it, or maybe it's in scroll view,
you could scroll up or something like that, but
you have to be careful about this. They keyboard,
just boom, comes up right on top of your UI and
it can really block things, okay? So,
you'll need to eventually learn how to respond to this
notification. There's lots of other TextField properties
that are interesting here. You can actually put a little
button on the side. You can decide where,
when the user touches it, does it clear out what's in there?
You can have a place holder in there, so
that when there's nothing in the field,
there's a kind of a light gray text.
Kind of telling the user what's supposed to be there,
that kind of thing.
Anytime I show you anything in this class,
like UITextField or UIButton or anything, of course I'm
expecting you to go read the documentation, okay. Otherwise
you're just not gonna know how to use these things.
I only have a minute or
two in these classes, in the lectures to
kind of tell you these exist. If you need to be able to go,
use the documentation to figure them out, okay?
And this is a classic example figuring out how to
use TextField here, Okay? Yeah, they have these left and
right overlays are kind of fun. You control the layout
all this all kinds of stuff. The keyboard has
an interesting bar in it which is sorry the input
trait protocol. Called input accessory view you can
actually put a little view on top of your keyboard.
You've probably seen that in some apps. Right,
has kind of like a little view has custom stuff,
you can put your own view just by setting this bar.
It's kinda fun. All right, so that's it. On Friday,
we do have a section. It's on UI Testing,
which is literally being able to record the UI being
interacted with and then writing code that tests,
to make sure it's doing what it's supposed to be doing.
That's really cool. A feature in x code. And then next week,
we're going to talk about Table View and
Core Data, okay?
Table View is a way of showing big huge amounts of data.
And Core Data is a database to store big huge amounts of
data in. Assignment four.
Since it's a table view based assignment,
we'll go out at the end of the next lecture, and it'll be due
a week later. And there are no more reading assignments.
I can tell some of you haven't done your reading assignment
because you don't know some of the questions I'm asking.
Go back and read that stuff, really.
it's not that much stuff, you should really understand all
these things, like the where clause,
or you're going to be writing weird code.
Because people say, why didn't they just use where there,
why did they put another if?.
Okay? So, you don't want to be that guy, okay? Al lright,
I'll see you guys next week. >> For
more, please visit us at Stanford.edu