[MUSIC]
Stanford University. >> Okay well
welcome to lecture number nine of CS193P. This is spring of
2016. Today, we're gonna talk all about Table View that's
the only topic for today. It's basically a way to create,
apps that are looking at large data sets.
And our demo is gonna be a Twitter client, and
of course Twitter is this humongous data set,
bunch of tweets out there and more all the time.
And so a Table View is a great way to, show tweets. So what
is Table View? UITableView is a sub class of UIView, okay.
It displays data in a big table, okay? And
there's really two different looks to it, all right?
There's the plain style which you see here on the left,
which is basically just all of the things it's showing in
a big, long straight list. And then there's group style
on the right, which is also a bunch of rows of data, but
grouped. A little more obviously into little groups
and this ones in the right, okay, are usually more for
static tables, okay, where the stuff that in there is fixed.
It's kinda fixed in your storyboard usually even,
whereas on the left is more for data that
changing every changing coming like even here.
If you know anything about NFL you'll know that this this
list has changed dramatically since I made this little list.
So dynamic data on the left basically and
more static data on the right. Is not exclusively that but
that's generally how we use these two styles,
okay. Now let's talk about all the parts of a UITableView so
we know the terminology, all right?
I'm gonna show this to you in plain style, but then I'll
show you the grouped style version of it afterwards.
So there's a Table Header at the top.
This is just a UIView. It can be any UIView you want.
In our demo we're gonna have one of these,
it's gonna be a UITextField, okay? But it can be,
it can be your own custom view with subviews in there.
It can be absolutely anything, and
it always lives at the top of the header and as
the table scrolls around it'll scroll off the top, right?
It's at the very top of this thing you're scrolling on. And
similarly there's a footer, also some UIView.
Notice at the bottom I'm showing you
a little bit of code like var tableViewFooter: UIView,
that's basically telling you the function or
the property where you set this thing. Okay,
these would be functions or properties in UITableView.
Okay? Next is a bunch of stuff that's, we grouped together,
we call it a section, okay? So the data that's in the table
can be sectioned off into little, pieces.
And you'll see in the next slide
a little more of an example of that. Each section, okay,
has a header, this is usually a string but it could also
be UIView if you wanted a complicated looking header,
maybe with images or something like that. But,
usually this is just a string. And also a section footer.
Okay, so that's every section has a header and footer,
header and footer, header and footer. Okay. And then inside
the sections there's the rows. Now these roads like Row 0,
Row 1, these two sections each have two rows,
but there can be any number of rows and it doesn't have to be
the same number of rows in every section.
One section might have zero rows or five rows and
another one might have 100 rows okay. This
row is basically represented in the table by a UIView. It's
actually a subclass of UIView called UITableViewCell. And
this method right here it's gonna get called in your code,
cellForRowAtIndexPath and it returns
one of these UITableViewCells. Okay, this is probably
the most important method in implementing Table View,
is this cellForRowAtIndexPath.
We'll be coming back to this again and again okay. So
those are all the names of the parts of a Table View.
So when I was talking about it you know what they are.
So that's what it looks in plain style.
Here's the exact same thing in group style. Okay, so
it has the same thing, headers, cells, footers,
it's just that it displays them a little bit differently.
Okay. All right, sections or not? What does it look like to
have sections or not? Now this is visible sections, so
look here on the right you see I have some cities in Japan
for example and this little gray bar right there.
I don't know how well you can see that, actually,
but there's a gray bar there,
it says Japan, that's a section header, okay?
So there's one section, the Japan section,
it's got three rows. Here's a Mexico section,
it's got three rows. Here's Italy section,
it's got at least two rows there at the top.
Okay, this one over here doesn't have any sections.
Now, it actually might have sections, but
no section headers. Okay, if you have sections but
no section headers, it looks like you have no sections. But
this is what we mean by sections, so just groups of
things in the table. The type of cell, those little rows,
there are five types of cells. Here are four of
them that are built into the system. The subtitle has
a piece of text and then a small little piece under it,
okay? This is called the title and the subtitle, or
the text and the detail text, sometimes we call it.
The basic one, the second one has no detail text,
only has the primary text. The right and
left are similar to the subtitle but it puts the text
in a little different place with a little different color.
Okay? So you can see that the basic
cell types that come with the system, pretty limited.
Okay? It also can pl, display an image,
turns out, but they're pretty limited. There's a fifth type,
which is custom cell, which let's you build any UI
you want inside the cell. You can drag buttons,
text fields, images, anything you want in there. And
we're going to talk about and demo that today. All right.
So, how do I use a table view in my application?
And the answer is, 99% of the time you're gonna
use a table view controller. Okay? TableViewController,
it's a UIViewController. A sub class of UIViewController.
That sub class is called UITableViewController. And,
just like when you use a UIViewController,
you sub class it to make a class you can hook
your outlets and actions up to. Same thing here.
You're gonna sub class UITableViewController so
you can wire up things if you want inside your controller.
Okay? Now it is possible to use a UITableView without
the UITableViewController but like I said we almost never
do. 99% of the time we're going to use UIViewController.
Okay, and so if you drag the UIViewController
out into your storyboard, UITableViewController,
sorry. If you drag UITableViewController out,
you're gonna get this thing right here,
that's gonna be a UITableViewController.
And the view, remember the view property
in a UIViewController is that top level view?
It's going to be of type UITableView. Okay. The very
top top level is a table view. So this, UITableViewController
the entire view is just one big table view.
Now it is possible to drag out your own UIViewController and
make the table view only be a part of the view.
Like be a subview of the main view, but again very rare
to do that. Not even really gonna talk about doing that.
But you could. Requires a little more work on your part.
This is kind of a nice pre-packaged way to use
TableView here. Okay? Of course when you sub class
UITableViewController up here, you create your own class.
We'll call it MyTableView Controller or
something like that.
You're going to want to remember to go to the identity
inspector and set that as the type just like you would any
other UIViewController. If you right click on
it, okay, if you right click on the thing that represents
the TableViewController, you'll see that, look,
here's view, it's hooked up to a UITableview. And
then down farther, you see dataSource and delegate.
Those are both delegates, okay, for
delegation. They are protocol based communication outlets,
communication portals. From the Table View,
to the Table View Controller. And you can see look,
they're automatically hooked up for you. And
what that means is that your UITableViewController subclass
Just has to implement any and all of the data source and
delegate methods that it wants. Okay?
To make things work. Just like we do with scroll view, right?
We set ourselves as a scroll view delegate.
We implement that view for zooming in scroll view.
Now we can zoom. Same thing with table view,
except for we're automatically hooked up as the delegate and
We'll talk about these, the difference between these two.
data source.
And there's just a bunch of methods in there like and
index path for us to implement the table,
all right? You can, of course, click on this table and
inspect it in the inspector, just like anything else there.
You can see things like, plain style and stuff. I'll show you
some of that. Remember when you have a table view,
you're gonna remember, wanna remember Ctrl+Shift click. If
you remember ctrl-shift-click. It lets you, kind of, cli-,
pick what's under the mouth,mouse,
if there are multiple things under there.
Mm-kay? That's really valuable here because you've got
the cell, under that you've got the table view, under that
you've got the controller. And if you had a custom cell,
you might have buttons and text fields in here.
So, kind of drilling down to which of those things you want
to chose. Ctrl-shift-click. Okay, you want that. So
here I'm gonna, switch the table view from being
plain style to being grouped, okay? You can see that,
when I switched a group, it changes a little bit and
looks a little bit different, okay? Another thing I can
switch is dynamic and static, okay? Now, grouped in plain,
I told you the plain was usually dynamic data, and
grouped is static. They don't have to be that way, okay?
You choose the dynamic versus static with this other pop up,
right here. But again, usually if it's grouped you're gonna
pick static from this one, and
if it's plain your gonna be picking dynamic. So
I'm gonna switch to static right here. When I switch to
static, all of this, these little rows in here,
now they become fully editable.
You can drag buttons out. You can drag text fields.
Whatever. And whatever you put in your story board,
that's what's gonna appear in your app, okay?
However many rows there are here,
that's how many rows are gonna be in the app.
Whatever buttons and stuff you put in here,
that's how many are gonna be in the app.
You can wire up outlets in these static ones directly
to your controller, just like if this were a view and
you dragged a button down to it, okay? So
think of static as really just normal view,
but grouped, okay? Grouped in these little sections.
Really great for things like settings like settings, like,
you know, the settings app in iOS is just a big table view,
a static grouped table view. So, it's really great for
that. It's not good at all for dynamic data.
It doesn't, grouped is not good for
that. And if you have this set to static content,
then you can't even do dynamic data, okay? So
static, you edit it all in the story board. Very different
from dynamic, okay? So let's go back to talk about dynamic,
though, cuz that's really the more interesting one here,
okay? We're also gonna switch back to plain style for
dynamic. Now, these rows are prototypes, or
templates, okay? Because I've got three rows here, but I can
have hundreds of rows in my app when I load my data up. So
these are just the different templates you can have.
And you could have different kinds of templates.
Like, in your homework, you're gonna have two different
kinds of rows in one of your table views. One shows image,
one's showing text. So you're gonna have one prototype for
images, and you're gonna have another prototype for text,
okay? And these prototypes are copied hundreds of times,
or however many times is necessary for all the data.
Now, it doesn't actually copy it hundreds of times, cuz
it's really smart. It reuses them, so it only uses them for
visible cells, okay? Table view's very efficient,
as you can imagine. If you had 100,000 items in there,
and you were making 100,000 UITableView cells,
it would be pretty inefficient so it doesn't do that.
It reuses them. But these prototypes are a template
that get, you know, essentially copied.
So, the cells can be inspected just like the table view.
So, here I'm gonna change,
I'm gonna pick this first cell, this first proto-type,
and I'm gonna change it to be subtitle.
And you can see it looks like this in the storyboard,
just to remind you that it's subtitle. Of course,
this is not gonna say subtitle and title when I launch.
It's gonna be replaced by the data that I load into that
cell, okay? Cuz I'm gonna have hundreds of these rows.
All right. You can also set a little
thing to appear on the right hand side of a row.
For example, I picked a detailed disclosure which is
this little greater than sign, and then this little round
circled i. This little gray, greater than sign means that
if I press on this row, it's gonna segue, okay? So, anytime
you set up a segue from a row, which we're gonna talk about,
you're always gonna wanna have your accessory be either
detail disclosure or just disclosure.
Detail disclosure means you have this little blue i, and
I'll talk about what that means in a second, okay?
So I'm gonna turn that off for now. All right.
So, another style that you can choose is the custom style.
So I'm gonna switch my style here to custom, okay? Now,
this custom area, I can resize it, okay?
Make it bigger. I can go over to my object pallet down here.
I can pick up a label or a button or something.
I can drag it out. I can use the blue lines.
I can use stack views. I can control drag to the edges.
I can build whatever UI I want in here. And remember, it took
prototype. So every row that's gonna use this prototype
is gonna have all those labels and buttons in each row, okay?
So there's a, when you have this kind of mechanism,
you might well ask yourself, well, how am I gonna hook up
to that label? How am I gonna control drag?
I can't really control drag an outlet to my table view
controller because my table view controller's just one
controller, and I've got hundreds of rows. So,
which row is the outlet hooked to?
So you can't hook your outlets up to dynamic prototype like,
rows like this. You have to hook it up to outlets in
a sub-classed UI table view cell, okay?
So we're gonna create a custom subclass of UITableViewCell.
And it's gonna have outlets in it. And we're gonna wire this
to it. And we know that, for all the visible cells anyway,
there's another TableUIViewCell that's hooked
up. So, we're gonna have all these UITableViewCells,
they're gonna all each have outlets to whatever is showing
in their custom cell, okay? So
you do this with the identity inspector in the same way.
So you're gonna do new file, right?
You're gonna go over to new file, and when you do new file
you're gonna say Tableview Cell as the superview class.
And then you're gonna go up here to the identity inspector
with this selected, with this cell selected, and
say that it's a my Tableview cell. And the reason you're
gonna do that sub-class is so that you can have outlets and
stuff. Just like the same reason you do it for
a controller, but this is not a controller,
this is a UI View subclass, actually.
UI TableView cell is a UI view subclass. All right. So now
once you have that, you can wire up all the outlets and
actions you want, okay?
And we're gonna do this in the demo and
make maybe a lot more sense. So, here's an example.
I'm creating an outlet to this label in my UI table view cell
subclass, you see that? Okay? All right. And again,
remember it's a prototype, it's gonna be duplicated.
All your label, this label and all the stuff and, it's
gonna be a different instance of this for every row, okay?
All right. So, let's talk about those protocols that
we're talking about dataSource and delegate, okay?
There's two of them because the delegate controls how
the table is displayed, okay? The dataSource controls what
data is in the table, okay? What's in the rows, okay?
So that's the difference between the two delegates.
Now, the UITableViewController automatically sets itself as
the delegate, and as the data source. So, it's all preset
up. And as I told you, the view, the top level view,
is a UITableView. There's also a var called TableView which,
the computed var, that just returns the view.
Okay, so that usually will access the table view,
because it's typed to be UITableView,
that's how we access our table view inside of
our table view controller sub class code. All right.
All right, so when do we need to implement the data source?
Only if we're doing dynamic cells. If we're doing static,
like, you know, the settings example, the group
settings thing. Then you just do it in your storyboard,
you don't need to do anything in the dataSource protocol to
make that work. Okay? But if you're doing dynamic,
you need to do it. And there are three very important
methods in the dataSource protocol, there's a bunch of
methods in there, but there's three really important ones.
One is how many sections are in this table?
How many rows are in each of the sections?
It's gonna ask for every section,
how many rows in this section? How many rows in this section?
How many rows in this section? And then, give me a view,
a UI table view cell subclass to draw this row, okay?
And that's when you're gonna implement cell for
row at index path and give it your sub class,
an instance of your sub class. And
I'm going to show exactly how you do that in a second here.
to skip the two easy ones, the number of sections and rows,
So we're going
and go straight to cell for row at index path. Okay?
So this method looks like this. Okay?
I already talked about the fact that it's reusing here.
And the method's called cell for row at index path,
you can see that it returns a UITablViewCell, right here.
This index path is really just the section and
row, section and the row in that section, okay? They could
have called this cell for row at section in row, two
separate arguments, but they decided to call it cell for
row and index path and they just made a thing called
NSIndexPath that's got the section row in it, okay?
And in fact, if you wanted to, like, get your data, you would
just say let the data equal my internal data structure,
whatever that is. IndexPath subsection, indexPath.row,
that will tell your internal data structure where an array
of arrays, where the sections were in there in the rows,
you can just do this. So this is how you get the section,
and this is how you get the row, okay? So
then you have to take the data
that corresponds to that section and row, and
you have to load it up into a UITableViewCell. Okay, so
let's talk about how that works. And
while I'm doing this, I'm gonna move this code on top of
the storyboard so that we can see the storyboard at the same
time we're looking at the code, okay? So here's how you
get the cell, okay? You call this table view method, okay?
This is the table view here that's passed along, table
view first argument. Dequeued reusable cell with identifier.
That's the thing that's reusing these cells. Okay?
As things go off screen, they get put back into this reuse
queue, and when people call this they get pulled out.
Okay? If there's not one available in the reuse queue,
it makes one. It copies your prototype to make one.
Okay? This says which prototype to use. Each of
these prototypes can have a different identifier. You just
select the row, and go into your storyboard, okay? And
you set the identifier. Just like when you do with a segue,
right? In a segue you set the identifier? Same thing here.
You're just saying what the name of this is so
that in your code, you can dequeue the kind of
one you want. So if you have multiple prototypes
you'll dequeue the right one here. And maybe some sections
use one kind of thing, and some sections use a different.
That's probably going to be in your homework, right?
You're gonna have a section using one of the prototypes
and a different section uses a different one, okay? Perfectly
fine. So after you get the cell, which I call dequeued
here by referencing that, you are going to load this cell
up with the data from your internal data structure.
See, data is this data right here, okay? And
I'm just gonna put this in this title, in subtitle.
Now you have to go look at the documentation for
UITableVIewCell, this is not a custom cell, right?
This is of type subtitle. So it's just a built
in one, it only has these two things. If you'll look at
the documentation for UITableViewCell,
you'll see that it has a property called text label,
which corresponds to that title thing, and detail text
label, which corresponds to this little text label. Okay?
So you can set the text of those things here.
To whatever information, important information or
less important information, from your data,
internal data structure. Then you just return the cell and
that's it. Okay so you dequeue the cell, load it up with
the information at that section and
row in your data structure, and return it. Any question
about that? Okay, now let's talk about the custom case.
Let's say you have a custom cell, okay? So
now my type here is custom, I got this label, but I could
have all kinds of buttons and stuff in here. In this
case you do the same thing, dequeueReusableCell, okay?
Probably has a different identifier here.
Okay, then instead of doing that textLabel.text equals
detailtextLabel.whatever equals, you just
call some public API in your subclass of TableViewCell that
passes the information to it. Then it's gonna take that and
put it in all of its outlets. Okay? Make sense?
So it's very very simple. Notice that I'm having to take
the cell which gets dequeued as a UITableViewCell and
I'm having to cast it here to be MyTableViewCell so
I can call this public function in MyTableViewCell.
See? Otherwise I wouldn't be able to call it because
dequeued would be a UITableViewCell,
not a subclass of it. Everybody got that? Okay.
The UITableViewlDataSource that cell for
row at index path is the most important thing in it.
The other two here, number of sections in TableView and
TableView's number of rows and section are the other two.
The number of sections by default is one. So if
you don't implement number of sections in table view at all,
you just don't even implement it, it'll be one,
okay? But the other one has to be implemented because
the TableView has to know how many rows there are.
TableView cannot survive unless it knows how many rows
there are. So you have to implement this number of rows
in section right here. And it's simple, it's just gives
you the section. You return how many rows are in that
section, okay? And it's gonna call that repeatedly, once for
every section. Okay, what about in a static table?
You don't have to do any of this, okay? Static table,
it's fixed in your storyboard. All right? So that's how our
table dataSource works. The section titles like you
remember I showed you the section had Japan and
the Japan things, and then Mexico and the Mexico cities?
Well those titles like Japan, those are considered part of
the data, as you might imagine. So there's another
TableView dataSource method called TableView,
titleForHeader or FooterInSection. Okay?
You give it this section and you return to string.
Or there's another one that you can return a view,
a UI view, okay? So
that's how you set the headers of your tables. There's
a number of other methods in here that have to do with
editing and moving rows because when you're deleting
rows you're affecting your data source, right?
Your deleting the data out of your data source.
So those can get involved, I'm not going to talk about those.
But this is the kind of thing you probably want to do either
for the extra credit or in your final project.
You're almost certainly going to want to have a table.
At least one where you can delete the rows or
move them around. Or something, or insert rows.
Etc. Okay? Now, what about segueing from TableView cells?
How do you do that? Exactly as you might imagine [LAUGH], you
just control drag from them to the MVC you want to segue to,
and when you do you're gonna get to choose what kind of
segue you want, show or show detail,
or eventually we'll talk about these other kinds of segues.
Okay, if you have that little blue i, told you I'd get back
to that, here it is, you can control+drag from it, over,
and when you choose your segue, you choose it from this
part that says Accessory Action down here. And when you
have a little i here, if you click on the row it will do
whatever segue is specified by the top selection segue thing.
And if you Click just on the blue i,
you'll get whatever segue is hooked up here, okay? So
you can basically have a row that has two different segues,
one if you click on the i and one if you click on the row.
All right, you set your segue identifier as usual,
nothing special there. But
to prepareForSegue obviously is gonna be a little different
when you're segueing from a row. So
let's look at prepareForSegue. And the difference is all
about who the sender is. Normally, the sender in
prepareForSegue is like the UI button you clicked
on that caused the segue to happen. Well, here,
of course, the sender is the UITableViewCell you clicked
on, okay. So you're gonna have to get that UITableViewCell,
and since this is any object, you're gonna have to convert
it to either MyTableViewCell if it's custom,
or UITableViewCell if it's not custom. Then you're gonna call
this very important method in tableView.indexPathforCell,
okay. It's gonna give you an NSIndexPath that's
basically gonna tell you which row in which section
you're segueing from. Cuz if you're preparing,
you gotta know which row it came from so you know
how to prepare with the guy you're segueing to. Okay, so
then you just take, you get your destinationViewController
Okay, this is just like in any other, prepareForSegue.
as usual.
And then you get your data out of your model, okay,
in your TableViewController, in that section and row. Okay,
however, you might have to call a function to do that or
however you do it, and then you just assign that
to the public API of the thing you are segueing to just like
you normally would in any prepareForSegue.
Okay, so the magic is just this little thing,
indexPathForCell, don't forget about that,
okay. That's how you figure out which row you're segueing
from. All right, how about the UITableViewDelegate,
not the dataSource but the delegate?
It has a lot of stuff for how the table view works.
I'm not gonna talk a lot about it but
I'll talk about a couple of interesting one.
Usually the dataSource and the delegate are the same object,
namely your controller,
your TableViewController. The delegate lets you
observe what's going on inside the table, okay?
It has a lot of will do something,
did do something kind of methods in it.
It has a very interesting one which is to let you know when
the user selects a row, when a user touches on a row. Now
normally when they touch on a row, you're just gonna segue,
but sometimes you might wanna touch on a row in a table and
not segue. You wanna do something else, okay?
And so this gives you, kind of, ta,
TableView Target/Action, okay. The way you do that,
is you implement this method in your controller,
didSelectRowAtIndexPath, okay. And the table view will send
you this whenever someone touches on a row, and
this is just telling you which row they touched on, okay,
simple. Another interesting one is if they
press on that little i, the little circled blue i,
you'll get this method, accessory button tapped for
row with index path. Okay, so you can find out that the i
button was pressed. Again, you might be segueing instead,
but you can do, you can get notified if you want
alternatively. Lots of other methods,
I'm not really have time to talk about them all. So, you,
providing the UIView for headers and
footers is kind of a drawing thing so they do that.
Editing and moving the rows,
there's not just a data source element to it,
there's actually the visual moving the rows.
It gets involved in that, that kind of thing, okay?
Now what if your model changes in your table view controller,
right, the underlying data? Well,
you need all those sections and rows to change, right?
You might have a different number of sections and
a different number of rows in each section.
So you're gonna call this method and
table you'll call it reloadData.
And that causes the table view to go back and
call all those methods, numberOfSectionsInTable,
number of rows in each section, cell or
row at indexPath for all the visible cells,
call them all again, okay, to get your table view reset up.
Now that might seem kinda heavy weight, and
for a large table, maybe it would be. So if you know how
your model changed such that you know which index paths,
which sections and which sections and rows,
like maybe only one section would have been changed. Then
you can try this more fine tuned reloadRowsAtIndexPaths,
which is just like reloadData but only certain index paths,
okay? How about the height of rows,
how tall are rows? Rows are a fixed width.
They're the entire width of of the table, but
what about the height? Normally the height is
just set in the inspector in your storyboard and
it's fixed. All of the rows are exactly the same height
rows of a certain prototype, all the rows that ma, or
of a certain prototype the same height.
But it is possible to let the system calculate the proper
height, and have the rows be different heights, okay.
So it'll use autolayout,
right, inside the area of custom cell to figure out how
high it should be, and then make it that high, and
it'll do that for every row. But if you're doing that and
you had a thousand rows, think about is really,
the system's gonna load up a cell for
every single one of those 10,000 rows? Do the autolayout
on each one to figure how big the table is? No way,
that would be horrendously inefficient. So
instead, it asks you to tell it an estimated height and
uses the estimated height just to estimate the total size
of the table view. But then as one comes on screen,
it makes it to be the actual height based on using
the autolayout. And the way you make it do the autolayout
is with this height UITableViewAutomaticDimension.
That's a special height which means calculate it for
me using autolayout. Okay, you can also control the height.
And you're probably gonna do this, hint hint,
you probably gonna do this in your homework assignment.
You control that height right here with a method that'll get
sent to you, okay.
The table view will send you this message,
heightForRowAtIndexPath. It'll give you the indexPath,
and it's asking you to tell it the height, okay.
And in here, you could calculate the height. So maybe
you don't want autolayout to make the decision about the
height, you wanna calculate it based on something else, okay,
some information that you might have about what's in
that cell, okay? So you don't wanna use autolayout to it,
that's fine, you can calculate it here. So here's a big hint,
you're gonna wanna do this in your homework,
okay? All right, so there's, in the TableView itself, we're
talking about its delegate methods, in the TableView
itself, there are tons and tons of methods, okay?
Can't go over them all, you're gonna wanna look to them,
look for them. But, you know, things like scrolling around
in there. The UITableView actually turns out to be
a subclass of UIScrollView, so it inherits all the ability
UIScrollView can to scroll around and stuff like that. So
you're gonna go take a look at UITableView and understand
what it can do. But you're controlling the TableView
mostly by these delegates, okay. But you can also send
messages directly to TableView to make it do things.
All right, so that's it on the slides for TableView.
Assignment 4 out, okay, it's basically going to be to do
a better version of the demo I'm doing today.
So you're gonna start with what I have today and
you're gonna improve it, okay? It's gonna be due in a week,
next Monday. On Wednesday, we're gonna start a two day
lecture on Core Data, which is object oriented database.
And next week's assignment is going to be enhance what
you're building this week to include an object oriented
database in there, okay.
Obviously, we're dealing with big data sets,
it would make sense to put it in a database so
we can query on it, things like that.
On Friday, if there's enough interest, which is still to be
determined, watch the bulletin boards in the class to find
out, we might have UICollectionView.
Now UICollectionView is just like TableView, except for
it's much more flexible. It's not just rows,
it can lay things out in almost any arrangement.
But it's still the same kind of thing, with the number of
sections, number of rows, all that. It's just that they're
not called rows, they're just number of items, okay,
because they can be laid out in different ways.
So now I'm going to do a demo, okay, it's a TableView demo.
We're going to build a Twitter client, okay. I'm calling
it Smash Tag because hashtags are at the middle of it, and
so Smash Tag is kind of a fun name for it. So let's go here.
I'm just gonna go to Xcode,
we're gonna start from scratch, as a brand new app,
okay. This is an iOS application as usual,
single view as always. We'll call it Smashtag here.
This one's gonna be iPhone only, okay, this app's gonna
be iPhone only. You will only be required
to do iPhone as well. You don't have to do,
you've already kind of learned your split view doing it on
multiple, so you don't have to do that again. So
we'll put it in the same place we put everything,
home directory developer, okay. Here it is. I'm gonna
clean up a little bit by going to my storyboard right here.
Here's my storyboard, and I'll zoom out so you can see it. It
comes with this pre-packaged freebie view controller.
I don't even want that, so I'm just gonna delete that
okay and ditto the code that came with
it too right here. I'm just gonna delete this, get that
out of there and move it to the trash. We'll go ahead and
put all these other things into, not our storyboard, but
these things into this little supporting files like we
usually do. Supporting 14 files. Okay,
so we're left with really a pretty much a blank app here.
Okay, storyboard's got nothing in it, and we're gonna have
one view controller in this app to start. You're gonna add
more view controllers in yours, but we're gonna start
one and, of course, it's gonna be a table view controller.
So let's drag it out, okay.
Well go down here. Go down to table view controller,
it's like 4th of 5th one down. I'm just gonna drag it out.
As promised, if you do the identity inspector, you can
see this view controller is a UITableViewController.
And if I click inside on the view that's inside this thing,
okay, you'll see that it's class is UITableView, okay.
If I click here, on a row, you'll see it's class is
a UITableViewCell. Does everyone got the parts here?
Have the parts all put together? Well,
we obviously need to have our own custom subclass of UI,
TableViewController, okay, just like we do with anything.
So let's go ahead an do that right off the bat.
File, New File. Okay, it's gonna be a Cocoa Touch class,
it's gonna be a subclass of UITableViewController.
I'm gonna call it TweetTableViewController,
because it's gonna be a table view full of tweets. Okay, so,
it's a tweet table view controller, or
a TweetTableViewController, whichever, you want to look at
it there, all right. So we got that, here it is,
we'll put it in the same place as everything else.
Okay, here's my TweetTableViewController,
we'll look at that in a second. Let's go back to our
story board and make sure we set our custom class, okay.
This is a easy thing to forget,
I'm sure a lot of you have. Let's go in here and
make sure it's a TweetTableViewController.
So, this is a TweetTableViewController right
here. Let's go look at the code that it generated for us.
This is a little more than we get when we normally
Make a UIViewController, okay? Because, of course,
we're getting table view specific stuff here. So,
here's our viewDidLoad, it has a couple
comments in here that you can look at when you go build your
app. Has to do with selection being cleared and
whether there's an Edit button for editing this thing. We're
not gonna be doing that in this demo, so get rid of that.
And we're not gonna have to worry about memory, so
we get rid of that. Here is our UITableViewDataSource
right here. Here's the number of sections in the table,
here's the numberOfRowsInSection,
here's cellForRowAtIndexPath.
Okay, and we know we're gonna want that, so
I'm even gonna uncomment that. Okay,
this is the heart of a dynamic table.
Okay? So, we'll implement that in a little bit.
Here's a bunch of other stuff that has to do with editing
the table, okay, deleting rows, things like that.
You really want to look at this stuff if,
again you're doing extra credit or the final project,
you want to make the rows editable,
but we'll clear it out of here to make it, clean. And
then here's our navigation, okay? I'll leave it in here.
Because you're gonna be doing a navigation,
but I'm not doing navigation in my demo, okay.
Tense, all right, that's our tweet controller.
So we, any time we have a new view controller, we probably
want to think about what our model is. Right? It's a really
good start for any time you're building a view controller,
what's it's model? And so, this is a table that contains
tweets, right? So, could say our model probably looks
something like an array of Tweet or something like that.
Okay? Where this is a class yet
to be determined. I'm actually going to make,
and I could even say, you know, equals an array of Tweet
to make an empty array of them to start off.
But I'm actually going to do a little bit trickier.
I'm actually going to have this be and array of and
array of Tweets. Okay, and the reason I'm gonna do this
is because I'm gonna go fetch a bunch of tweets and
put it in one section in my table and then later
I'm gonna let the use of fetch more tweets, and I'll put that
in another section, okay. And I'm gonna add the other
section by just adding another array of tweets. So this array
of array of tweets each array inside is just a fetch. Okay?
So that's why I'm doing an array of an array of tweets,
so I can just adding sections, okay? So this is really
nice, having an array of array of something is really
nice for table views, because this really makes it easy to
implement all the table view methods. Because it's really
clear, the section is the outer part of the array, and
then the row is in the inner part. Okay, everybody cool?
Clear why I'm doing that? Now,
of course, if anyone sets my model, I'm going to need to
reload my table, which I do with TableView.reloadData().
Okay, that's gonna call all these methods down here to get
called again. Okay. Make sense? Now,
my model is actually gonna be a little more than that.
I'm gonna have another part of my model which is searchText,
which is gonna be a string, okay? I'm gonna allow people
to set this part of my model. And I'm gonna go search for
those tweets, tweets that match that search text and
load up the other part of my model with it. Okay, so
its kinda part of my model as well,
even though they're related in that way,
they're both part of the model. Now in this one,
if someone set this one, okay, I'm gonna remove all
the tweets I got, okay, using the removeAll method in array,
just wipe out all my tweets that I have. And then I'm
gonna call searchForTweets or something like that,
that's gonna actually have to go do a search. By the way,
I'm also gonna set my title to whatever that searchText is.
So if I'm in a navigation controller or something,
the title up there will be whatever the search text was.
So I need to search teets,
Tweets here, so we'll private func searchForTweets, and
we're gonna have to implement that. So that's my model,
all right, and I can also, here in my viewDidLoad,
maybe I would maybe even say something like searchText
equals, I don't know, #stanford or something. Just,
I'll, in viewDidLoad for testing purposes,
I'll just have a initial thing that I'm gonna search for,
okay? And when I set this it's gonna call this.
It's gonna remove all the tweet, it's gonna search for
new tweets, okay? Eventually this thing's gonna find
the tweets and call this. That's gonna reload the data,
that's gonna call these. Okay, these are gonna load up
the table and start making cells to, put the tweets.
Everybody understand that flow? All right,
let's talk about tweet, this class tweet right here.
I just typed that. What is that, okay?
Well I could make you go and learn how to query Twitter and
get tweets down and all that stuff.
But I really want you to learn about table views here, so
I'm gonna provide a framework for you that will do that.
Will go out and you give it a search text, it'll,
search text of some sort,
it'll just go do the tweets and
give it back to you as an array of these tweet objects,
okay? Now I'm gonna give that to you
as a framework. Now we haven't really talked about frameworks
too much. The only time I ever mentioned frameworks actually
was when I talked about public and private. Remember that? I
said there's private, there's public, and there's nothing.
And nothing means kind of public within your app,
right? And the word public, which we never use, that means
public outside of my app or in the case I'm gonna do it,
outside of my framework. So I've made a framework for you,
and it has public methods, methods marked public, okay.
Actually public put on the line there, and
that means that you can call those methods,
use those classes outside of the framework, okay?
So to make a framework work, though, okay, you have to
create a higher level project than your project,
called a workspace, that has both the framework and your
project in it, okay? So let's do that right away, let's go
over here to Xcode, and I'm gonna say New > Workspace.
We've never done this, okay,
this is a new kind of project-like thing, but
it's really just a collection of other projects. So
I hit New > Workspace. It says what do you wanna call it and
where do you wanna put it?
So I'm gonna put it in my home directory Developer here.
I'm gonna call it Lecture9. I could call it anything.
I could even call it Smashtag if I want, but
it can be kind of confusing.
So I'm gonna call it Lecture9, okay, and it creates this.
And look, it looks kinda like an empty project.
Okay, it has no files over here, and what you
put over here are other projects. So in a workspace,
this is gonna have other projects. And in fact,
I'm just gonna go grab my Smashtag, here it is right
here. You take the xcodeproj, okay, and you drag it in.
Boom, I've added this to my workspace. Now, I can work on
my project here just as easily as working at it directly,
by double-clicking it to xcodeproj, okay? And, in fact,
better, because when I put this other framework in there,
that framework will work here. If I don't,
work here then that framework's not gonna be
visible, okay. So what about this Twitter framework?
Where's that? Well, that turns out to be right here, okay?
Here's my little Twitter project.
This will be available to you obviously when you're doing
your homework. And I'm just gonna drag it's Xcode project
in here too. Now, when I do, be very careful not to put it
inside the Smashtag project. You see how this is trying to
put it inside? You want it to be a sibling of sash,
SmashTags. So put it right up at the top so
the two of them are siblings in this workspace.
Oops, in this workspace right here, okay? See what I'm
saying by that? Question. >> If you make
changes to Smashtag in your workspace,
do they stay? >> Yeah, so the questions is
if I change my framework or my project here in the workspace,
do they effect the project? Absolutely, here you
are actually working on those projects in this workspace.
But it's those projects you are working on, okay?
Putting in the workspace, just relates them,
it just gets them in the same grouping. So
here's our Twitter project right here.
And we still have to say that this
Smashtag uses this framework, and we do that, right,
by clicking on our Smashtag project. We need to drag
our Twitter framework in here to let Smashtag know,
yeah, I want you to use Twitter. So what do we,
where do we do that? We do it right here where it says
products Twitter framework, okay, this right here.
We're just gonna take this guy, and pick it up and
drag it in here. Now before I do that, when you
download this you might find this to be red, okay.
That means it's not built. So to build it, you're
gonna wanna go up to the top here, you can see now that in
the workspace I have two choices of things I can build.
You're gonna go to Twitter. Very importantly, you want to
pick generic iOS device, because this is a framework.
And you wanna build it as a generic framework, okay, for
all iOS devices, okay. So do that and then it'll probably
automatically build when you do that. But if not,
you can hit Play to build and it'll build Twitter, and
then this will stop being red, okay.
Very important, if this is red and you drag it in,
it's not gonna work. This has to be black, okay?
So I'm gonna drag it in, okay, okay, to Smashtags1.
Okay, so here I picked Smashtag, drag this down here,
it adds it. Notice it shows in Smashtag inside Smashtag's
project, it shows it right there as well. If you're doing
that objective C, by the way, there's some headers right
here because even though I wrote this in Swift, you could
use an objective C using these headers right here, okay.
If you're in Swift, you don't care about those headers,
all right? But now inside of our code of our Smashtag, we
can reference that framework by saying import Twitter,
which is the name of this framework, okay.
And once we import Twitter, look, this, in fact,
if we go back here, which is where it is. And then we're
gonna build this one for, iPhone 6. If you go back here,
you'll see that Tweet no longer generates an error, and
it turns purple, cuz it's recognized.
Now this is the only Tweet in our namespace, but the full
name of this thing is actually Twitter.Tweet. Okay, and
you can either specify full name or if there's no other
Tweets around, you could leave this off.
I'll put it in there just so you're reminded, okay,
that that's coming from that framework. Got it? Now let's
go look at this Twitter.Tweet and see what it is. Okay, so
I'm gonna look at my Twitter framework right here, here's
Tweet. You can see Tweet is really just a collection of
information about a Tweet. The text in the Tweet, the user
who Tweeted it, when it was created, a unique identifier,
images that are attached to it, and hashtags, URLs and
users that are mentioned in the Tweet. And you're homework
is gonna be about showing me these Mentions. Okay,
I'm not gonna do that in my demo, that's for you to do.
Okay, so that's what a Tweet is. Now we have user,
which is you know, the name, screenName of the user.
MediaItem, this is for attached images.
Notice it has the aspectRatio, that'll be very valuable to
you as you try to build your table view, okay.
This is just an image that's attached with the Tweet.
When people tweet, sometimes they attach an image or
whatever. And then there's this very important class
called Request, okay, Twitter.Request. And
I'm gonna look at the public API of this actually. Let's go
over here, look at generated interface, here it is.
You can see that I've marked a lot of these things public,
you see public, public class. Here's all the public API.
The things you're gonna, we're gonna use is this
public initializer which gives the search String to search on
Twitter and then how many results you want, okay.
And then this guy fetchTweets, and what
fetchTweets does is it uses that search String to go fetch
Tweets. And it calls a little function here, this function,
okay, a function of this type. It just hands you an array of
the Tweets when they come back. Now this is
asynchronous, okay, obviously. We're gonna go to the network
here. So this is coming back and the thread that this comes
back and calls you on is not necessarily the main thread.
So we will wanna be sure to dispatch async outta here,
back to the main thread if we're gonna be doing any UI.
Everyone understand that?
Okay, so that's it. This is a really easy class to use,
right? We just initialize it with the search we want and
then just fetch the Tweets, okay? It's also got this
little thing down here, which is kinda fun,
requestFromNewer, ForNewer. If you have a request that was
successfully got you some Tweets, you can call this
requestForNewer and it'll give you a new request that will
request only more new Tweets. Tweets you didn't get in
the last request. See what I'm saying? Cuz people are alway
Tweeting all the time, so sometimes you just want
the ones that were Tweeted since the last time
you got it. So we'll use this as well, okay, in our demo.
All right, everyone understand this Twitter thing? Pretty
simple to use, all right? >> One more thing.
>> Yeah.
>> So it looked like it was
returning a void. Do you have to type cast
that to a Tweet array- >> On the previous one?
>> Down here?
It returns void, but remember, this is a function that takes
an array of Tweets as the argument. So
you're gonna pass a closure here,
and that closure is going to take that array and
do something with it. Okay, it does,
it can't return the array because it's asynchronous.
It has to go off and on that, it has to call you back.
Okay, with this function, when it's got the tweets, so
that's a good question. All right, back here,
we're in our tweets, let's get to the heart of this,
which is this guy, searchForTweets.
That's the thing that's gonna use the Twitter,
framework to search for tweets. So how's this thing,
gonna do what it does basically, to do the tweets.
Well I'm actually going to create a little private var
which I'm going to call my twitterRequest. It's going to
be of type Twitter.Request. Okay, and it's going to be
computed, and this is just going to be a little way I can
have a little var which is the request I want to make.
And I'm going to say if, I can let query = searchText,
okay that's this thing right here, okay. And
I also don't want it to be empty so
I'm gonna say where the query is not empty.
Okay, there's that where clause again. So
here I'm checking to see if it's not null with if let, and
then I'm also making sure it's not empty, so,
because I don't wanna do a Twitter request for empty,
that like asking for all Tweets. That makes no sense,
there's gotta be at least something to search for. So
if that's okay, then I'm just gonna return your request by
saying Twitter.Request. I'm gonna call that initializer
that we were talking about. Search, we can search for
the query as its own but maybe I wanna add some other stuff
like I don't want retweets. So there if
you can in the API for doing, for looking for
tweets you can specify things like filter out retweets I
don't want them, so I'm gonna do that. And then count,
let's get a hundred at a time. So we'll get a hundred tweets
at a time, okay. Otherwise I'm just going to return nil here.
Okay, so if, if some, if I want to do
a ter, twitter request, but I don't have any search text
then I'm just going to return nil,
Ill know not actually do any kind of search.
Okay, do you understand what that var is?
It's just giving me the request that I'm gonna do. So
let's use that request. I'm just gonna say if I can let
the request = TwitterRequest, so it's gonna call that
little computed var up there, okay. Then I'm going to use
that request to fetch tweets, okay. So here's fetchTweets,
here's that argument which is the handler.
By the way a really fun way when you're doing closures
is to do the escape completion til it shows this in blue, and
then double click on it.
You see, cuz then it'll put the closure out there for
you with the right argument type here.
Now I like closing, close, trailing, closure syntax.
So I'm just gonna get rid of my parentheses and put this
closure at the end. Okay, so that's kinda cool right?
Fetch tweets, it's gonna call this closure.
Here's the tweets that it's gonna give back,
an array of tweets, I'll call this newTweets, okay. And
then in this code I can use the new tweets,
add them to my table basically is really easy. But
of course I have to dispatch async, okay,
because this closure is being executed off the main queue
when those tweets come back sometime in the future. So
I've got to dispatch async. So, for my queue right here
I'm going to dispatch back to the main queue, so
that's dispatc_ge_mai_queue and here's my block.
Again I'm going to double click it, okay.
Again I'm going closing, trailing closure syntax,
okay, and so this is now dispatched to the main queue.
So all I need to do here is just say if the new tweets
are not empty, in others words I got some back, then I'm just
going to insert to my to my tweets at the beginning,
these new tweets at index 0.
Okay, cuz I want the new tweet at the top of my table so
I'm putting it at the beginning of my array, okay.
Make sense? Now I've got a red error there,
anyone know what that is? It's pointing to right here.
Any ideas? Don't be shy. >> Self.
>> Self, absolutely.
We need self here. That's Swift trying to remind us,
hey, this closure, this closure right here is keeping,
and actually this one out here too, okay, is keeping this
self in the heap. Now I don't think we want
that here cuz what if we make some Twitter request and
it takes forever and meanwhile the user just navigates away
from this thing.
We want this thing to be able to leave the heap. So
we're going to fix this using weak.
weak weakSelf = self.
So I'm just creating a new variable here called weakSelf.
It's weak so it don't won't hold anything in a heap and
I'm gonna set it equal to self.
So it's a weak version of self. And then down here I'm
gonna use weak self, okay, but this is an optional because it
gets set to nil if this thing leaves the heap.
So I have to do question mark there so that this will just
not happen if it leaves the heap. And that's perfect,
that's exactly what I want. If those tweets come back and
this thing has left the heap, just ignore this. Okay,
perfect. Now there's another problem here,
multi-threading problem we gotta think about, okay,
which is what if this takes a long time and by the time it
comes back the user has issued a different Tweet request?
They type something else in to search for, okay.
You don't wanna show them these tweets,
they were from some old thing. So
just like we did in the image view controller here,
we're gonna have to have a var,
we'll have some private var,
which is our lastTwitterRequest, okay,
which is gonna be a Twitter.Request,
okay. And, we're gonna have to keep track of
this, okay. When we go off and do this fetch, right, before
we do it I'm gonna remember what that last Twitter request
was, okay, which is the request we're doing. And
then down here I'm gonna say, if the request that we did
is the last one that we requested,
then we can do this.
Otherwise just ignore these tweets coming back. Okay,
this needs weakSelf in front of it as well. Okay, everyone
see that? I really want you to start understanding,
this is really gonna be important in your homework.
Okay cuz in your homework you're going to be
doing multi-thread stuff. And stuff's gonna come back and
this is a table view that's gonna be scrolling up and
down, reusing the cells.
It might come back to a cell that's no longer displaying
the same row as it was before cuz
it got reused, okay. So you really got to understand this
thing about understanding the world when you come back from
all asynchronous requests, okay. The three things,
the two things really to understand about asynchrony.
One is memory cycles,
make sure you break them when appropriate. And number two is
understanding that these things take time and
when they come back things might not be the same. Okay,
those are the two things to make sure you understand when
you're doing asynchronous programming. All righty then,
we have our, this is all we need to do to build our model,
build our data structure up.
Okay, this thing is now built up. Okay, this tweets,
when we add, when we insert more tweets to it, that's
gonna cause didSet to happen because this is a value type.
Okay, so didSet is gonna happen and boom,
reload data's gonna happen. So now we gotta make sure that
when reload data happens down here, that these things all do
what they're supposed to, right. So let's talk about
number of sections. That one's real easy. Tweets.count,
okay, cuz our tweet is an array of arrays.
The number of arrays in the top
level is how many sections we have, okay. So that's good.
Got that warning out of there. How about this one? This one
is tweets(section).count. So now we're looking at our array
of arrays, finding the array that is, that is this section,
and looking at how many rows are in it. Everybody got that?
This is really cool to have really simple implementations
of these by designing our data structure to make this simple.
Hint, hint, hint, I strongly recommend that for
your homework as well. Try to design your data structure
using all you've learned about Swift,
Swift is really awesome at being able to design
sophisticated flexible data structures.
Design a data structure, you can have one liners like this,
okay. Now you have a different thing going on. Your table's
gonna have mixed things, different kinds of things,
I have all the same kind of thing,
all mine are all tweaked. You have mixed things so its
a little more complicated for you, but it still can be done.
All right so now we have to do this self wrote index pass we
have to make a cell. Well the first thing we want to
do is this reuse identifier right here. So I'm actually
going to make a private struct called storyboard, just like I
did in the last demo. And it's gonna have a static let called
TweetCellIdentifier and we'll call it- we'll just call it
Tweet. So this is gonna be the identifier,
of the cells in the storyboard.
So I'm gonna replace this reuse identifier with
Storyboard.TweetCellIdentif- ier. Okay?
So that's specifying it. Now I need to do that same thing in
my storyboard. Okay, here's my row right here,
my prototype row. I'm gonna start off by making it be
a subtitle row, we'll eventually make it custom, but
let's make it be a subtitle role. And I gotta make sure my
reuse identifier is the same, so I'll make it be Tweet.
See the two things I did there? So that makes it so
this code matches up with my storyboard. All right?
So now, here I've dequeued this reusable cell, might have
reused it, might have made one from my prototype in there
which is a subtitle cell. So now I'm just gonna get
the tweet that corresponds to this index path right here.
Again, super simple because of our data structure,
tweets[indexPath.section] [indexPath.row].
Got it? Okay, cuz this is an array of arrays, right?
So now I just need to load this cell up so I'll,
in its text label, which is that main label of the thing,
I'll put the text which is the tweets text. Okay,
that's the text of the tweet, and then in the detail,
TextLabel, we'll put the tweet user's name,
okay? All right, so that's it. Loaded our table up,
should just work fine. Here we go. This is where we cross our
fingers in the live demo we didn't forget anything.
All right, here we go. It's running, and black, and
what do we got down here in the console?
Failed to instantiate the default view controller Main,
perhaps the designated entry point not set? Yeah,
let's go look at that. Main storyboard,
Zoom out, there's no little arrow going in here, okay.
I'm sure your guys have experienced that as well. So
let's go here and just slack this, View Controller and
say that it is the initial View Controller and
now we have this arrow. Okay? Excellent.
Party on. All right. So look at that, it worked perfectly.
Okay, look at that, we can look at all these tweets,
who tweeted them, okay, we're looking at Stanford here,
fantastic, scrolling up and down. Okay,
this is about the ugliest Twitter client I've ever seen.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Okay? This is,
if you put this in the app store you've,
the ridicule would be, would be unending for this.
Now how we gonna fix this, though? Really there's no way,
none of these standard cells are gonna make it look good.
We need to build a custom cell, obviously,
to make this look good.
So it's doing the right thing, it just looks terrible. So
instead of using this subtitle cell right here,
we're gonna do a custom cell. All right, so
how do we do that? First thing we need to do is, let's change
this from subtitle to custom. Then we're gonna be a, need to
go here and change the, the, the identity inspector,
need to change this to be some subclass of UITableViewCell
because obviously we're gonna have some labels and
stuff in here that we need to have outlets to, okay? So
let's go up here, new, file, okay.
Cocoa Touch Class,
this time instead of UITableViewController,
it's gonna be UITableViewCell subclass. And we'll call
this a TweetTableViewCell cuz that's what it is, shows
a Tweet. Okay, click that, put it in the same place we put
everything. [SOUND] Here we go, there's our TableViewCell,
we'll look at that in a second.
In our storyboard, we're gonna change the custom class here
to be TweetTableViewCell, okay. And
here's our TweetTableViewCell. We don't need to wait for
a nib, you all remember what that is and
we don't need it. Here's an interesting one right here.
This one will get called
in the table view cell if the table view gets selected.
I showed you how you can find out in the controller,
here you can actually find out in the table view cell. But
we don't need either of those things, okay?
We're not gonna do either of those things.
What we really need is just to build our UI. So let's
go back to our storyboard, and build the UI that we want,
eh in here. So what kind of stuff do we need, for
a tweet? Well let's see, we probably need,
want something which is, the Tweets Text.
Okay. The Tweets Text, by the way, is long and
I want it to wrap into multiple lines. So
I'm actually gonna go to the inspector up here and
make the number of lines in this text label be zero.
Zero means keep wrapping. Okay,
don't try to fit it all on one line with dot dot dot.
Remember our display would always say dot dot dot. Zero
means keep wrapping around so we definitely want that.
We also want the tweeter. So lets have one for
the tweeter. Okay, and that we do want to be on one line.
Lets show when the tweet was created. Maybe? And how about,
let's put an image in there. Let's put where's our UI
image view? Here it is. Put an u, image view, out here.
We'll have this be the profile image basically of the user.
Now, some things here we gotta do to arrange this, and I'm
gonna try and keep this mostly in what you already know.
One thing is the font, okay. These things
are very different from like a button in terms of fonts.
These are user data. This is what the user is looking at.
So we need to not use system font here. We need to pick
a different font which is one of the textiles.
Remember I mentioned the textiles? So
tweeter is kind of like a headline. It goes at the top.
Tweet Text is probably like the body. That's the main,
oops, that's the main body of the, of what's showing here.
Created is kind of like a caption.
It's just a little thing on the side. So
we'll say, caption one. And we might play with these various
things to find out what, you know, is the best font that
we want in each circumstance. So, let's say one thing is
a font. Next thing is, we need to arrange them in stack
views. Obviously, we love stack view, so let's do that.
Let's go here and embed these two in a stack view how about,
we'll have them both be filled there.
Let's put these two in a stack view,
thank you. Also we'll fill both directions there so
we got those. Let's put these in a stack view.
You can see a stack view, very powerful.
Now let's put a little spacing between there. Like that.
One thing that's not really very nice about this.
Okay, we probably want this to be fill also. One thing that's
not very nice about this is, look at this space right here.
Look how it's giving so much space to the tweeter. And not
pretty much space to the Tweet text, okay. Well, it turns out
there's a way in auto layout to control that, which is you
can go to something that you want to hug to it's contents,
right. You want to can it, be the smallest possible content.
You can select it, go over to the size inspector over here,
which is where all the constraints are, right here.
And change its content hugging priority. See content hugging
priority? I'm gonna make its content hugging priority in
the vertical direction to be high, higher than the other
one, okay? And when I do that, look what happened,
it hugged, okay? And now it made this one be the big one.
Because this one's content hugging priority is 251,
this one's 300. So, it's more of a priority to hug,
you got it? That's the only kinda special trick I'm gonna
show you today. I am going to do a whole
lecture on autolayout next week. All right, so
we've got this. So now, let's do our thing when we hook it
up to the edges. Leading edge up to top
down here to the bottom and over here to the trailing.
Let's go ahead and click on these, and
see if we can make standard. No? So, let's make this zero,
see if we can make this one a standard. No, make this one
also zero. See if we can make this one a standard. No, make
this one zero. And the top one is probably already zero.
Let's go ahead and look at it in our Spectre. Here, yeah,
the top is already zero. So, it's zero. Now, this is also
not looking like I want. Okay, the image view is dominating.
This is just the image view of the guy who tweeted it.
So, it just wants to be small and in the corner. So,
I'm actually going to fix the size of this. So,
if you control drag to itself, you can set a constraint,
a constraint itself. So it's going to react to controlled
to itself, so I'm going to fix its height and width.
So, that has fixed it's height and width,
of course I don't want it to be this big.
I want it to be like, you know, 60 by 60, let's say.
So, I'm going over here to the inspector, size inspector.
On this thing. And I'm gonna change, this constraint, right
here, just by clicking edit. I'm gonna change it to 60. And
I'm gonna change the height to also be 60. Okay. Now,
we have a much more reasonable layout here, right. The text
is using most of the space. The tweeter's just at the top.
We got the little image for the tweeter up there, and
we've got this created in here. We're good? Okay.
Now let's go and create outlets to all these things.
So, let's make more space here. Now one thing to
be careful of, if I go to, man to automatic here, and
I try to make an outlet look at the class it puts here.
[NOISE] The tableview controller. We know we cannot
hook these outlets up to the tableview controller, because
they have to be different for every cell. So instead, we
have to go to Manual up here, okay, and go not in Twitter.
We need to go, actually we'll, let's go here.
[LAUGH] How do we get to there? Let's see, Manual,
TweetTableView, so here it is. Okay, so let's go here, so
here's our, our TweetTableViewCell right here,
but this is not quite right either. Hold on a second here.
Manual. Automatic.
Level object. Okay.
It's showing me the interface here for some reason.
Lets do something different here. Lets go over here.
[SOUND] Okay, I'm not sure why it's doing that.
Okay, strange let's do TweetTableViewCell.
Very sorry about that.
For some reason you see it's fixed.
It's showing me the interface for
this. I'm not sure exactly why. Okay. Let's try this.
Let's go here, and then over here.
[INAUDIBLE] Okay,
well you know what I'm gonna do, I'm gonna quit this thing
and re-launch. By the way when you go back in,
be careful not to go back in with your Xcode project,
you gotta go back in with your workspace, alright? Alright,
now let's see. All right, we got our storyboard,
manual swift module, that's no good either. Mm.
This, all right, no.
Okay, this. This.
Okay, hm. I better back out there.
Well, weird. Hm,
I guess maybe we can do this, there we go. Okay, so
we are going to, I'll make this wider too,
so we are going to hook up our outlets, okay?
From here to here. So we do that with control drag,
just as we normally would, so here we'll control drag this.
I'm gonna call this one the tweetScreenNameLabel,
okay, because it's showing the screen name of the user.
Well do this one here. We'll call the tweetTextLabel.
We'll do here, this is the TweetCreatedLabel,
and we'll do this one. This is the,
TweetProfileImageView, okay.
And that's a UI image view. Okay, so
I've got these nice outlets right here. And,
let's go back to here, get our Text here all right, so
we got these nice outlets. So, now we need to be able to
load these outlets up. When this cell, okay,
comes on the screen, and we do self-reload index path we need
to be able to tell this cell here is the tweet okay, so
that you can load up all this information about the tweet.
So, I'm gonna have a public var here called tweet,
which is the tweet. And it's a twitter.tweet.
Okay, and when you set that,
I'm going to update my UI to set all of these things. So,
I'm gonna have some private func updateUI here.
Okay, makes sense? Now this is complaining
about twitter.tweet, because I have to import Twitter.
Don't forget, import Twitter, otherwise you're not gonna see
the classes from that in this swift file. Okay, so
we have this update UI right here. In the interest of time,
I'm gonna type this really fast okay, there it is.
okay, you can go look at this at you later offline, but
basically what's it's doing it
firstly just clearing out all the outlets,
okay, then it's one by one going through and
setting each of them based on the tweet, okay.
Tweet that we have. Notice by the way here,
kind of fun thing, in the tweet's text, I add cameras,
a bunch of cameras at the end if the tweet has an image
attached. Okay, that's what this little thing is here. I'm
just going looking at all the images that this tweet has.
That's just media array and for each one, I'm adding
a little camera there just to let us know there's an image.
Okay, tha's being added to the text of the end of
the text, all right? Then her's the created date in
the nice little format. Here's the image view, if it exists.
All right. UI image. Notice this blocks the main
thread. Fix this in your homework because one of your
required tasks is you cannot block the main thread. So
even though I'm not doing the dispatch here, you need to.
Got it? All right so, that's our TweetLabel.
So now to make this work, we just need to set this tweet
var in our cellForRowAtIndexPath.
Okay, so here's our cellForRowAtIndexPath.
Right now, it's doing all this business right here.
We don't want that. Okay, instead we're just gonna say
if we can let a tweetCell equal the cell as one of our
TweetTableViewCells, okay, which this should be, because
all these the tweet prototype in our storyboard over here,
okay, that this is this is the tweet prototype cell right
here if we look at it Type, it is, if I can select it here.
Here's where I wanna use Ctrl+Shift, okay,
Ctrl+Shift lets me pick which, what I want,
which is the TableView cell.
You can see that it's a custom type, right? So this should be
good right here. So if I can get this cell as that,
then I'm just gonna set the cell's tweet equal to
the tweet at that row and index path. Okay, all right,
tweetCell. Okay? Got it? So
that's it. Not that hard to just custom UI.
Let's go take a look, make sure it's working. All right,
here it is! So, well, this looks somewhat better,
I guess. It's really not much better because, one thing is,
look at the heights of the rows.
They're all the same. Even if it's a short little one like
this, it gets all this yucky white space, this extra white
space. Compared to a long one, right? So that's bad. And, and
big ones are not even fitting, okay? Also, where's my profile
image view? Got a couple problems here. So let's talk
about the height first. What's going on with the height?
And remember I said you can have the height be dynamic and
automatically calculated from the tweet by just
setting the height to automatic dimension. And
the place to do that is in your viewDidLoad.
Okay, so here's my viewDidLoad and
I'm just gonna set in here my tableView's row height
equal to this UITableView automatic dimension thing.
Okay, but now what about the estimated height?
I need to give it an estimate height so I'm actually going
to set the tableView's estimated row height equal to
the row height that came out of the storyboard. Okay?
So this is the row height I'm getting now. Same on every
one. I'm gonna make that one just be the estimated one,
and then I'm gonna set the row height to be this automatic.
And that's gonna recalculate it all the time.
How about the fact that I'm not getting those profile
image views? Well look, I have something in my console right
here. You recognize this? App Transport Security, okay?
You all remember that from last time? So let's fix that.
We go into our Info.plist. We're going to add a row here.
It's going to be the App Transport Security row right
there. We're going to go down here and add arbitrary loads,
okay. And we're going to set it to yes. So
we're going to allow arbitrary URLs. Okay?
Makes sense? Get this down out of there.
Okay, let's run again. Hopefully, things will look
really nice. Okay, that does look quite a bit better,
okay. It starts to look like some, I don't know if we could
post it on the abstract quite yet, okay but getting there,
okay. So I want to ask one more thing, which is I wanna
put a search thing at the top here, so we can search. Okay,
for not just always being #Stanford, as much as
we love #Stanford. So the way we're gonna do that is we're
gonna go to our storyboard. One thing is I'm gonna put
it inside of a navigation controller here and
embed this whole thing inside a navigation controller.
That means I can have a nice title on it, right?
Remember I set the title to be what I search for.
So I'm gonna have that there. Then I'm also going to go and
drag out a text field to be my search. So
this is gonna be the editable kind of text field. Which
is right here. And if you drag right up at the top. You have
to be a little bit careful. It has to look like this,
you see where it stretches out.
You can set the tableView's header.
So I've set this text field as the tableView's header. Okay?
And I probably wanna changed some things about it.
Maybe a little bit bigger font. Maybe I wanna use
the place holder here like, Twitter, search,
text, or something like that. That's a little something
that tells what this field is. Okay. That's just always gonna
be in the background til they start typing or whatever.
And I'm gonna need to have an outlet to it. So let's
do that. Okay, this time, I do want automatic, okay,
because this is not in a cell, this is at the top. So
let's Ctrl+Drag down here, let's put this, I don't know,
down at the bottom here. Let's Ctrl-Drag out here, and
call this searchTextField. All right. When,
searchTextField is set, we're gonna set its delegate,
to be ourself. We know that with text fields, we want our
delegate. We're also gonna set the searchTextField's text,
equal to our own search text. Okay.
Everybody understand that? Let's go back here and, so we
can see a little better. Okay it's complaining about self.
It doesn't like self because we are not
a UI text field delegate,
so we better set ourselves to be that. All right,
what else do we got down here? >> The didSet.
>> The didSet, yeah thanks,
didSet. There we go, okay,
so when the searchTextField is set we're gonna do this and
then of course we're gonna implement that method,
the textField method which is the textField,
the textFieldShouldReturn. Okay, and in here,
we're just going to have the textField.resignFirstRespon-
der. Okay, and then we're gonna return true.
And let's, also have the text, let's grab
our search text out of there. searchText = textField.text.
Okay, so when someone hits the return key, we're going to
grab the text out of there and hide the keyboard, okay makes
sense? All right, I believe that's all we need to do,
let's get our Stanford out of there, where's Stanford?
There it is. No more Stanford. Run.
Okay, so we've got our search text up there. So let's try,
let's put Stanford back in there, see if that works.
There it is, that's good. Let's try something else like
NBA. Okay, there's the NBA. Okay, looking good.
Go back to Stanford again, and see that again, okay?
There you go. All right, CS193P mentioned right there.
How about that? Okay, so that's it. Now,
I have a couple more things I wanted to show, but we ran
outta time, so I'm going to post them in this code.
I'll be posting this code, I'll add a couple of things.
The two things I wanna do is. One is
I want to be able to pull down on this tableView and
show more tweets. Okay, so the tableView,
the way to kind of update it, if you pull down on it and
a little spinner comes up on it,
and it's gonna show more, okay. So I'll put that,
I'll basically add that code into what I'm going to post.
That's all I'll show. Okay? That's it, sorry to run long.
See you next time. >> For
more, please visit us at Stanford.edu.